<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-BT.05151</field>
		<field name="filename">BTP_1985_28_3_08_Gas_liquid_two.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">Gas-Liquid Two-Phase Flow Pattern Prediction Computer Library
ATTILIO ALBERTO TRIGGIA, Região de Produção da Bahia, ELISIO CAETANO, Centro de Pesquisas e O VADIA SHOHAM, Universidade de Tulsa.
RESUMO — Foi desenvolvida uma biblioteca computacional aplicável na predição do arranjo das fases existentes no fluxo de gás e I íquido. Tal biblioteca baseia-se em modelos anal íticos, que predizem o arranjo das fases através do uso de princípios físicos. Estes modelos incorporam importantes parâmetros concernentes ao fluxo, tais como: vazões de líquido e gás, propriedades físicas dos fluidos, diâmetro da tubulação e ângulo de inclinação da mesma. São também apresentadas a descrição de todos os arranjos das fases existentes no fluxo bifásico através de tubulações para todos os ângulos de inclinação da mesma e as equações que governam as transições entre arranjos de acordo com os respectivos modelos.
A biblioteca computacional, escrita em linguagem FORTRAN 77, é usada principalmente para: monitorar o arranjo das fases ao longo de um oleoduto ou coluna de poço e desenvolver o mapa do arranjo das fases em termos das velocidades superficiais das fases I íquida e gasosa conforme um dado conjunto de condições. Tais informações têm significante contribuição no pré-proje-to de sistemas que envolvem fluxo bifásico.
ABSTRACT — A computer library for gas-liquid two-phase flow pattern prediction has been developed. The library is based on analytical mechanistic models which predict flow patterns from physical principles. These models incorporate the important flow parameters such as gas and liquid flow rates, physical properties, pipe diameter and inclination angle. Also presented are a description of two-phase flow patterns occurring in pipes for all inclination angles; and, the equations governing the transition boundaries in the models.
The computer library, written in FORTRAN 77, can be used mainly for two purposes: to monitor the existing flow pattern along a pipeline or wellbore; and, to develop flow pattern maps in terms of superficial liquid and gas velocities for a given set of conditions. This type of information can contribute significantly to the design of two-phase flow systems.
(Originais recebidos em 19-XI-84.)
1 - INTRODUCTION
When gas and liquid flow simultaneously in a pipe, various flow configurations can occur, differing from each other in the spatial distribution of the interface. These flow configurations are called flow regimes or flow patterns. The existing flow pattern depends on the operational variables, namely the gas and liquid flow rates, physical properties of the fluids (density, viscosity, and surface tension) and on geometrical variables such as conduit shape,diameter and inclination angle.
An a priori knowledge of the flow pattern is essential to the designer, because the hydrodynamics of the flow, as well as the mechanisms of momentum, mass and heat transfer, change significantly from one flow pattern to another.
The most common approach for flow pattern determination has been through visual observations of two-phase flow in transparent pipes. Usually the data are mapped on a two-dimensional plot, and the boundaries between the
different flow patterns are determined. There has been no physical basis for the selection of the coordinates for flow pattern maps. Therefore, each map is reliable only in the narrow range of conditions under which the data have been taken, and extension to other flow conditions is uncertain. Such a flow pattern map is the Mandhane et al. f1) map. The coordinates of this map are dimensional, namely the superficial velocities of the gas and liquid phases. Some investigators have tried to extend the validity of their map by choosing dimensionless coordinates (Griffith &amp;amp; WALLIS (2)), or by suggesting correction factors for physical properties (Govier &amp;amp; Aziz (3)).Still,the general applicability of these maps is questionable.
Recently, analytical models based on physical concepts have been presented for flow pattern prediction. In this approach, the physical mechanisms which cause transition between the various flow patterns are determined. Once the transition mechanisms are defined, a theoretical model can be constructed consisting of analytical
stratified smooth flow
slug flow
stratified wavy flow
annular flow
elongated bubble flow
dispersed bubble flow
Fig. 1 - Flow patterns in horizontal and near horizontal flow.
transition boundaries between the different flow pattern regions. The main advantage of these models is that they incorporate the important effects of physical properties, pipe diameter and gas and liquid fluxes. Thus, they can be applied more confidently to conditions for which no data are available. The models used in the computer library will be discussed later.
2 - FLOW PATTERN DEFINITIONS
There remains a lack of agreement among two-phase flow investigators on the classification and definition of flow patterns. Some tend to detail as many flow patterns as possible, while others try to group similar flow configurations together. The disagreement is due to the fact that flow patterns are subjective visual phenomena which sometimes are complex and hard to determine.
Shoham (4) defined a set of flow patterns which occur in horizontal, vertical, and inclined flow. This set is followed in this study.
2.1	— Horizontal and Near Horizontal Flow
Flow patterns for horizontal and near horizontal flow are shown in figure
1.	A description of each follows:
Stratified (S): Liquid flows at the bottom of the pipe with gas at the top. The stratified pattern is subdivided into Stratified Smooth (SS), where the liquid
surface is smooth, and Stratified l/Vavy (SW), where the interface is wavy.
Intermittent (I): In this flow pattern, the inventory of liquid in the pipe is nonuniformly distributed axially. Plugs or slugs of liquid which fill the pipe are separated by gas zones, which contain a stratified liquid layer flowing along the bottom of the pipe. The liquid in the slug may be aerated by small bubbles which are concentrated toward the front of the slug and the top of the pipe. The intermittent pattern is usually subdivided into Slug (SL) and Elongated Bubble (EB) patterns. In principle, the flow behavior of slug and elongated bubble flow seems to be the same with regard to the flow mechanism and, therefore, there is no particular advantage in distinguishing between them. In this work, the elongated bubble pattern is considered the limiting case of slug flow, when the liquid slug is free of entrained gas bubbles. Thus, when the flow is calm and the liquid slug is free of gas bubbles, the pattern is that of elongated bubble flow. For high flow rates, in which the flow at the front of the liquid slug is in the form of an eddy (where gas bubbles are generated and swept into the liquid slug), the flow is designated as slug flow. With this criterion, the elongated bubble-slug transition is easy to identify.
Annular (AN): The liquid flows as a film around the pipe wall. The liquid film surrounds a core of high velocity
gas, which may contain entrained liquid droplets. The film is usually thicker at the bottom than at the top, depending on the gas and liquid flow rates. At the lowest gas rates at which transition from slug to annular flow is observed, most of the liquid flows as a film at the bottom of the pipe while aerated, unstable waves are swept around the pipe periphery and wet the upper wall occasionally. This flow occurs on the border of stratified wavy, slug and annular flow. It is not stratified wavy because liquid is swept around and wets the upper wall with a thin film. It is also not slug flow, because no liquid bridge is formed. As a result, the frothy waves are not accelerated to the gas velocity, but move much slower than in slug flow. Nor is it fully developed annular flow, which requires a stable film over the entire pipe perimeter. Nicholson et al. (1978) also recognized the existence of this hybrid pattern and designated it as "proto-slug" flow. Based on the definitions and mechanisms of slug and annular flows, it is suggested that this regime be termed as Wavy Annular (WA) and classified as a subclass of the annular regime.
The difference between slug flow and wavy annular flow is more distinguishable in upward inclined flow. During slug flow, back flow of the liquid film between slugs is observed, whereas in wavy annular flow the liquid film moves forward uphill, as in the case of stratified flow, with frothy waves superimposed on the film.
Dispersed Bubble (DB): The gas phase is distributed as discrete bubbles within a continuous liquid phase. The transition to this pattern is defined by the condition where bubbles are first suspended in the liquid, or when elongated bubbles, which touch the top of the pipe, are destroyed. When this first happens, most of the bubbles are located near the upper wall. At higher liquid rates, the bubbles are dispersed more uniformly in the entire pipe cross section.
2.2	— Vertical and Sharply Inclined Flow
In vertical and sharply inclined flow, the stratified regime disappears and a new pattern is observed (churn flow). The flow patterns for this configuration are shown in figure 2. A description of each flow pattern follows:
Bubble IBB): As in the horizontal case, the gas phase is dispersed into
small discrete bubbles in a continuous liquid phase. However, in this case the distribution is approximately homogeneous through the pipe cross section.
Slug (SL): The slug flow regime in vertical flow is symmetrical around the pipe axis. The gas phase is located in a large bullet shape bubble termed "Taylor-bubble", with a diameter almost equal to the pipe diameter. The flow consists of successive Taylor bubbles and liquid slugs which bridge the pipe cross section. The slugs are usually aerated by small gas bubbles. A thin liquid film flows backwards between the Taylor bubble and the pipe wall.
Churn (CH): The churn flow regime is characterized by an oscillatory motion. Churn flow is similar to slug flow, but looks much more chaotic. It occurs at higher gas flow rates, where the liquid slugs, bridging the pipe, become shorter and frothy, are usually blown through by the gas phase, break, fall backwards and merge with the following slug. As a result, the bullet shaped Taylor bubble is distorted and churning occurs.
Annular (AN): In vertical flow the annular pattern is usually symmetrical, resulting in an approximately uniform liquid film around the pipe. As in the horizontal case, the flow is characterized by a continuous gas core. The liquid
phase moves as a film around the pipe wall and as droplets entrained in the gas core.
In vertical downward flow, the annular regime also exists at low gas flow rates, in the form of a falling film. The slug regime in downward flow is similar to that in upward flow, except that usually the Taylor bubble is unstable and eccentrically located off the pipe axis. The Taylor bubble may either rise or descend, depending on the relative flow rates of the gas and the liquid.
3 - FLOW PATTERN PREDICTION MODELS
Generalized mechanistic models for flow pattern prediction for horizontal and near horizontal flow and for upward vertical flow were developed by Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler (5) and Taitel et al. (9). BARNEA et al. extended these models to upward inclined flow (6), downward inclined flow (7) and vertical downward flow (8).Thus it is now possible to predict flow patterns for any given inclination angle. These five models are used in the computer library for flow pattern prediction.
3.1 - Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler (5) Model for Flow Pattern Prediction in Horizontal and Near Horizontal Flow
The starting point of this model is
stratified equilibrium flow. Assuming that stratified flow exists, the mechanism which causes a change to non-stratified conditions is proposed, and the resulting flow pattern is determined.
Equilibrium Stratified Flow: For steady state stratified flow (see fig. 3), the combined momentum equation for the gas and the liquid phases is:
- (PL~i°G&gt; 9 sin 0 = 0
(1)
Transforming Eq. (1) todimensionless form yields:

+ 4Y = 0
(2)
where m = n = 1 for laminar flow and m
fSL
X2 =----
n = 0.2 for turbulent flow and:
PLVSL
2D
(#)
(3)
_ Ipf PG»9sin0
(4)
I	t	t
slug	churn	annular
flow	flow	flow
I
bubble flow
Fig. 2 - Flow patterns in vertical and sharply inclined upward Fig, 3 - Equilibrium stratified flow, flow.
Fig. 4- Generalized chart for equilibrium liquid level in stratified flow.
Note that X is the well" known Lockhart &amp;amp; Martinelli parameter. The dimensionless variables designated by a tilde (~) are normalized with respect to the following reference variables: D for length, D2 for area and vg[_ and v§q for the liquid and gas velocities, respectively.
All the dimensionless variables in Eq. (3) are unique functions of the dimensionless liquid level h|_ = h|_/D. Thus, Eq. (3) is an implicit equation for h[_. The solution is presented in a graphical form in figure 4.
Stratified to NonStratified Flow Transition Boundary: The mechanism of this transition is based on the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability criterion. As the gas or the liquid flow rates are increased, waves start to develop on the interface. Gravity forces tend to dissipate the waves and cause stratified conditions to prevail, while pressure suction forces on the wave crest tend to support wave growth and promote transition to either slug or annular flow. Comparing these forces, Taitel &amp;amp; DUKLER derived the following criterion for the transition from stratified to non-stratified flow:
where F is a modified Froude number:
VSG
Dg cos 9
(6)
(7)
dAi ,-----------~~
= Vi - (2hL - I)2 = Sj (8) dhL
Slug to Annular Flow Transition Boundary: As described in the previous transition, when either the gas or the liquid flow rates are increased, transition from stratified to non-stratified flow occurs. At low gas and high liquid flow rates, the liquid level in the pipe is high and the growing waves block the pipe cross-sectional area. This blockage forms a stable liquid slug supported by the high liquid level, and slug flow develops. However, at low liquid and high gas flow rates, the liquid level in the pipe is low. Once waves form, they are unstable due to the insufficient liquid supply from the film, and are swept up and around the pipe. Under these conditions, an annulus is created rather than a slug, resulting in a transition to annular flow. Thus, Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler proposed that this transition from slug to annular flow depends uniquely on the liquid level in
the pipe. They suggested that if h |_ &amp;lt;0.5, the flow regime will be annular, and slug flow occurs if h|_ &gt; 0.5.
Stratified Smooth to Stratified Wavy Transition Boundary: Waves develop on the interface when the gas phase velocity is sufficient to cause waves to form, but lower than the velocity needed for rapid wave growth causing transition to non-stratified conditions. Generally, waves are initiated at a stratified surface when pressure and shear work on the wave overcome viscous dissipation in the waves. TaiTEL&amp;amp;DUKLER used the following criterion for wave initiation:
where:
K = F2ReSL =
(9)
pgvsg
(PL~PG&gt; Dg cos 0
(10)
and s'= 0.01 is Jeffrey's sheltering coefficient.
Slug to Dispersed Bubble Transition Boundary: For slug flow at high liquid flow rates, the equilibrium level is high and approaches the upper pipe wall. The gas phase occurs in the form of a long bubble at the top of the pipe. With such high liquid velocities, the long bubble is shattered into small dispersed bubbles that mix with the liquid phase. TAITEL &amp;amp; Dukler proposed that the transition to dispersed bubble flow occurs when the turbulent fluctuations are strong enough to overcome the net buoyant forces tending to retain the gas as a long bubble at the top of the pipe. Thus dispersed bubble occurs when:
Sj v'l (vlDl&gt;
(11)
where:
(12)
The preceding criteria for flow pattern transition boundaries were used to create a generalized flow pattern map for horizontal flow, given in figure
5.
3.2	- Tait EL et al. (9) Model for Flow Pattern Prediction in Upward Vertical Flow
A similar approach to that of TAITEL &amp;amp; Dukler (s) for modeling horizontal flow pattern transitions was used by Taitel et al. (9) for upward vertical flow. The authors suggested physical mechanisms for the transitions among the various flow patterns and modeled them mathematically. Their flow pattern maps for vertical air-water systems at atmospheric conditions for 5.0 and 2.54 cm pipes are given in figure 6. The authors consider the following transitions between the different flow patterns:
Bubble to Slug Transition Boundary (Transition A): This transition occurs at low liquid flow rates. As the gas flow rate increases, the gas void fraction increases, and coalescence of small bubbles takes place. Taitel et al. suggested than when the gas void fraction is a = 0.25, the coalescence intensity is high and the small bubbles form large bullet-shaped Taylor bubbles characteristic of slug flow. Thus transition to slug flow at low liquid rates occurs when:
Bubble or Slug to Dispersed Bubble Transition Boundary (Transitions B and C): At high liquid flow rates, the turbulent fluctuations tend to break the large Taylor bubbles and disperse them as small bubbles in the liquid phase. When the turbulent fluctuation intensity is sufficiently high to break the Taylor bubble into fine bubbles smaller than a critical bubble size to prevent reagglomeration, then dispersed bubble flow will occur. The mathematical equation for this criterion is:
VSL + VSG ~ 4-°
p 0.429 O 0-089 PL	sípl-pg1	0.446
,,0.072	PL	
Since bubble flow cannot exist at packing densities above a = 0.52, transition B is terminated at curve C, for which:
(13)
VSL
VSG +vSL
0.52
(15)
Bubble Flow Existence at Low Liquid Flow Rates: Note that transition A is absent in small diameter pipes. TAITEL et al. suggested that this phenomenon depends on the relative velocities of a small bubble and a Taylor bubble. This leads to the following criterion for the non-existence of transition A:
PL 9p2 (PL — PG^°
(16)
For all diameters satisfying the inequality, bubble flow will occur only at high liquid flow rates (transitions B and C) and transition A will be absent.
Slug to Churn Transition Boundary (Transition D): Churn flow is considered by this model as an entry region to slug flow. Thus the region of churn flow is determined by the entry length required to develop a stable slug
CURVE:	A&amp;amp;B
COORDINATE:	F vs X
D
TvsX
where v^ = vg[_ + vgQ. Referring to figure 6, slug flow occurs at lower gas flow rates, to the left of curve D, and churn flow to the right of curve D, provided that the gas flow rate is not high enough to cause the annular regime.
Annular Flow Transition Boundary (Transition E): This transition occurs at high gas flow rates. The liquid film flows around the pipe periphery, and the gas flows in the center, carrying entrained liquid droplets. The mechanism suggested for the transition to annular flow is based on the minimum gas phase velocity required to suspend a droplet in the core stream. This is determined from a balance between the
gravity and drag forces acting on the droplet, as follows:
r	n1/4
vg&gt;3.i
pg
(18)
.]
1/2
(dP/dx)SL
X = ------------
(dP/dx)SG |(dP/dx)s|_| (P|_- Pq) 9 cos
C K vs X
Pg
VSG \/Dg cos O'
3.3 — Flow Pattern Prediction for Upward and Downward Inclined Flow (BARNEA etal. (6'7))
1/2
2 PçVSGVSL (PL-pG)gl/|_cosO
Fig. 5- Taitel &amp;amp; DUKLER (5) generalized flow pattern.
The Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler (5) model for horizontal and near horizontal flow can be applied with an accepted accuracy in the inclination range of
T =
Fig. 6- TAITEL et a/. (9) flow pattern map for upward vertical air-water systems at atmospheric conditions.
± 15°. Flow pattern for sharper inclined flow can be predicted by modifications of both the TAITEL &amp;amp; DUKLER (5) and the Taitel et a/. (9) models. These modifications are presented in the following sections.
3.3.1	— Upward Inclined Flow (15°&amp;lt;6&amp;lt;90°)
The major effect of upward inclination angles is observed on the stratified-slug transition boundary. Upward inclined flow promotes slugging, resulting in the expansion of the slug region and the shrinkage of the stratified region which disappears completely at inclination angles above 20°. The extension of the Taitel et al. (9) model to include the effect of the inclination angles follows.
Bubble-Slug Transition Boundary:
This transition occurs at low liquid flow rates as a result of bubble coalescence
(20)
when the gas void fraction reaches a = 0.25. The transition boundary given by Taitel et al. (Eq. (13)) is simply modified by taking the component of the bubble rise velocity along the pipe:
Annular Flow Transition Boundary: The transition to annular flow in vertical upward flow is based on the
This transition occurs only in large diameter pipes as given by Eq. (16). In addition, this region occurs only in sharply inclined flow for inclination angles larger than 60°.
Bubble or Slug to Dispersed Bubble Transition Boundary: This transition occurs at high liquid flow rates in which turbulent forces act against surface tension forces to break the Taylor bubbles into small fine bubbles. This transition is independent from pipe inclination, and thus the transition boundary expression is the same as given by Eq. (14). However, better accuracy can be achieved by including the relatively small effect of the gas void fraction on the process of coalescence and breakup. The modified equation is:
1/2
0.4o
(7l
(')■
= 0.725 + 4.
v2(3-n)/5
VM
minimum gas velocity required to suspend a drop of entrained liquid in
the gas core, as given by Eq. (18). The same concept can be easily modified to
off-vertical pipes by taking the g component along the pipe axis, as
follows:
1/4
o g sin d (pL-pG)
pl
(21)
Slug to Churn Transition Boundary: Pipe inclination has a substantial effect on this transition suppressing the chaotic nature of churn flow by enhancing the separation between the liquid slugs and the gas bubbles. As a result, the region of churn flow shrinks considerably in sharp inclination angles and disappears at about 70°. Thus, it is suggested that this narrow region of churn flow is considered part of the intermittent flow region.
3.3.2	— Downward Inclined Flow (-15°&amp;lt;6&amp;lt;-90°)
As opposed to upward inclined flow, for downward inclination angles the stratified region is considerably expanded and the slug flow region shrinks and occurs only at very high liquid flow rates. Also, for sharply inclined flow, namely —70°&lt;0 &amp;lt;—90°, annular flow occurs at low gas flow rates in the form of falling film, and there is a direct transition from stratified to annular flow. Flow pattern for downward inclination angles can be predicted by a modification of the Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler (5) model, as follows.
Stratified to Non-Stratified Transition Boundary: This transition boundary can be predicted accurately by the Taitel &amp;amp; DUKLER model in the whole range of downward inclined flow, as qiven by Eq. (5).
Stratified Smooth to Stratified Wavy Transition Boundary: Stratified smooth flow occurs in downward inclinations only in slightly inclined pipes (up to about —5°). Contrary to the case of horizontal or slightly inclined upward flow, for downward inclined flow waves are not generated by the gas shear on the interface. In this case, natural instability of the interface occurs also for pure gravity flow with negligible gas flow rates. Thus, Eq. (9) is not adequate to predict the stratified smooth stratified wavy transition for a downward configuration. Instead, a critical Froude number criterion is
Fig. 7 - General description of the flow pattern prediction computer library.
applied to predict this transition
Intermittent to Annular Transition Boundary: The criterion for this transition in the Taitel &amp;amp; DUKL.ER model is that when the amount of liquid in stratified flow is half of the amount in the liquid slug. This criterion is modified here to account for the gas void fraction in the liquid slug, which is assumed to be a —	0.3. Thus, the
modified criterion for this transition is hL/D = 0.5x0.7 = 0.35.
Slug to Dispersed Bubble Transition Boundary: As mentioned before, this transition is independent from pipe inclination angle. Thus, the prediction of this transition is given by Eq. (20).
Stratified to Annular (Falling Film) Transition Boundary: The proposed mechanism by which stratified flow is changed into annular flow at low gas flow rates is through liquid lumps which are torn away from a wavy turbulent interface and are thrown upward. Once the energy is sufficient to throw the liquid lumps all the way to the top wall, annular flow occurs. When this energy is not sufficient, stratified flow prevails. The mathematical form of this criterion is:
, J gD cos 9 (1 - hi/D)
Vl&gt;[—i—
(23)
3.4	— Flow Pattern Prediction for
Downward Vertical Flow (Barnea etal. (8))
The natural and dominant regime in downward vertical flow is the annular flow, which takes the form of falling film at low gas flow rates, and typical annular flow at high gas flow rates. Therefore the process of analyzing transition boundaries between the different flow patterns starts from conditions of annular flow.
Equilibrium Annular (Falling Film) Flow: For steady staté annular falling film flow, the combined momentum equation for the gas and the liquid phases is:
TjSj (—!_+ JL) +g (p|_ - Pq) -
AL Ag
-’■wL—=0	&lt;24&gt;
al
A solution of Eq. (24) yields S, the film thickness for a given set of data. Once S is known, one can calculate the phase velocities and the liquid holdup for a given set of flow conditions.
Annular to Slug Transition Boundary: The criterion for transition between annular to slug flow is based on the same concept as in the Taitel &amp;amp; Dukler horizontal model. It is assumed that a stable slug is formed when the liquid holdup in the slug is twice.the liquid holdup in annular flow. Assuming also that the gas void fraction
in a slug is 0.3, the transition to slug flow occurs at A|_/0.7A = 0.5 or Al/A = 0.35.
Dispersed Bubble Transition: Prediction of this transition is given by Eq. (20).
4	- GENERAL DESCRIPTION OF THE COMPUTER LIBRARY
The computer library for flow pattern prediction includes 25 subroutines written in FORTRAN 77. It can be applied mainly for two purposes:
1)	Flow Pattern Detection: For a given set of flow conditions, including gas and liquid flow rates, their physical properties, pipe diameter and angle of inclination, the existing flow pattern is determined. This option can be applied to monitor flow patterns when performing design calculations for pipelines or wellbores.
2)	Flow Pattern Transition Boundaries: For a given two-phase flow system, specifying gas and liquid physical properties, pipe diameter and inclination angle, the transition boundaries between the various flow patterns are determined as a function of the gas and liquid superficial velocities. The calculated transition boundaries can be plotted either by a plotter or by a printer in a form of flow pattern maps, using vg|_ and vgG as coordinates. This option provides important information needed for two-phase flow system design.
A general description of the library FLOPAT is given in figure 7. As shown, it consists of four "main" subroutines: FPDETC, FPTRAN, FPPRT and FPPLOT. The function of each of these "main" subroutines is as follows:
1.	FPDETC: This subroutine detects the flow pattern which exists for a given set of input flow data. The user of FPDETC must provide a main program which calls this subroutine.
2.	FPTRAN: This is a symbolic name given for a package of four subroutines which calculate the transition boundaries between the various flow patterns for a given system. These four subroutines are actually main programs, and each one performs calculations for different flow configurations.
2.1	TRNH:This subroutine calculates flow pattern transition boundaries
Superficial Gas Velocity (m/s)
Superficial Gas Velocity (m/s)

’* Flopat Computer Library "
DP = 0.406 E/D = 0.00044
RHOL = 761.900
RHOG = 92.7100
VISL = 0.0009150
VISG = 0.0000160
ALFA = 0.00
SIGMA = 0.0087
m
kg/rr? kg/rn kg/m/s kg/m/s degree newton/m
**Flopat Computer Library **
DP	=	0.076	m
E/D	=	0.01549	
RHOL	=	761.900	kg/n?
RHOG	=	92.7100	kg/rn
VISL	=	0.0009150	kg/m/s
VISG	=	0.0000160	kg/m/s
ALFA	=	90.00	degree
SIGMA	=	0.0087	newton/m
Fig. 8- Flow pattern map for a 016" horizontal pipeline (natural gas and crude oil @ 38°C &amp;amp; 68 atm.).
Fig. 9- Flow pattern map for a 03" vertical wellbore (natural gas and crude oil @ 38°C &amp;amp; 68 atm.).
for horizontal and near horizontal flow with inclination angles between —15 to + 15 degrees with the horizontal.
2.2TRID: The same as TRNH for steep downward inclined flow for —15°&lt;0&lt;—90°.
2.3TRUP: The same as TRNH, but for steep upward inclined flow between + 15 and + 90 degrees.
2.4	TRVD: The same as TRNH, but for vertical downward flow (inclination angle of —90 degrees).
3.	FPPRT: This subroutine is actually a main program which plots flow pattern maps with the printer. It gives distribution of the flow regimes, and the boundaries must be drawn by the user. The purpose of this subroutine is primarily to check the results given by the FPTRAN subroutines, and it can be used for verification purposes.
4.	FPPLOT: This subroutine is actually a main program which generates flow pattern maps using a HP 7475A Graphics Plotter. It uses the
transition boundaries calculated by the subroutines TRNH, TRID, TRUP and TRVD. These four subroutines provide a file to be used as an input to the plotter. If other plotters are used, this file should be accessed with the appropriate plotter programs.
Subroutines TRNH, TRID, TRUP and TRVD detect the existing flow pattern for a given set of data calling subroutines FPNH, FPID, FPUP and FPVD, respectively. All the other subroutines which appear in figure 7 are called by the above mentioned subroutines.
4.1	— Unit Systems
The computer library can be applied either with SI or with British units. However, all the calculations in the program are performed in SI units. When working in British units, the program converts the input data to SI units, and once the calculations are completed, the results are then converted back to British units. Thus, if
the user wants to output intermediate results, these are always in SI units.
5	- RESULTS
The applicability of the computer library is demonstrated in this section. Two flow pattern maps were developed, typical for the oil and gas industry.
Figure 8 shows the flow pattern map generated by the computer library for a 16" diameter horizontal pipeline carrying natural gas and crude oil at 38°C and 68 atm. Figure 9 shows the flow pattern map for a 3" vertical wellbore flowing the same fluids flowing under the same conditions. One simply changes an input variable such as inclination angle to get a flow pattern map for other conditions.
6	- CONCLUSIONS
A computer library written in FORTRAN 77 for flow pattern prediction in gas-liquid two phase flow has been developed. The library is capable of predicting the existing flow
pattern for all the possible range of inclination angles, namely —90° to + 90°. Also, the library can be applied with either the SI or the British unit systems.
The main applications of the computer library are to monitor flow patterns in pipes and to generate flow pattern maps for a given two-phase flow system. This information is essential for two-phase flow designs.
The results of the computer library are expected to be more reliable since it is based on analytical physical models, incorporating the effects of gas and liquid flow rates, physical properties, pipe diameter and inclination angle. This reliability is of primary importance when experimental data are not available.
NOMENCLATURE
Item	Description
A	cross-section area
ALFA	inclination angle
C	coefficient
D, DP	pipe diameter
E/D	relative roughness
f	Fanning friction factor
F	dimensionless group
g	acceleration of gravity
h	liquid level
K	dimensionless group
I	length
m	coefficient
n	coefficient
p	pressure
Re	Reynolds number
RHOG gas density
RHOL liquid density
s	Jeffrey's sheltering coefficient
S	perimeter
SIGMA surface tension
T	dimensionless group
v	velocity
VISG gas absolute viscosity
VISL liquid absolute viscosity
x	axial coordinate
X	dimensionless group
Y	dimensionless group
a	void fraction
v	kinematic viscosity
p	density
a	surface tension
9	inclination angle
t	shear stress
S	film thickness
Subscripts
E	entrance
G	gas
i	interface
L	liquid
M	mixture
S	superficial
W	wall
REFERENCES
I1) Mandhane, J. M., Gregory,
G.	A. &amp;amp; Aziz, K. A flow pattern map for gas liquid flow in horizontal pipes.	I nt.	J.
Multiphase Flow, 1: 537-53, 1974.
(2)	Griffith, P. &amp;amp; Wallis, G. B.
Two phase slug flow. J. Heat Trans. 3 (3): 307-20, Aug. 1961.
(3)	Govier, G. W. &amp;amp; Aziz, K. The
flow of complex mixtures in pipes. New York, Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1972.
(4)	SHOHAM, Ò. Flow pattern
transition and characterization in gas liquid twophase flow in inclined pipes. Tel-Aviv, Tel-Aviv University, 1982. Ph. D. Thesis.
(s) Taitel, Y. ? Dukler, A. E. A model for predicting flow regime transition in horizontal and near horizontal gas-liquid flow. AICHE J., 22 (1): 47-55, Jan. 1976.
(6) BARNEA, D. et alii. Flow pattern transition for upward inclined two phase flow; horizontal to vertical. Tel-Aviv, Tel-Aviv University, 1980.
C) Barnea, D., Shoham, O. &amp;amp; Taitel, Y. Flow pattern transition for downward inclined two phase flow; horizontal to vertical. Chem. Eng. Sci.,37 (5): 735-40, May 1982.
(8)	Barnea, D., Shoham, O. &amp;amp;
Taitel, Y. Flow pattern transition for vertical downward two-phase flow. Chem. Eng. Sci., 57 (5): 741-6, May 1982.
(9)	Taitel, Y., Barnea, D. &amp;amp;
Dukler, A. E. Modeling flow pattern transitions for steady upward gas-liquid flow in vertical tubes. AICHE j., 26 (3): 345-54, May 1980.
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
The authors wish to thank the Tulsa University Fluid Flow Projects for providing support for this project.
</field>
	</doc>
</add>