<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.15967</field>
		<field name="filename">22481_Master%20thesis_final%20version.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">




i 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

DEDICATORY 

This is a special recognition for the valuable effort of  

my parents and my little brother, 

 as well as all the people who have  

shared with me memorable  

life experiences during this time 



ii 

 

Acknowledgments 

 

The current work was carried out with the financial support of the Aquatic Ecology 

Laboratory (LEA) of Universidad San Francisco de Quito (USFQ) with the collaboration of 

the EVOTRAC project (Evolutionary and Ecological Variability in Organismal Trait 

Response with Altitude and Climate) and the funding of the MARE (Marine and 

Environmental Science Center) scholarship. 

This research started thanks to the confidence that Andrea Encalada had on me the 

first time that I knocked her door and was possible to continue with the support and 

patience of Manuel Graça, who accepted me as his master student in the University of 

Coimbra. Thanks to let me became part of your research groups and allow me to growth as 

a professional and as a person. I have no words to thank you enough for your trust in me 

and for your invaluable lessons.  

I appreciate the support of the researchers and field assistants, as well as laboratory 

technicians, who were involved over the different stages of this project.  

I want to thank specially to Maja Celinscak who worked with me in the experiment 

set up and material preparation for Ecuador and Colorado sites and also collaborate with the 

field trips, as well as José Schreckinger, who accompanied and help me with the samples 

collection and data information in Ecuador. I am grateful with Patricio Aigaje who was my 

assistant in the field and Luis Granizo. I appreciate the collaboration of Nathaly Quiroz and 

Andrea Tapia, who cooperated processing the samples. Thanks to all the laboratory team 

for the effort before, during and after the long days monitoring the streams. To Keeley 

MacNeil and Carla Atkinson, who work with me in the laboratory analyses in LEA 

laboratory. Thanks to Diana Muñoz to cooperate with this research voluntarily. 

One of the experiments could not be possible without the collaboration of Marisa 

Rojas, who collected, packed and transported the leaf material from Colorado to Ecuador. 



iii 

 

An special recognition to my friend and college Andrea Landeira and also to Alberto 

Puime, thank you both to prepare and process the samples, without you effort this part 

could not be possible. 

I really appreciate the patience of Veronica Ferreira while was teaching me the 

chemical-physical procedures in the laboratory and the statistical analyses. Special thanks 

to the technical support of Cristina Ducal during the chemical analyses. Thanks to Sonia 

Serra, Seena Saavedan and Olimpia Sobral for the logistical support in the laboratory, as 

well as to Dona Teresa to take care of the laboratory material when I was working in the 

MARE installations. 

Finally, but not less important I want to thanks to Fernanda Cássio and Claudia 

Pascoal, who allow me to performed the molecular analyses of my thesis in the Laboratory 

of Biodiversity at the University of Braga (Campus of Minho). I am especially grateful with 

Daniela Batista, who taught me the methodological steps for the denaturing gradient gel 

electrophoresis, as well as the support of Sofia Duarte and Isabel Fernandes and all the 

laboratory team who work with me during my short time there.  

This work have received valuable data from different students, technicians, 

researchers and PIs who have been involved in the EVOTRAC project, thanks for your help 

sending the information that has contribute to conclude this master thesis.  



iv 

 

ABSTRACT 

The microbial decomposition rate and species richness of aquatic fungi and bacteria 

were studied along an altitudinal gradient from 1600 to 3800 m.a.s.l. in Ecuador (tropical 

ecosystem at 0° Lat) and from 1992 to 3200 m.a.s.l. in Colorado US (temperate ecosystem 

at 40°N). Fine mesh bags (0.5 mm) containing native alder leaves from tropical (Alnus 

acuminata Kunth) and temperate (Alnus incana (L.) Moench) zones were incubated in five 

locations along the altitudinal gradient at each latitude and retrieved at selected sampling 

dates to decomposition rates and diversity of decomposers.  

Decomposition rates (k) were faster in Colorado (0.0197 - 0.0453 range) than in 

Ecuador (0.0065 - 0.014 range). In Ecuador litter decomposition decreased with elevation 

(linear regression, p &amp;lt;0.001; R
2 

= 0.95), which was explained by temperature difference 

across sites. In Colorado litter decomposition did not change with altitude (linear 

regression, p = 0.48; R
2 

&amp;lt;0.001) and was not related to any of the measured environmental 

parameters. Nitrates in Colorado were ~30 fold higher than in Ecuador (11.28 vs. 0.40 

µg/L; t-test, p = 0.04) and might be overridden the temperature effect.  

Microbial decomposers diversity was estimated applying the denaturing gradient gel 

electrophoresis (DGGE) technique and assessing the ribosomal DNA (rDNA) for aquatic 

fungi (ITS2 region) and bacteria (V3 variable region). Aquatic fungi diversity in Ecuador 

increased with elevation (linear regression, p = 0.03; R
2 

= 0.83), whereas in Colorado the 

maximum number of taxa peaked at middle altitudes (polynomial regression; p = 0.7; R
2 

= 

0.57). The three PCA axis in Ecuador explained 93% of the total variability and the number 

of fungal OTUs related with PO4. In Colorado, the three PCA axis explained 92% of the 

total variability and taxa richness was related with CPOM standing stock, shallow waters 

and moderate concentrations of NO3. The number of fungal taxa recorded in Ecuador and 

Colorado (13.3 and 15.2 OTUs) was not statistically different (t-test; p = 0.2; t =1.43;         



v 

 

df  = 8). The MDS analysis using Bray-Curtis similarity coefficient determined that fungi 

taxa is biogeographically distributed by latitude.  

Bacteria taxa units in Ecuador and Colorado decreased with altitude (linear 

regression; p = 0.0001; R
2 

= 0.58 and p = 0.0004; R
2 

= 0.99). The higher number of OTUs 

along the Ecuadorian gradient was primarily correlated with the 2
nd

 PCA axis, which in turn 

was correlated with CPOM standing stock, NO3 and NO2. In Colorado the taxa variability 

was negatively correlated with the first PCA axis, which was mainly correlated with 

temperature and NO3 concentrations. Bacteria community exhibited a cosmopolitan 

distribution (MDS; stress value: 0.19).  

The dissimilarity among communities along the altitudinal gradients (? diversity) 

was lower in Ecuador than in Colorado for aquatic fungi (ANOSIM, p = 0.51; Global R= 

0.004 vs. p = 0.003; Global R= 0.54) and bacteria (ANOSIM, p = 0.54; Global R= -0.021 

vs. p = 0.003; Global R= 0.51). 

These results suggest that (1) litter decomposition is a temperature dependent 

process, which can be overridden by other factors such as nutrients in the water. (2) Species 

richness and the community composition of microbial decomposers may be controlled by 

local environmental variables, such as dissolved nutrients in water and substrate 

characteristics (leaf quality), which may imply that broadly patterns observed on large 

organisms might not affect small size organisms. Besides, latitudinal species richness 

tendency might be barely observed along an altitudinal gradient, considering the 

temperature as the mainly environmental factor driving the diversity and the taxa turnover.  

 

Key words: microbial decomposition, temperature, latitude, altitude, OTUs. 

 



vi 

 

RESUMO 

A taxa de decomposição microbiana de folhas senescentes em rios e a riqueza em taxa 

de fungos e bactérias aquáticas foram estudados ao longo de um gradiente de altitude em dois 

sistemas, 1600-3800 m snm no Equador (ecossistema tropical a 0 ° Lat) e 1992-3200 m snm em 

Colorado EUA (ecossistema temperado a 40 ° N). Sacos de malha fina (0,5 mm) contendo 

folhas de amieiro nativo em cada una das zonas (Equador: Alnus acuminata Kunth; Colorado: 

Alnus incana (L.) Moench) foram incubadas em cinco locais ao longo do gradiente de altitude 

em cada latitude e recuperados em datas de amostragem selecionados para determinar as taxas 

de decomposição e a diversidade de decompositores. 

As taxas de decomposição (k) foram mais rápidos em Colorado (0,0197-0,0453 gama de 

valores) do que no Equador (0,0065 - 0.014). No Equador a decomposição diminuiu com a 

elevação (regressão linear, p&amp;lt;0,001; R
2
 = 0.95), o que foi explicado pela diferença de 

temperatura entre locais. Em Colorado a decomposição não mudo com a altitude (regressão 

linear, p = 0,48; R
2
&amp;lt;0,001) e não esteve ligada a nenhum dos parâmetros ambientais 

registrados. Os nitratos no Colorado foram ~ 30 vezes mais elevada do que no Equador (11,28 

vs 0,40 mg / L; t-test, p = 0.04) podendo o seu efeito sobrepor-se ao da temperatura. 

A diversidad de microrganismos decompositores foi estimada aplicando a eletroforese 

em gel com gradiente desnaturante (DGGE), avaliando o DNA ribossomal (rDNA) para fungos 

aquático (região ITS2) e bactérias (V3 região variável). A diversidade de fungos aquáticos no 

Equador aumentou com a elevação (regressão linear, p = 0.03; R
2
 = 0.83), enquanto no 

Colorado o número máximo de taxa atingiu um pico em altitudes médias (regressão polinomial; 

p = 0.7; R
2
 = 0.57). Os três primeiros eixos de uma “análise de componentes principais” (PCA) 

no Equador explicaram 93% da variabilidade total e o número de OTUs em fungos esteve 

relacionada com PO4, que foi maior nos locais mais altos e desceu para os locais mais baixos. 

No Colorado, os três eixos da PCA explicaram 92% da variabilidade total e a riqueza de taxa 

foi relacionada com CPOM, baixa profundidade da água e concentrações moderadas de NO3. O 

número de taxa para fungos registrados no Equador e no Colorado (13.3 e 15.2 OTUs) não foi 



vii 

 

estatisticamente diferente (teste t; p = 0.2; t = 1.43; df = 8). A análise MDS usando o coeficiente 

de similaridade de Bray-Curtis mostrou que a identidade dos OTUs em Colorado e Equador foi 

diferente. 

As unidades taxonómicas das bactérias no Equador e Colorado diminuiu com a altitude 

(regressão linear; p = 0,0001; R
2
 = 0.58 e p = 0.0004; R

2
 = 0.99, respetivamente). O maior 

número de OTUs ao longo do gradiente equatoriana foi correlacionado principalmente com o 

segundo eixo do PCA, que por sua vez se correlaciona com CPOM, NO3 e NO2. Em Colorado a 

variabilidade dos taxa foi negativamente correlacionada com o primeiro eixo do PCA, o qual foi 

correlacionado principalmente com concentrações de temperatura e NO3. A comunidade das 

bactérias exibiu uma distribuição cosmopolita, i.e., não houve diferenças na identidade entre 

Equador e Colorado (MDS; stress value: 0.19). 

A dissimilaridade entre as comunidades ao longo dos gradientes de altitude (? 

diversidade) foi menor no Equador do que em Colorado para fungos aquáticos (ANOSIM,        

p = 0.51; global R = 0.004 vs p = 0.003; global R = 0.54) e bactérias (ANOSIM, p = 0.54;         

R = -0.021 global vs. p = 0.003; global R = 0.51). 

Estes resultados sugerem que (1) A taxa de decomposição é um processo dependente da 

temperatura, mas que pode ser mascarada por outros fatores, tais como nutrientes na água. (2) A 

riqueza de espécies e a composição da comunidade de microrganismos decompositores pode ser 

controlada por variáveis ambientais locais, como os nutrientes dissolvidos na água e 

características de substrato (qualidade das folhas), o que sugere que os padrões observados em 

organismos de grandes dimensões pode não afetar aos organismos de menor tamanho. Além 

disso, a riqueza latitudinal de espécies pode ser dificilmente observada ao longo de um 

gradiente de altitude, caso a temperatura seja o principal fator ambiental que controla a 

diversidade e o turnover de espécies, uma vez que as alterações térmicas na água são menores 

do que for a dela. 

Palabras-chave: decomposição microbiana, temperature, latitude, altitude, OTUs.  



viii 

 

INDEX 

1. GENERAL INTRODUCTION .............................................................................................. 1 

1.1 Latitudinal Patterns in Ecology ................................................................................................. 2 

1.2 Altitudinal patterns of species richness ..................................................................................... 3 

1.3 Stream ecosystem processes at different latitudes and elevations ............................................ 4 

1.4 Microbial communities as key players of organic matter processing ....................................... 5 

1.5 Molecular techniques ................................................................................................................ 6 

1.6 Thesis hypotheses ..................................................................................................................... 8 

2. CHAPTER I...............................................................................................................................  

Microbial leaf litter decomposition along altitudinal gradients in tropical and temperate streams ...... 9 

2.1 Introduction ............................................................................................................................. 10 

2.2 Methodology ........................................................................................................................... 12 

2.3 Results ..................................................................................................................................... 19 

2.4 Discussion ............................................................................................................................... 21 

3. CHAPTER II ......................................................................................................................... 27 

Microbial decomposers diversity in tropical and temperate streams along an altitudinal gradient .... 27 

3.1 Introduction ............................................................................................................................. 28 

3.2 Methodology ........................................................................................................................... 32 

3.3 Results ..................................................................................................................................... 37 

3.3.1 Aquatic fungi........................................................................................................................... 37 

3.3.2 Bacteria ................................................................................................................................... 38 

3.4 Discussion ............................................................................................................................... 40 

3.4.1 Aquatic fungi........................................................................................................................... 40 

3.4.2 Bacteria ................................................................................................................................... 44 

4. GENERAL CONCLUSIONS AND PERSPECTIVES ...................................................... 49 

5. TABLES ................................................................................................................................. 53 

6. FIGURES ............................................................................................................................... 58 

7. ANNEX .................................................................................................................................. 66 

8. REFERENCES ...................................................................................................................... 75 



ix 

 

 
LIST OF TABLES  

Table 1. Geographical coordinates and temperatures (mean and range, recorded during the 

experiments) for the 10 streams in the tropical and temperate systems. E = Ecuador C = Colorado, 

USA. Average temperature (±SE). ................................................................................................ 54 

Table 2. Riparian vegetation and bed stream characterization for tropical and temperate streams 

(mean ± SD). The site code refers to the place (E= Ecuador, C = Colorado) and altitude. ........... 54 

Table 3. Physical and chemical parameters of the tropical sites (mean ± SD; n = 5) ................... 55 

Table 4. Differences among streams for several environmental parameters. ANOVA (F) or Kruskal 

Wallys (H) when data was not normally distributed. Oxygen was subjected to an arc-sin 

transformation. Degrees of freedom (df) for all the parameters were equal to 4. .......................... 56 

Table 5. Physical and chemical parameters collected once during the decomposition experiment for 

the temperate streams .................................................................................................................... 56 

Table 6. Decomposition rates (k), p values and R squares for each altitude applying the exponential 

decay model. .................................................................................................................................. 57 

Table 7. Initial litter quality of both Alnus leaves species used in this study (mean±SD) where all the 

variables were significantly different. ........................................................................................... 57 

 

LIST OF FIGURES 

Figure 1. Mean of benthic fine (red bars) and coarse (blue bars) particulate organic matter (mean± 

SE) for the 5 tropical streams along the altitudinal gradient. ........................................................ 59 

Figure 2. Breakdown (k/day) of A. acuminate (Ecuador, red squares) and A. incana (Colorado, blue 

triangles) along elevation gradients and respective regression parameters. .................................. 59 

Figure 3. Decay rates expressed in terms of degree days related with the elevation for tropical and 

temperate latitudes. Equations, R squares and p values are included. ........................................... 60 

Figure 4. Decomposition rates of Alnus acuminate (red) and Alnus incana (blue) in their respective 

native range area (2013) and the second (2014) essay in the Ecuadorian site (E2838) to compare the 

differences of litter decomposition under the same environmental variables. Bars represent the mean 

± SE. .............................................................................................................................................. 60 

Figure 5. Temporal dynamic of aquatic fungi OTUs during leaf litter decomposition for a) Ecuador 

and b) Colorado streams. Percentages indicate the remaining mass (RM) for each sample after 32 

and 28 days for both latitudes and further details of decomposition are described in the Table 6, 

Chapter 1. ...................................................................................................................................... 61 

Figure 6.  a) Linear regression between elevation vs number of aquatic fungi OTUs pooled by site 

for Ecuador and b) polynomial regression (order 2) for Colorado gradient. The number of bands 

were counted from the acrylamide gels detailed in the Annex 8. .................................................. 61 

Figure 7.  PCA calculated with the environmental variables collected from the five streams along 



x 

 

the altitudinal gradient in Ecuador. Axes 1, 2 and 3 explained 92.9% of the total variability (Axis 1: 

47.7%; Axis 2: 26%; Axis 3: 19.2%).  a) Axis 1 and 2 and b) Axis 1 and 3. The first axis was 

positively related with higher pH values and negatively with higher phosphates concentrations in 

water and FPOM. The second axis was associated with higher levels of nitrites, nitrates and CPOM. 

The third axis was negatively related with temperature and ammonia and negatively with depth.62 

Figure 8. PCA analysis for Colorado streams with the environmental variables. The three principal 

axis of the PCA explained 91.8% of the biological variability (Axis 1: 52.2%; Axis 2: 29.2%; Axis 

3: 10.4%). a) Axis 1 and 2 and b) Axis 1 and 3. The fist axis was positively related with discharge 

and negative related with temperature and nitrates. The second axis was negatively related with 

width, depth and CPOM. Axis 3 was mainly associated with nitrates. ......................................... 63 

Figure 9. MDS performed with Bray-Curtis similarity separated the tropical (left) and the temperate 

(right) sites (stress value = 0.17). .................................................................................................. 64 

Figure 10. Temporal dynamic of bacteria communities for the 10 low order streams in a) Ecuador 

and b) Colorado over time. ............................................................................................................ 64 

Figure 11. Relationship between the total number of bacteria OUT recorded in the a) tropical and b) 

temperate streams, during the three and four sampling dates, respectively. The number of bands, 

considered as OTUs are detailed in the Annex 14. ........................................................................ 65 

Figure 12. MDS performed with Bray-Curtis similarity among tropical (red squares) and temperate 

(blue triangles) streams .................................................................................................................. 65 

 

LIST OF ANNEX 

Annex 1. Representation of fungal and bacteria rRNA sequences used for molecular analyses. a) 

ITS region diagram based on the illustrations published by White et al. (1990) and Karp (2005). b) 

Variable regions within the 16S rRNA gene of E.coli as a model organism. The arrows depict the 

primer sets selected in this study to assess the fungal ITS2 region (ITS3GC/ ITS4) and the V3 

region of bacteria (338GC/518) to determine their community assemblage. ................................ 67 

Annex 2. Map of the five head order streams a) Ecuador (tropical latitude) and b) Colorado 

(temperate latitude). The square within each figure (left) show the study area for each system, which 

is amplified (right) to visualize the streams along the altitudinal gradient where the study was 

carried out. Table 1 contains the site names and the geographical coordinates for each site ........ 67 

Annex 3. IHF Scores for the 5 study sites are above 75%, meaning lower anthropogenic impact and 

a suitable environment for the benthic macroinvertebrates development. .................................... 68 

Annex 4. Quality of riparian vegetation according the QBR (? 96 Very good; 76-95 = Good). .. 68 

Annex 5. Protocol of Power Soil DNA Isolation Kit (MO BIO Laboratories, Inc.) ..................... 68 

Annex 6. Reagent concentrations for acrylamide matrix denaturant gradient. LD = Low density; HD 

= High density ............................................................................................................................... 69 

Annex 7. Species of aquatic hyphomycetes and bacteria amplified from pure cultures and used as 



xi 

 

reference bands for the gel alignment ............................................................................................ 69 

Annex 8. DGGE gels (a-c) with the fungal communities? fingerprinting during the decomposition in 

the 10 low order streams. M = Mix of pure fungal cultures used for the alignment. The sample 

E1645_32 was amplified twice due to PCR inconveniences. The figure 6.d shows the second 

amplification. ................................................................................................................................. 70 

Annex 9. Eigenvectors or coefficients in the linear combinations of variables for the five axis 

determined in the PCA for Ecuador. Values with r &gt; ? 0.4? in bold. .............................................. 71 

Annex 10. Correlation coefficients (r) calculated between the scores determined by the five axis of 

the PCA for Ecuadorian streams and the total number of OTUs for microbial decomposers (aquatic 

fungi and bacteria). ........................................................................................................................ 71 

Annex 11. Principal Component Scores determined by the PCA on the environmental variables 

performed for the Colorado streams. ............................................................................................. 71 

Annex 12. Eigenvectors for the five principal axes calculated by the PCA analysis with the 

environmental variables for Colorado. Values with r &gt; ? 0.4? in bold. ........................................... 72 

Annex 13. Cluster analyses with Bray-Curtis similarity and UPGM group linkage method of 24 

samples of aquatic fungi from the tropical (squares) and the temperate (triangles) streams. ........ 72 

Annex 14. Bacteria community fingerprint displayed in the DGGE gels for samples in the tropical 

and temperate streams along the altitudinal gradient recovered different dates over the litter 

breakdown. M = Mix of pure bacteria cultures used for the alignment. Samples? identification 

follows the same criteria as explained for the fungal fingerprinting. ............................................ 73 

Annex 15. Bacteria dendogram with Bray- Curtis similarity of 24 samples from Ecuador (E;  

squares) and Colorado (C; triangles). ............................................................................................ 74 

Annex 16. Species of aquatic hyphomycetes recorded in the five low order streams in Ecuador. The 

morphological identification of spores was induced incubating leaf pieces of Alnus acuminate 

Kunth. retrieved from fine mesh bags after 30 days of submersion in the streams (1
st
 of February to 

3 of March of 2014). ...................................................................................................................... 74 

  



1 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

1. GENERAL INTRODUCTION 



2 

 

1.1 Latitudinal Patterns in Ecology  

One of the most recognizable ecological patterns on the earth is the variation in 

species composition and diversity among geographic locations (Willig et al. 2003; 

Hawkins and Felizola 2004). These patterns, depending on the scale, are mostly controlled 

by geographic isolation, evolutionary history, global and local climate and species 

interactions (Willig et al. 2003).  

Von Humboldt described higher diversity patterns at tropical latitudes and a gradual 

decrease towards to the poles. Subsequently, numerous examples in a wide range of taxa 

have been documented (Rosenzwig 1992; Rex et al. 2005; Willig 2003). For instance, in 

North America higher diversity of butterflies occurs at lower latitudes (Kocher and 

Williams 2000) and on a global scale this gradient is corroborated in gastropods, 

freshwater and marine fishes, amphibians, certain migrant and non-migrant birds, bats and 

many other mammals, as well as with plants in terrestrial ecosystems (Gaston 2000; Willig 

et al. 2003; Rex et al. 2005). However, there are exceptions to the latitude-richness trend.  

For instance, aquatic macrophytes are more diverse in the median - higher latitudes  and 

parasite richness is not directly related with latitude (Willig et al. 2003).  

Several explanations have been proposed to explain the taxa richness – latitude 

relationship. One of the explanations is the species-area relationship, which states that 

larger areas house larger number of species because of larger populations sizes and lower 

extinction rates (MacArthur and Wilson 1963). The terrestrial and ocean areas in the 

tropics have larger areas that higher latitudes and therefore most likely to harbor a larger 

number of taxa (Rex et al. 2005; Brown 2014). Another theory relates species richness 

with primary production (Waide et al. 1999; Brown 2014) because allows large 

populations and narrower niches (Waide et al. 1999; Mittelback et al. 2001; Schmid 

2002). Other theories relate taxa richness with climatic stability (Hawkins and Felizola 

2004; Brown 2014), the diversification time and biotic factors such as competition and 



3 

 

predation (Pianka 1966; Molles 2010). Nevertheless, the species richness distribution can 

be the consequences of several non-exclusive factors.  

The mean and annual temperature variations differ along the latitudinal gradient. In 

the tropics, temperature tends to be more stable along the year compared with the higher 

latitudes where larger annual seasonality is recorded. Hence, tropical species are 

evolutionary adapted to experience narrow changes of temperature and as a consequence, 

these organisms might show limited dispersion ability (Janzen 1967). Thereby, 

temperature regimes would be determining the distribution of species because of their 

thermal tolerance ranges.  

 

1.2 Altitudinal patterns of species richness 

Since the temperature decreases with the latitude and with the elevation, is it could 

be expected that the altitudinal gradient would mirror the latitudinal pattern in biological 

structural and functional parameters. On the other hand, if species dispersion depends of 

physiological constrains (narrower thermal niche) more than geographical barriers 

(mountains) as Janzen proposed (1967) and temperature fluctuation in altitude do not  

mirror temperature fluctuations in latitude, at lower latitudes I expect a higher species 

replacement across  altitudinal gradients than at higher latitudes (see Chapter II). 

Furthermore, according to the Island Biogeography theory developed by MacArthur and 

Wilson (1963) that predict that higher number of species are likely to inhabit in larger 

spatial areas;  as the elevation increases, the surface area becomes narrow (Körner 2007) 

and as a consequence, the lower altitudes would support higher diversity than higher 

altitudes. 

As expected, species riches in hummingbirds in the Andean mountains in South 

America and wild bees in the German Alps decrease with altitude (Graham et al. 2009; 

Hoiss et al. 2012). Nonetheless, other taxonomic groups like leaf litter ants in the Western 



4 

 

USA and non-endemic birds in the Hendgduam Mountains at East Asia, display a hump 

shaped curve, a peak of diversity in middle elevations (Sanders 2002; Wu et al. 2013). 

 

1.3 Stream ecosystem processes at different latitudes and elevations 

 

As the diversity increases from the poles toward to the equatorial line and from 

high to lower altitudes, it is plausible that temperature (and other related factors) would be 

pivotal variables controlling key ecosystem processes; thus biological rates might be 

higher near to the tropics and at lower altitudes, as predicts the metabolic theory of 

ecology (MTE; Brown et al. 2004). The transformation (uptake and allocation) from food 

resources into energy by organisms is catalyzed by enzymatic activities, which obeys to 

the physic laws. Thus, the rate of the reactions would depend of the kinetic energy 

available in the environment, meaning that higher temperatures will accelerate the 

metabolic rates, as is explained by the Boltzmann factor (e
-E/kT

) (Brown et al. 2004). 

Freshwater lotic systems, receive at least 2 billon tons of terrestrial organic and 

inorganic carbon inputs each year. This material is transported by streams, rivers and 

groundwater fluxes to the sea (Cole et al. 2007) or processed (decomposed, incorporated 

into living mass) in situ. In forested low order streams, allochthonous organic matter make 

up around 41-98% of energy incorporated into the aquatic food web by many 

microorganisms and macroinvertebrates (Fisher and Likens 1973; Abelho 2005). Once 

that the leaves enter into streams, their soluble compounds are released into the water 

(leaching), they are colonized by microorganisms such as bacteria and fungi, consumed by 

macroinvertebrate shredders and fragmented by physical abrasion (Hieber and Gessner 

2002). High water temperatures (Suberkropp and Chauvet 1995; Fernandes et al. 2009; 

Geraldes et al. 2012) dissolved nutrients in streams (Gulis and Suberkropp 2003; Ferreira 

et al. 2006; Ferreira and Chauvet 2011a) and flow (Ferreira and Graça 2006; dos Santos 

Fonseca et al. 2013), enhance litter decomposition rates. In addition, intrinsic leaf features 



5 

 

that encompasses chemical and physical characteristics, such as toughness and defense 

compounds also control the rates of litter decomposition (Ferreira and Chauvet 2011b; 

Rezende et al. 2014).  

 

1.4 Microbial communities as key players of organic matter processing 
 

Studies carried out in temperate streams have determined the major decomposer of 

leaf litter is a group of microorganisms identified as aquatic hyphomycetes, which 

macerate the organic substrate and improve its palatability for other consumers, 

particularly macroinvertebrates (Maharning and Barlocher 1996; Graça and Canhoto 

2006; Bärlocher 2010; Ferreira and Chauvet 2011b).  Environmental variables such as pH, 

oxygen saturation, nutrient availability in the water and particularly the temperature, play 

a pivotal role determining rates of microbial activities and shaping species assemblages, 

specifically regarding aquatic hyphomycetes (Dangles et al. 2004; Medeiros et al. 2009; 

Duarte et al. 2013; Martínez et al. 2014). 

Microcosms assays revealed that several fungi species differ in their optimal 

temperature for growth and sporulation, displaying optimal performance within variables 

ranges of temperature depending of their origin (Duarte et al. 2006; Geraldes et al. 2012; 

Ferreira et al. 2014). If temperature affects biological performance of aquatic fungi, it also 

has the capability to affect ecological functions such as litter decomposition. In fact, this 

assumption has been corroborated by some authors who report a positive relationship 

between higher loss mass rate and fungal biomass (Maharning and Barlocher 1996; 

Ferreira et al. 2012).  

There is a succession in fungal communities through the decomposition, in which 

taxa specialized in lignin and cellulose are more frequent at the end of the process due to 

the rapid loss of easily digested compounds at the beginning of the process (Dodds 2002; 

Royer and Minshall 2003). In more advanced stages of decomposition, bacteria start 



6 

 

replacing fungi as the main decomposers of small particles of organic matter (Gessner 

1997). Laboratory experiments have determined that temperature modify the aquatic 

fungal community composition and the litter processing can be stimulated, inhibited or 

affected depending of the thermal conditions tested (5-24°C) and the species identity 

involved in the assays (Fernandes et al. 2012; Geraldes et al. 2012; Duarte et al. 2013; 

Martínez et al. 2014).  

Since aquatic fungi species differ in their temperature niche (Fernandes et al. 2012; 

Jabiol et al. 2013) and assuming that their thermal tolerance range is wider in the species 

from temperate than from tropical latitudes (Sridhar and Bärlocher 1993), it is likely to 

expect faster replacement of species along the tropical gradient than in the temperate one.  

 

1.5 Molecular techniques 

 

Traditionally, the identification of aquatic hyphomycetes has been performed 

microscopically by conidia (asexual spores) morphology recognition, which makes it a 

high consuming method (Maharning and Barlocher 1996). Moreover, it is plausible that 

many species are unable to produce spores under laboratory conditions and others have 

not been described in the available keys (Duarte et al. 2007; Bärlocher and Marvanová 

2010). Molecular techniques has become a useful, quick and reliable tool to overcome 

these drawbacks, because they allow to distinguish between genotypes within a 

community, assessing an specific DNA region called genetic or molecular marker 

(Maharning and Barlocher 1996; Bärlocher 2007; Duarte et al. 2012), which is defined as 

a gene or non-coding segment within the genome of organisms that displays enough 

genetic variability (Schlötterer 2004). 

Different markers have been developed for fungi and bacteria identification, based 

on the polymorphism of the ribosomal genes, located within the RNA sequence (rRNA) 

(White et al. 1990; Karp 2005; Bärlocher 2007). The nuclear Internal Transcribed Spacer 



7 

 

or known as ITS region is useful for fungal phylogenetic and taxonomical analysis (White 

et al. 1990; Bruns et al. 1991; Muyzer et al. 1993) and specifically the ITS2 region (Annex 

1.a) has proved to be a suitable sequence to assess the taxa diversity in aquatic fungi 

(Belliveau and Bärlocher 2005; Bärlocher 2007, 2010; Duarte et al. 2007, 2010). Unlike 

eukaryotic organisms, the bacteria identification is assessed amplifying the variable 

regions from the 16S rRNA sequence (Annex 1.b), which encodes the small ribosomal 

subunit in prokaryotes (Muyzer et al. 1993; Karp 2005). Both molecular markers display 

slow mutation rates that allow the identification of taxonomical units within a microbial 

community (White et al. 1990; Muyzer et al. 1993). 

The target sequences are amplified by the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and 

then resolved in a polyacrylamide gel by electrophoresis, which allows the separation of 

the segments through the pores of the matrix applying electric fields. The amplified 

sequence are visualized as bands in the gel (Karp 2005) and they are consider as 

operational taxonomic unit (OTU), which are not equivalent to species in large organisms 

(Fuhrman 2009). The use of fingerprinting techniques, such as the denaturing gradient gel 

electrophoresis (DGGE), provide the genetic diversity profile of the microbial community 

(Muyzer and Smalla, 1998). In this technique, the amplified fragments with the same 

length are denatured by the chemical gradient (formamide and urea concentrations) and 

then each molecule gets halt when the double strand is separated according to the Guanine 

(G) and Citocine (C) content. It means that GC- rich sequences stop the migration in the 

gel at higher denaturing gradients, which remains attached by a GC tail of 40-bp added 

during the amplification reaction (Muyzer et al. 1993; Muyzer and Smalla 1998; Duarte et 

al. 2007).  

Molecular techniques allow inferences of taxa richness and environmental factors 

in situations in which poor taxonomical expertise are limiting factors and in which there 

fauna and flora are poorly known. This is particularly important when dealing with 



8 

 

microorganisms in the environment. It is plausible that is short time molecular techniques 

will be common in studies addressing the identity and the role of microorganisms in the 

environment. 

 

1.6 Thesis hypotheses 

 

Here I am testing five hypothesis relating diversity, function and biogeography. 

The two first hypotheses relate temperature with function. If temperature controls 

metabolism then, within a same geographic area, litter decomposition should decrease 

with an increase in elevation since temperature predictably decrease with altitude 

(Hypothesis 1).  In the same way, microbial decomposition rates are expected to be faster 

at lower than higher latitudes (Hypothesis 2). The other two hypotheses relate diversity 

with elevation. If the distribution of species richness depends of the thermal tolerance of 

organisms then, species diversity (? diversity) of bacterial and fungi would decrease with 

increasing elevation because thermal fluctuations increase with elevation (Hypothesis 3) 

and higher microbial diversity is expected toward to the tropics (Hypothesis 4). Finally, 

microbial species turnover rates would be higher in the tropical gradients (? diversity) 

while we expect them to be lower at temperature gradients (Hypothesis 5). 

To test these previous hypotheses I run litter decomposition experiments in two 

latitudes: tropical (Ecuador) and temperate (United States, Colorado) systems and along 

an elevation gradient in both latitudes. Hypotheses 1 and 2 will be addressed in chapter 1 

whereas hypotheses 3, 4 and 5 will be addressed in chapter 2.  

This research is part of a large scale project called EVOTRAC (Evolutionary and 

Ecological Variability in Organismal Trait Response with Altitude and Climate; Poff, et 

al. 2010), which main goal is predict the vulnerability of the organisms associated to the 

freshwater systems due to the climate change using elevation gradients as a model to 

foresee changes in the biological processes and community structure.



9 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 
 

 

2. CHAPTER I 

 

 

Microbial leaf litter decomposition along altitudinal gradients in 

tropical and temperate streams 

 

 

 

 



10 

 

 

2.1 Introduction 

The main energy source of the aquatic organisms in low order streams is the organic 

matter produced in the riparian zone (Vannote et al. 1980). Leaf litter material is 

transformed and incorporated into higher levels of the food web by the action of microbial 

decomposers and detritivores (Baldy et al. 1995; Gessner 1997; Graça et al. 2001). In the 

first stages of the decomposition, aquatic hyphomycetes colonize the leaves (conditioning) 

decomposing the substrate due to their exoenzymes activity and enhancing the palatability 

for macroinvertebrates (Graça 2001; Hieber and Gessner 2002; Bärlocher 2010). Variables 

such as leaf quality (Lecerf et al. 2007), nutrients dissolved in water (Gulis and 

Suberkropp 2004; Ferreira et al. 2006) and temperature (Boyero et al. 2011; Ferreira and 

Chauvet 2011b; Martínez et al. 2014) can retard or hasten the litter breakdown. 

Leaves with high leaf quality (high nitrogen concentration and low lignin content) 

tend to decompose faster than low quality leaves (Hobbie 2005; Lecerf et al. 2007; 

Schindler and Gessner 2009). Since aquatic hyphomycetes are the main microbial 

decomposer in low order streams, their activity has being associated with the intrinsic leaf 

features and its influence with the decomposition rate. Aquatic fungi grow faster and 

reproduce earlier on leaf substrates rich in nutrients with low concentrations of 

polyphenolic compounds (Canhoto and Graça 1996; Ferreira et al. 2012). Likewise,  

tougher leaves are also more difficult to decompose by fungi (Ferreira and Chauvet 

2011a). 

Although nutrients in the leaves are important determining the decomposition rates, 

aquatic hyphomycetes are also able to uptake nutrients from the water column (Ferreira et 

al. 2014). Nitrogen enrichment in streams stimulates fungal activity (e.g. growth, conidia 

production) and accelerate the decomposition rates despite the poor quality of the substrate 

(Gulis and Suberkropp 2003; Taylor and Chauvet 2014). Similar observations were 



11 

 

reported for phosphorous (Grattan and Suberkropp 2001). Consistently, microcosms and 

field studies revealed that an increment of both, nitrogen and phosphorous concentrations 

in water, increase fungal biomass, sporulation and microbial respiration; and consequently, 

stimulate litter breakdown. The effect of higher levels of nutrients in the decomposition 

rates is more noticeable when the background conditions have lower concentrations 

(Ferreira and Chauvet 2011a; Grattan and Suberkropp 2001; Ferreira et al. 2014). 

 Temperature also affects litter decomposition under laboratory conditions (Ferreira 

and Chauvet 2011b; Fernandes et al. 2012) and large scale studies suggest that 

temperature microbial stimulation is more important at lower latitudes (Irons et al. 1994; 

Boyero et al. 2011). However, even when microbial activity seems to hasten leaf litter 

processing near to the equatorial line, others studies have reported lower microbial 

decomposition rates and lower fungal activity (e.g. sporulation) in the tropics compare 

with higher latitudes (Ferreira et al. 2012; Gonçalves et al. 2006, 2007). These results 

suggesting that aquatic hyphomycetes may be playing a minor role in litter processing at 

tropics streams in contrast with previous reports.  

Since temperature decreases 6ºC every 900 m in altitude increase (Sarmiento 1986; 

Dudgeon 2008; NASA 2014), I may speculate that changes in altitudinal gradients in 

mountains could mirror changes in latitudinal gradients regarding biological diversity and 

ecological functional parameters, given the relationship between temperature and 

metabolism (Brown et al. 2004). In a recent study, Taylor and Chauvet (2014) documented 

an increase of microbial litter breakdown rates along a river altitudinal gradient, with 

higher rates in downstream sites. Authors concluded that temperature was the main 

environmental factor driving the decomposition. At present, it would be critical to analyze 

whether microbial litter breakdown decreases in a similar fashion along both latitudinal 

and altitudinal gradients. 

Given that litter breakdown is a biological process that depends on the enzymatic 



12 

 

activity of microbial decomposers and knowing that the rate at which the molecules are 

transformed depend of the kinetic energy available, which is measured as temperature; 

higher metabolic rates are expected at higher temperatures due to an increment of the 

enzymatic transformations (Brown et al. 2004).  

The objective of this study was to test whether litter breakdown in streams changes 

along an altitudinal gradient in lower and higher latitudes according to the metabolic 

theory. If temperature is the major controller of microbial decomposition, I am expecting 

higher decomposition rates in the tropical streams than in the temperate ones, and a 

decrease in litter decomposition with an increase in elevation. In order to test these 

hypotheses, this study was carried out in low order streams within an altitudinal gradient 

(from 1600 to 3800 m.a.s.l.) in two latitudes: the tropic (Ecuador) and the temperate 

(Colorado, USA) zones using native congeneric Alnus species as the substrate deployed in 

lotic ecosystems. 

 

2.2 Methodology 

Study sites 

The hypothesis was tested in 10 first order streams located along an elevation 

gradient in two latitudes: Ecuador (tropical ecosystem at 0? Lat; five streams) and 

Colorado, United States (temperate ecosystem at 40? Lat; five streams). The tropical sites 

are localized in Oyacachi sub-basin at the Andean Cordillera in the Napo catchment area 

(Amazon Basin) within a gradient from 1645 to 3847 m.a.s.l. The temperate streams are 

located at the Rocky Mountains Range in the Cache Poudre Basin along an altitudinal 

gradient spanning from 1992 to 3200 m.a.s.l. (Table 1, Annex 2). The tree line was located 

at 3000 m.a.s.l. in Ecuador and the riparian vegetation was composed by herbaceous plants 

in the upper sites, whereas in the lower locations the streams were covered by dense tree 

canopy. There is a gradual increase in shrub and tree diversity along the gradient being 



13 

 

always higher at the tropical site compared with the temperate region. In Ecuador the 

vegetation in the highlands was characterized for scrublands such as Calamagrostic sp.and 

Festuca sp., Andean bogs (Azorella spp.) and several shrubs (Gynoxis spp., Diplostephium 

spp.). In the lower sites the arboreal vegetation includes species such as Symplocos 

quitensis, Buddleja bullata, Alnus  acuminata Kunth., Weinmannia sp. and Myrica 

pubescens.  Wider daily temperature fluctuations is registered between 3000 and 4500 

m.a.s.l. (Rendón 2012). Higher rainfall was registered along the gradient. In Colorado the 

vegetation above the 2700 m is mainly dominated by Picea abies, whereas the lower sites 

are characterized by Pinus spp. and Alnus incana. Markedly seasonality is recorded during 

the year, with intermediated (&amp;lt;2700) and persistent (&gt;3000 m.a.s.l.) snow cover areas 

(Harrington et al. 2015). Geology in Ecuador is characterized by inceptisol type (MAGAP 

2012) and by gypsiferous for Colorado (Waltz 1969). 

 

Streams characterization  

Selected streams for both latitudes were pristine or with low anthropogenic impact. 

For each sampling site, canopy cover was estimated with a spherical densiometer in three 

points of the stream within a 100 m section and then averaged to obtain the total measure 

for each sampling site. At each location 4 counts were made facing upstream, right, left 

and downstream. For tropical sites, two indices were applied to characterize the quality of 

the stream bed (fluvial habitat quality index; IFH; Annex 3) and the quality of the riparian 

vegetation  (QBR; Acosta et al. 2009; Annex 4).   

During the study period (see below) stream water temperature was recorded hourly 

for each site with submersed data loggers (Solinst Levelogger Junior Edge Water Level 

Loggers). Only for one tropical site E1805, the temperature was registered in situ with 

point measurements using a field probe (YSI 63) once at each sampling date.  

For tropical streams, conductivity and pH (field probe YSI 63), dissolve oxygen 



14 

 

(field probe YSI 550A) as well as water discharge, were measured five times during the 

experiments (details below). For nutrients analysis, 150 mL of stream water were 

collected, filtered through fiber glass filters (47 mm ø, pore size 0.7µm; Milipore, MA, 

USA), transported in an ice chest to the laboratory, and frozen at -20° C until being 

processed. Phosphorus was determined using the ascorbic acid method and read at 885 nm 

(Algilent Technologies, Cary 60 UV-Vis). Nitrates were measured with the cadmium 

reduction method (detection limit: 0.3 to 30.0 mg/L NO3
-
N), nitrites were determined with 

the diazotization method (detection limit: 0.002 to 0.300 mg/L NO2
-
N), sulfates by the 

SulfaVer 4 method (detection limit: 2 to 7 mg/L SO4
2-

) and ammonia measurements were 

performed by salicylate method (detection limit: 0.01 to 0.50 mg/L NH3-N), all of them 

using a Hatch kit (Hatch Company). 

In the temperate streams, all physic-chemical measurements were performed only 

once during the experiment: conductivity and pH (field probe YSI30), dissolve oxygen 

(field probe YSI proODO) and discharge. For the nutrients analysis, water was collected 

in the same fashion than in the tropical sites and once in the laboratory water nitrates were 

measured using a Dionex 1100 ion chromotography  and phosphates were analyzed by the 

ascorbic acid method using the Asoria2 Segmented flow analyzer (Astoria-Pacific, 

Clackamas, OR).  

At both, tropical and temperate sites, fine benthic organic matter (FBOM) was 

sampled using a hollow cylinder device placed in a flat area on the stream bed. Sediments 

in the bottom were vigorously agitated and 1L of the confined water was filtered (250 mL) 

using pre-weighed glass fiber filters (47 mm diameter GFF Whatman filters, USA) with a 

field vacuum pump. Three samples were collected at each sampling occasion. Each filter 

was transported to the laboratory into an aluminum envelope within an ice cooler and 

froze at -20° C until be oven dried (70° C for 48 h), burned (550° C for 4 h) and weighed 

to estimate ash free dry mass (AFDM), which was expressed in mass weight per area 



15 

 

(g/m
2
) for each date. FBOM was averaged for the dates collected at each sites to perform 

further analyses (detailed below).  

At both, tropical and temperate sites, coarse particulate organic matter (CPOM) 

was collected along three random transects perpendicular to the stream, using a surber net 

bottom sampler (30 cm x 30 cm; 0.5 mm pore size). The CPOM samples collected across 

each transect were transported in individual Ziploc bags to the laboratory in an ice chest. 

Once in the laboratory, samples were air dried for 24 hours, oven dried (70° C for 48 h), 

weighed and ignited (550° C for 4 h) to calculate the AFDM. Due to logistical constrains 

the CPOM samples in Colorado were not ignited, but their AFDM was calculated 

multiplying the DM coefficient of Colorado samples by a correction factor (0.77), which 

was obtained from the relationship between DM/AFDM in the Ecuadorian samples 

collected in this study and calculated with unpublished data collected in a decomposition 

experiment carried out in Portugal by several authors (Capps et al. 2011; Graça and 

Poquet 2014; Ferreira 2014, personal communications). 

 

Litter decomposition experiment  

Microbial litter decomposition was measured using the litter bag method (15 x 17 

cm, 0.5 mm mesh size). Alnus acuminata Kunth (tropical species) leaves were gathered 

directly from trees in two locations (0?14?46”S; 78? 0?21”W and 0?22?0”S; 78? 8?0”W) 

during April and May 2013. Leaves were dry stored until needed. Bags containing 5.00 g 

(± 0. 02 S.D.) of litter were deployed in the streams on August 29
th

 of 2013 and six 

replicates were retrieved from each stream and at each sampling time after 3, 12, 30 and 

60 days. Alnus incana (L.) Moench (temperate species) leaves were collected directly 

from several threes (40° 49?48”N; 105?43?32”W) during June 2013. Five replicates with 

portions of 4.00 g (± 0. 02 S.D) were deployed in each stream site on July 26
th

 of 2013 and 

then recouped after 3, 12, 23 and 28 days. Experimental time in the temperate site was 



16 

 

shorter due to fast decomposition rates, even when the planned dates were the same as the 

tropical latitude.  

Litterbags were placed in stream sections with moderate velocity and depth; they 

were laid on the bottom and tied to a rod. Samples were recovered according the 

scheduled dates in individual Ziploc bags and transported to the laboratory inside a chest 

with ice. In the laboratory they were gently washed with abundant distilled water to 

remove sediments. Leaf material was air dried for 24h and then oven dried (70° C for 48 

h), weighed, ignited in a muffle (550° C for 4 h) and weighed again to calculate the ash 

free dry mass (AFDM). Three additional replicate bags were transported to the field and 

returned to the laboratory the first date of the experiment (Day 0) to calculate the loss 

mass by handling and to determine the corrections for air:oven dry mass (AFDM).  

 

Comparison of litter decomposition between Alnus species 

Since litter breakdown is affected by the chemical and physical quality of the 

leaves and by environment conditions, I carried out a second essay with leaves from both 

plant species in a same location (under identical environmental conditions) to investigate 

the importance of the environment and intrinsic leaf characteristics differences in 

decomposition rates. Fine mesh litter bags containing leaves of Alnus acuminata Kunth. 

and of Alnus incana  (5 and 3 replicates of each) were incubated in the Ecuadorian site 

E2838. The leaves were deployed in 5 October and recovered in 7 November 2014. They 

were transported to the laboratory, dried and weighed as before to determine mass loss.  

 

Initial litter quality 

Initial specific leaf area (SLA; as a surrogate of toughness), expressed as cm
2
 g

-1
 

was determined in 10 leaf discs (10 mm) taken with a cork borer from different leaves. 

Leaf discs were oven dried, weighted and registered. Initial concentration of Nitrogen (N), 



17 

 

Carbon (C), Phosphorus (P), total phenols and lignin content was determined from grinded 

(Retsch, ZM100) and oven dried at 105° C, 24 h (total phenols, lignin and phosphorus) 

and at 60°C, 7 days (nitrogen and carbon). Polyphenolics were extracted from 100 mg of 

leaf powder (n=4) with 70% acetone and quantified by the Folin Ciocalteu method g 

(Bärlocher and Graça 2005). Lignin was extracted from 0.5 g (±0.1 mg) leaf powder  

portions (n=6) with 72% H2SO4 and quantified by the Klason lignin method (Goering and 

Van Soest 1970). Phosphorous was extracted from 0.002 (±0.1) mg leaf powder portions 

(n=4) with NaOH 1M and Na2S2O8 0.5M (American Public Health Association 1998). 

Carbon and nitrogen were measured from 0.5 (±0.2) mg leaf powder (n=4), were weighted 

and measured in an EA-IRMS (Thermo Delta V Advantage Conflo III and Flash EA 1112 

series). 

Considering that Alnus acuminata Kunth leaves (tropical species) were collected in 

two localities but did not show significant differences of remaining mass loss in the first 

experiment (p = 0.66; t-test), the leaf quality analyses were carried out with no distinction 

between sites. 

 

Data analyses  

Environmental parameters: In the tropical sites, stream physical and chemical parameters 

across the five sites were compared by analysis of variance (ANOVA) or Kruskal-Wallys 

(H) when the data was not normally distributed. Dissolved oxygen data was subjected to 

arc-sin transformation since original data was in percentage. Analyses were computed 

with SigmaStat 3.5 statistical software. ANOVA tests were not calculated for the 

temperate system since parameters were measured only once.   

 

Litter decomposition: Decomposition rates (k/d) were computed as the slope of the 

regression of ash free dry mass remaining (log) over time. To account for temperature 



18 

 

variations across sites, decomposition rates were also normalized using degree days 

(k/dd), substituting in the previous model the time for accumulative mean daily 

temperature. In the case of the site E1805 (that did not have the temperature logger) the 

accumulated temperature during the experiment was determined assuming an average 

temperature from one date to the next one.  

 

Relation between the environment and decomposition: To determine the importance of 

environmental factors on litter breakdown, I performed a linear regression between decay 

rate (k/d) and the environmental variables which were significant different in the ANOVA 

test with STATISTICA 7 software (StatSoft, OK, USA). Since dissolved oxygen and 

conductivity were autocorrelated with temperature in the tropical stream (Pearson and 

Spearman coefficients; SigmaStat 3.5 software), they were not considered as variable 

responses.  

 

Temperature coefficient (Q10) 

Temperature coefficient was computed for both latitudes using the following 

function: 

 

Where k2 and k1 are the observed decay rates constant for the decomposition 

process at two temperatures, T2 and T1. Values of Q10 &gt;1 means that the rate of the 

reaction is completely dependent  of the temperature (Kirschbaum 1995). 

Toughness, nitrogen, phosphorous, polyphenolics and lignin content for both 

species of leaves, were compared by a pair unbalance t-test of two tails. T-test was also 

used to compare decomposition rates of A. incana in Ecuador and Colorado, and 

decomposition rates of A. acuminata in both experiments. 



19 

 

 

2.3 Results 

Streams characterization   

Stream water temperature in Ecuador ranged from 6.9 °C in the highest site to 17.4 

°C in the lowest site, whereas in Colorado it ranged from 6.5 – 14.9 °C (Table 1). 

Ecuadorian streams? substrate was composed mainly by cobble and pebbles and densely 

covered by vegetation, except in the highest site where the boulder was the main substrate 

and the canopy cover was scarce. In Colorado substrate was dominated by sand and gravel 

and all sites were canopy covered (Table 2).    

In Ecuador streams were moderate alkaline and oxygenated (Table 3).  They were 

not different in terms of CPOM (p = 0.249; F = 1.476; df = 4) nor FPOM (p = 0.190; 

F=1.705; df = 4); the variability was high in some streams (Figure 1). 

Only four parameters differed along the gradient: temperature, conductivity, 

dissolved oxygen and levels of phosphates and sulfates in the water (Table 4). 

Temperature, conductivity, sulfates and oxygen decreased, while phosphorous increased 

with elevation.  Some of such relationships were linear (temperature p = 0.002; R
2 

= 0.87; 

dissolved oxygen p = 0.001; R
2 

= 0.99; phosphorous; p = 0.016; R
2 

= 0.23). Additionally, 

conductivity and pH displayed a significant negative relationship with the altitude            

(p = 8E-06; R
2 

= 0.68 and p = 0.013; R
2 

= 0.25, respectively), as well as sulfates               

(p = 0.005; R
2 

= 0.29). In Colorado the environmental data set was nor so complete, but 

temperature also decreased with altitude (regression analysis, p = 0.010; R
2
 = 0.92) no 

tendency for altitudinal changes was observed (Table 5). None of the other parameters 

were linearly related with elevation (p &gt; 0.05). 

Nitrates in Colorado were one order of magnitude higher than in Ecuador (11.28 

vs. 0.40 µg/L; balance t-test with one tail, p = 0.04), but levels of phosphates were not 

statistically different (6.75 µg/L in Colorado vs.11.29 µg/L Ecuador; t-test, p = 0.05), as in 



20 

 

discharge (0.017 in Colorado vs 0.14 m
3
/s in Ecuador; t-test, p = 0.05).  

 

Litter decomposition 

 In Ecuador, breakdown of Alnus acuminata leaves ranged from 0.0065 to 0.0144 

k/d and decreased with increased altitude (linear regression, p = 0.00064; R
2
 = 0.96). In 

Colorado, the breakdown rates of Alnus incana ranged from 0.0197 to 0.0453 k/d without 

any tendency along the altitudinal gradient (linear regression, p = 0.48; R
2 

= 0.0005; Table 

6; Figure 2).  

When the decay rates (k/d) were expressed in terms of degree days (k/dd), 

differences of decomposition rates among the tropical streams and along elevation 

disappeared (linear regression, p = 0.002; R
2 

= 0.036). The global decomposition rate in 

k/dd for the Ecuadorian was -4E-08. In Colorado the faster decomposition in degree days 

was observed in the three highest sites, compared with the two lowest sites (0.0016 – 

0.0044 k/dd; p = 0.76; R
2 
= 0.402; Figure 3).  

Litter decomposition rates in Ecuador and Colorado were not related with 

phosphorous levels (linear regression; p = 0.17; R² = 0.04 and p = 0.20; R² = 0.633) and 

nether with nitrogen (linear regression; p = 0.80; R
2 

= 0.003 and p = 0.68; R
2 

= 0.06). The 

same applies when the results were expressed in degree days (linear regression; 

phosphates: p = 0.08; R
2 
= 0.13 and p = 0.57; R

2 
= 0.19; nitrates: p = 0.63; R

2 
= 0.01 and p 

= 0.20; R
2 

= 0.47). 

Therefore only in the tropical streams litter breakdown were explained by 

temperature. In the temperate streams other environmental factors seems to be influencing 

strongly the decomposition  

Finally, the Q10 in tropical and temperate streams were 1.89 and 1.27, respectively. 

Both factors calculated to determine the dependence of the decomposition rate with the 

temperature were above 1, which means that litter breakdown in both latitudes are 



21 

 

completely dependent of the temperature.  

The analyses of these contradictory results will be discussed later on. 

 

Comparison of litter decomposition between Alnus species 

Litter decomposition was faster in Ecuador than in Colorado (k = 0.0098 vs. 

0.0262; p &amp;lt;0.0001 – t-test). To investigate whether differences were due to (a) litter 

quality, (b) environmental conditions or (c) latitude, I firstly analyzed the litter properties. 

A. acuminata leaves had higher lignin content and low SLA compared with A. 

incana which was soften.  Polyphenolics content in A. acuminata was three times higher 

than its counterpart. A. incana had lower nitrogen and high phosphorous than A. 

acuminata (Table 7). Therefore, except for nitrogen, A. incana was a better quality 

substrate for decomposers than A. acuminata. 

When exposing leaves of both species under the same environmental conditions 

(site E2838, Ecuador), breakdown rates of the tropical A. acuminata were still slower than 

A. incana (unbalance t-test with two tails; p = 0.038), although its k values increased 61% 

compared with the first experiment. There were no differences in breakdown rates of A. 

incana leaves when exposed in both latitudes (unbalance t-test with two tails; p = 0.11; 

Figure 4). 

 

2.4 Discussion 

Since the latitude and the elevation can be used as a surrogate of the temperature 

(Rahbek 2004) and considering that metabolic activity lies in the thermodynamic laws 

(Brown et al. 2004), this study assessed the relevance of the temperature as the main 

environmental factor controlling the microbial decomposition in freshwater systems along 

an altitudinal gradient in the tropical and temperate latitude. 

As hypothesized, for the tropical system, decomposition decreased with increased 



22 

 

altitudes. The results, were consistent with the study carried out along an altitudinal 

gradient in a temperate river by Taylor and Chauvet (2014), in which small rises of 

temperature increased the litter breakdown rates. This trend was confirmed when the 

temperature effect were factored out (degree days-1). However, contrary to my 

hypothesis, Colorado streams did not exhibited the expected tendency despite the water 

temperature changes with elevation. Considering that the positive trend was deployed only 

in the tropical system, other variables might be influencing strongly the breakdown rates. 

Such variables will be discussed further down. 

According to the MTE, microbial metabolism is predicted to increase with 

temperature and consequently, accelerating the litter processing. Since the enzymatic 

activity depends directly on temperature to degrade the substrate (Peterson et al. 2004), 

fungal enzymes would catalyze faster the transformation of organic matter as the 

temperature increases. Laboratory experiments have determined that the magnitude of the 

stimulation on litter decomposition depends on the fungal optimum ranges of the aquatic 

hyphomycetes species involved (Fernandes et al. 2009, 2012; Geraldes et al. 2012), 

considering that sensitivity of the enzymatic activity is affected when the temperature rises 

or decreases out of their optimal limits (around 10° C; Ferreira et al. 2014) . Therefore, the 

higher decomposition rates recorded at lower altitudes in the Ecuadorian gradient, suggest 

that fungal communities at higher elevations might be still below of their thermal 

optimum limit, which is translated in lower metabolic activity of aquatic hyphomycetes 

that slowdowns the leaf litter processing.  

The temperature dependence of the microbial leaf litter decomposition in Ecuador 

was corroborated with the thermal coefficient value (Q10= 1.89), which is comparable with 

other biological processes such as soil respiration (Q10= 2.4; Raich and Schlesinger 1992) 

and terrestrial  decomposition (Q10 = 2.12; Kätterer et al. 1998). 

Contrary to the tendency found between the decomposition rates and the 



23 

 

temperature along the altitudinal gradient in Ecuador, Colorado streams did not display 

any relationship with the temperature as the main variable controlling this process, despite 

the Q10 value (1.27) determined the opposite. Probably, there are other environmental 

factors such as nutrients in water (Ferreira  et al. 2014), in this case specifically the high 

nitrogen concentration and microbial community assemblages (Fernandes et al. 2012) that 

are affecting the decomposition, overriding the temperature effect determined by the 

thermal coefficient. 

 Nitrogen and phosphorous have been identified as limiting macronutrients 

responsible to affect decomposition in lotic freshwater ecosystems (Suberkropp and 

Chauvet 1995; Gulis and Suberkropp 2004; Hobbie 2005; Ferreira et al. 2006). However, 

none of these nutrients were correlated with the litter breakdown. Studies of litter 

decomposition in terrestrial systems reveal that limiting concentrations of micronutrients 

might affect the litter breakdown rates (Hobbie 2008; Kaspari et al. 2008; Powers and 

Salute 2011). For instance, Manganese (Mn) constrains could reduce the  lignolytic 

activity of microorganisms (Kaspari et al. 2008) and the lower levels of Postasium (K) 

could diminish the cytoplasmic transmission, restricting the substrate colonization and 

resource uptake (Powers and Salute 2011). Probably, the absence of the trend along the 

temperate gradient could be the result of a great variability of the local environmental 

variables, which should be investigated further.  

In terms of latitudinal comparisons, lower decomposition rates were recorded in 

Ecuador than in Colorado, contrary to the expectations. Decay rates (k/d) values recorded 

in the current study for tropical and temperate streams were consistent with the literature 

(0.0060 and 0.017, respectively) using Alnus leaves as substrate (Gonçalves et al. 2006; 

Ferreira et al. 2012). Some studies have documented slower microbial litter breakdown 

rates in tropical streams compared with their counterparts in the temperate areas 

(Gonçalves et al. 2007; Boyero et al. 2011). Then, even when the microbial decomposition 



24 

 

depends of the temperature and should be faster as it increases toward to the tropics, the 

opposite pattern recorded in this study might be the result of certain regional factors that 

could override the temperature effect. 

The incubation of both leaf species in the same stream site (E2838) in Ecuador 

reveled that differences in litter breakdown between Ecuador and Colorado were partially 

due to litter quality and partially due to environmental local conditions. Since the litter 

processing is affected by the leaf quality (Baldy et al. 1995; Ferreira et al. 2012; Schindler 

and Gessner 2009), researchers have employed the use of a single species (e.g. Alnus 

glutinosa) to compare the decay rate among different ecosystems (Gonçalves et al. 2007; 

Boyero et al. 2011). Nevertheless, the use of exogenous species may lead to misconstrue 

the results because the performance of the decomposers will not reflect what happens in 

natural conditions. In order to overcome this issue, the current research used native Alnus 

species.  

The high lignin content and the elevated production of secondary metabolites 

(polyphenolics), as well as the poor nutrient quality (low C:N ratio) of the leaves in 

tropical areas, have been documented as an evolutionary strategy of plants against the high 

herbivory rates (Coley and Barone 1996).  The higher concentrations of polyphenolics in 

A. acuminate might retard the microbial colonization. However, due to these secondary 

compounds are easily washed out in the leaching phase of the process (Graça and Cressa 

2010), others intrinsic leaf factors seems to be more relevant. In lotic systems, the lignin 

content has been identified as the major factor limiting the decomposition (Hobbie 2005; 

Suberkropp and Chauvet 1995; Fernandes et al. 2012). Since the lignin-rich content in the 

leaf provides higher toughness (Perez et al. 2000), higher investment of microbial 

decomposers to degrade this constitutive compound is required (Gonçalves et al. 2007; 

Graça and Cressa 2010; Ferreira et al. 2012). Despite A. acuminate had higher nitrogen 

content compared with A. incana, the higher toughness in the tropical leaf might be 



25 

 

limiting the fungal activity and as result, the litter decomposition was slower in the 

tropical latitude. Lower phosphorous levels in the tropical leaf would be an unlikely 

explanation limiting the decomposition because it is quickly washed in the initial stage of 

the leaching phase (Sangkyu and Kang?Hyun 2003; Gessner et al. 2010). 

The higher loss mass exhibited by A. acuminata leaf in this second experiment is 

beyond of my scope, nonetheless it might be due to higher nutrients in the water (data no 

recorded) and the increment of 2.3° C of temperature that correspond to 52.4 degree days 

of difference (data not shown) between the experiments, which may lead to hasten the 

process. The synergistic effect of both variables might enhance the microbial activity and 

as a result, the decomposition process was faster (Ferreira and Chauvet 2011a) . On the 

other hand, the lower decomposition rate of A. incana might be related with the fungal 

assemblage community in the site, which probably was not efficient enough to degrade 

this foreign substrate, as have been suggested by Gonçalves and collaboratores (2007). 

Considering the higher energy cost that represents to uptake nutrients directly from 

the substrate (Ferreira, et al. 2014), microbial decomposers may be using preferentially 

nitrates from the water to compensate the low nitrogen content of A. incana leaf. The 

velocity of the enzymatic reaction can be measured based on the substrate availability by 

the Michaelis-Mentel model and according to the results published by Ferreira and 

collaborators (2006), the litter breakdown rate (degree days
-1

) increases exponentially 

when the concentrations of nitrates in water range between 0 and 100 µg/L. The higher 

levels of nitrates registered in Colorado streams suggest that even when decomposition is 

dependent of the temperature (Raich and Schlesinger 1992; Tjoelker et al. 2001), nitrates 

concentrations in water hasten the process, as reported for other authors (Gonçalves et al. 

2006, 2007). Because in the tropical sites the nitrates levels in water were significantly 

lower (one order of magnitude difference), the temperature effect in the decomposition 

rates was clearly detected. 



26 

 

In summary, the results obtained in this study suggest that microbial 

decomposition is ruled by the temperature, as predicts the MTE. Nevertheless, leaf 

physical and chemical features such as the poor leaf quality (high lignin content) (Hobbie 

2005; Fernandes et al. 2012) on the tropical leaves, delayed the litter breakdown. 

Concurrently, in the temperate system the microbial decomposition was hasten by the 

higher nitrogen concentrations dissolved in water. It seems that even when the microbial 

decomposition is temperature dependent, this process is strongly influenced by inherent 

local factors that can nullify the temperature effect along the altitudinal gradients. 

Considering that decomposition includes microbial and macroinvertebrates decomposers, 

future experiments are required to determine if the overall process would exhibit the same 

temperature dependence obtained in this study.  

 



27 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 
 

3. CHAPTER II 

 

Microbial decomposers diversity in tropical and temperate streams 

along an altitudinal gradient 

 



28 

 

 

3.1 Introduction 

The latitudinal increment in species richness towards the equator, has been 

recorded for several organisms in terrestrial, marine and freshwater environments (Gaston 

2000; Hawkins 2001; Hawkins and Felizola 2004). Nevertheless, this unimodal trend 

differs among taxonomic groups (Willig et al. 2003) and have not been well stablished for 

microorganisms such as fungi and bacteria, probably because their lack of knowledge, 

high abundance and cosmopolitan distribution (Fierer et al. 2007, 2011). 

Different hypotheses have been proposed to explain the latitudinal variation in 

species richness. Those include the larger areas of tropical systems, primary production 

gradients, climate patterns and stability, biotic interactions such as the intensity of 

predation and competition, as well as the evolutionary history of the species (Krebs 2001; 

Molles 2010). If high number of taxonomical groups follow this ubiquitous tendency, 

there should be a prevailing  component along the different geographical habitats shaping 

this patterns of species richness (Hawkins 2001; Martiny et al. 2006). Then, since 

temperature changes gradually from the poles towards to the tropics, as happens with the 

species richness, the evolutionary adaptations of the organisms and their habitat 

colonization might be explained broadly by this environmental factor and others that 

covariate with it (Rosenzwig 1992; Gaston 2000).  

Higher latitudes exhibit larger annually temperature fluctuations compared with 

the tropics, where only daily seasonality is documented (Janzen 1967; Sarmiento 1986; 

Ghalambor et al. 2006). Consequently, due to evolutionary adaptations, tropical organisms 

living at lower latitude should experience narrow thermal tolerance ranges that constrain 

their habitat niche and  lead to harbor higher species diversity (Janzen 1967).  

Additionally, since the temperature also decreased with elevation, is reasonable to expect 

that the altitudinal gradients mirror the latitudinal species richness changes. High altitude 



29 

 

sites can be considered as isles from the biogeographic point of view (MacArthur and 

Wilson 1963), because their smaller area (Lomilino 2001) and their distance between 

mountain tops, lower number of species is likely to inhabit high elevation sites. 

The spatial distribution patterns of the local species richness (? diversity) and 

within a region (? diversity) has been widely documented (Rosenzweig and Sandlin 1997). 

However, less attention has been given to the variation of species along habitat gradients 

such as the elevation. The degree of species changes across habitats and along gradients is 

known as ? diversity (Whittaker 1972).  Since species are evolutionary adapted to occupy 

a certain niche constrained by their physiological adaptations (Janzen 1967), along an 

habitat gradient the species composition is likely to experience changes because they 

might display niches overlap.  

The rate at which the air temperature changes in terrestrial systems are more 

extreme than in the aquatic environments (Molles 2010), due to the thermal capacity of 

water (Doods 2002). As a consequence, aquatic species are likely to exhibit different 

patterns of adaptations in response of these temperature variations. Hence, the thermal 

tolerance limits in the tropical organisms might be expected to be wider, but there is still 

expected to find differences between the tropical and temperate latitudes if the 

temperature is leading the species distribution. 

In low order streams, the input of allochthonous organic matter is consider one of  

the main energy source for aquatic biota, which include aquatic fungi and bacteria. 

Aquatic hyphomycetes, accounts more than the 87% of the total microbial biomass 

associated to the decomposing leaves in forested streams in temperate systems (Baldy et 

al. 1995), for that reason, and because they produce enzymes capable of decomposing 

leaves, they are considered to be the main decomposers in stream (Hieber and Gessner 

2002; Baldy et al. 1995), increasing the nutrient content and facilitating 

macroinvertebrates feeding through softening the leaves (Graça 2001). However, bacteria 



30 

 

main gain more relevance at later stages of leaf litter decomposition (Baldy et al. 1995; 

Gessner and Chauvet 1997). Hence, fungi could be important decomposers of CPOM 

while bacteria in FPOM (Gessner and Chauvet 1997). Therefore, both would have 

complementary roles in the lotic decomposition (Graça 2001). 

Aquatic hyphomycetes and bacteria may exhibit synergistic relationships if their 

enzymatic capabilities are complementary (Bengtsson 1992; Gulis and Suberkropp 2003). 

Nonetheless, it was also postulated that fungi and bacteria may interact antagonistically 

(Gulis and Suberkropp 2003) and compete for the limited amount of nutrients in leaf 

substrate (Schneider et al. 2010).  

The potential dispersion and the high density described by microorganisms, may 

explain the ubiquitous distribution of unicellular organisms such as bacteria. In marine 

environments, the richness of planktonic bacteria  displays a strong positive correlation 

with temperature as  the latitude decreases (Fuhrman et al. 2008).  In lentic freshwater 

systems, the distribution of bacteria is mainly controlled by pH and temperature 

(Lindström et al. 2005). The positive correlation between the bacteria distribution with the 

pH has also been described for terrestrial bacterial communities, which tend to decreases 

as the soils becomes more acid independently of the altitude, the latitude and temperature 

(Lindström 2000; Fierer and Jackson 2006; Fuhrman 2009). Bacterial decomposers vary 

greatly according the substrate characteristics and contrary to fungi, the richness of  

bacteria taxa tend to increase toward the end of the decomposition (Das et al. 2007). 

Studies along an altitudinal gradient and between different latitudes with terrestrial 

bacteria colonizing the surface soil and leaves demonstrated the absence of the unimodal 

pattern described for larger organisms (Fierer and Jackson 2006). However, there is still a 

barely knowledge regarding how the species richness and composition of bacteria 

involved in the litter breakdown in streams vary along temperature gradients in a broad 

spatial scale. 



31 

 

Regarding aquatic hyphomycetes, they exhibited a cosmopolitan distribution, 

although some taxa may have a more restricted distribution (Wong et al. 1998). In the 

only study across several latitudes, aquatic hyphomycetes were shown to be more diverse 

at middle latitudes, around the temperate and Mediterranean areas (Jabiol et al. 2013). 

Nevertheless, the lack of studies comparing the fungal species richness along an 

altitudinal gradient and nether the thermal tolerance limits of taxa at different latitudes. 

Traditionally, the identification of aquatic hyphomycetes was based on the conidia 

morphological characteristics (asexual spores), which is highly time consuming and 

depends on the capability to obtain conidia under laboratory conditions (Duarte et al. 

2007; Bärlocher and Marvanová 2010). Fingerprinting techniques allow the identification 

of genetic variation within a community and for this reason, the use of molecular 

techniques assessing the polymorphisms of the ribosomal genes, located within the RNA 

sequence (rRNA), have been implemented as a useful tool for phylogentic and 

taxonomical analyses (White et al. 1990, Belliveau and Bärlocher 2005; Bärlocher 2010). 

Nuclear Internal Transcribed Spacer (ITS2 region) is a suitable marker to assess the 

aquatic hyphomycetes taxa diversity (Belliveau and Bärlocher 2005; Duarte et al. 2007, 

2010). For bacteria the marker is the 16S rRNA sequence within the small ribosomal 

subunit (Muyzer et al. 1993; Karp 2005). In microorganisms the use of fingerprinting 

techniques, such as the denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) allow to visualize 

bands, which are considered as operational taxonomic unit (OTU), which are not 

equivalent to species in large organisms (Fuhrman 2009). 

Here I test several hypotheses regarding the biodiversity changes along altitudinal 

gradients in two latitudes, using molecular biology techniques to assess decomposers 

diversity. Since prevailing temperatures may determine the thermal tolerance ranges of the 

organisms as was proposed by Janzen, the temperature is likely to affect the number of 

microbial species and the community composition, which can be translated in the 



32 

 

modification of the leaf litter decomposition. Laboratory experiments have determined 

that the identity of species involved in this process, matters more than the species number 

(Fernandes et al. 2012; Geraldes et al. 2012; Duarte et al. 2013). Considering that higher 

latitudes exhibit higher seasonality during the year compared with the tropical systems, 

where the organisms? dispersion is constrained by their thermal tolerance ranges, the 

species richness of microbial decomposers (aquatic hyphomycetes and bacteria) is 

expected to be higher in the tropical latitude than in the temperate regions, according the 

Janzen hypothesis (Janzen 1967). In the same way, due to the temperature variation as the 

elevation increases, the number of microbial taxa (fungi and bacteria) would decrease with 

the altitude, as has also predicted by the Biogeography Island theory, because the area is 

larger in the lowlands. Furthermore, due to the physiological constrains of the organisms, 

the species turnover in the tropics is likely to be higher than in the temperate areas, where 

higher similarity of taxonomical groups are expected to be shared within the gradient. 

To test these hypotheses I assessed the taxa richness and community composition 

of microbial decomposers (aquatic fungi and bacteria) involved in the leaf litter processing 

in10 low order streams along an altitudinal gradient in a tropical (Ecuador) and temperate 

latitude (Colorado, USA; see previous chapter) by the DGGE technique. Leaves of Alnus 

acuminatada and Alunes incana were deployed in fine mesh bags (0.5 mm) in 5 sites 

along altitudinal gradients in Ecuador (1645-3847 m.a.s.l.) and Colorado, USA (1992-

3200 m.a.s.l.), respectively. The methodology is detailed in chapter 1. 

 

3.2 Methodology 

 

General information 

Leaves of two riparian trees in Ecuador and Colorado were used in litter 

breakdown experiments. Portions of leaves were enclosed in fine mesh bags and incubated 

in streams along altitudinal gradients in both systems to measure decomposition and 

associated microbial communities. The experimental design is detailed in chapter 1. 



33 

 

 

Microbial DNA samples 

Primary material for DNA extraction was obtained from three replicate of fine 

mesh bags (0.5 mm mesh size; 5 x 5 cm) containing 2 to 3 alder leaves: Alnus acuminata 

in Ecuador and Alnus incana in Colorado (Table 1, chapter 1). Replicate bags were 

recovered after 3, 12 and 32 days in tropical and 3, 12, 23 and 28 days in temperate 

streams. Samples were washed with distilled water, placed into an aluminum envelope, 

transported in liquid nitrogen to the laboratory and storage at -80° C until being processed. 

 

Microbial DNA extraction and amplification 

Fungal and bacteria DNA extraction was performed with MoBio Power Soil DNA 

Isolation Kit™ using 3 freeze-dried leaf discs of 12 mm of diameter (¼ of 4 leaf discs was 

cut from each replicate and pooled) following the manufacturer?s instruction (Annex 5). 

DNA was eluted in 100 µl of 10mM Tris buffer, storage at -20°C and used as template for 

PCR amplifications. Replicates bags were pooled and treated as one sample to maximize 

the number of taxonomical units by site. 

Microbial diversity of the 35 samples was assessed in two independent 

amplification reactions with different primer sets.  To assess the fungal assemblage the 

ITS2 region of the rDNA sequence was amplified using ITS3GC/ITS4 pair primers. 

Bacteria were analyzed with the primer set 338GC/518 that targets the V3 region located 

in the 16S rDNA sequence. The total volume of the amplification reaction was performed 

in 25 µl containing 1X of GoTaq® Green Master Mix (Promega), 0.4 µM of each primer 

set and 1 µL of template DNA. Polymerase chain reactions were performed in a T100™ 

thermocycler (BIO-RAD) following the protocol detailed by Sahadevan et al. (2012) with 

an initial denaturation at 95°C for 2 minutes; 36 cycles with a denaturation at 95°C for 30 

seconds, annealing at 55°C for 30 seconds, and elongation at 72°C for 1 minute; and a 



34 

 

final  polymerization at 72°C for 30 seconds. To confirm the amplification of the target 

sequences with both primer sets, PCR products were resolved by electrophoresis in a 2% 

agarose gel at 80 V for 30 minutes with an expected size product between 380 and 400 bp 

for fungi and 200 bp for bacteria. 

 

Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) 

PCR confirmed products (20 µl) were resolved in an 8% polyacrylamide 

denaturing gel in 1X TAE (Tris Acetate-EDTA) and run at 56°C, 55 V during 16 hours in 

a DCode™ Universal mutation Detection System (BIO-RAD). Three acrylamide gels 

were prepared for fungi and bacteria, separately. The denaturing gradient used for fungal 

amplification products was 40% to 70% and for bacteria 30% to 70%, where 100% 

denaturant corresponds to 40% formamide and 7M urea (Annex 6).  For gels alignment 

purposes, the extremes lines of each gel were occupied by 20 µl of a DNA mixture 

containing 4µl of 9 aquatic hyphomycetes species and 4 bacteria species, pooled 

separately according the electrophoresis run. The species used for the DNA mixtures were 

extracted and amplified with the same protocol described above from isolated strands 

which are deposited in the Biodiversity Laboratory at the University of Braga (Annex 7).  

To visualize the fingerprinting pattern on the polyacrylamide matrix, the gel was 

stained with 10 µl of Midora Green® and incubated during 10 minutes at 18°C in 

darkness and agitation at 40 RPM. The images were captured under UV light in a 

transiluminator (Molecular imager® Gel Doc™ XR, BIO-RAD) using the Quantity One 

XMS software (BIO-RAD). 

 

Statistical analyses 

For the microbial analyses, the alignment and normalization of the acrylamide gels 

were performed with the BioNumerics software (version 5.0). To align the three gels of 



35 

 

fungi and bacteria, the bands selected in the reference line were the ones strongly marked 

and clearly separated from each other. Once that the bands were selected in the first gel, 

the same bands were chosen in the reference lines from the remaining gels, in order to 

make the comparisons possible among them. Band selection in the samples lines were 

accomplished with the following criteria: 1) clearly and defined bands with black and 

white background; 2) ambiguous bands were marked if they showed a define peak 

comparable with the bands previously selected. Smearing was assumed when the profile 

of the peak was bolder and excluded from the analyses. The software generates a matrix 

based on the height and intensity of the bands, which was used for further analyses 

(BioNumerics software 5.0 Manual). 

Each DGGE band selected was considered as an operational taxonomic unit 

(OTU), taking into account that more than one species could migrate to the same position 

in the gel. The number of OTUs for each stream was recorded by time counting the bands 

in the respectively line, whereas the total number of OTUs by site was determined 

considering that DGGE bands that appear at the same height for all sampling dates must 

be counted only once. Fungal and bacteria assemblages were analyzed independently. 

To determine if the time or the altitude influences on the number of microbial 

taxonomic units (fungi and bacteria, independently), an Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) 

was performed for Ecuador and Colorado. The homocedasticity assumption of the data 

was corroborated with the Barlett test, as well as the normality of the model applying the 

Shapiro test (R studio). The relationship between total number of OTUs at stream and the 

elevation was investigated with a regression analysis (OTUs vs. elevation). To identify the 

causes of OTUs along the altitudinal gradient in Ecuadorian and Colorado, environmental 

parameters were normalized and related using the Principal Components Analysis (PCA) 

with Primer v6. Afterwards, the five first axes scores obtained from the PCA were 

correlated with the total number of OTUs for fungi and bacteria, separately. For Ecuador 



36 

 

the conductivity and oxygen were excluded of the analyses because were highly correlated 

with temperature. In the case of Colorado, the PCA was performed excluding phosphates 

because of missing data in site C1992. 

In a next step and to investigate taxa turnover along the elevation gradient, only 

three comparable altitudes were selected (3415, 2838 and 1805 m in Ecuador and 3200, 

2798 and 1992 m in Colorado) to allow further comparisons between latitudes. The 

similarity among samples was calculated with the Bray Curtis index followed by 

ANOSIM analyses, in which values near to 1 means higher separation among factors, 

allowing the identification of taxa composition of microbial decomposers at each 

altitudinal gradient (indirect measure of taxa turnover). 

Since fungi from terrestrial origin may remain in litter substrates during early 

stages of decomposition (Ferreira et al. 2012), day 3 was not included in data analyses. 

This assumption was confirmed in the exploratory analyses, in which samples from day 3 

tended to form groups (cluster analysis). For consistency, the same was applied to 

bacteria. Two samples, one from Colorado (2590m, day 23) and one from Ecuador 

(1645m, day 32), were excluded from the fungal and bacteria analyses respectively, due to 

the methodological drawbacks in the PCR. 

The total number of OTUs in Ecuador and Colorado were compared by a pair t-

test. To identify the differences of species composition between latitudes, the output 

matrix from the BioNumerics software was exported, square root transformed and 

normalized using Bray-Curtis similarity to perform a metric multidimensional scaling 

(MDS) with 999 permutations and to build cluster applying the Unweightened Paire-

Group Method Average (UPGMA) in Primer v6 software package. The differences among 

groups were calculated by the analyses of similarities (ANOSIM) using the same 

statistical software.  

 

 



37 

 

3.3 Results 

3.3.1 Aquatic fungi 

Altitudinal gradients 

Ecuador 

The number of fungal OTUs were not significantly different across sampling dates 

and altitudes (one way ANOVA; p = 0.54; F = 0.68; df = 2 for time and p = 0.11; F = 2.7; 

df = 4 by altitude; Figure 5.a). However, when the total number of OTUs is considered for 

each stream (all samples pooled), the number of aquatic fungi increased with the elevation 

(p = 0.03; R
2 

= 0.83; Figure 6.a).  

The two first axis of PCA explained 74% of the variability (three axis = 93%; 

Figure 7; Annex 9). The number of fungal OTUs was inversely correlated with the first 

PCA axis (r = -0.97; Annex 10). FPOM and PO4 decreased along this axis. These results 

suggest that the main environmental factor influencing the OTUs numbers along the 

altitudinal gradient in Ecuador were phosphates in water. 

Fungal composition on the three selected altitudes (3415, 2838 and 1805 m) along 

the tropical gradient were similar (ANOSIM; p = 0.5; R
2 

= 0.004), meaning that streams 

share many taxonomical units of aquatic fungi among the analyzed streams. 

 

Colorado  

There were not significantly differences in the number of OTUs for the aquatic 

fungi when time and altitude were analyzed independently in Colorado (ANOVA;            

p = 0.71; F = 0.47; df  = 3 for time and p = 0.16; F = 1.97; df = 4 by altitude; Figure 5.b). 

Unlike of the unimodal tendency recorded in the tropical gradient between elevation and 

the overall OTUs number by stream, the fungal richness in the temperate sites displayed a 

Gaussian curve with the elevation (p = 0.7; R
2 

= 0.57), in which the maximum number of 

taxa was attained at 2212 m and then decreasing above and below this value (Figure 6.b).  



38 

 

The two main axis of the PCA for Colorado streams explained 82% of the 

variability (three axis = 92%; Figure 8, Annex 11). The number of fungal OTUs was 

strongly correlated with the third axis (correlation; r = -0.88), which, in turn, was 

correlated positively with NO3 (0.629) and negatively with CPOM standing stock (-0.545; 

Annex 11). These results suggested that moderate concentrations of nitrate in water, 

higher amounts of CPOM and shallow waters could be responsible for the higher number 

of taxonomical units of aquatic fungi in the temperate studied system.  

Species composition of aquatic fungi along the elevation zones (3200, 2798 and 

1992 m) were different (ANOSIM; p = 0.003; global R= 0.5), particularly the highest and 

the lowest sites (p = 0.03; global R= 0.57 between 3200-1992 and p = 0.03; global R = 

0.57 between 2798 and 1992). 

 

Latitudinal comparisons 

The number of fungal taxonomic units (OTUs) recorded in Ecuador (n = 13.3) and 

Colorado (n = 15.2) was not statistically different (t-test; p = 0.2; t =1.43; df = 8) between 

latitudes. The community composition of aquatic fungi differed between the tropical and 

the temperate latitude (ANOSIM; p = 0.001; global R = 0.69; Figure 9; see also Annex 

13).  

 

3.3.2 Bacteria 

Altitudinal gradients 

Ecuador 

The number of bacteria taxonomical units did not significantly differ across time 

nor altitude in the five tropical streams (ANOVA; p = 0.57; F = 0.61; df = 2 for time and p 

= 0.08; F= 3.2; df = 4 by altitude; Figure 10.a). However, when the total number of OTUs 

recorded in the three sampling dates were pooled, lower altitudes in the gradient harbored 



39 

 

higher number of bacterial taxa (p = 0.0001; R
2 

= 0.58; Figure 11.a).  

The number of bacterial OTUs primarily correlated with the 2
nd

 PCA axis (0.64), 

which in turn was correlated with CPOM standing stock (0.46), NO3 (0.55) and NO2 

(0.53). Therefore lower number of bacterial OTUS tended to occur in sites with high 

concentrations of nitrates and nitrites, as well as with larger amounts of CPOM and lower 

concentrations of phosphates dissolved in water (Figure 7; Annex 9). ANOSIM analysis 

segregated bacterial communities among the three altitudes in the gradient (p = 0.54; 

global R
 
= -0.021).  

 

Colorado 

Bacterial species richness (in terms of OTUs) did not change significantly with 

time and elevation (ANOVA; p = 0.13; F = 2.3; df = 3 by time and p = 0.12; F = 2.3; df = 

4 by altitude; Figure 10. b). However, when OTUs were pooled by elevation, it was clear a 

strong decline with altitude (linear regression; p = 0.0004; R
2 

= 0.99; Figure 11.b).  

The variability of bacteria species richness in Colorado was strong and negatively 

correlated with the first PCA axis (r = -0.95; Annex 11). PCA analysis associated lower 

sites of the gradient (C1992 and C2212; high OTUs number), with high temperature and 

low discharge. Additionally, those sites were positive related with higher concentrations 

of nitrates in water and CPOM. Low OTUs, number were associated with deeper streams 

and higher current velocity (Figure 8; Annex 12).  

Community identity changed significantly among the three selected streams (p = 

0.003; global R
 
= 0.51). Site C2798 was similar of C3200 and C1992 (ANOSIM; p = 0.11; 

global R = 0.27 between 3200 and 2798 and p = 0.06; global R
 
= 0.41 between 2798 and 

1992), whereas the extreme sites of the gradient were statistically different (p = 0.03; 

global R= 0.76).  

 



40 

 

Latitudinal comparisons 

When Ecuador and Colorado samples are jointly analyzed, the number of bacterial 

taxonomical units (33 vs 32) were not significantly different (t test; p = 0.84; t = 0.21 df = 

8). MDS analysis (stress value: 0.19) depicted no significant difference between latitudes 

(ANOSIM; p = 0.41; global R= 0.008; Figure 9 and Annex 15). It means that both systems 

harbor similar bacterial species in the both studied systems, the tropical and the temperate 

latitude. 

 

3.4 Discussion 

3.4.1 Aquatic fungi 

Altitudinal gradients 

Here I predicted a decrease in taxonomical units with increased elevation. 

However, this was not the case for aquatic fungi in Ecuador, where the number of OTUs 

increased with altitude, whereas in Colorado higher number of OTUs peaked in 

intermediate sites.  

It is plausible that, besides (a) the increased daily temperature variation with 

altitude and (b) the island effect, other factors could be more important determining 

diversity. The evidences from this study are that nutrients could be such factors.  

Microcosms experiments have shown that high levels of nutrients (nitrates and 

phosphates) allow the coexistence of a larger number of aquatic fungi species (Grattan and 

Suberkropp 2001; Bärlocher and Corkum 2003). In Ecuador, phosphorous in water 

increased with elevation, and so the number of fungal taxonomical units, suggesting this 

nutrient could be controlling for fungal diversity. The importance of phosphorus to fungal 

growth was previously demonstrated in foregoing studies  (e.g. Suberkropp and Chauvet 

1995; Kavahagh 2005).  



41 

 

The same could explain changes in OTUs numbers in Colorado, although with 

lesser intensity. Moderate concentrations of nitrates and high quantities of CPOM standing 

stock were associated with the increment of fungal OTUs number. The outlier of this 

relationship is the lowest site (C1992) which exhibited the highest nitrate concentrations 

(50.9 µg/L) and the lowest number of taxonomical units (7). Some studies have 

documented that fungal diversity tend to increases at moderate eutotrophic conditions 

(Pascoal and Cássio 2004; Sridhar et al. 2005; Ferreira et al. 2014). I do not know why the 

site with highest nitrogen was the one with lower OTUs number. Potential explanations 

could be limitation by other factors (e.g. P, not measured), or an unmeasured perturbation. 

The role of aquatic fungi as main decomposers of particulate organic matter in 

temperate streams has been widely recognized, as well as their association to the CPOM 

(Gulis and Suberkropp 2003; Krauss et al. 2011). The successful strategy to colonize a 

variety of substrate consists in the ability to get attach to the detritus by their conidia 

shapes and penetrate the vegetative tissues with the hyphae to uptake nutrients during the 

growth stage of their life cycle (Wurzbacher et al. 1998). The strong correlation of higher 

fungal taxonomic units to higher quantities of CPOM standing stock found in Colorado 

streams, suggests that nutrients may interact with substrate availability to explain fungal 

taxonomic richness.  

Whatever the explanations for the OTUs distribution along the altitudinal 

gradients, it is clear that, although temperature daily variation and biogeography could be 

important, other factors are more prominent.  

 

Community composition along altitudinal gradients 

Assuming that the thermal tolerance range of the organisms would control the taxa 

distribution along the altitudinal gradient, I was expecting to find higher fungal taxa 

turnover in Ecuador than in Colorado, because the organisms would tend to occupy 



42 

 

narrow niches as a consequence of the temperature stability in the tropical regions. In 

Ecuador, taxonomical dissimilarities (as a measurement of ? diversity) across sites were 

lower (i.e. higher similarity) than in Colorado, contrary to my expectations. The two 

highest Colorado streams were very similar, whereas the lowest site harbored different 

fungal taxa.  

The most parsimonious explanation may be the geographic distance between the 

highest and lowest sites in the gradients (shorter in Colorado). There should be also 

consider that the Janzen proposal may not apply to aquatic fungi. Two reasons can be 

invoked. Firstly, the thermal range in the water is lower than on land, with minimum 

temperature never below 0º C and the maxima most likely never exceeding the 25º C (in 

the studied area). Hence, temperature limitation is less important for stream organisms. 

Secondly, microorganisms may have a larger thermal tolerance than large size organisms. 

If this is the case, then we should not expect differences in ? diversity between tempered 

and tropical streams.  

 

Latitudinal comparisons in taxa numbers 

If the temperature is the main environmental factor leading the variability of 

species richness between latitudes, higher number of fungal taxonomic units will be 

expected in the tropical region, due to the narrow thermal tolerance of the organisms. 

However, Ecuador and Colorado had similar OTUs numbers. It has been proposed that 

highest species diversity of freshwater fungi is localized in temperate regions, at middle 

latitudes between 40-50° (Shearer et al. 2006). It is possible that fungal decomposers 

diversity do not follow the pervasive species richness gradient reported for the majority of 

the eukaryotic species (Willig 2003), as has been reported in the meta-analysis conducted 

by Hillebrand (2004), in which this pattern becomes weaker as the organism size 

decreases, an explanation fitting as well in the results discussed above.  



43 

 

The currently results should be interpreted with caution, considering that diversity 

in Ecuador could be underestimated due to the earlier stage of decomposition compared 

with Colorado, where the process was faster. For instance, in Ecuador by day 30 leaves 

already lost 30% of their mass, whereas in Colorado they lost 50% of their mass. It is 

plausible that in a comparable stage of decomposition, leaves in Ecuador could harbor a 

larger number of OTUs than the observed. Higher number of aquatic fungi recovered from 

submerged wood and identified by morphological techniques, was documented by Ho and 

collaborators (2001) in tropical and subtropical streams than in temperate sites for the 

north and south hemisphere, suggesting that longer tracking time in the process is required 

for future studies. 

There were no differences in the number of taxa between Colorado and Ecuador, 

but the overall fungal community analysis (Cluster) segregated Ecuador and Colorado 

samples in two clades. This suggest that the two areas harbor unique fungal taxa, as has 

been reported on the literature for subtropical and temperate region (Ho et al. 2001).  

Since this work assessed the ITS2 region that is common for fungi, the use of molecular 

techniques allowed to identify that the fungal community composition in Ecuador an 

Colorado were different, but further studies should be performed in order to determine the 

different taxa identity focused in aquatic hyphomycetes. Given the methodology used, I 

was unable to identify the species, but in a side experiment carried out in Ecuador, in 

which fragments of leaves recovered from the five streams studied in this work were 

incubated to obtain spores and then isolated, I observed the presence of Lunulospora 

curvula (E2839), Clavatospora longibrachiata, (E3415), Tetrachaetum elegans, 

Tetracladium marchalianum, Heliscus lugdunensis and Lemoniera spp. (E1805 and 

E1645; Annex 16). The occurrence of these aquatic hyphomycetes species have been 

reported for temperate streams (Duarte et al. 2006; Garnett et al. 2000), corroborating that 

tropical streams share some aquatic hyphomycetes with temperate latitudes. However, 



44 

 

tropical systems may greatly differ from each other. For instance, Ferreira et al. (2012) 

record no colonization of litter by aquatic hyphomycetes. 

Differences between Ecuador and Colorado in terms of fungi, could also been 

related with the litter substrate. Despite the nitrogen content was higher in A. acuminata 

(from Ecuador) than in A. incana (from Colorado; Table 7 chapter 1), which encourages a 

faster colonization of aquatic fungi (Fellman et al. 2013), the toughness and lignin were 

higher in the Ecuadorian species. Tough and lignin rich leaves are low quality substrate 

for fungi (Ferreira and Chauvet 2011a).  Because of structural compounds (Andrew and 

Hughes 2005) and polyphenolics tropical litter has been classified as poor quality (Ferreira 

et al. 2012), which can constrain the number of fungal taxa in the tropics (Jabiol et al. 

2013) as well as it may be influencing the fungal taxa identity (Bärlocher 2005).  

Another factor that could explain fungal differences between Ecuador and 

Colorado was water nutrient content. Nutrients were shown to be important controllers  of 

fungal taxa in previous studies (Ferreira and Chauvet 2011b). Nutrient concentrations 

differences observed in Ecuador and Colorado (0.4 µg/mL vs. 18.02 µg/mL; Table 5 

chapter 1), may influence taxa numbers and taxa identity in those sites. 

 

3.4.2 Bacteria 

Altitudinal gradients 

The number of bacteria taxonomical units decreased along the altitudinal gradient 

in Ecuador and Colorado, as hypothesized. This result conforms with the predictions of 

the Island Theory (MacArthur and Wilson 1963) and the temperature effect. Indeed, PCA 

analysis in both areas related OTUs richness with bacterial OTUs numbers (higher at 

lower sites). Nevertheless, it is plausible that temperature was not the pivotal 

environmental variable leading this biological variability. Higher quantities of CPOM 

standing stock and higher nitrates concentrations in water also influenced the diversity of 



45 

 

bacteria in lower sites at both gradients.  

Studies have demonstrated that higher bacteria abundance and metabolic activity 

are positive correlated with larger surface areas of sediments and organic debris (Hargrave 

1972; Yamamoto and Lopez 1985). Since heterotrophic bacteria require substrates with 

organic compounds as source of energy (Molles 2010) and higher quantities of coarse 

organic matter in tropical and temperate streams were associated with higher number of 

bacteria taxa, is likely to infer that more availability of organic substrate in the sites 

enhanced the probability to colonize organic substrates such as leaves, resulting in higher 

number of bacteria OTUs. 

In both, Ecuador and Colorado, PCA suggest a relationship between nitrogen and 

OTUs numbers. Nutrients may allow high production and therefore high numbers and 

high diversity. However, most likely ecosystems are co-limited by several factors. For 

instance, Farjalla et al. (2002) observed that bacteria production is not stimulated by the 

addition of nitrogen in Amazonian freshwater ecosystems. 

Additionally, the high number of OTUs recorded in the lower Ecuadorian  site 

(E1645) might be interpreted with caution, because the assessed V3 region within the 

bacterial 16 rDNA sequence is common for any bacteria taxa (Case et al. 2007), meaning 

that the identification of OTUs is not selectively only for the bacteria associated with the 

litter decomposition, which may overestimated the number of taxonomical units in the 

site. Furthermore, higher number of fecal coliforms are apparently natural abundant in 

tropical systems (Boulton et al. 1998) and since the mentioned stream was near a farm, 

OTUs numbers may be responding to animal waste, which is consistent with higher 

concentrations of nitrites at this site (Table 3 Chapter 1). 

In summary, although different environmental variables can be controlling OTUs 

numbers along the gradients in Ecuador and Colorado, results suggest that temperature 

may be a prominent factor, followed by CPOM standing stock, and nitrogen. 



46 

 

 

Community composition along altitudinal gradients 

In Ecuador, OTUs similarity along the altitudinal gradient was high (i.e. low ? 

diversity) whereas in Colorado the similarity was lower across sites, particularly the sites 

located at 2798 m and 3200 m, with lower similarity with the lowest site (1992 m). 

Therefore, ? diversity in Colorado was higher than in Ecuador.  

These results lesser the importance of temperature as a main environmental factor 

controlling bacterial species diversity, as expected if local organisms would be adapted to 

occupy narrow (Ecuador) or wide (Colorado) niches as a consequence of their thermal 

tolerance ranges (Janzen 1967).  

These results were consistent with the observed for fungi and the explanations 

could be the same: (1) low thermal range of aquatic systems, (b) wide thermal tolerance 

for microorganisms and (3) other factors may override temperature effects. Probably the 

moderate levels of nitrates recorded in the stream C2798 offer more suitable conditions for 

different taxa which are restricted only in the highest and the lowest sites, constrained by 

the contrasting levels of nitrates (5.8 vs 50.9 µg/mL).  

 

Latitudinal comparisons 

The latitudinal gradient in species richness have been corroborated for larger and 

small organisms, such as planktonic marine bacteria and zooplankton (Fuhrman et al. 

2008). Notwithstanding, this study recorded similar quantities of freshwater bacteria taxa 

in the tropical and the temperate latitude, which is consistent with other studies indicating 

null or weak latitudinal pattern (Hillebrand and Azovsky 2001; Hillebrand 2004; Fierer et 

al. 2007, 2011). The similarity on the taxa identity between Ecuador and Colorado streams 

stablished in this study, suggest that freshwater bacteria had a cosmopolitan distribution, 



47 

 

as has been documented in the literature for small size organisms. The most probable 

explanation for the absence of differences between latitudes in terms of OTUs number and 

taxa identity, might be due to the small organisms usually exhibit higher dispersal ability 

and may be less influenced by broader scale variables that regulates larger individuals 

(Hillebrand and Azovsky 2001; Hillebrand 2004; Fierer et al. 2007, 2011), making them 

capable to colonize broader areas  and as consequence, diminishing spatial differentiation 

worldwide (Fuhrman et al. 2008). 

 

Conclusive remarks 

The present work reveals that biogeography of the aquatic fungi is highly 

influenced by the substrate type available (Alnus species) and by local factors such as 

nutrients dissolved in water (particularly phosphates in Ecuador). Because organisms at 

higher latitudes, experienced wider variability of temperature during the year and 

increasing their thermal tolerance ranges (Janzen 1967; Ghalambor et al. 2006), the 

species richness of fungi in the tropics was expected to be higher than the temperate 

region. However, the same number of taxa richness in terms of OTUs was recorded for 

Ecuador and Colorado. Given the temperature decreased with the elevation, the altitudinal 

gradient was expected to mirror the latitudinal gradient pattern described for larger 

organisms. Nevertheless, this trend was absent in this study for aquatic fungi along the 

altitudinal gradient. In Ecuador, the number of fungal taxa increased with the elevation 

and was strongly correlated with higher phosphates concentrations in water; whereas the 

moderate levels of nitrates influenced the Gausian curve depicted in Colorado. 

On the other hand, the high similarity of bacteria between the tropical and the 

temperate latitude suggest that unicellular organisms display a cosmopolitan distribution. 

As was hypothesized, the temperature at lower altitudes was consistence with the raise in 

the number bacteria taxa in Ecuador and Colorado, despite this pattern was no find in a 



48 

 

broader scale, in which the diversity was similar between latitudes. The PCA analysis 

related temperature with the number of bacteria OTUs in Ecuador and Colorado, but in the 

same way the higher amounts of CPOM standing stock in the streams were highly 

correlated with this result.  

 

In conclusion, the latitudinal pattern of species richness for larger organisms was 

no corroborated for microbial decomposers assessed in this study (aquatic fungi and 

bacteria), confirming that small organisms had a null relationship with the large scale 

patterns as has been reported in the literature (Hillebrand and Azovsky 2001; Hillebrand 

2004) and rejecting the hypothesis that the latitude variability in temperature mirror the 

altitudinal gradient in species richness. The current results suggest that the number and the 

distribution of fungal and bacteria taxa, as well as the community assemblage depends of 

local environmental variables more than broadly factors that apparently influenced larger 

organisms, which confirming that small size organisms do not follow the pervasive 

species richness trend (Fuhrman et al. 2008). The lower dissimilarities recorded in the 

tropical streams along the altitudinal gradient suggest that the distribution of 

microorganisms nether respond to the temperature influenced as the main factor. Given 

that the thermal tolerance ranges were not measured specifically for representative species 

of bacteria and fungi in the studied sites, further research should be done in order to reveal 

the influence of temperature in the microorganisms distribution and its consequently effect 

in the microbial decomposition on leaf litter in streams. 

To confirm the results recorded in the current study future studies should assess 

longer time of decomposition in the tropics, because earlier stages of the process might be 

underestimate the diversity and influencing the temporal community composition of 

decomposers. 



49 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 
 

 

4. GENERAL CONCLUSIONS AND PERSPECTIVES 

 



50 

 

1. In Ecuador, the decrease of microbial decomposition rates with elevation and the 

relationship between elevation and temperature strongly suggests that temperature is an 

important factor controlling litter decomposition. This was not the case for Colorado where 

fastest decomposition rate was attained at middle altitude. Litter decomposition was not 

correlated with temperature not with any of the measured variables. Further studies should 

be carried out in order to elucidate the reasons for these results. The difference between 

Colorado and Ecuador data could be related with nutrient availability. Since nitrates were 

~30 fold higher in Colorado than in Ecuador, it is plausible that nutrients override the 

temperature effect on litter decomposition.  

 

2. In terms of latitudinal comparisons, microbial decomposition rates were faster in 

Colorado than in Ecuador. Two factors could explain this difference. (1) As mentioned 

above, the higher nitrogen concentrations in Colorado than in Ecuador could be responsible 

for faster decomposition in Colorado. (2)  Better quality if Colorado leaves (Alnus incana) 

than leaves from Ecuador (A. acuminata), which were tougher and had higher 

concentrations of polyphenolics. 

 

3. Contrary to my expectations, the number of fungal taxonomic units along altitudinal 

gradient in Ecuador increased with elevation, whereas in Colorado the number of OTUs 

peaked at middle altitudes. In Ecuador differences in OTUs can be explained by differences 

in phosphorus (which increases with altitude). In Colorado, there was not a clear 

relationship between OTUs numbers and any of the environmental parameters, except 

moderate concentrations of nitrates and higher quantities of CPOM standing stock.  

 

 

 

 



51 

 

4. ? Diversity (measured as dissimilarity relationships across altitudinal gradients) was 

lower in Ecuador than in Colorado, suggesting that Janzen proposal (thermal tolerance 

range of the organisms) may not apply to aquatic fungi.  The taxonomical units of aquatic 

fungi in the tropical and the temperate latitude were similar. These results suggest that 

microbial community structure, as well as the diversity, respond to small scale variations 

in the environment such as nutrients concentrations in water and leaf substrates, more than 

the temperature. However, future research should assess the thermal tolerance of certain 

fungal species to corroborate that the temperature may not play a pivotal role constraining 

the aquatic fungi distribution. 

 

5. As hypothesized, the number of bacteria taxonomical units decreased along the 

altitudinal gradient in Ecuador and Colorado. These results agree with the Island Theory if 

the taxa identity differs in the upper sites and with the temperature effect on diversity. 

However, higher quantities of CPOM standing stock and higher nitrates concentrations in 

water also influenced the diversity at lower sites at both gradients.  

 

6. In terms of identity, contrary to my expectations, the similarity of bacteria taxa within 

Ecuador was higher than in Colorado. This result lesser the importance of the temperature 

as the main environmental factor controlling the distribution of bacteria taxa, because it 

suggest that bacteria in the tropical gradient occupy wider niches than in the temperate 

system. On the other hand, the number of bacteria OTUs and the identity of taxa between 

the two latitudes were not statistical different, suggesting that the latitudinal pattern in 

species richness observed in large individuals cannot be applied for the small size 

organisms, probably because of its wider capability to colonize broader areas and lower 

temperature variability in waters when compared with land systems. 

 



52 

 

7. Future works should assess the importance of aquatic fungi and specifically of aquatic 

hyphomycetes in the microbial decomposition in the tropical streams, as has been well 

stablished for the temperate systems. It would be interesting to determine the identity of 

aquatic hyphomycetes which are playing a pivotal role in the degradation of leaf litter in 

tropical streams combining morphological and molecular techniques, which can allow to 

identify specially the active species during the process assessing the RNA expression. 

Given that the structural compounds of the vegetative organic matter are degraded by the 

enzymatic activity, the quantification of the gene expression of certain enzymes such as 

cellulase or ligninase, could be tracked during the decomposition to understand this process 

at molecular level and linked with the identity of the taxa in the microbial community. 



53 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

5. TABLES 



54 

 

Table 1. Geographical coordinates and temperatures (mean and range, recorded during the 

experiments) for the 10 streams in the tropical and temperate systems. E = Ecuador C = 

Colorado, USA. Average temperature (±SE). 

 

Site code Altitude (m asl) Latitude Longitude Temperature (°C) 

E3847 3863 0?14?51”S 78? 9?60”W 6.9 (3.4-7.5) 

E3415 3417 0?13?47”S 78? 7?46”W 9.3 (3.0-10.7) 

E2838 2838 0?14?46”S 78? 0?21”W 8.4 (5.1-9.8) 

E1805 1805 0?15?20”S 77?52?34”W 14.2 (13.2-14.9) 

E1645 1645 0?20?45”S 77?49?22”W 17.4 (14.0-20.2) 

C3200 3200 40?42?60”N 105?26?28”W 6.5 (3.1-13.3) 

C2798 2798 40?42?12”N 105?35?46”W 7.1 (4.8-9.8) 

C2590 2590 40?56?40”N 105?47?28”W 10.4 (6.2-17) 

C2212 2212 40?49?48”N 105?43?32”W 11.9 (8.5-15.8) 

C1992 1992 40?37?30”N 105?43?30”W 14.9 (10.7-20.6) 

 

 

Table 2. Riparian vegetation and bed stream characterization for tropical and temperate 

streams (mean ± SD). The site code refers to the place (E= Ecuador, C = Colorado) and 

altitude. 

 

Site  Canopy cover (%) Substrate 

E3847 0 ± 0.0 Boulder (66%); Lime (11%); Rock (9%) 

E3415 94 ± 1.2 Cobble (64%); Pebble (29%); Grave (7%) 

E2838 92 ± 1.0 Pebble (36%); Cobble (24%); Sand (14%); Gravel (14%) 

E1805 93 ± 5.7 Cobble (28%); Pebble (25%); Grave (24%); Sand (16%) 

E1645 96 ± 3.8 Cobble (32%); Pebble (30%); Gravel (15%); Sand (13%) 

C3206 24 ± 0.7 N/A 

C2798 68 ± 0.3 Sand (58%), Pebble (6%), Gravel (6%) 

C2590 39 ± 1.3 Sand (47%), Pebble (30%), Gravel (12%) 

C2212 76 ± 0.4 Sand (35%), Pebble (30%), Gravel (24%) 

C1992 47 ± 1.1 Sand (41%), Pebble (24%), Gravel (18%) 

N/A= No information available  

 



55 

 

 

 

 

 

Table 3. Physical and chemical parameters of the tropical sites (mean ± SD; n = 5)  

 

 

 
SITES 

  
 

E3847 E3415 E2838 E1805 

 

E1645 

 

Conductivity µS/cm (25°C) 50.9 ± 12.1 32.6 ± 3.4 71.8 ± 16.5 124.9 ± 18.8 109.4 ± 11.7 

pH 7.6 ± 0.3 7.9 ± 0.3 8.2 ± 0.3 8.3 ± 0.5 8.1 ± 0.1 

Atmospheric pressure 

(hPa) 644.2 ± 1.0 676.5 ± 335.1 732.4 ± 0.8 822.4 ± 1.6 836.4 ± 1.5 

Oxygen (%) 65 ± 2 68 ± 3 73 ± 2 81 ± 2 81 ± 3 

Average flow m
3
/s 0.05 ± 0.02 0.21 ± 0.17 0.18 ± 0.16 0.38 ± 0.46 0.08 ± 0.05 

Depth (m) 0.21 ± 0.15 0.24 ± 0.17 0.20 ± 0.15 0.40 ± 0.55 0.18 ± 0.10 

Width average (m) 0.74 ± 0.29 1.53 ± 0.14 3.16 ± 1.44 2.66 ± 0.59 0.55 ± 0.87 

Phosphates (µg/L) 15.7 ± 7 13.1 ± 3.5 10.0 ± 4.2 5.6 ± 1.6 12.0 ± 2.5 

Sulfates (µg/L) 3.2 ± 1.3 1.8 ± 1.3 3.0 ± 2.0 12.4 ± 3.1 3.6 ± 0.9 

Nitrates (µg/L) 0.42 ± 0.08 0.38 ± 0.08 0.42 ± 0.04 0.38 ± 0.08 0.40 ± 0.07 

Nitrites (µg/L) 0.0016 ± 8.9E-04 0.0008 ± 0.001 0.0024 ± 0.002 0.0014 ± 0.001 0.0022 ± 0.001 

Ammonia (g/L) 0.060 ± 0.090 0.050 ± 0.062 0.048 ± 0.053 0.042 ± 0.053 0.092 ± 0.030 



56 

 

Table 4. Differences among streams for several environmental parameters. ANOVA (F) or 

Kruskal Wallys (H) when data was not normally distributed. Oxygen was subjected to an arc-sin 

transformation. Degrees of freedom (df) for all the parameters were equal to 4. 

 

Parameter Test P Comparisons 

Water Temperature (°C)* F= 158.88&amp;lt;0.001 1645 &gt; 1805; 2838; 3415; 3847 

   1805 &gt; 2838; 3415; 3847 

   2838 &gt; 3847 

   3415 &gt; 3847 

Conductivity (µS/cm)* F=7.979&amp;lt;0.001 1645 &gt; 3415; 2838 

   

1805 &gt; 3415 

pH H=6.773 0.148 

 Dissolved oxygen (%)* F=19.568&amp;lt;0.001 1645; 1805 &gt; 2838; 3415; 3847 

 

            2838 &gt; 3847 

Discharge (m
3
/s) F=1.121 0.378  

Phosphates (µg/L)* H=10.733 0.03 1805 &amp;lt;3847 

Nitrates (µg/L) H=1600 0.809 

 Nitrites (µg/L) F=1.241 0.326 

 Ammonia (µg/L) H.4.937 0.294   

Sulfates* F=26.43&amp;lt;0.001 1805 &gt; 1805; 2838; 3415; 3847 

FPOM (g/m
2
) F=1.705 0.190  

CPOM(g/m
2
) F=1.476 0.249  

* Variables that significantly differed among streams 

 
Table 5. Physical and chemical parameters collected once during the decomposition experiment 

for the temperate streams  

 

 

SITES 

  C3200 C2798 C2590 C2212 C1992 

Conductivity µS/cm (25°C) 38 N/A 113.03 N/A 184 

pH N/A N/A 8.38 N/A 7.7 

Oxygen (%) 65.4 N/A 86.69 N/A 71 

Depth (m) 0.10 0.14 0.14 0.06 0.10 

Width (m) 0.80 2.25 1.10 1.30 1.40 

Discharge (m
3
/s) 0.026 0.023 0.022 0.009 0.004 

Phosphates (µg/L) 7.192 10.720 2.098 6.999 N/A 

Nitrates (µg/L) 5.836 12.653 4.951 15.704 50.9104 

CPOM (g/m
2
) 0.0011 0.0099 0.0008 0.0014 0.0011 



57 

 

 

Table 6. Decomposition rates (k), p values and R squares for each altitude applying the exponential 

decay model. 

 

 ID site k SE p R
2
 

E3847 0.0065 0.017 0.0001 0.50 

E3415 0.0062 0.017 1E-05 0.57 

E2838 0.0094 0.027 5E-07 0.69 

E1805 0.0127 0.036 0 0.92 

E1645 0.0144 0.040 2E-07 0.81 

C3200 0.0197 0.030 3E-09 0.85 

C2798 0.0231 0.056 3E-05 0.63 

C2590 0.0453 0.172 1E-05 0.66 

C2212 0.0187 0.036 5E-06 0.68 

C1992 0.0240 0.043 0 0.90 

 
 
 
 
Table 7. Initial litter quality of both Alnus leaves species used in this study (mean±SD) where all 

the variables were significantly different. 

 

 

Alnus acuminata Kunth  Alnus incana (L.)  

 
Quality parameters Mean Mean p 

P (%DM) 0.57 ± 0.26 1.61 ± 0.44 0.010 

N (%DM) 3.64 ± 0.15 2.33 ± 0.17 2.71E-05 

Polyphenolics (%DM) 27.88 ± 6.65 9.24 ± 1.21 0.002 

Lignin (%DM) 49.67 ± 0.96 34.32 ± 1.30 1.66E-09 

Specific leaf area (cm2 g-1) 402.75 ± 76.41 954.68 ± 277.05 0.00010 

Unbalance t-test with two tails, p ? 0.05 



58 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

6. FIGURES 

 



59 

 

 

 

Figure 1. Mean of benthic fine (red bars) and coarse (blue 

bars) particulate organic matter (mean± SE) for the 5 

tropical streams along the altitudinal gradient.   

 

  

Figure 2. Breakdown (k/day) of A. acuminate (Ecuador, red 

squares) and A. incana (Colorado, blue triangles) along elevation 

gradients and respective regression parameters.  

 



60 

 

 

  

Figure 3. Decay rates expressed in terms of degree days related 

with the elevation for tropical and temperate latitudes. 

Equations, R squares and p values are included. 

 

 

 

Figure 4. Decomposition rates of Alnus acuminate (red) and 

Alnus incana (blue) in their respective native range area (2013) 

and the second (2014) essay in the Ecuadorian site (E2838) to 

compare the differences of litter decomposition under the same 

environmental variables. Bars represent the mean ± SE. 



61 

 

 

 
 
Figure 5. Temporal dynamic of aquatic fungi OTUs during leaf litter decomposition for a) 

Ecuador and b) Colorado streams. Percentages indicate the remaining mass (RM) for each sample 

after 32 and 28 days for both latitudes and further details of decomposition are described in the 

Table 6, Chapter 1. 

 

 

 

 
Figure 6.  a) Linear regression between elevation vs number of aquatic fungi OTUs pooled by site 

for Ecuador and b) polynomial regression (order 2) for Colorado gradient. The number of bands 

were counted from the acrylamide gels detailed in the Annex 8. 

 

        78%               79%              73%     71%           51%               62%   55%       14%           61%                52% RM 

b) 



62 

 

-4 -2 0 2 4

PC1

-2

0

2

4

P
C

2

3847

3415

2838

1805

1645T

pH

Q

Width

Depth

CPOM

FPOM

PO4

SO4

NO3

NO2

NH3

 
 

    
-4 -2 0 2 4

PC1

-4

-2

0

2

P
C

3

3847

3415

2838

1805

1645

T

pH

Q

Width

Depth

CPOM

FPOM

PO4

SO4NO3

NO2

NH3

 
 

Figure 7.  PCA calculated with the environmental variables collected from the five 

streams along the altitudinal gradient in Ecuador. Axes 1, 2 and 3 explained 92.9% of 

the total variability (Axis 1: 47.7%; Axis 2: 26%; Axis 3: 19.2%).  a) Axis 1 and 2 and 

b) Axis 1 and 3. The first axis was positively related with higher pH values and 

negatively with higher phosphates concentrations in water and FPOM. The second 

axis was associated with higher levels of nitrites, nitrates and CPOM. The third axis 

was negatively related with temperature and ammonia and negatively with depth. 

a) 

b) 



63 

 

 

 

 

-3 -2 -1 0 1 2

PC1

-2

-1

0

1

2
P

C
2

3200

2798

2590

2212

1992

Depth

Width

Q
NO3

CPOM

T

 
 

-3 -2 -1 0 1 2

PC1

-2

-1

0

1

P
C

3

3200

2798

2590

2212

1992

Depth

Width Q

NO3

CPOM

T

 
 

Figure 8. PCA analysis for Colorado streams with the environmental variables. The three 

principal axis of the PCA explained 91.8% of the biological variability (Axis 1: 52.2%; Axis 2: 

29.2%; Axis 3: 10.4%). a) Axis 1 and 2 and b) Axis 1 and 3. The fist axis was positively related 

with discharge and negative related with temperature and nitrates. The second axis was 

negatively related with width, depth and CPOM. Axis 3 was mainly associated with nitrates. 

a) 

b) 



64 

 

 

 

E1645_12

E1805_12

E2838_12

E1805_32

E3415_12

E3415_32

E2838_32

E1645_32

E3847_12

E3847_32

C1992_12

C1992_28

C1992_23

C3206_12

C3206_28
C2798_23C3206_23

C2798_12

C2212_28

C2590_12
C2212_12

C2212_23

C2798_28

C2590_28

2D Stress: 0.17

 

Figure 9. MDS performed with Bray-Curtis similarity separated the tropical (left; 

squares) and the temperate (right; triangles) sites (stress value = 0.17). 

 
 

 

Figure 10. Temporal dynamic of bacteria communities for the 10 low order streams in a) Ecuador 

and b) Colorado over time. 



65 

 

 

 

 
 
 
Figure 11. Relationship between the total number of bacteria OUT recorded in the a) tropical and 

b) temperate streams, during the three and four sampling dates, respectively. The number of 

bands, considered as OTUs are detailed in the Annex 14. 

 

 

C1992_12

C1992_23

C1992_28

C2212_12

C2212_23

C2212_28

C2590_12C2590_23

C2590_28

C2798_12

C2798_23

C2798_28

C3206_12

C3206_23

C3206_28

E1645_12

E1805_12

E1805_32

E2838_12

E2838_32

E3415_12

E3415_32

E3847_12

E3847_32

2D Stress: 0.19

 

Figure 12. MDS performed with Bray-Curtis similarity among tropical 

(squares) and temperate (triangles) streams. 

 

b) a) 



66 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

7. ANNEX 
 

  



67 

 

 
Annex 1. Representation of fungal and bacteria rRNA sequences used for molecular analyses. a) 

ITS region diagram based on the illustrations published by White et al. (1990) and Karp (2005). b) 

Variable regions within the 16S rRNA gene of E.coli as a model organism. The arrows depict the 

primer sets selected in this study to assess the fungal ITS2 region (ITS3GC/ ITS4) and the V3 

region of bacteria (338GC/518) to determine their community assemblage. 

 

 

 

Annex 2. Map of the five head order streams a) Ecuador (tropical latitude) and b) Colorado 

(temperate latitude). The square within each figure (left) show the study area for each system, 

which is amplified (right) to visualize the streams along the altitudinal gradient where the study 

was carried out. Table 1 contains the site names and the geographical coordinates for each site.  

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

C3200 
C2798 

C2590 

C2212 

C1992 

a) 

b) 

E3847 

E3415 

E2838 

E1805 

E1645 



68 

 

 

Annex 3. IHF Scores for the 5 study sites are above 75%, meaning lower anthropogenic impact 

and a suitable environment for the benthic macroinvertebrates development. 

 

 

  E3847 E3415 E2838 E1805 E1645 

1.- Riffles inclusion 10 7 8 10 8 

2.- Riffles frequency 10 10 10 10 10 

3.- Substrate composition 17 17 20 17 20 

4.- Regimes of speed/depth 10 10 10 10 10 

5.- Shadow percentage in the river channel 5 10 10 10 7 

6.- Heterogeneity elements (litter presence) 4 8 10 9 10 

7.- Aquatic vegetation presence 25 25 11 20 15 

  TOTAL 81 87 79 86 80 

 

Annex 4. Quality of riparian vegetation according the QBR (? 96 Very good; 76-95 = Good). 

 

  E3847 E3415 E2838 E1805 E1645 

1.- Riparian vegetation cover 25 25 17 23 15 

2.- Riparian vegetation structure 20 25 25 25 25 

3.- Vegetation cover quality 25 25 25 25 25 

4.- Degree of fluvial channel naturalness  15 25 23 25 23 

  TOTAL 85 100 90 98 88 

 
 
Annex 5. Protocol of Power Soil DNA Isolation Kit (MO BIO Laboratories, Inc.)  

1. Place the sample into the PowerBead Tubes and gently vortex to mix it with the buffer contained in 

the tube. It will helps to protect the nucleic acid from degradation and will begin to dissolve humic 

acid. 

2. Add 60 µl of Solution C1 that contains SDS and other disruption agents for the cell lysis. If the 

Solution C1 is precipitated, it must be heated to 60° C until the SDS gets dissolved and it can be 

used while it is still warm 

3. Vortex the tubes in a horizontal flat-bed vortex pad (Mini-Tube Vortex) during 10 min to 

homogenize the content inside the tube and to complete the cell lysis 

4. Centrifuge tubes at 10,000 x g for 30 seconds at room temperature 

5. Transfer the supernatant (around 450 µL) to a clean 2 mL collection tube and add 250 µL of 

Solution C2. This reagent contains a solution called Inhibitor Removal Technology (IRT) that 

precipitates the inorganic and non DNA organic material such as humic substances, cell debris and 

proteins which could interfere in the subsequent DNA applications 

6. Vortex for 5 seconds and incubate the samples at 4°C for 5 minutes 

7. Recovered around 500 µL of the supernatant to a clean 2 mL Eppendorf tube avoiding the contact of 

the pellet which contains the precipitated substances 

8. Add 200 µL of Solution C3 and invert the tubes. This solution is also an IRT reagent that 

precipitates for second time the non-DNA organic substance as well as inorganic compounds. 

9. Incubate again the samples at 4°C for 5 minutes 



69 

 

10. Centrifuge the tubes at room temperature for 1 minute at 10,00 x g 

11. Transfer around 650 µL of supernatant to a clean Eppendorf tube 

12. Add 1200 µL of Solution C4 to the supernatant and vortex 5 seconds to allow the DNA binding to 

the membrane 

13. Load around 670 µL of the previous solution into the Spin Filter and centrifuge at 10,000 x g for 1 

minute at room temperature. Repeat this step three times until all the solution of each sample get 

processed 

14. To remove residual salts, humic acid and other contaminants the next step is going to wash the DNA  

15. Add 500 µL of Solution C5 and centrifuge at room temperature for 30 seconds at 10,000 x g to 

remove residual salts from the DNA. 

16. Discard the flow and centrifuge again 1 minute under the same conditions above to complete the 

wash step using ethanol contained in the Solution C5 (wash solution) 

17. Place the Spin Filter in a clean 2 mL collection tube avoiding the contact with the wash solution 

18. Add 100 µL of Solution C6 in the center of the filter membrane to elude effectively the DNA from 

the silica membrane. This solution contains 10 mM Tris which selectively released the DNA from 

the membrane.  

19. Centrifuge 30 seconds under the same conditions described above and discard the Spin Filter 

20. Storage the DNA recovered at -20° C 

 

Annex 6. Reagent concentrations for acrylamide matrix denaturant gradient. LD = Low density; 

HD = High density 

 

Fungi  Bacteria 

 

LD HD LD HD 

  30% 70% 40% 70% 

Urea 2.016 g 4.705 g 2.688 g 4.705 g 

Bis-acrylamide 3200 µL 3.2 µL 3200 µL 3200 µL 

TAE 50X 320 µL 320 µL 320 µL 320 µL 

Formamide 192 µL 448 µL 2.56 µL 448 µL 

H20 deionized up to 16 mL up to 16 mL up to 16 mL up to 16 mL 

TEMED 14.4 µL 14.4 µL 14.4 µL 14.4 µL 

APS                                  144 µL 144 µL 144 µL 144 µL 

 

Annex 7. Species of aquatic hyphomycetes and bacteria amplified from pure cultures and used as 

reference bands for the gel alignment 

 

Aquatic hyphomycetes Bacteria  

Dimosphora folicola Proteus vulgaris 
Angillispora filiformis Staphylococcus aureus 

Triphosphorus acuminatus Pseudomona putida 

Flagellospora renicillioides Eschericha coli 
Alatospora pulchella 

 Tricladium splendens 

 Articulospora tetracladia 
 Clavatospora longibrachiata 

 Tetrachaetum elegans   



70 

 

Annex 8. DGGE gels (a-c) with the fungal communities’ fingerprinting during the decomposition in the 10 low order streams. M = Mix of pure fungal cultures used 

for the alignment. The sample E1645_32 was amplified twice due to PCR inconveniences. The figure 6.d shows the second amplification. 

 
 

 

 

   
 

 
 

d) 

a) b) c) 

E
1

8
0
5

_
3
 

 M
 

C
3

2
0
6

_
2

3
 

 C
3

2
0
6

_
1

2
 

C
3

2
0
6

_
3
 

 C
3

2
0
6

_
2

8
 

C
2

7
9
8

_
3
 

 C
2

7
9
8

_
1

2
 

C
2

7
9
8

_
2

3
 

 C
2

7
9
8

_
2

8
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
1

2
 

 C
1

9
9
2

_
2

8
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
3
 

 C
1

9
9
2

_
2

3
 

M
 

M
 

C
2

5
9
0

_
3
 

 C
2

5
9
0

_
1

2
 

C
2

5
9
0

_
2

3
 

 C
2

5
9
0

_
2

8
 

C
2

2
1
2

_
3
 

 C
2

2
1
2

_
1

2
 

C
2

2
1
2

_
2

3
 

 C
2

2
1
2

_
2

8
 

E
3

8
4
7

_
3
 

 E
3

8
4
7

_
1

2
 

E
3

8
4
7

_
3

2
 

 E
3

4
1
5

_
3
 

M
 

M
 

E
1

6
4
5

_
3

2
 

 E
1

6
4
5

_
1

2
 

E
1

6
4
5

_
3
 

 E
1

8
0
5

_
3

2
 

E
1

8
0
5

_
1

2
 

 E
2

8
3
8

_
3

2
 

E
2

8
3
8

_
1

2
 

 E
2

8
3
8

_
3
 

E
3

4
1
5

_
3

2
 

 E
3

4
1
5

_
1

2
 

M
 

E
1

6
4
5

_
3

2
  

M
 



71 

 

Annex 9. Eigenvectors or coefficients in the linear combinations of variables for the five axis determined in the 

PCA for Ecuador. Values with r &gt; ? 0.4? in bold. 

 
 

Variable    PC1    PC2    PC3    PC4    PC5 

T 0.274 -0.027 -0.483 0.191 -0.038 

pH 0.385 0.144 0.041 -0.308 -0.459 

Q 0.322 -0.248 0.143 0.442 -0.056 

Width 0.328 0.25 0.234 -0.275 -0.172 

Depth -0.135 0.34 0.464 0.213 0.039 

CPOM 0.241 0.439 -0.152 -0.132 0.02 

FPOM -0.407 -0.079 0.091 0.119 -0.305 

PO4 -0.404 0.013 -0.161 -0.059 -0.711 

SO4 0.319 -0.193 0.153 0.535 -0.342 

NO3 -0.217 0.439 0.128 0.329 0.129 

NO2 0.062 0.534 -0.102 0.278 -0.137 

NH3 -0.082 0.159 -0.606 0.213 0.051 

 

 

Annex 10. Correlation coefficients (r) calculated between the scores determined by the five axis of the PCA for 

Ecuadorian streams and the total number of OTUs for microbial decomposers (aquatic fungi and bacteria). 

 

  

SCORES 

 

Sample Ax 1 Ax 2 Ax 3 Ax 4 Ax 5 

 

3847 -3.27 -0.257 0.593 0.996 -4.96E-16 

 

3415 -1.04 -1.79 -0.0886 -1.3 4.48E-16 

 

2838 0.522 2.56 1.28 -0.534 -3.85E-16 

 

1805 3.25 -1.38 0.785 0.638 4.09E-16 

  1645 0.533 0.857 -2.57 0.205 -9.71E-17 

r coefficient 
Aquatic Fungi -0.97 -0.14 0.17 0.44 -0.46 

Bacteria 0.46 0.64 -0.43 0.44 -0.36 

 
  
 
 

Annex 11. Principal Component Scores determined by the PCA on the environmental variables performed for the 

Colorado streams. 

 

 

  SCORES 

 
Sample Ax 1 Ax 2 Ax 3 Ax 4 Ax 5 

 
3200 1.87 1.71 0.379 0.3 -1.11E-16 

 
2798 1.02 -1.9 0.112 0.617 2.78E-16 

 
2590 0.759 -0.433 -0.18 -1.19 3.47E-17 

 
2212 -1.24 0.509 -1.22 0.301 5.55E-17 

 
1992 -2.42 0.12 0.91 -3.25E-02 0 

r coefficient 
Aquatic Fungi 0.40 -0.21 -0.88 -0.11 0.35 

Bacteria -0.91 -0.19 -0.18 -0.09 0.15 



72 

 

 
 

 

Annex 12. Eigenvectors for the five principal axes calculated by the PCA analysis with the environmental 

variables for Colorado. Values with r &gt; ? 0.4? in bold. 

 

 

Variable    PC1    PC2    PC3    PC4    PC5 

Depth 0.288 -0.486 0.55 -0.528 0.282 

Width -0.053 -0.675 0.032 0.627 -0.171 

Q 0.562 -0.057 0.046 -0.079 -0.774 

NO3 -0.485 -0.016 0.629 0.181 -0.134 

CPOM -0.271 -0.551 -0.545 -0.33 0.008 

T -0.538 0.038 0.047 -0.424 -0.523 

 

 

 
Annex 13. Cluster analyses with Bray-Curtis similarity and UPGM group linkage method of 24 samples of aquatic 

fungi from the tropical (squares) and the temperate (triangles) streams. 

 
 

C2798_12

C2212_28

C2212_23

C2590_12

C2212_12

C2590_28

C2798_28

C3206_12

C3206_28

C2798_23

C3206_23

C1992_12

C1992_28

C1992_23

E1805_32

E1645_32

E3415_32

E3415_12

E2838_32

E2838_12

E3847_12

E1645_12

E1805_12

E3847_32

S
a
m

p
le

s

100806040200

Similarity  
 

 
 



73 

 

Annex 14. Bacteria community fingerprint displayed in the DGGE gels for samples in the tropical and temperate streams along the altitudinal gradient recovered 

different dates over the litter breakdown. M = Mix of pure bacteria cultures used for the alignment. Samples’ identification follows the same criteria as explained for 

the fungal fingerprinting. 

 
 
 
 
 

                 

 

 

C
2

2
1
2

_
3
 

C
2

2
1
2

_
1

2
 

  M
 

E
3

4
1
5

_
3
 

 E
3

4
1
5

_
1

2
 

E
3

4
1
5

_
3

2
 

 M
 

C
2

5
9
0

_
3
 

C
2

5
9
0

_
1

2
 

 C
2

5
9
0

_
2

3
 

C
2

5
9
0

_
2

8
 

 E
3

8
4
7

_
3

2
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
3
 

M
 

 E
2

8
3
8

_
3

2
 

E
1

8
0
5

_
3
 

 E
1

8
0
5

_
1

2
 

E
1

8
0
5

_
3

2
 

 E
1

6
4
5

_
3
 

E
1

6
4
5

_
1

2
 

 E
2

8
3
8

_
3
 

E
2

8
3
8

_
1

2
 

 E
1

6
4
5

_
3

2
 

M
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
1

2
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
2

8
 

M
 

 C
2

7
9
8

_
2

8
 

C
1

9
9
2

_
3
 

 C
2

7
9
8

_
1

2
 

C
2

7
9
8

_
2

3
 

 C
3

2
0
6

_
2

3
  

C
2

2
1
2

_
2

3
 

C
2

2
1
2

_
2

8
 

  E
3

8
4
7

_
3
 

E
3

8
4
7

_
1

2
 

 M
 

C
3

2
0
6

_
3
 

C
3

2
0
6

_
1

2
 

 C
3

2
0
6

_
2

8
 

C
2

7
9
8

_
3
 

 



74 

 

Annex 15. Bacteria dendogram with Bray- Curtis similarity of 24 samples from Ecuador (E; 

squares) and Colorado (C; triangles). 

C2212_12

C2212_23

C1992_23

C2212_28

C2590_12

C2590_23

C2590_28

C2798_12

C2798_23

C2798_28

C3206_23

C3206_12

C3206_28

C1992_12

C1992_28

E1645_12

E1805_12

E1805_32

E2838_12

E2838_32

E3415_12

E3415_32

E3847_12

E3847_32

S
a
m

p
le

s

10080604020

Similarity  

 

Annex 16. Species of aquatic hyphomycetes recorded in the five low order streams in Ecuador. The 

morphological identification of spores was induced incubating leaf pieces of Alnus acuminate Kunth. 

retrieved from fine mesh bags after 30 days of submersion in the streams (1
st
 of February to 3 of 

March of 2014). Leaves were air dried and transported from Ecuador to Portugal. Ones in the 

laboratory, the leaves were incubated at 15° C during 24 h in glass flasks containing 150 mL of 

distilled (five replicates for each stream) and autoclaved water with aeration, followed by a period of 

incubation between 48 to 72 hours after which the spores were dyed with 0.08% trypan blue in 60% 

lactic acid, filtered (0.5 µm pore size, Millipore) and observed under the microscope. The water was 

renewed after the first 24 h and after 72 h when the spores in the samples were absent.  

 
Aquatic hyphomycete species Altitude 

Heliscus lugdunensis 3847; 3415; 2838; 1805; 1605 

Lemonniera spp. 3847; 3415; 2838; 1805; 1605 

Cilindrocarpus  3847 

Alatospora pulchela  3847 

Varicosporium spp 3415 

Trichladium splendes 3415 

Clavatospora longibrachiata 3415 

Lunulospora curvula 2838 

Tetrachaetum elegans 2838; 1805; 1645 

Tetracladium marchalianum 2838; 1605 

 



75 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

8. REFERENCES 



76 

 

Abelho, Manuela. 2005. “Extration and Quantification of ATP as a Measure of Microbial 

Biomass.” In Methods to Study Litter Decomposition: A Practica Guide, edited by Manuel A.S. 

Graça, Felix Barlocher, and Mark O. Gessner, 223–29. The Netherlands: Springer. 

Acosta, Raúl, Blanca Ríos, Maria Rieradevall, and Narcís Prat. 2009. “Propuesta de Un 

Protocolo de Evaluación de la Calidad Ecológica de Ríos Andinos ( CERA ) y su Aplicación a Dos 

Cuencas en Ecuador y Perú.” Limnetica 28 (1): 35–64. 

American Public Health Association. 1998. Standard Methods for the Examination of Water 

and Wastewater. 20th ed. Washington DC. 

Andrew, Nigel R., and Lesley Hughes. 2005. “Herbivore Damage along a Latitudinal 

Gradient: Relative Impacts of Different Feeding Guilds.” Oikos 108 (1): 176–82.  

Baldy, Virginie, Mark Gessner, and Eric Chauvet. 1995. “Bacteria, Fungi and the Breakdown 

of Leaf Litter in a Large River.” OIKOS 74: 93–102. 

Bärlocher, Felix. 2005. “Freshwater Fungal Communities.” The Fungal Community: Its 

Organization and Role in the Ecosystem, no. JANUARY 2005: 39–59. 

Bärlocher, Felix. 2007. “Molecular Approaches Applied to Aquatic Hyphomycetes.” Fungal 

Biology Reviews 21: 19–24. 

Bärlocher, Felix.. 2010. “Molecular Approaches Promise a Deeper and Broader Understanding 

of the Evolutionary Ecology of Aquatic Hyphomycetes.” Journal of the North American 

Benthological Society 29 (3): 1027–41.  

Bärlocher, Felix, and Miranda Corkum. 2003. “Nutrient Enrichment Overwhelms Diversity 

Effects in Leaf Decomposition by Stream Fungi.” Oikos 101 (November 2002): 247–52.  

Bärlocher, Felix, and Ludmila Marvanová. 2010. “Aquatic Hyphomycetes (Deuteromycotina ) 

of the Atlantic Maritime Ecozone.” In Species Diversity in the Atlantic Maritime Ecozone. 

Belliveau, Michel J R, and Felix Bärlocher. 2005. “Molecular Evidence Confirms Multiple 

Origins of Aquatic Hyphomycetes.” Mycological Research 109 (December): 1407–17.  

Bengtsson, Göran. 1992. “Interactions between Fungi, Bacteria and Beech Leaves in a Stream 

Microcosm.” Oecologia 89: 542–49. 

Boulton, a, S Findlay, P Marmonier, E Stanley, and H Valett. 1998. “The Functional 

Significance of the Hyporheic Zone in Streams and Rivers.” Annual Review of Ecological Systems 

29: 59–81.  

Boyero, Luz, Richard G Pearson, Mark O Gessner, Leon a Barmuta, Verónica Ferreira, 

Manuel A.S. Graça, David Dudgeon, et al. 2011. “A Global Experiment Suggests Climate 

Warming Will Not Accelerate Litter Decomposition in Streams but Might Reduce Carbon 

Sequestration.” Ecology Letters 14 (3): 289–94. 



77 

 

Brown, James, James Gilloly, Andrew Allen, Van M Svagae, and Geoffrey West. 2004. 

“Perspectives: Toward a Metabolic Theory of Ecology.” Ecology 85 (7): 1771–89. 

Brown, James H. 2014. “Why Are There so Many Species in the Tropics?” Journal of 

Biogeography 41: 8–22.  

Bruns, Thomas, Thomas White, and Jhon Taylor. 1991. “Molecular Evolution of Fungi.” 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics 22: 525–264. 

Canhoto, Cristina, and Manuel A.S. Graca. 1996. “Decomposition of Eucalyptus Globulus 

Leaves and Three Native Leaf Species (Alnus Glutinosa, Castanea Sativa and Quercus Faginea) in 

a Portuguese Low Order Stream.” Hydrobiologia 333: 79–85.  

Capps, Krista a., Manuel a. S. Graça, Andrea C. Encalada, and Alexander S. Flecker. 2011. 

“Leaf-Litter Decomposition across Three Flooding Regimes in a Seasonally Flooded Amazonian 

Watershed.” Journal of Tropical Ecology 27 (02): 205–10.  

Case, Rebecca J., Yan Boucher, Ingela Dahllöf, Carola Holmström, W. Ford Doolittle, and 

Staffan Kjelleberg. 2007. “Use of 16S rRNA and rpoB Genes as Molecular Markers for Microbial 

Ecology Studies.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 73 (1): 278–88.  

Cole, J. J., Y. T. Prairie, N. F. Caraco, W. H. McDowell, L. J. Tranvik, R. G. Striegl, C. M. 

Duarte, et al. 2007. “Plumbing the Global Carbon Cycle: Integrating Inland Waters into the 

Terrestrial Carbon Budget.” Ecosystems 10 (1): 172–85. 

Coley, Phyllis D, and J.A. Barone. 1996. “Herbivory and Plant Defenses in Tropical Forests.” 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics 27 (1): 305–35.  

Dangles Olivier, Mark O. Gessner, Francois Guerold, and Eric Chauvet. 2004. “Impacts of 

Stream Acidification on Litter Breakdown: Implications for Assessing Ecosystem Functioning.” 

Journal of Applied Ecology 41 (2): 365–78.  

Das Mitali, Todd V. Royer, and Laura G. Leff. 2007. “Diversity of Fungi, Bacteria, and 

Actinomycetes on Leaves Decomposing in a Stream.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 

73 (3): 756–67.  

Dodds. Walter. 2002. “Microbes and Plants.” In Freshwater Ecology: Concepts and 

Environmental Applications. Kansas State University. San Diego: Academic Press. 

Dos Santos Fonseca, André Luiz, Irineu Bianchini, Cristiane Marques Monteiro Pimenta, 

Cássio Botelho Pereira Soares, and Norberto Mangiavacchi. 2013. “The Flow Velocity as Driving 

Force for Decomposition of Leaves and Twigs.” Hydrobiologia 703 (1): 59–67.  

Duarte, Sofia, Fernanda Cássio, and Cláudia Pascoal. 2007. “Denaturing Gradient Gel 

Electrophoresis ( DGGE ) in Microbial Ecology – Insights from Freshwaters.” In Gel 

Electorphoresis-Principles and Basics, edited by Sameh Magdeldin. INTECH. 

www.interchopen.com. 



78 

 

Duarte, Sofia, Isabel Fernandes, Maria João Nogueira, Fernanda Cássio, and Cláudia Pascoal. 

2013. “Temperature Alters Interspecific Relationships among Aquatic Fungi.” Fungal Ecology 6 

(3): 187–91. 

Duarte, Sofia, Cláudia Pascoal, Artur Alves, António Correia, and Fernanda Cássio. 2010. 

“Assessing the Dynamic of Microbial Communities during Leaf Decomposition in a Low-Order 

Stream by Microscopic and Molecular Techniques.” Microbiological Research 165 (5): 351–62.  

Duarte, Sofia, Cláudia Pascoal, Fernanda Cássio, and Felix Bärlocher. 2006. “Aquatic 

Hyphomycete Diversity and Identity Affect Leaf Litter Decomposition in Microcosms.” Oecologia 

147 (4): 658–66.  

Duarte, Sofia, Sahadevan Seena, Felix Bärlocher, Fernanda Cássio, and Cláudia Pascoal. 2012. 

“Preliminary Insights into the Phylogeography of Six Aquatic Hyphomycete Species.” PloS One 7 

(9): e45289.  

Dudgeon, David. 2008. Tropical Stream Ecology. Amsterdam: Academic Press, Elsevier. 

Farjalla, Vinicius, Francisco Esteves, Reinaldo Bozelli, and Fábio Ronald. 2002. “Nutrient 

Limitation of Bacterial Production in Clear Water Amazonian Ecosystems.” Hydrobiologia 489: 

197–205.  

Fellman, Jason B., Neil E. Pettit, Jesse Kalic, and Pauline F. Grierson. 2013. “Influence of 

Stream–floodplain Biogeochemical Linkages on Aquatic Foodweb Structure along a Gradient of 

Stream Size in a Tropical Catchment.” Freshwater Science 32 (1): 217–29.  

Fernandes, Isabel, Cláudia Pascoal, Helena Guimarães, Rute Pinto, Inês Sousa, and Fernanda 

Cássio. 2012. “Higher Temperature Reduces the Effects of Litter Quality on Decomposition by 

Aquatic Fungi.” Freshwater Biology 57 (11): 2306–17.  

Fernandes, Isabel, Begüm Uzun, Cláudia Pascoal, and Fernanda Cássio. 2009. “Responses of 

Aquatic Fungal Communities on Leaf Litter to Temperature-Change Events.” International 

Review of Hydrobiology 94 (4): 410–18.  

Ferreira, Verónica, Bastien Castagneyrol, Julia Koricheva, Vladislav Gulis, Eric Chauvet, and 

Manuel a S Graça. 2014. “A Meta-Analysis of the Effects of Nutrient Enrichment on Litter 

Decomposition in Streams.” Biological Reviews.  

Ferreira, Verónica, and Eric Chauvet. 2011a. “Synergistic Effects of Water Temperature and 

Dissolved Nutrients on Litter Decomposition and Associated Fungi.” Global Change Biology 17 

(1): 551–64.  

Ferreira, Verónica, and Eric Chauvet.. 2011b. “Future Increase in Temperature More than 

Decrease in Litter Quality Can Affect Microbial Litter Decomposition in Streams.” Oecologia 167 

(1): 279–91.  

Ferreira, Verónica, Andrea C. Encalada, and Manuel A.S. Graça. 2012. “Effects of Litter 

Diversity on Decomposition and Biological Colonization of Submerged Litter in Temperate and 

Tropical Streams.” Freshwater Science 31 (3): 945–62.  



79 

 

Ferreira, Verónica, and Manuel A.S. Graça. 2006. “Do Invertebrate Activity and Current 

Velocity Affect Fungal Assemblage Structure in Leaves?” International Review of Hydrobiology 

91 (1): 1–14.  

Ferreira, Verónica, Vladislav Gulis, and Manuel A.S. Graça. 2006. “Whole-Stream Nitrate 

Addition Affects Litter Decomposition and Associated Fungi but Not Invertebrates.” Oecologia 

149 (4): 718–29.  

Ferreira, Verónica, Vladislav Gulis, Cláudia Pascoal, and Manuel A.S. Graça. 2014. “Stream 

Pollution and Fungi.” In Freshwater Fungi and Fungal-like Organisms (Marine and Freshwater 

Botany), edited by Jones Gareth, Kevin Hyde, and Ka-Lai Pang, 389–412. Berlin/Boston: Walter 

de Gruyter GmbH. 

Fierer, Noah, and Robert B Jackson. 2006. “The Diversity and Biogeography of Soil Bacterial 

Communities.” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 

103 (3): 626–31.  

Fierer, Noah, Christy M. Mccain, Patrick Meir, Michael Zimmermann, Joshua M. Rapp, Miles 

R. Silman, and Rob Knight. 2011. “Microbes Do Not Follow the Elevational Diversity Patterns of 

Plants and Animals.” Ecology 92 (4): 797–804.  

Fierer, Noah, Jennifer L Morse, Sean T Berthrong, Emily S Bernhardt, and Robert B Jackson. 

2007. “Environmental Controls on the Land-Scale Biogeography of Stream Bacterial 

Communities.” Ecology 88: 2162–73.  

Fisher, S.G., and G.E. Likens. 1973. “Energy Flow in Bear Brook, New Hampshire: An 

Alternative Approach to Stream Metabolism Ecological Monographs,” 43:421–39. 

Fuhrman, Jed. 2009. “Microbial Community Structure and Its Functional Implications.” 

Nature 459 (May): 193–99.  

Fuhrman, Jed, Joshua Steele, Michael S. Schwalbach, Ian Hewson. 2008. “A Latitudinal 

Diversity Gradient in Planktonic Marine Bacteria.” Proceedings of the National Academy of 

Sciences of the United States of America 105: 7774–78.  

Garnett, Heather, Felix Barlocher, and Donna Giberson. 2000. “Mycological Society of 

America Seasonal in Catamaran Brook?: Colonization Dynamics , Aquatic Hyphomycetes and 

Logging Effects Patterns ,.” Mycologia 92 (1): 29–41. 

Gaston, K J. 2000. “Global Patterns of Biodiversity.” Nature 405 (6783): 220–27.  

Geraldes, Paulo, Cláudia Pascoal, and Fernanda Cássio. 2012. “Effects of Increased 

Temperature and Aquatic Fungal Diversity on Litter Decomposition.” Fungal Ecology 5 (6): 734-

40.  

Gessner, Mark O. 1997. “Fungal Biomass, Production and Sporulation Associated with 

Particulate Organic Matter in Streams.” Limnetica 13 (2): 33–44. 



80 

 

Gessner, Mark O., and Eric Chauvet. 1997. “Growth and Production of Aquatic 

Hyphomycetes in Decomposing Leaf Litter.” Limnology and Oceanography 42 (3): 496–505.  

Gessner, Mark O., Christopher M. Swan, Christian K. Dang, Brendan G. McKie, Richard D. 

Bardgett, Diana H. Wall, and Stephan Hättenschwiler. 2010. “Diversity Meets Decomposition.” 

Trends in Ecology and Evolution 25. Elsevier Ltd: 372–80.  

Ghalambor, Cameron K, Raymond B Huey, Paul R Martin, Joshua J Tewksbury, and George 

Wang. 2006. “Are Mountain Passes Higher in the Tropics? Janzen?s Hypothesis Revisited.” 

Integrative and Comparative Biology 46 (1): 5–17. 

Goering, H.K., and P.J. Van Soest. 1970. Forage Fiber Analyses (Apparatus,Reagents, 

Procedures and Some Applications). Washington, D.C. 

Gonçalves, J. F., Manuel A.S. Graça, and M. Callisto. 2007. “Litter Decomposition in a 

Cerrado Savannah Stream Is Retarded by Leaf Toughness, Low Dissolved Nutrients and a Low 

Density of Shredders.” Freshwater Biology 52 (8): 1440–51.  

Gonçalves, José F, Manuel A.S. Graça, and Marcos Callisto. 2006. “Leaf-Litter Breakdown in 

3 Streams in Temperate, Mediterranean and Tropical Cerrado Climates.” Scoiety of Freshwater 

Science 25 (2): 344–55. 

Graça, Manuel A.S.  and Veronica Ferreira. 2001. “Litter Processing along a Stream Gradient?: 

The Role of Invertebrates and Decomposers Litter Processing along a Stream Gradient?: The Role 

of Invertebrates and Decomposers.” North American Benthological Society 20 (3): 408–20. 

Graça, Manuel A.S., and J. M. Poquet. 2014. “Do Climate and Soil Influence Phenotypic 

Variability in Leaf Litter, Microbial Decomposition and Shredder Consumption?” Oecologia 174 

(3): 1021–32.  

Graça, Manuel A.S.. 2001. “The Role of Invertebrates on Leaf Litter Decomposition in 

Streams – a Review of Organic Matter.” Hydrobiology 86: 383–94. 

Graça, Manuel A.S., Felix Baerlocher, and Mark O. Gessner. 2005. Methods to Study Litter 

Decomposition. Edited by Manuel A.S. Graça, Felix Bärlocher, and Mark O. Gessner. 

Berlin/Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag. 

Graça, Manuel A.S., and Cristina Canhoto. 2006. “Leaf Litter Processing in Low Order 

Streams.” Limnetica 25 (1-2): 1–10. 

Graça, Manuel A.S., and Claudia Cressa. 2010. “Leaf Quality of Some Tropical and 

Temperate Tree Species as Food Resource for Stream Shredders.” International Review of 

Hydrobiology 95 (1): 27–41. 

Graham, Catherine H, Juan L Parra, Carsten Rahbek, and Jimmy a McGuire. 2009. 

“Phylogenetic Structure in Tropical Hummingbird Communities.” Proceedings of the National 

Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 106 Suppl (November): 19673–78.  



81 

 

Grattan, Robert, and Keller Suberkropp. 2001. “Effects of Nutrient Enrichment on Yellow 

Poplar Leaf Decomposition and Fungal Activity in Streams.” Journal of the North American 

Benthological. 20 (1): 33–43. 

Gulis, V., and K Suberkropp. 2003. “Leaf Litter Decomposition and Microbial Activity in 

Nutrient-Enriched and Unaltered Reaches of a Headwater Stream.” Freshwater Biology 48: 123–

34. 

Gulis, Vladislav, and Keller Suberkropp. 2003. “Interactions between Stream Fungi and 

Bacteria Associated with Decomposing Leaf Litter at Different Levels of Nutrient Availability.” 

Aquat Microb Ecol 30 (Bengtsson 1992): 149–57. 

Gulis, Vladislav, and Keller Suberkropp. 2004. “Effects of Whole-Stream Nutrient Enrichment 

on the Concentration and Abundance of Aquatic Hyphomycete Conidia in Transport.” Mycologia 

96 (1): 57–65.  

Hargrave, Barry T. 1972. “Aerobic Decomposition of and Detritus as a Function of Particle 

Surface Area and Organic Sediment Content.” Limnology and Oceanography 17 (4): 583–86.  

Hawkins, Bradford a. 2001. “Ecology?s Oldest Pattern?” Trends in Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution 16 

(8): 470. 

Hawkins, Bradford, and José Felizola. 2004. “„Latitude? and Geographic Patterns in Species 

Richness.” Ecography 27 (2): 268–72.  

Hieber, Maggi, and Mark Gessner. 2002. “Contribution of Stream Detritivores, Fungi, and 

Bacteria to Leaf Breakdown Based on Biomass Estimates.” Ecology by the Ecological Society of 

America 83 (4): 1026–38. 

Hillebrand, Helmut. 2004. “On the Generality of the Latitudinal Diversity Gradient.” The 

American Naturalist 163 (2): 192–211.  

Hillebrand, Helmut, and Andrey I Azovsky. 2001. “Body Size Determines the Strength of the 

Latitudinal Diversity Gradient.” Ecography 24 (August 2000): 251–56.  

Ho, Wai Hong, Kevin D. Hyde, and I. John Hodgkiss. 2001. “Fungal Communities on 

Submerged Wood from Streams in Brunei, Hong Kong, and Malaysia.” Mycological Research 105 

(July 2000): 1492–1501. 

Hobbie, Sarah E. 2005. “Contrasting Effects of Substrate and Fertilizer Nitrogen on the Early 

Stages of Litter Decomposition.” Ecosystems 8 (6): 644–56.  

Hobbie, Sarah E. 2008. “Nitrogen Effects on Decomposition: A Five-Year Exeriment in Eight 

Temperate Sites.” Ecologial Society of America 89 (9): 2633–44. 

Hoiss, Bernhard, Jochen Krauss, Simon G Potts, Stuart Roberts, and Ingolf Steffan-Dewenter. 

2012. “Altitude Acts as an Environmental Filter on Phylogenetic Composition, Traits and 

Diversity in Bee Communities.” Proceedings. Biological Sciences / The Royal Society 279 (1746): 

4447–56.  



82 

 

Irons, John G, Mark Oswood, Jean Stout, and Cathy M Pringle. 1994. “Latitudinal Pattems in 

Leaf Litter Breakdown?: Is Temperature Really Important??” Freshwater Biology 32: 401–11. 

Jabiol, Jérémy, Andreas Bruder, Mark O. Gessner, Marika Makkonen, Brendan G. McKie, 

Edwin T.H.M. Peeters, Veronique C.a. Vos, and Eric Chauvet. 2013. “Diversity Patterns of Leaf-

Associated Aquatic Hyphomycetes along a Broad Latitudinal Gradient.” Fungal Ecology 6 (5): 

439–48.  

Janzen, Daniel. 1967. “Why Mountain Passes Are Higher in the Tropics.” The American 

Naturalist 101 (No.919): 233–49. 

Karp, Gerald. 2005. Biología Celular Y Molecular: Conceptos Y Experimentos. Edited by 

Martha Araiza and Ismael Vásquez. Fourth. México: McGraw-Hill Interamericana. 

Kaspari, Michael, Milton N. Garcia, Kyle E. Harms, Mirna Santana, S. Joseph Wright, and 

Joseph B. Yavitt. 2008. “Multiple Nutrients Limit Litterfall and Decomposition in a Tropical 

Forest.” Ecology Letters 11 (1): 35–43.  

Kätterer, T., M. Reichstein, O. Andrén, and a. Lomander. 1998. “Temperature Dependence of 

Organic Matter Decomposition: A Critical Review Using Literature Data Analyzed with Different 

Models.” Biology and Fertility of Soils 27 (3): 258–62.  

Kavahagh, Kevin, ed. 2005. “Introduction to Fungal Physiology.” In Fungi: Biology and 

Aplications, 15–28. 

Kirschbaum, Miko U.F. 1995. “The Temperature Dependence of Soil Organic Matter 

Decomposition, and the Effect of Global Warming on Soil Organic C Storage.” Soil Biology and 

Biochemistry 27 (6): 753–60.  

Kocher, Scott, and Ernest Williams. 2000. “The Diversity and Abudnance of North American 

Butterflies Vary with Habitat Disturbance and Geography.” Journal of Biogeography 27 (4): 785–

94. 

Körner, Christian. 2007. “The Use of „Altitude? in Ecological Research.” Trends in Ecology &amp;amp; 

Evolution 22 (11): 569–74.  

Krauss, Gerd Joachim, Magali Solé, Gudrun Krauss, Dietmar Schlosser, Dirk Wesenberg, and 

Felix Bärlocher. 2011. “Fungi in Freshwaters: Ecology, Physiology and Biochemical Potential.” 

FEMS Microbiology Reviews 35 (4): 620–51. 

Krebs, Charles. 2001. Ecology. 5th ed. San Francisco: Benhamin Cummings. 

Lecerf, Antoine, Geta Risnoveanu, Cristina Popescu, Mark Gessner, and Eric Chauvet. 2007. 

“Decomposition of Diverse Litter Mixtures in Streams.” Ecology 88 (1): 219–27. 

Lindstrom, E.S. 2000. “Bacterioplankton Community Composition in Five Lakes Differing in 

Trophic Status and Humic Content.” Microbial Ecology 40: 104–13.  



83 

 

Lindström, Eva S, Miranda P Kamst-van Agterveld, Eva S Lindstro, and Gabriel Zwart. 2005. 

“Distribution of Typical Freshwater Bacterial Groups is Associated with pH , Temperature , and 

Lake Water Retention Time” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 71 (12): 8201–6.  

Lomilino, Mark. V. 2001. “Elevational Gradients of Species-Density: Historical and 

Prospective Views.” Global Ecology and Biogeography 10: 3–13. 

MacArthur, Robert, and Edward Wilson. 1963. “An Equilibrium Theory of Insular 

Zoogeography.” Iternational Journal of Organic Evolution 17 (4): 373–87. 

Maharning, Ardhini Rin, and Felix Barlocher. 1996. “Growth and Reproduction in Aquatic 

Hyphomycetes.” Mycological Society of America 88 (1): 80–88. 

Martínez, Aingeru, Aitor Larrañaga, Javier Pérez, Enrique Descals, and Jesús Pozo. 2014. 

“Temperature Affects Leaf Litter Decomposition in Low-Order Forest Streams: Field and 

Microcosm Approaches.” FEMS Microbiology Ecology 87 (1): 257–67.  

Martiny, Jennifer B Hughes, Brendan J M Bohannan, James H Brown, Robert K Colwell, Jed 

a Fuhrman, Jessica L Green, M Claire Horner-Devine, et al. 2006. “Microbial Biogeography: 

Putting Microorganisms on the Map.” Nature Reviews. Microbiology 4 (February): 102–12.  

Medeiros, a. O., C. Pascoal, and M. a. S. Graça. 2009. “Diversity and Activity of Aquatic 

Fungi under Low Oxygen Conditions.” Freshwater Biology 54 (1): 142–49.  

Ministerio de Agricultura, Ganadería, Acuacultura y Pesca (MAGAP). 2012. “Mapa de Suelos 

(variable Taxonomia).” Reública Del Ecuador. 

http://geoportal.magap.gob.ec/mapas/pichincha/mapa_suelos_taxonomia_pichincha.pdf. 

Mittelback, Gary, Christopher Steiner, Samuel Scheiner, Katherine Gross, Heather Reynolds, 

Robert Waide, Michael Willig, Stanley Dodson, and Laura Gough. 2001. “What is the Observed 

Relationsihp between Species Richness and Productivity?” Ecology 82 (9): 2381–96. 

Molles, Manuel (University of New Mexico). 2010. “Natural History and Evolution.” In 

Ecology, Concepts and Applications, Fifth edit, 10–77. Boston: McGraw-Hill. 

Muyzer, G, and K Smalla. 1998. “Application of Denaturing Gradient Gel Electrophoresis 

(DGGE) and Temperature Gradient Gel Electrophoresis (TGGE) in Microbial Ecology.” Antonie 

van Leeuwenhoek 73 (1): 127–41.  

Muyzer, Gerard, Ellen C D E Waal, and Andre G Uitierlinden. 1993. “Profiling of Complex 

Microbial Populations by Denaturing Gradient Gel Electrophoresis Analysis of Polymerase Chain 

Reaction-Amplified Genes Coding for 16S rRNA.” Applied and Environmental Microbioology 59 

(3): 695–700. 

National Aeronautics and Space Administration: NASA. 2014. “Temperature and Altitude.” 

June 12. http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/k-12/problems/Jim_Naus/TEMPandALTITUDE_ans.htm. 



84 

 

Pascoal, Cláudia, and Fernanda Cássio. 2004. “Contribution of Fungi and Bacteria to Leaf 

Litter Decomposition in a Polluted River Contribution of Fungi and Bacteria to Leaf Litter 

Decomposition in a Polluted River.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 70 (9): 5266–73.  

Perez-Harguindeguy, N, S Diaz, Johannes H. C. Cornelissen, F Vendramini, M Cabido, and a 

Castellanos. 2000. “Chemistry and Toughness Predict Leaf Litter Decomposition Rates over a 

Wide Spectrum of Functional Types and Taxa in Central Argentina.” Plant and Soil 218: 21–30.  

Peterson, Michelle E., Robert Eisenthal, Michael J. Danson, Alastair Spence, and Roy M. 

Daniel. 2004. “A New Intrinsic Thermal Parameter for Enzymes Reveals True Temperature 

Optima.” Journal of Biological Chemistry 279 (20): 20717–22.  

Pianka, Eric R. 1966. “Latitudinal Gradients in Species Diversity: A Review of Concepts.” 

The American Naturalist 100 (910): 33.  

Poff, N Leroy, William Funk, Cameron Ghalambor, Boris Kondretieff, Steven Thomas, 

Alexander Flecker, Joseph Bernardo, and Kelly Zamudio. 2010. “EVOTRAC Project.” Vol. 267. 

Powers, Jennifer S., and Stefani Salute. 2011. “Macro- and Micronutrient Effects on 

Decomposition of Leaf Litter from Two Tropical Tree Species: Inferences from a Short-Term 

Laboratory Incubation.” Plant and Soil 346 (1): 245–57.  

Rahbek, Carsten. 2004. “The Role of Spatial Scale and the Perception of Large-Scale Species-

Richness Patterns.” Ecology Letters 8 (2): 224–39.  

Raich, J.W., and W.H. Schlesinger. 1992. “The Global Carbon Dioxide Flux in Soil 

Respiration and Its Relationship to Vegetation and Climate.” TELLUS 44B: 81–99. 

Rendón, María José. 2012. “Hifomicetes Tropicales de Páramo y su Rol en la 
Descomposición de Hojarasca.” Univesidad San Francisco de Quito. 

Rex, Michael, Alitair Crame, Carol Sturat, and Andrew Clarke. 2005. “Large-Scale 

Biogeographic Patterns in Marine Mollusks: A Confluence of History and Productivity?” Ecology 

86 (9): 2288–97. 

Rezende, Renan S, Mauricio M Petrucio, and José F Gonçalves. 2014. “The Effects of Spatial 

Scale on Breakdown of Leaves in a Tropical Watershed.” PloS One 9 (5): e97072.  

Rosenzweig, Michael, and Elizabeth A Sandlin. 1997. “Species Diversity and Latitudes: 

Listening to Area?s Signal.” Nordic Society Oikos 80 (May): 172–76. 

Rosenzwig, Michael. 1992. “Species Diversity Gradients: We Know More and Less than We 

Thought.” American Society of MammalogY 73 (4): 715–30. 

Royer, Todd, and Wayne Minshall. 2003. “Controls on Leaf Processing in Streams from 

Spatial-Scaling and.” The North American Benthological Society 22 (3): 352–58. 



85 

 

Sahadevan, Seena, Sofia Duarte, Cláudia Pascoal, and Fernanda Cássio. 2012. “Intraspecific 

Variation of the Aquatic Fungus Articulospora Tetracladia: An Ubiquitous Perspective.” PloS One 

7 (4): e35884.  

Sanders, Nathan J. 2002. “Elevational Gradients in Ant Species Richness: Area, Geometry, 

and Rapoport?s Rule.” Ecography 25: 25–32. 

Sangkyu, Park, and Cho Kang?Hyun. 2003. “Nutrient Leaching from Leaf Litter of Emergent 

Macrophyte (Zizania Latifolia) and the Effects of Water Temperature on the Leaching Process.” 

Korean Journal of Biological Sciences 7 (4): 289–94.  

Sarmiento, G. 1986. “Ecologically Crucial Features of Climate in High Tropical Mountains.” 

High Altitude Tropical Biogeography, 11–45. 

Schindler, Markus, and Mark Gessner. 2009. “Functional Leaf Traits and Biodiversity Effects 

on Litter Decomposition in a Stream.” Ecological Society of America 90 (6): 1641–49. 

Schlötterer, Christian. 2004. “The Evolution of Molecular Markers--Just a Matter of Fashion?” 

Nature Reviews. Genetics 5 (January): 63–69.  

Schmid, Bernhard. 2002. “The Species Richness–productivity Controversy.” Trends in 

Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution 17 (3): 113–14.  

Schneider, Thomas, Bertran Gerrits, Regula Gassmann, Emanuel Schmid, Mark O Gessner, 

Andreas Richter, Tom Battin, Leo Eberl, and Kathrin Riedel. 2010. “Proteome Analysis of Fungal 

and Bacterial Involvement in Leaf Litter Decomposition.” Proteomics 10 (9): 1819–30.  

Shearer, Carol a., Enrique Descals, Brigitte Kohlmeyer, Jan Kohlmeyer, Ludmila Marvanová, 

David Padgett, David Porter, et al. 2006. “Fungal Biodiversity in Aquatic Habitats.” Biodiversity 

and Conservation 16 (1): 49–67.  

Sridhar, K R, and F Bärlocher. 1993. “Effect of Temperature on Growth and Survival of Five 

Aquatic Hyphomycetes,” 377–87. 

Sridhar, K. R., Felix Bärlocher, Gerd Joachim Krauss, and Gudrun Krauss. 2005. “Response of 

Aquatic Hyphomycete Communities to Changes in Heavy Metal Exposure.” International Review 

of Hydrobiology 90 (1): 21–32.  

Stevens, George C. 1992. “The Elevational Gradient in Altitudinal Range?: An Extension of 

Rapoport ? S Latitudinal Rule to Altitude Author ( S ): George C . Stevens Reviewed Work ( S ): 

Source?: The American Naturalist , Vol . 140 , No . 6 ( Dec ., 1992 ), Pp . 893-911 Published B.” 

American Society of Naturalists 140 (6): 893–911. 

Suberkropp, Keller, and Eric Chauvet. 1995. “Regulation of Leaf Breakdown by Fungi in 

Streams?: Influences of Water Chemistry.” Ecological Society of America 76 (5): 1433–45. 

Taylor, Barry R., and Eric E. Chauvet. 2014. “Relative Influence of Shredders and Fungi on 

Leaf Litter Decomposition along a River Altitudinal Gradient.” Hydrobiologia 721 (1): 239–50.  



86 

 

Tjoelker, Mark, Jacek Oleksyn, and Peter Reich. 2001. “Modelling Respiration of Vegetation?: 

Evidence for a General Temperature-Dependent Q 10.” Global Change Biology 7: 223–30. 

Todd, Royer, and Wayne Minshall. 2001. “Effects of Nutrient Enrichment and Leaf Quality on 

the Breakdown of Leaves in a Hardwater Stream.” Freshwater Biology 46: 603–10. 

Vannote, Robin L., G.Wayne Minshall, Kenneth W. Cummins, James R. Sedell, and Colbert 

E. Cushing. 1980. “The River Continuum Concept.” Fish.Aquat.Sci. 37 (River concept): 7. 

Waide, R B, M R Willig, C F Steiner, G Mittelbach, L Gough, S I Dodson, G P Juday, and R 

Parmenter. 1999. “The Relationship between Productivity and Species Richness.” Annu. Rev. Ecol. 

Syst. 30: 257–300. 

Waltz, James P. 1969. “Hydrology and Water Quality Studies in the Cache La Poudre Basin, 

Colorado.” Colorado State University- Fort Collins, Colorado. 

White, T.J., T. Bruns, S. Lee, and J. Taylor. 1990. “Amplification and Direct Sequencing of 

Fungal Ribosomal RNA Genes for Phylogenetics.” In PCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and 

Applications, edited by MA Innis, DH Gelfand, JJ Sninsky, and TJ White, 315–22. New York: 

Academic Press. 

Whittaker, R H. 1972. “Evolution and Measurement of Species Diversity.” International 

Association for Plant Taxonomy 21 (2/3): 213–51. 

Willig, M.R., D.M. Kaufman, and R.D. Stevens. 2003a. “Latitudinal Gradients of 

Biodiversity: Pattern, Process, Scale, and Synthesis.” Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and 

Systematics 34 (1): 273–309.  

Wong, Michelle K M, Teik-khiang Goh, I John Hodgkiss, Kevin D Hyde, V Mala Ranghoo, 

Clement K M Tsui, Wai-hong Ho, Wilson S W Wong, and Tsz-kit Yuen. 1998. “Role of Fungi in 

Freshwater Ecosystems.” Biodiversity and Conservation 1206: 1187–1206. 

Wu, Yongjie, Robert K. Colwell, Carsten Rahbek, Chunlan Zhang, Qing Quan, Changke 

Wang, and Fumin Lei. 2013. “Explaining the Species Richness of Birds along a Subtropical 

Elevational Gradient in the Hengduan Mountains.” Edited by K. C. Burns. Journal of 

Biogeography 40 (12): 2310–23. 

Wurzbacher, Christian, Janice Kerr, and Hans-Peter Grossart. 1998. “Aquatic Fungi.” In The 

Dynamical Processes of Biodiversity- Case Studies of Evolution and Spatial Distribution, edited 

by Oscar Grillo, 227–58.  

Yamamoto, Nobuyuki, and Glenn Lopez. 1985. “Bacterial Abundance in Relation to Surface 

Area and Organic Content of Marine Sediments.” Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and 

Ecology 90 (3): 209–20.  

 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>