<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.11562</field>
		<field name="filename">16923_2016_GuilhermeFerreiraCanedo.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
UNIVERSIDADE DE BRASÍLIA – UnB 
INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS – IG 
PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOLOGIA 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

OS DEPÓSITOS SERROTE DA LAJE E CABOCLO (CU – Au), NORDESTE DO BRASIL: SULFETOS 

MAGMÁTICOS HOSPEDADOS EM ROCHAS RICAS EM MAGNETITA E ILMENITA ASSOCIADAS A 

INTRUSÕES MÁFICAS-ULTRAMÁFICAS.  

 

 

 

 

 

 

GUILHERME FERREIRA CANEDO 

 

 

 

DISSERTAÇÃO DE MESTRADO No 370 

 

 

 

 

 

 

BRASÍLIA 2016 



UNIVERSIDADE DE BRASÍLIA – UnB 
INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS – IG 
PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOLOGIA 

 

 

 

 

 

OS DEPÓSITOS SERROTE DA LAJE E CABOCLO (CU – Au), NORDESTE DO BRASIL: SULFETOS 

MAGMÁTICOS HOSPEDADOS EM ROCHAS RICAS EM MAGNETITA E ILMENITA ASSOCIADAS A 

INTRUSÕES MÁFICAS-ULTRAMÁFICAS.  

 

 

 

Guilherme Ferreira Canedo 

 

 

Dissertação de Mestrado em Geologia no 370 

 

 

Orientador: Prof. Dr. César Fonseca Ferreira Filho (IG-UnB) 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Brasília, setembro de 2016 

 



UNIVERSIDADE DE BRASÍLIA – UnB 
INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS – IG 
PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOLOGIA 

 

 

 

 

OS DEPÓSITOS SERROTE DA LAJE E CABOCLO (CU – Au), NORDESTE DO BRASIL: SULFETOS 

MAGMÁTICOS HOSPEDADOS EM ROCHAS RICAS EM MAGNETITA E ILMENITA ASSOCIADAS A 

INTRUSÕES MÁFICAS-ULTRAMÁFICAS.  

 

 

Guilherme Ferreira Canedo 

 

Dissertação de mestrado submetida ao Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geologia, como parte dos 

requisitos necessários à obtenção do grau de Mestre em Geologia. 

 

 

 

Aprovada por: 

_____________________________________________________ 

César Fonseca Ferreira Filho, Doutor, Professor Associado. 
Instituto de Geociências – Universidade de Brasília - UnB  
_____________________________________________________ 
Claudinei Gouveia de Oliveira, Doutor, Professor Associado. 
Instituto de Geociências – Universidade de Brasília - UnB  
_____________________________________________________ 
José Haroldo da Silva Sá, Doutor, Professor Adjunto. 
Instituto de Geociências – Universidade Federal da Bahia - UFBA 

 

 

 

 

Brasília, 08 de setembro de 2016 

 



FICHA CATALOGRÁFICA 

 

 
 

Fc221d 

 
Ferreira Canedo, Guilherme 

OS DEPÓSITOS SERROTE DA LAJE E CABOCLO (CU – 
Au), NORDESTE DO BRASIL: SULFETOS MAGMÁTICOS 
HOSPEDADOS EM ROCHAS RICAS EM MAGNETITA E  
ILMENITA ASSOCIADAS A INTRUSÕES MÁFICAS-
ULTRAMÁFICAS. / Guilherme Ferreira Canedo; 
orientador César Fonseca Ferreira Filho. -- Brasília, 
2016. 

57 p. 
 
Dissertação (Mestrado - Mestrado em Geologia) - 

Universidade de Brasília, 2016. 
 
 1. Depósitos Magmáticos Sulfetados. 2. Cobre e 

ouro. 3. Serrote da Laje e Caboclo. 4. Rochas máfica 
ultramáficas. I. Fonseca Ferreira Filho, César, orient. 

 
 

 

 

 

REFERÊNCIA BIBLIOGRÁFICA 

CANEDO, G. F. Os Depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo (Cu-Au), nordeste do Brasil: Sulfetos 

magmáticos hospedados em rochas ricas em magnetita e ilmenita associadas a intrusões 

máficas-ultramáficas. Brasília: Instituto de Geociências, Universidade de Brasília, 2016, 57 p. 

Dissertação de Mestrado 

 

CESSÃO DE DIREITOS 

NOME DO AUTOR: Guilherme Ferreira Canedo  

TÍTULO DA DISSERTAÇÃO: Os Depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo (Cu – Au), nordeste do Brasil: Sulfetos 

magmáticos hospedados em rochas ricas em magnetita e lmenita associadas a intrusões máficas-ultramáficas. 

GRAU: Mestre ANO: 2016  

É concedida à Universidade de Brasília de Brasília permissão para reproduzir cópias desta dissertação de 

mestrado para única e exclusivamente propósitos acadêmicos e científicos. O autor reserva para si os outros 

direitos autorais, de publicação. Nenhuma parte desta dissertação de mestrado pode ser reproduzida sem a 

autorização por escrito do autor. Citações são estimuladas, desde que citada a fonte. 

_______________________________________________________________________________ 

Nome: Guilherme Ferreira Canedo 

Email: guilherme_canedo@yahoo.com.br 

 



a 
 

AGRADECIMENTOS 

 

 Ao professor Dr. César Ferreira Fonseca Filho, por toda dedicação e comprometimento 
com o projeto de pesquisa e comigo. 
 
 Ao professor Dr. Elton Luiz Dantas pela ajuda com os dados geocronológicos. 
 
 Aos professores do Instituto de Geociências da Universidade de Brasília pelo 
conhecimento transmitido durante os cursos de graduação e mestrado. 
 
 Ao CNPq e IG-UnB pelo suporte nos custeios de várias etapas do projeto. 
 
 À Aura Minerals Inc. pela liberação de dados e amostras para o projeto de pesquisa. 
 
 Ao geólogo e amigo Marcos Paulo Aguiar de Deus por todas colaborações e discussões, 
muito importantes para o projeto de pesquisa. 
 
 Ao amigo e colega de trabalho José Deyvson pelo auxílio na arte de figuras. 
 
 Aos meus pais, Maria de Lourdes e Carlos, e meu irmão, Frederico, por todo aprendizado, 
carinho e apoio recebidos durante toda vida, fatores determinantes para construção da pessoa 
que sou hoje. 
 

A todos familiares e amigos da confraria naja que contribuíram para meu sucesso e 
crescimento como pessoa. 

  
 À minha esposa, Lionária, pelo carinho, compreensão e apoio, fundamentais para a 
conclusão de mais esta etapa da minha vida. 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



b 
 

ÍNDICE 

 

I – RESUMO........................................................................................................................... i 

II – ABSTRACT........................................................................................................................ iii 

III – CONSIDERAÇÕES GERAIS................................................................................................ 01 

i. Introdução........................................................................................................ 

ii. Localização e fisiografia..................................................................................... 

iii. Justificativa e objetivos..................................................................................... 

iv. Métodos............................................................................................................ 

v. Escopo do estudo.............................................................................................. 

vi. Referências....................................................................................................... 

01 

02 

03 

04 

05 

06 

IV – THE SERROTE DA LAJE AND CABOLCO CU-AU DEPOSIT, NORTHEAST BRAZIL: 

MAGMATIC SULFIDES HOSTED BY ILMENITE-MAGNETITE-BEARING MAFIC-ULTRAMAFIC 

INTRUSIONS.......................................................................................................................... 

Abstract................................................................................................................................. 

1. Introduction………........................................................................................................... 

2. Exploration History……………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

3. Tectonic Setting………………………………………………………….................................................. 

3.1 Borborema Province……………………………………………………………………………….............. 

3.2 Sergipano Belt………………………………………………………................................................ 

3.3 Layered MUM intrusions of the SB……………………………………………………………………… 

4. Methods……………………………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

4.1 Petrography of mafic-ultramafic rocks………………………………………………………………… 

4.2 Microprobe analyses…………………………………………………………………………………………… 

4.3 Lithogeochemistry………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

4.4 Sulfur isotopes……………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

4.5 Sm-Nd isotopes…………………………………………………………………………………………………… 

4.6 U-Pb isotopes……………………………………………………………………………………………………… 

5. Results………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

5.1 Geology and structure of the Serrote da Laje Deposit…………………………………………. 

5.2 Geology and structure of the Caboclo Deposit…………………………………………………….. 

5.3 Petrography of mafic-ultramafic rocks………………………………………………………………… 

5.4 Whole-rock geochemistry…………………………………………………………………………………… 

 

 

08 

08 

10 

10 

11 

11 

13 

16 

17 

17 

17 

17 

18 

18 

18 

19 

19 

22 

24 

29 



c 
 

5.5 Mineral chemistry………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

5.6 Petrography, mineralogy and geochemistry of sulfide ore…………………………………… 

5.7 Sulfur isotopes……………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

5.8 U-Pb and Sm-Nd isotopes…………………………………………............................................. 

6. Discussion…………………………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

6.1 Magmatic structure and composition of mafic-ultramafic bodies………………………… 

6.2 The origin of magnetitite…………………………………………………………………………………….. 

6.3 How Cu-Au magmatic sulfides are formed?............................................................. 

6.4 Classification of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo Cu-Au deposits………………………… 

6.5 Implications for exploration………………………………………………………………………………… 

7. Conclusions………………………………………………………………………………....................……………. 

8. Acknowledgements…………………………………………………………………………………………………… 

9. References……………………………………………………………….................................................... 

32 

33 

37 

40 

43 

43 

44 

45 

46 

47 

48 

49 

50 

V – CONCLUSÕES................................................................................................................... 57 

ANEXOS.................................................................................................................................   I 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



d 
 

ÍNDICE DE FIGURAS 

 

Figura i. Mapa de localização das áreas de estudo............................................................. 

Figura 1. Borborema structural province map indicating the location of the Meridional 

subprovince, highlighted in green tones. Adapted from Santos (1998, 

2000)................................................................................................................................... 

Figura 2. Lithostratigraphic domains of the Sergipano Belt. Adapted from Silva Filho et 

al. (2003)............................................................................................................................. 

Figura 3. Geological map of central part of Alagoas state, showing the localization of the 

Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. Adapted from Mendes et al. (2009)……………………. 

Figura 4. Geological map from Serrote da Laje Deposit. The insert shows the analytical 

signal image of the mapped area. Note the close fit of the mafic-ultramafic intrusion 

with domains with high magnetic signal. The cross section A-A´ is illustrated in figure 

6……………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

Figura 5. Country rocks of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. a) pink gneiss 

composed by quartz + K-feldspar + plagioclase + sillimanite + cordierite. b) garnet gneiss 

composed by quartz + biotite +garnet + plagioclase + cordierite…………………………………….. 

Figura 6. 3D view of the mafic-ultramafic rocks (greenish color) and major faults (reddish 

color) of the Serrote da Laje Deposit. The north, central and south domains are shown 

in different projections…………………………………………………………........................................... 

Figura 7. Geological E-W cross section of the north domain of the Serrote da Laje 

Deposit………………………………………………………………………………………………………………............. 

Figura 8. Geological map of the Caboclo Deposit. The insert shows the analytical signal 

image of the mapped area. Note the close fit of the main bodies (i.e., Rogerio, Zeze, 

Maninho, Petrucio and Adriano) with domains with high magnetic signal. The cross 

section A-A´ is illustrated in figure 9……………………………………………………………………………….. 

Figura 9. Geological E-W cross section of the Rogerio target. See figure 8 for location of 

the section…………………………………………………………………………………………………………………….. 

Figura 10. Photographs and photomicrographs of representative rock textures of 

orthopyroxenite, magnetite orthopyroxenite and magnetitete in the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo deposits. A) Contact of orthopyroxenite (Opxt) and magnetitite (Mag); B) 

Orthopyroxenite consisting mainly of cumulus orthopyroxene (Opx) and Fe-Ti oxides 

(opaque minerals); C) Fe-Ti oxides (opaque mineral) enclosed in orthopyroxene (Opx) or 

03 

 

 

12 

 

14 

 

15 

 

 

 

20 

 

 

21 

 

 

21 

 

22 

 

 

 

23 

 

24 

 

 

 

 

 



e 
 

associated with interstitial plagioclase (whitish mineral) in orthopyroxenite; D) Detail of 

corona of garnet between orthopyroxene (Opx) crystals. Note also green spinel 

(hercynite) associated with magnetite (Mag) crystal; E) Fe-Ti oxides (Mag/Ilm) enclosed 

in or interstitial to orthopyroxene in magnetite orthopyroxenite; F) Irregular magnetite-

rich domains (Mag) in orthopyroxenite………………………………………………………………………..... 

Figura 11. Photographs and photomicrographs of representative rock textures of norite 

and gabbronorite in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. A) Photomicrograph of 

norite with adumulus texture; B) Photomicrograph of norite with abundant apatite. C) 

Core sample of banded norite. The intercalated white bands are composed by 

plagioclase; D) Core sample of leuconorite. The dark brown minerals are orthopyroxene 

with dark green alteration rim of talc. E) Photomicrograpf of gabbronorite consisting of 

cumulus orthopyroxene, clinopyroxene, plagioclase and apatite. Hornblende occurs as 

mineral product of alteration. F) Core sample showing veins and bag-like bodies of 

magnetite in leuconorite………………………………………………………………………………..…………..... 

Figura 12. Stratigraphic variations of selected major and minor elements. A) Drill hole 

SLJE-0272 in the Serrote da Laje Deposit. B) Drill hole CBCR-0071 in the Caboclo 

Deposit………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………….. 

Figura 13. Plot of FeO content versus major oxides and selected minor elements. A) Drill 

hole SLJE-0272 in the Serrote da Laje Deposit. B) Drill hole CBCR-0071 in the Caboclo 

Deposit………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………….. 

Figura 14. Stratigraphic variation of En content in orthopyroxene through drill hole SLJE-

0272………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………. 

Figura 15. Representative sulfide textures of ore. A) Disseminated sulfides (mainly 

chalcopyrite) in a magnetitite core sample (typical type 1 ore). B) Photomicrograph of 

sulfides interstitial to Fe-Ti oxides and orthopyroxene (type 1 ore). Sulfides consist of an 

intergrowth of bornite and chalcopyrite. C) Sulfide vein cross cutting a hydrothermally 

altered gabbroic rock (typical type 2 ore). Sulfides consist mainly of pyrite (yellow) and 

pyrrhotite (bronze color). D) Photomicrograph of a bornite-rich sulfide bleb enclosed in 

an orthopyroxene crystal. The rock is a magnetite orthopyroxenite……………………………..... 

Figura 16. Stratigraphic variations of FeO, S, Cu, Au and Pd through drill hole SLJE-0272 

in the Serrote da Laje Deposit………………………………………………………………………………………… 

Figura 17. Plot of S content versus Cu, Au and Pd for type 1 (blue) and type 2 (red) ore 

intervals in drill hole SLJE-0272 in the Serrote da Laje Deposit (see Fig. 16 for location of 

 

 

 

 

26 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

28 

 

 

30 

 

 

31 

 

33 

 

 

 

 

 

 

35 

 

36 

 

 



f 
 

indicated ore intervals). Cu/S ratios for bornite (Bn) and chalcopyrite (Cpy) in the S-Cu 

plot are based on average microprobe analyses of sulfides (Aura Minerals internal 

report)…………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………… 

Figura 18. Histogram of ?34S ‰ V-CDT values of sulfides from ultramafic rocks (type 1 

ore) and hydrothermally altered gabbroic rocks (type 2 ore) of the Serrote da Laje 

deposit………………………………………………………………………………………………………………………….. 

Figura 19. Concordia diagram of U-Pb analyses of zircons. A) Sample SLJE-17 

(leuconorite). B) Sample SLJE-28 (magnetite orthopyroxenite)………………………………………. 

Figura 20. Relative value of the contributions of Ni, Cu, and PGE to magmatic sulfide 

deposits. Modified from Naldrett (2004)……………………………………………………………………….. 

 

 

37 

 

 

38 

 

42 

 

47 

 

 

ÍNDICE DE TABELAS 

 

Tabela 1. Petrographic summary of the rock types in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo 

deposits…………………………………………………………………………………………………......................... 

Tabela 2. Sulfur isotope data for sulfide minerals of Serrote da Laje deposit………………….. 

Tabela 3. U-Pb LA-MC-ICPMS data for sample SLJE-17……..…………………………………………….. 

Tabela 4. U-Pb LA-MC-ICPMS data for sample SLJE-28……..…………………………………………….. 

Tabela 5. Sm-Nd isotopic data for the Serrote da Laje Complex……………………………........... 

 

 

25 

39 

40 

41 

43 



i 
 

RESUMO 

 

Intrusões máfica-ultramáficas são amplamente conhecidas por hospedar depósitos 

sulfetados de Ni-Cu-EGP formados a partir da segregação e concentração de gotas de um líquido 

de sulfeto de magmas máficos ou ultramáficos. A assembleia de sulfetos dos depósitos de Ni-Cu-

EGP consiste essencialmente de pirrotita, pentlandita e calcopirita. A origem de depósitos 

sulfetados ricos em Cu hospedados em intrusões máfica-ultramáficas, como os depósitos de 

Caraíba (Brasil) e Okiep (África do Sul), permanecem como uma questão controversa, com 

modelos genéticos muito distintos sendo propostos (de magmático a hidrotermal). Este estudo 

apresenta a descrição de dois depósitos ricos em sulfeto de Cu, hospedados em intrusões máfica-

ultramáficas, e discute a origem da mineralização sulfetada. 

Os depósitos do Serrote da Laje e Caboclo estão localizados na Faixa Sergipana (Província 

Borborema). As rochas máfica-ultramáficas que hospedam a mineralização de Cu-Au consistem 

em corpos irregulares de rochas mafica-ultramáficas interpretadas como pequenos diques e/ou 

pipes. Embora essas intrusões estejam parcialmente modificadas pelo metamorfismo de alto grau 

e associadas a um tectonismo dúctil, texturas e minerais magmáticos primários estão amplamente 

preservados. As intrusões máfica-ultramáficas consistem principalmente de ortopiroxenito, 

magnetitito, norito e gabronorito. A sequência de cristalização consiste em ortopiroxênio e óxidos 

de Fe-Ti, seguidos por plagioclásio e depois clinopiroxênio. O acamamento destes tipos de rochas 

é resultante do fracionamento a partir do magma parental, seja em situ ou devido sucessivos 

pulsos de magmas com fracionamento variável. As composições dos ortopiroxênios variam entre 

En65,5 a En79,2 mol % indicando composições primitivas a mais fracionadas para o magma 

parental. Tipos de rochas incomuns com flogopita e/ou granada abundante, comumente 

associadas com as rochas máfica-ultramáficas, são interpretadas como produto da assimilação das 

encaixantes gnáissicas durante a ascensão do magma. A assimilação de rochas crustais mais 

antigas também é consistente com os dados isotópicos de Sm-Nd do depósito Serrote da Laje, 

indicado pela alta variabilidade e dispersão dos valores de ?Nd (T = 1.99 Ga) (-4,33 a 3,87). 

Os sulfetos disseminados nos depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo são intersticiais ou 

inclusos dentro de piroxênios e óxidos de Fe-Ti cúmulos. A forte associação de magnetita e sulfetos 

nestes depósitos é indicada pela correlação positiva de FeO e Ti-V nas rochas máfica-ultramáficas 

hospedeiras, combinadas com a correlação positiva de FeO e S-Cu-Au no minério sulfetado. 

Características texturais e químicas descritas nos depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo suportam a 

interpretação que os sulfetos de Cu são magmáticos e diretamente associados com as rochas ricas 



ii 
 

em magnetita. As assembleias de sulfetos de ambos os depósitos consistem principalmente de 

bornita e calcopirita, com razão Cu/Fe variando entre 1, em amostras de minério ricas em 

calcopirita, e 5 em amostras ricas em bornita.  Os resultados dos isótopos de enxofre para 

calcopirita e bornita têm uma estreita gama de valores, entre -1,0 e 2,5 ?34S ‰, suportando a 

origem magmática do minério. A combinação de cristalização fracionada do magma parental 

combinada com a oxidação do magma é sugerida como mecanismo apropriado para formar 

sulfetos magmáticos ricos em Cu com alta razão Cu/Fe dos depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo. 

Mineralização de Cu sulfetada subordinada ocorre em veios e/ou brechas em rochas 

máfica-ultramáficas alteradas. Resultados de isótopos de enxofre em pirita, pirrotita e calcopirita 

de veios ou brechas variam entre 7,5 to 13,0 ?34S ‰, sugerindo origem hidrotermal. Esta 

mineralização secundária é interpretada como resultado da percolação de fluidos pelas rochas 

máfica-ultramáficas mineralizadas que remobilizou parcialmente os sulfetos do minério primário. 

Esta interpretação não indica a existência de uma mineralização hidrotermal de Cu-Au robusta, 

que poderia indicar diferentes alvos de exploração além dos investigados neste estudo. 

A idade magmática das rochas máficas-ultramáficas hospedeiras dos depósitos Serrote da 

Laje (ca. 1,99 Ga) e Caraíba (ca 2,05 Ga) sugerem que importantes depósitos de Cu localizados 

próximos a borda norte do Cráton do São Francisco estão associados a intrusões 

Paleoproterozóicas.   

 

Palavras-chave: sulfetos magmáticos, cobre, ouro, Serrote da Laje, Caboclo, rochas máfica-

ultramáficas 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



iii 
 

 

ABSTRACT 

 

Mafic-ultramafic intrusions are widely known for hosting Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide deposits 

formed as the result of the segregation and concentration of droplets of liquid sulfide from mafic 

or ultramafic magma. The bulk sulfide assemblage of Ni-Cu-PGE deposits consists essentially of 

pyrrhotite, pentlandite and chalcopyrite. The origin of Cu-rich sulfide deposits hosted in mafic-

ultramafic intrusions, exemplified by the Caraíba (Brazil) and Okiep (South Africa) deposits, 

remains however a controversial issue, and highly distinct genetic models have been proposed 

(from magmatic to hydrothermal). This study present the description of two Cu-rich deposits 

hosted by mafic-ultramafic intrusions and discuss the origin of the sulfide mineralization. 

 The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are located in the Sergipano Belt (Borborema 

structural province). The mafic-ultramafic rocks hosting Cu-Au mineralization in the Serrote da 

Laje and Caboclo deposits consist of irregular bodies of mafic-ultramafic rocks interpreted as small 

dikes and/or pipes. Although these intrusions are partially modified by high-grade metamorphism 

and associated ductile tectonism, primary magmatic textures and minerals are largely preserved. 

Mafic-ultramafic intrusions consist mainly of variably textured orthopyroxenite, magnetitite, 

norite and gabbronorite. The crystallization sequence consists of orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides 

followed by plagioclase and then by clinopyroxene. Systematic interlayering of these rock types 

are consistent with all rock types resulting from fractionation from a parental magma, either in 

situ or due to successive pulses of variably fractionated magma. Orthopyroxene compositions 

ranging from En65.5 to En79.22 mol % indicate moderately primitive to fractionated compositions 

for the parental magma. Unusual rock types with abundant phlogopite and/or garnet, commonly 

associated with mafic-ultramafic rocks, are interpreted as products of assimilation of country 

gneissic rocks during magmatic emplacement. Assimilation of older crustal rocks is also consistent 

with Sm-Nd isotopic data of the Serrote da Laje Complex, as indicated by highly variable and 

scattered ?Nd (T = 1.99 Ga) values (-4.33 to 3.87). 

 Disseminated sulfides in both Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are interstitial to or 

enclosed into cumulus orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides. The close association of magnetite and 

sulfides in the Serrote da Laje deposit is indicated by positive correlations of FeO and Ti-V in hosted 

mafic-ultramafic rocks matched with positive correlations of FeO and S-Cu-Au in sulfide ore. 

Textural and chemical features described in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits support the 

interpretation that Cu-rich sulfides are magmatic and closely associated with magnetite-rich rocks. 



iv 
 

The sulfide assemblages in both deposits consist mainly of bornite and chalcopyrite, with Cu/Fe 

ratio in sulfides ranging from about 1 in chalcopyrite-rich ore samples to about 5 in bornite-rich 

samples. Sulfur isotope results for chalcopyrite and bornite has a narrow range of values from -

1.0 to 2.5 ?34S ‰, thus supporting a magmatic origin for the ore. A fractional crystallization of the 

parental magma combined with magmatic oxidation is suggested as an appropriate mechanism to 

generate the Cu-rich magmatic sulfides with high Cu/Fe ratios of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo 

deposits. 

 Subordinated Cu-sulfide mineralization occurs in veins and/or breccia in altered mafic-

ultramafic rocks. Sulfur isotope results for pyrite, pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite in veins or breccia 

range from 7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰, suggesting a hydrothermal origin. This secondary ore is 

interpreted as the result of sulfides from hydrothermal fluids that percolate the Cu-Au mineralized 

mafic-ultramafic rocks and partially remobilized the primary ore. This interpretation does not 

indicate the existence of a robust Cu-Au hydrothermal mineralization that may lead to different 

exploration targets than those investigated in this study.  

Close magmatic ages of mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote da Laje deposit (ca. 1.99 Ga) 

and the Caraíba deposit (ca. 2.05) suggest that significant Cu deposits are associated with 

Paleoproterozoic mafic-ultramafic intrusions in the region located close to the northern border of 

the São Francisco Craton in Brazil. 

 

Key Words: magmatic sulfides, copper, gold, Serrote da Laje, Caboclo, mafic-ultramafic rocks 



1 
 

CONSIDERAÇÕES GERAIS 

Introdução 

Trabalhos de exploração e avaliação desenvolvidos pela Aura Minerals Inc. 

(www.auraminerals.com) nos depósitos de Cu-Au do Serrote da Laje e Caboclo indicaram grande 

recurso mineral (~750 kt de Cu contido) hospedado em uma associação de rochas máfica-

ultramáficas compostas por piroxenito norito e ilmenita-magnetitito acamadados. Além do 

aumento significativo dos recursos minerais, os trabalhos desenvolvidos pela Aura Minerals 

propiciaram um melhor entendimento da estrutura geológica-estratigráfica dos complexos 

máfico-ultramáficos e mineralizações de Cu-Au. 

  Trabalhos anteriores desenvolvidos pela DOCEGEO sugerem um modelo de mineralização 

magmática para o depósito de Serrote da Laje (Horbach &amp;amp; Marimon, 1988). Segundo estes autores 

a mineralização está hospedada em um complexo máfico-ultramáfico submetido a intensos 

processos pós-magmáticos, incluindo um evento metamórfico de alto grau. As características do 

depósito de Serrote da Laje são, contudo, distintas daquelas observadas nos depósitos de Ni-Cu 

associados a complexos máficos-ultramáficos (Naldrett, 2004, 2010). Intrusões máfico-ultramáfica 

são conhecidas por hospedar depósitos de Ni-Cu-PGE sulfetado originados pela segregação de um 

líquido imiscível de sulfeto a partir de magmas máfico-ultramáficos (Barnes &amp;amp; Lightfoot, 2005). A 

origem de depósitos ricos em Cu associados a intrusões máfico-ultramáficas é, contudo, 

controversa. A origem destes depósitos, exemplificados pelos depósitos de Caraíba (Bahia) e 

Okiep (África do Sul), tem sido interpretada como resultante de processos magmáticos (i.e., 

segregação de um líquido imiscível de sulfeto; Oliveira and Tarney, 1995; Clifford and Barton, 

2012), como resultado de processos magmáticos transformados por processos metamórficos de 

alto grau (Cawthorn &amp;amp; Meyer, 1993; Barnes &amp;amp; Maier, 1999) e, mais recentemente, como depósitos 

hidrotermais do tipo IOCG (Williams et al., 2005; Groves et al., 2010; Maier et al., 2012). Os 

trabalhos de exploração mineral desenvolvidos pela Aura Minerals indicam a existência de 

diferentes tipos de mineralizações e/ou remobilizações no depósito Serrote da Laje, sugerindo 

que o depósito tem uma origem mais complexa do que aquela aventada nos trabalhos anteriores.  

 A proposta do projeto é apresentar descrição geológica dos depósitos Serrote da Laje e 

Caboclo, utilizando os dados de exploração adquiridos pela Aura Minerals Inc, e resultados obtidos 

neste estudo, incluindo litogeoquímica, química mineral e dados isotópicos de enxofre, U-Pb e 

Sm-Nd, e, com isso contribuir para a definição da origem da mineralização sulfetada destes 

depósitos e auxiliar nos trabalhos de exploração mineral.  



2 
 

Localização e fisiografia 

O depósito do Serrote da Laje está localizado à aproximadamente 10 km a noroeste da 

cidade de Arapiraca, na porção central do estado de Alagoas (Figura i). A cidade de Arapiraca 

possui aproximadamente 210.0000 habitantes (IBGE, 2009), sendo a segunda maior do Estado de 

Alagoas, e é o centro social, político e econômico da região do Agreste Alagoano. O acesso a partir 

de Maceió é feito através da rodovia pavimentada BR-316, BR-101 e AL-220, com percurso total 

em torno de 136 km. Já o depósito do Caboclo está localizado à aproximadamente 15km a 

noroeste do depósito Serrote da Laje, próximo da cidade de Craíbas que possui cerca de 22.000 

habitantes. O acesso a partir de Arapiraca é feito pela através da rodovia pavimentada AL-115, 

com percurso em torno de 20 km. 

A região em que se inserem os depósitos é caracterizada principalmente por áreas planas, 

com cotas que variam de 265 a 300 metros, arrasadas e de baixa declividade. Essa paisagem é 

interrompida apenas por poucos inselbergs, como o Serrote da Laje. 

O clima é definido por temperaturas elevadas, com a média anual de 25ºC e precipitação 

segundo o intervalo de 750 a 1000 mm. Os três meses mais chuvosos são maio, junho e julho, 

concentrando geralmente mais de 50% do total anual, e os mínimos pluviométricos são 

registrados na primavera ou no verão, com variação de quatro a cinco meses de seca. 

 A vegetação da região é típica do Agreste, rala e de pequeno porte, como mirtáceas, 

combretáceas, leguminosas e cactáceas. A região apresenta intensa degradação, principalmente 

para cultivo de fumo, milho e pastagem.  

 



3 
 

 

Figura i – Mapa de localização dos depósitos de Cu-Au do Serrote da Laje e Caboclo. 

 

Justificativa e objetivos 

O objetivo do projeto é o determinar a origem dos sulfetos de Cu nos depósitos do Serrote 

da Laje e Caboclo, contemplando os diferentes tipos de mineralização identificados. Estudos 

específicos que foram desenvolvidos incluem a caracterização detalhada dos aspectos 

petrográficos-petrológicos das rochas que compõem o complexo máfico-ultramáfico, a idade da 

intrusão e a caracterização do minério (petrografia, litogeoquímica, isótopos de S).  

A utilização de modelos genéticos, ou processos metalogenéticos, como ferramenta na 

exploração de depósitos de Cu-Au associados a rochas máfica-ultramáficas é dificultada pela 

existência de propostas marcadamente distintas. O melhor entendimento destes processos nos 

depósitos de Serrote da Laje e Caboclo, especialmente considerando a existência de diferentes 

tipos de mineralização, deve subsidiar os trabalhos de exploração mineral para mineralizações 

deste tipo. 

 

 



4 
 

Métodos 

• Levantamento bibliográfico 

Para o alcance destes objetivos foi realizado levantamento bibliográfico referente ao 

contexto geológico regional da área de estudo, bem como publicações existentes sobre o depósito 

Serrote da Laje. O estado da arte enfocando a metalogênses dos depósitos de sulfetos 

magmáticos, em especial os processos que propiciam o enriquecimento em Cu nos líquidos 

sulfetados, foi criticamente avaliada nesta fase. 

• Petrografia 

Foram desenvolvidos trabalhos petrográficos em 292 amostras das intrusões máfica-

ultramáficas, bem como das respectivas encaixantes. Destas, 250 amostras são do banco de dados 

da Aura Minerals Inc e 42 são novas laminas (30 do depósito Serrote da Laje e 12 do depósito 

Caboclo), confeccionadas a partir de amostras de 2 furos representativos selecionados para 

trabalhos específicos do projeto.  

• Geoquímica mineral 

Análises químicas de mineral em microssonda eletrônica foram realizadas utilizando o 

equipamento JEOL JXA-8230 do Laboratório de Microsonda Eletrônica da Universidade de Brasília. 

As análises foram realizadas de forma sistemática apenas em cristais de ortopiroxênios, sendo 

realizado o tratamento dos dados em planilha Excel. Os resultados analíticos encontram-se no 

Anexo 1.   

• Geoquímica de rocha  

As análises litogeoquímicas foram realizadas de forma sistemática pela Aura Minerals Inc., 

sendo utilizado como laboratório principal o da SGS Geosol Ltda. Resultados para 35 elementos 

foram obtidos utilizando ICP-MS. Resultados de Cu foram adquiridos por análises de AA, enquanto 

Au, Pt e Pd foram obtidos por fire assay, utilizando ICP-MS para finalizar.  A descrição completa 

dos procedimentos analíticos é disponibilizada pela SGS Geosol (www.sgs.com). Ao todo, foram 

realizadas análises em cerca de 49.000 amostras, tomadas de forma contínua, em intervalos de 1 

m dentro do intervalo de rochas máfica-ultramáficas, respeitando-se os contatos litológicos. 

Foram selecionados os resultados analíticos de 2 furos representativos para ilustrar as 

importantes características litogeoquímicas destas rochas. 

 



5 
 

• Isótopos de S 

Composições isotópicas de pirrotita, bornita, calcopirita e pirita foram determinadas pelo 

Laboratório de Geocronologia do Instituto de Geociências da Universidade de Brasília. Um total 

de 09 amostras, incluindo 06 amostras de minério classificado como tipo 1 e 03 amostras de 

minério tipo 2, foram coletadas para este estudo, ambas do depósito Serrote da Laje (Tabela 2). 

As composições dos isótopos de enxofre foram reportadas em notação relativa ao V-CDT, com 

valores de 32S/34S de 22,6436 (Ding et al., 2001).  

• Isótopos de Sm-Nd 

As análises de isótopos de de Sm-Nd seguiram o método descrito por Gioia &amp;amp; Pimentel 

(2000), e foram realizados no Laboratório de Geocronologia da Universidade de Brasília. A 

análise baseia-se no decaimento do isótopo 147 Sm para 143Nd com emissão de uma partícula 

?. Ao todo foram realizadas análises em 07 amostras e os resultados obtidos estão no Tabela 5.  

• Isótopos de U-Pb 

Concentrados de zircão foram extraídos de amostras de sondagem diamantada usando 

técnicas convencionais gravimétricas e magnéticas, e a partir de seleção manual com lupa 

binocular no Laboratório de Geocronologia da Universidade de Brasília. As análises U-Pb LA-ICPMS 

seguiram os procedimentos analíticos descritos por Buhn et al (2009), e foram realizados no 

Laboratório de Geocronologia da Universidade de Brasília. As amostras selecionadas incluem 

norito (SRLJ 28) e leuconorito (SRLJ 17) com zircões magmáticos associados e os resultados obtidos 

são apresentados nas tabelas 3 e 4. 

 

Escopo do estudo 

 Esta dissertação de mestrado apresenta-se em estruturada em forma de artigo à ser 

submetido para publicação em periódico com corpo editorial. Esta forma de apresentação está 

prevista no regulamento do Curso de Pós-graduação em Geologia da Universidade de Brasília. O 

artigo é apresentado na mesma forma que será submetido, mantendo o formato previsto no 

periódico. 

 O artigo “The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo Cu-Au deposits, northeast Brazil: Magmatic 

Sulfides hosted by ilmenite-magnetite-bearing mafic-ultramafic intrusions” foi elaborado 

durante o ano de 2016 e será submetido à revista Economic Geology. O artigo tem como objetivo 



6 
 

principal descrever as características petrológicas, geoquímicas e isotópicas dos depósitos e 

propor a origem dos sulfetos de Cu 

 

Referências 

Barnes, S.-J., Lightfoot, P.C., 2005. Formation of magmatic nickel sulfide ore deposits and 

processes affecting their copper and platinum group element contents. Economic Geology 100th 

Anniversary Volume, p. 179–213. 

 

Buhn, B., Pimentel, M.M., Matteini, M., Dantas, E.L., 2009. High spatial resolution analysis of Pb 

and U isotopes for geochronology by laser ablation multicollector inductively coupled plasma mass 

spectrometry (LA-MC-ICP-MS). Anais Academia Brasileira de Ciências, v. 81, p. 1-16. 

 

Cawthorn, R.G., Meyer, F.M., 1993. Petrochemistry of the Okiep cooper district basic intrusive 

bodies, northwestern Cape province, South Africa. Economic Geology, v. 88, p. 590-605 

 

Clifford, T.N., Barton, E.S., 2012. The O'okiep Copper District, Namaqualand, South Africa: a 

review of the geology with emphasis on the petrogenesis of the cupriferous Koperberg Suite. 

Mineralium Deposita, v. 47, p. 837-857. 

 

Ding, T., Valkiers, S., Kipphardt, H., De Biève, P., Taylor, P.D.P., Gonfiantini, R., Krouse, R., 2001. 

Calibrated sulfur isotope abundance ratios of three IAEA sulfur isotope reference materials and V-

CDT with a reassessment of the atomic weight of sulfur. Geochim Cosmochim Acta, v. 65, p. 2433–

2437. 

 

Gioia, S.M.C.L., Pimentel, M.M., 2000. The Sm-Nd isotopic method in the geochronology 

laboratory of University of Brasilia. Anais da Academia Brasileira de Ciências, v. 72, p. 219-245. 

 

Groves, D.I.P., Bierlein, F.P., Meinert, L.D., Hitzman, M.W., 2010. Iron oxide copper–gold (IOCG) 

deposits through Earth history; implications for origin, lithospheric setting, and distinction from 

other epigenetic iron oxide deposits. Economic Geology, v. 105, p. 641–654. 

 



7 
 

Horbach, R., Marimon, M. P. C., 1988. O Depósito de Cobre do Serrote da Laje, em Arapiraca, 

Alagoas. XXXV Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, Belém, SBG, Anais, v. 1, p. 01- 15. 

 

Naldrett, A.J., 2004. Magmatic sulfide deposits: Geology, Geochemistry and Exploration. 

Heidelberg, Springer Verlag, 728 p.  

 

Naldrett, A.J., 2010. Secular Variation of Magmatic Sulfide Deposits and Their Source Magmas. 

Economic Geology, v. 105, p. 669-688. 

 

Maier, W.D., Andreoli, M.A.G, Groves, D.I., Barnes, S-J., 2012. Petrogenesis of Cu-Ni sulphide ores 

from Okiep and Kliprand, Namaqualand, South Africa: Constraints from chalcophile metal 

contents. South African Journal of Geology, v. 114.4, p. 499-514.  

 

Maier, W.D., Barnes, S-J., 1999. The origin of Cu sulfide deposits in the Curaca Valley, Bahia, Brazil; 

evidence from Cu, Ni, Se, and platinum-group element concentrations. Economic Geology, v. 94, 

p.165-183 

Oliveira, E.P., Tarney, J., 1995. Genesis of the precambrian copper-rich Caraiba hypersthenite-

norite complex, Brazil. Mineralium Deposita, v. 30, p. 351-373. 

 

Williams, P.J., Barton, M.D., Fontbote´ L, 2005. Iron-oxide–copper–gold deposits: Geology, space–

time distribution, and possible modes of origin. Economic Geology 100th Anniversary Volume, p. 

371–406. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



8 
 

THE SERROTE DA LAJE AND CABOCLO CU-AU DEPOSITS, NORTHEST BRAZIL: MAGMATIC 

SULFIDES HOSTED BY ILMINITE-MAGNETITE-BEARING MAFIC-ULTRAMAFIC INTRUSIONS 

 

Authors: Guilherme Ferreira Canedo (gcanedo@auraminerals.com), Cesar F. Ferreira Filho and 

Elton L. Dantas  

 

Abstract 

Mafic-ultramafic intrusions are widely known for hosting Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide deposits 

formed as the result of the segregation and concentration of droplets of liquid sulfide from mafic 

or ultramafic magma. The compositions of the segregated Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide melts are controlled 

by the fractionation of monosulfide solid solution (mss), such that the last sulfide composition 

before complete crystallization takes place should be close to the intermediate solid solution (iss). 

The bulk sulfide assemblage of Ni-Cu-PGE deposits consists essentially of pyrrhotite, pentlandite 

and chalcopyrite. The origin of Cu-rich sulfide deposits hosted in mafic-ultramafic intrusions, 

exemplified by the Caraíba (Brazil) and Okiep (South Africa) deposits, remains however a 

controversial issue, and highly distinct genetic models have been proposed (from magmatic to 

hydrothermal). In this study we present the description of two Cu-rich deposits hosted by mafic-

ultramafic intrusions and discuss the origin of the sulfide mineralization. 

 The mafic-ultramafic bodies hosting Cu-Au mineralization in the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo deposits consist of irregular bodies of mafic-ultramafic rocks interpreted as small dikes 

and/or pipes. Although these intrusions are partially modified by high-grade metamorphism and 

associated ductile tectonism, primary magmatic textures and minerals are largely preserved. 

Mafic-ultramafic intrusions consist mainly of variably textured orthopyroxenite, magnetitite, 

norite and gabbronorite. The crystallization sequence consists of orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides 

followed by plagioclase and then by clinopyroxene. Systematic interlayering of these rock types 

are consistent with all rock types resulting from fractionation from a parental magma, either in 

situ or due to successive pulses of variably fractionated magma. Orthopyroxene compositions 

ranging from En65.5 to En79.2 mol % indicate moderately primitive to fractionated compositions 

for the parental magma. Unusual rock types with abundant phlogopite and/or garnet, commonly 

associated with mafic-ultramafic rocks, are interpreted as products of assimilation of country 

gneissic rocks during magmatic emplacement. Assimilation of older crustal rocks is also consistent 

with Sm-Nd isotopic data of the Serrote da Laje Complex, as indicated by highly variable and 

scattered ?Nd (T = 1.99 Ga) values (-4.33 to 3.87). 



9 
 

 Disseminated sulfides in both Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are interstitial to or 

enclosed into cumulus orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides. The close association of magnetite and 

sulfides in the Serrote da Laje deposit is indicated by positive correlations of FeO and Ti-V in hosted 

mafic-ultramafic rocks matched with positive correlations of FeO and S-Cu-Au in sulfide ore. 

Textural and chemical features described in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits support the 

interpretation that Cu-rich sulfides are magmatic and closely associated with magnetite-rich rocks. 

The sulfide assemblages in both deposits consist mainly of bornite and chalcopyrite, with Cu/Fe 

ratio in sulfides ranging from about 1 in chalcopyrite-rich ore samples to about 5 in bornite-rich 

samples. Sulfur isotope results for chalcopyrite and bornite has a narrow range of values from -

1.0 to 2.5 ?34S ‰, thus supporting a magmatic origin for the ore. Fractional crystallization of the 

parental magma combined with magmatic oxidation is suggested as an appropriate mechanism to 

generate the Cu-rich magmatic sulfides with high Cu/Fe ratios of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo 

deposits. 

 Subordinated Cu-sulfide mineralization occurs in veins and/or breccia in altered mafic-

ultramafic rocks. Sulfur isotope results for pyrite, pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite in veins or breccia 

range from 7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰, suggesting a hydrothermal origin. We interpreted this secondary 

ore as the result of sulfides from hydrothermal fluids that percolate the Cu-Au mineralized mafic-

ultramafic rocks and partially remobilized the primary ore. This interpretation does not indicate 

the existence of a robust Cu-Au hydrothermal mineralization that may lead to different 

exploration targets than those investigated in this study.   

Close magmatic ages of mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote da Laje deposit (ca. 1.99 Ga) 

and the Caraíba deposit (ca. 2.05) suggest that significant Cu deposits are associated with 

Paleoproterozoic mafic-ultramafic intrusions in the region located close to the northern border of 

the São Francisco Craton in Brazil. 

 

Keywords: mafic-ultramafic intrusion, Cu-rich sulfide, magnetite, orthopyroxene, sulfur isotope, 

oxidation 

 

  



10 
 

1 - Introduction 

 Recent data from Aura Minerals (www.auraminerals.com) for the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo Cu-Au sulfide deposits indicate a large (~750 Kt of contained metal) resource hosted in 

interlayered pyroxenite, norite and ilmenite-magnetitite. Mafic-ultramafic intrusions are widely 

known for hosting Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide deposits formed as the result of the segregation and 

concentration of droplets of liquid sulfide from mafic or ultramafic magma (e.g., Naldrett, 2004; 

Barnes and Lightfoot, 2005). The origin of Cu-rich sulfide deposits hosted in mafic-ultramafic 

intrusions, exemplified by the Caraíba (Brazil) and Okiep (South Africa) deposits, remains however 

a controversial issue. These deposits were interpreted as the result of primary magmatic origin 

(e.g., Oliveira and Tarney, 1995; Clifford and Barton, 2012), of high-grade metamorphic 

modification of an originally magmatic deposit (e.g., Cawthorn and Meyer, 1993; Barnes and 

Maier, 1999) and more recently as a member of IOCG-type hydrothermal deposits (e.g., Williams 

et al., 2005; Groves et al., 2010; Maier et al., 2012). The use of genetic models for the exploration 

of such deposits is hampered by such distinct and unrelated propositions. In this study we present 

a geological description of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits based upon extensive 

exploration data acquired by Aura Minerals Inc. These geological descriptions, together with 

geochemical results from this study, including lithogeochemistry, mineral compositions and sulfur, 

U-Pb and Sm-Nd isotopic data, provide a basic framework to constraint the origin of the Cu-Au 

sulfide mineralization. The Serrote da Laje and Caboblo Cu-Au deposits are interpreted in this 

study to belong to a significant but yet poorly investigated class of Cu-rich magmatic deposits. 

 

2 - Exploration History 

 A brief description of more than 30 years of exploration in the Serrote da Laje is provided 

by Aura Minerals Ltd (www.auraminerals.com). The Brazilian Geological Survey (previously known 

as Companhia de Pesquisa de Recursos Minerais - CPRM; a state-owned exploration company), 

reported anomalous copper and nickel values associated with mafic intrusion in the region of 

Arapiraca in 1979. This report described the Serrote da Laje as a magnetite-rich outcrop that 

contained anomalous values of copper (up to 0.03 wt. %), zinc (up to 0.50 wt. %), vanadium (up to 

0.20 wt. %) and chromium (&gt; 0.50 wt. %). Upon confirming the anomalous values reported by 

CPRM, Rio Doce Geologia e Mineração (DOCEGEO), the former exploration arm of VALE S.A., 

began in 1982 a detailed exploration campaign guided by geochemical and geophysical surveys in 

the area. The resulting geochemical anomaly maps for copper and nickel indicated a good 

agreement with the ground magnetic and gravity anomaly maps. The anomalous geochemical and 



11 
 

geophysical maps were used to direct subsequent drilling programs. By 1991 DOCEGEO reported 

an estimated mineral resource of 26.7 Mt @ 0.72% Cu based on 37 drill holes (10,818 m). 

Exploration in the Serrote da Laje was interrupted in the 1990s when the new discoveries of 

copper deposits in the Carajas Mineral Province (e.g., Alemao, Cristalino, Sossego and Solobo) 

became VALE's main focus of exploration. From 1998 to 2002 a second drilling campaign was 

undertaken by VALE aiming to increase mineral resources of the Serrote da Laje deposit. During 

this campaign VALE drilled 52 drill holes (15,348 m) totalling 89 drill holes (26,166) and an 

estimated resource of 73.9 Mt @ 0.62% Cu was reported in 2002.  

On July 2007, Aura Minerals acquired the property, through its subsidiary, Mineração Vale 

Verde Ltda. (MVV). MVV conducted additional exploration work between 2007 and 2010, 

including 291 drill holes totalling 62,686 m. Most holes were drilled vertically with depths ranging 

from 30 to 507 m. The exploration work by MVV resulted in a measured and indicated resource 

for Serrote da Laje deposit of 137.46 Mt @ 0.49% Cu. The MVV completed the feasibility study in 

2012 and negotiations for project financing and development are currently (i.e., 2016) under way. 

In the Caboclo deposit, from 1999 to 2001, VALE conducted a drilling campaign, totalling 

18 drill holes (2,349 m). MVV conduct additional exploration work between 2007 and 2010, 

including 174 diamond drill holes (24,950 m), on five targets including the Rogerio and Zeze. MVV 

estimated a measure and indicated resource of 10.91 Mt @ 0.51% Cu for Rogerio target, and 

inferred resources of 2.26 Mt @ 0.61% Cu for Zeze target. 

 

3 - Tectonic Setting 

3.1 - Borborema Province 

 The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits, northeast of Brazil, are located in the Borborema 

structural province (BP), a mosaic of paleo-neoproterozoic metassedimentary fold belts and 

massifs separated by a complex system of continental-scale strike-slip shear zones (Almeida et al., 

1981). These sequences together with the voluminous granitic magmatism are the most 

outstanding features of this province (Caby et al., 1991) (Fig. 1). Neoproterozoic events (Brasiliano 

Cycle), including the continental-scale EW shear zones (e.g., Patos and Pernambuco lineaments in 

Fig. 1) and NE megastructures, separate the major subprovinces and domains (Santos 1996; 1998; 

2000) (Fig. 1). The Meridional subprovince occurs between the Pernambuco shear zone and the 

São Francisco craton and is comprised of a tectonic collage of various blocks, terranes, or domains 

ranging in age from Archean to Neoproterozoic (Van Schmus et al, 2011). The Meridional 

subprovince is composed by Pernambuco-Alagoas massif and Rio Preto, Riacho do Pontal and 



12 
 

Sergipano fold belts (Brito Neves et al, 2000). The Sergipano Fold Belt (SB), a sedimentary basin 

that was generated and deformed in the proterozoic, separates the BP from the São Francisco 

Craton. 

 

 

Figure 1 - Borborema structural province map indicating the location of the Meridional 

subprovince, highlighted in green tones. Adapted from Santos (1998, 2000). 



13 
 

3.2 - Sergipano Belt 

 The Sergipano Belt (SB) was formed by the continental collision of the São Francisco-Congo 

Craton and the Pernambuco-Alagoas massif during the Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny (Brito 

Neves et al., 1977). The SB (Fig. 2) is divided into lithostratigraphic domains separated by strike-

slip shear zones (Davison and Santos, 1989; Silva Filho and Torres, 2002). The southern portion of 

the SB consists of metavolcanics and metasedimentary rocks deposited around 

Archean/Paleoproterozoic basement gneiss. In the northern portion occur domain of 

paragneisses, partially migmatised, and metasediments, besides domains with syn and tardi 

granitic intrusions. Silva Filho and Torres (2002) separated the Sergipano Belt in 5 domains:  

Macururé, Vaza Barris, Estância, Rio Coruripe and Viçosa. The Rio Coruripe domain contains rift-

related volcano-sedimentary sequence, metabasalts and iron-formation bearing, intruded by 

mafic-ultramafic layered intrusion. 

The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are part of the Rio Coruripe domain, which 

includes the Jaramataia Group and the Serrote da Laje suite of rocks of Proterozoic age (Figure 3). 

The Jaramataia Group is composed of a metavolcanosedimentary sequence in which the dominant 

lithotypes are quartz-feldspathic gneisses and garnet-biotite gneisses. Marbles, calcsilicate rocks 

and iron-formations are also common. A mafic-ultramafic intrusion forms the Serrote da Laje 

suite. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



14 
 

 

Figure 2 - Lithostratigraphic domains of the Sergipano Belt. Adapted from Silva Filho et al. (2003). 

 

 

 

 

 



15 
 

Figure 3 – Geological map of central part of Alagoas state, showing the localization of the Serrote 

da Laje and Caboclo deposits. Adapted from Mendes et al. (2009). 



16 
 

3.3 - Layered MUM intrusions of the SB 

 The geology and Cu mineralizations of the Serrote da Laje deposit were previously 

described by Horbach and Morimon (1988). This study, based on data provided by the 

exploration program developed by DOCEGEO from 1982 to 1986, provided a broad geological 

description of the mafic-ultramafic rocks, sulfide mineralization and its country rocks.  

 The mafic-ultramafic rocks are hosted in paragneiss of the Jaramataia group. Horbach and 

Marimon (1988) identified two main country rocks, the quartz-feldspar gneiss, pinkish color, and 

the garnet gneiss, grayish color. Both gneiss has medium grained and they have silimanite and 

cordierite in their composition, indicating a high grade of metamorphism. Mafic-ultramafic rocks 

were described as a tectonically disrupted layered intrusion composed by hypersthenites, norites, 

gabbronorites, gabbros and anorthosites. Magnetitite bodies occur associated with 

hypersthenites and norites. The author's recognized two types of mineralization: i. disseminated 

sulfides associated with hypersthenites, norites and magnetitites, and ii. sulfide-bearing veins 

mainly associated with gabbroic rocks. The main ore minerals are chalcopyrite and bornite, in the 

sulfide zone, and malachite in the oxidized zone.  

The metamorphism of the deposit reached the granulite facies (Horbach and Marimon, 

1988), as indicated by the occurrence of the sillimanite+garnet+biotite+quartz paragenesis in the 

metasedimentary rocks; as well as metamorphic orthopyroxene in the mafic-ultramafic rocks. 

During the evolution of the deformation some reactions of re-equilibrium occurred, reaching high 

amphibolite facies (Amcoff and Figueiredo, 1990). Probably due to uplift movements associated 

to granitc intrusions, a hydrated paragenesis were developed, and marked the metassomatism 

common to all rock types of the deposit. 

Previous works (Brito et al., 2000) suggested that the age of the mafic-ultramafic intrusion 

is Paleoproterozoic. U-Pb zircon data from the metanorite provided a crystallization age for the 

copper-bearing mafic-ultramafic suite at 1965 Ma, whilst a round zircon fraction, present in the 

same sample, yielded an inherited age of 2.049 Ga. Metanorite, metamorphosed magnetite-

hypersthenite and related fine-grained metagabbro display TDM model ages from 2.4 Ga to 2.74 

Ga. The country rocks apparently have two types sediments source with different ages. One with 

207Pb/206Pb radiometric ages between 2.03 and 2.25 Ga and provided Archaean TDM model 

ages around 2.7 Ga and the other with detrital Pb-Pb ages varying from 2.4 to 2.52 Ga and Sm-Nd 

TDM model ages that span from 2.89 to 3.1 Ga.  

 

 



17 
 

4 - Methods 

4.1 - Petrography of mafic-ultramafic rocks 

 Detailed petrography was performed in a large collection (about 250 samples) of thin-

polished sections from the Aura Minerals database, as well as 42 new thin-polished sections of 

Serrote da Laje (30 samples) and Caboclo (12 samples) deposits. These new thin sections were cut 

from samples collected from two representative drill holes, one of Serrote da Laje deposit and 

another of Caboclo deposit. The petrographic study was developed in optical microscopes of the 

Mineralogy Laboratory of the Geosciences Institute, University of Brasilia.  

 

4.2 - Microprobe analyses 

 Mineral analyses were performed on polished thin section using a 5-spectrometer JEOL 

JXA-8230 SuperProbe at the Electron Microprobe Laboratory of the University of Brasília (Brazil). 

The wavelength dispersive (WDS) analyses were performed at an accelerating voltage of 15 kV 

and a beam current of 10 nA. Both synthetic and natural mineral standards were used for the 

analyses and the same standards and procedure were retained throughout the analytical work. 

Systematic WDS analyses were obtained just for orthopyroxene (see supplementary material for 

microprobe analyses). 

 

4.3 - Lithogeochemistry  

SGS Geosol Ltda was used as the principal analytical laboratory by Aura Minerals Inc. 

Assays were checked with additional analyses, following the same analytical procedures, by ALS 

Chemex Laboratory (ALS). Results for 35 elements were obtained by 4-acid digestion Inductive 

Coupled Plasma Mass Spectroscopy (ICP-MS). A complete description of analytical methods is 

available in the SGS Geosol (www.sgs.com) and ALS Chemex Home Page (www.alsglobal.com). 

Results for 35 elements were obtained from half drill core whole-rock samples. They were sampled 

continuously at approximately 1-m intervals. Cu assays by AA were also obtained. Samples with 

FeO contents higher than 20 wt. % by ICP-MS analyses were submitted to a lithium tetraborate 

fusion and analysis by x-ray fluorescence (XRF). Au, Pt and Pd were determined by 50 g fire assay 

(ALS Chemex code FD50) using an ICP-MS finish. Results for two representative drill holes of Aura 

Minerals Inc database (drill holes SLJE-272 and CBCR-71) were used to illustrate significant 

lithogeochemical features (Appendix 01). 

 

 



18 
 

4.4 - Sulfur isotopes 

 Sulfur isotope compositions of pyrrhotite, pentlandite, chalcopyrite, and pyrite were 

determined at the Geochronology Laboratory of the Geosciences Institute of the University of 

Brasilia. A total of nine samples, including six samples of ore type 1 and three samples of ore type 

2 were collected from the Serrote da Laje deposit for sulfur isotopic study. Representative sulfides 

of each ore type were hand picked and individually mounted. Thin polished sections of the 

samples were prepared and cleaned in an ultrasonic bath. The laser equipment employed was a 

New Wave UP 213 laser with 213-?m wavelength, coupled to a Finnigan-Neptune multicollector 

inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometer. The laser was run at 9-Hz frequency and 36% 

energy. The Helium gas flux through the sample chamber was 0.35 l/min. The MCICPMS was run 

in medium resolution, a forward power of 930W, and an Ar gas flux of 0.857 l/min, using the 

procedures described in Bender et al. (2007). Analytical precision was better than ±0.4‰ 1 sigma 

standard deviation. The external reproducibility (accuracy) measured against a second standard 

was ±0.3‰ 1 s SD. Sulfur isotope compositions are reported in the ? notation relative to V-CDT 

with a 32S/34S value of 22.6436 (Ding et al., 2001). 

 

4.5 - Sm-Nd isotopes 

 Sm-Nd isotopic analyses followed the method described by Gioia and Pimentel (2000) and 

were carried out at the Geochronology Laboratory of the University of Brasília. Whole-rock 

powders (~300 mg) were mixed with 149Sm-150Nd spike solution and dissolved in Savillex bombs. 

Sm and Nd extraction of whole-rock samples followed conventional cation exchange techniques. 

The isotopic measurements were carried out on a multi-collector Finnigan MAT 262 mass 

spectrometer in static mode. The 143Nd/144Nd ratios were normalized to 146Nd/144Nd of 

0.7219 and the decay constant used was 6.54 x 10-12 yr-1. The TDM values were calculated using 

the model of DePaolo (1981). Nd procedure blanks were better than 100 pg. Sm-Nd results for 07 

samples are shown in Table 5. 

 

4.6 - U-Pb isotopes 

 Zircon concentrates were extracted from drill core samples using conventional gravimetric 

and magnetic techniques at the Geochronology Laboratory of the University of Brasília. Selected 

samples include a norite (SRLJ 28) and a leuconorite (SRLJ 17) with accessory zircon crystals. Clear 

fine-grained prismatic euhedral crystals with growth zoning were handpicked under a binocular 

microscope. For U-Pb isotopic LA-ICPMS analyses, the sample was mounted in an especially 



19 
 

adapted laser cell and loaded into a New Wave UP213 Nd:YAG laser, linked to a Thermo Finnigan 

Neptune Multi-collector ICPMS. The laser was run at a frequency of 10 Hz and energy of ~100 

mJ/cm2 with a spot diameter of 30 mm. The U-Pb LA-ICPMS analyses followed the analytical 

procedure described in detail by Buhn et al. (2009) and were carried out at the Geochronology 

Laboratory of the University of Brasília. U-Pb results for samples SRLJ-17 and SRLJ-28 are shown in 

Tables 3 and 4. 

 

5. Results 

The ore types and host rocks of Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are very similar and 

will be described together in this study. Both deposits are associated with mafic-ultramafic 

intrusions consisting mainly of magnetitite, orthopyroxenite, norite and gabbronorite. Mafic-

ultramafic intrusions are concordant with host paragneiss and occur as several tectonically 

dismembered bodies (Fig. 3). Due to tectonism and post-magmatic transformation of the original 

igneous rocks the magmatic architecture of these intrusions is hard to decipher. Post-magmatic 

processes include metamorphism up to high-grade conditions (granulite facies) as well as 

hydrothermal alteration. Despite these processes, primary mafic-ultramafic rocks partially 

preserve primary igneous mineralogy and texture, except for discrete highly sheared and/or 

altered zones.  

 

5.1 - Geology and structure of the Serrote da Laje Deposit 

In the area of the Serrote da Laje Deposit, ultramafic rocks crop out just in the south 

portion of the NWN-SES elongated intrusion, which extends for 2 km as defined by drilling and 

trenching information (Fig. 4). Mafic-ultramafic bodies are concordant with host rocks, the later 

consisting of two easily recognized different types of quartz-feldspathic paragneiss, designated as 

pink gneiss and garnet gneiss by the geologists of Aura Minerals Inc. (Fig. 4 and Fig. 5). The pink 

gneiss is a medium-grained granolepidoblastic banded rock composed mainly by quartz + K-

feldspar + plagioclase + sillimanite + cordierite (Fig. 5A), whereas the garnet gneiss is a medium-

grained porphyroblastic rock composed mainly by quartz + biotite + garnet + cordierite + 

plagioclase (Fig. 5B). The thickness of partially disrupted mafic-ultramafic bodies is up to 140m, 

with width variable from 100 to 1000m and up to 800m in length (Fig. 4 and Fig. 7). Two main 

WEW faults crosscut the intrusion, dividing the deposit in north, central and south domain (Fig. 

6). In the north domain the mafic-ultramafic bodies are larger and more continuous (Fig. 4 and 

Fig. 7). The regional foliation follows an average 120/20-30o trend, which are disturbed by the 



20 
 

WEW faults. The central domain, located between the fault zones, has the most hydrothermally 

altered rocks.  

 

 

Figure 4 – Geological map from Serrote da Laje Deposit. The insert shows the analytical signal 

image of the mapped area. Note the close fit of the mafic-ultramafic intrusion with domains with 

high magnetic signal. The cross section A-A´ is illustrated in figure 6.  



21 
 

 

Figure 5 – Country rocks of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. a) pink gneiss composed by 

quartz + K-feldspar + plagioclase + sillimanite + cordierite. b) garnet gneiss composed by quartz + 

biotite +garnet + plagioclase + cordierite. 

 

 

 

Figure 6 – 3D view of the mafic-ultramafic rocks (greenish color) and major faults (reddish color) 

of the Serrote da Laje Deposit. The north, central and south domains are shown in different 

projections. 

 

 



22 
 

 

Figure 7 – Geological E-W cross section of the north domain of the Serrote da Laje Deposit. 

 

5.2 - Geology and structure of the Caboclo Deposit 

The Caboclo Deposit, located 15 km to the NW, is smaller but is hosted by very similar 

mafic-ultramafic rocks compared to the Serrote da Laje Deposit. Divided in 5 bodies (i.e., Rogerio, 

Zeze, Petrucio, Adriano and Maninho) separated by shear zones (Fig. 8), the Caboclo Deposit has 

better outcrops of ultramafic rocks than those in the Serrote da Laje deposit. The main body is 

Rogerio, which extends for 800 m as defined by drilling and trenching information. In Rogerio, the 

bodies’ thickness is up to 60m, with width variable from 50 to 375m and up to 500m in length (Fig. 

9). The Sn foliation trend is very variable in Caboclo deposit area, from 040-050/20-40o (Rogerio) 

to 300/20o (Maninho and Petrucio). The Caboclo Deposit is more segmented than the Serrote da 

Laje Deposit, probably due the proximity with the faulted contact with the Pernambuco-Alagoas 

Domain (Fig. 2). 

 

 

 



23 
 

 

Figure 8 - Geological map of the Caboclo Deposit. The insert shows the analytical signal image of 

the mapped area. Note the close fit of the main bodies (i.e., Rogerio, Zeze, Maninho, Petrucio and 

Adriano) with domains with high magnetic signal. The cross section A-A´ is illustrated in figure 9. 

 

 

 



24 
 

 

Figure 9 - Geological E-W cross section of the Rogerio target. See figure 8 for location of the section.  

 

5.3 - Petrography of mafic-ultramafic rocks 

The main rock types of the mafic-ultramafic intrusions of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo 

deposits are magnetitite, magnetite orthopyroxenite, orthopyroxenite, norite and gabbronorite 

(Table 1).  

 Orthopyroxenite is a medium- to coarse-grained adcumulate composed of cumulus 

orthopyroxene (&gt; 90 vol. %) and Fe-Ti oxides (usually 1-5 vol. %) with minor intercumulus 

plagioclase and phlogopite (Fig. 10A and 10B). Orthopyroxene occurs as short prismatic pleochroic 

(colorless to light reddish) crystals. Fe-Ti oxides consist mainly of magnetite and ilmenite with 

minor associated dark green spinel (hercynite). Magnetite orthopyroxenite and magnetitite are 

closely associated with orthopyroxenites as irregular pods or layers in variable scales, from few 

centimeters to dozens of meters thick (Fig. 10A and 10F). The modal proportion of Fe-Ti oxides 

spread from 1 % in orthopyroxenite to massive (up to 100 %) in ilmenite magnetitite. Magnetite 

orthopyroxenite consists of large orthopyroxene crystals, commonly enclosing tiny euhedral Fe-Ti 

oxides, surrounded by an aggregate of Fe-Ti oxides (Fig. 10E). The later consists of fine- to medium-

grained euhedral to subeuhedral magnetite and ilmenite crystals with polygonal contacts and 



25 
 

dihedral angle close to 120°. The modal proportion of magnetite relative to ilmenite is variable 

but magnetite prevail over ilmenite (magnetite:ilmenite ratios are usually at the 3 to 10 range). 

The ilmenite to magnetite proportion does not vary with the amount of Fe-Ti oxides in 

orthopyroxene-magnetite-ilmenite cumulates. Subsolidus textures are abundant in Fe-Ti oxide 

crystals. Magnetite commonly exhibits different types of intergrowth, including ilmenite lamellae 

as trellis and tiny lenses, thin ulvospinel lamellae, as well as small irregular ilmenite grains on the 

margins. Ilmenite crystals are relatively homogeneous (i.e., compared with magnetite) with rare 

magnetite lamellae. 

 

Rock types cumulus mineral intercumulus mineral 
Disseminated Cu 

sulfide (%vol.) 

Magnetitite Magnetite+Ilmenite (&gt;50%) 
Hercynite 
Opx 
 
 

Plagioclase 
Phlogopite 

5-10 

Mag Orthopyroxenite Opx 
Magnetie+Ilmenite (10-50%) 
Hercynite 
 
 

Plagioclase 
Phlogopite 

5-10 

Orthopyroxenite Opx 
Magnetite+Ilmenite (1-5%) 
Hercynite 
 
 

Plagioclase 
Phlogopite 

5-10 

Norite Opx 
Plagioclase 
Magnetite+Ilmenite (0-5%) 
Apatite 
 
 

Phlogopite 
Magnetite+Ilmenite 

1-5 

Gabbro-norite Opx 
Plagioclase 
Cpx 
Apatite 

Phlogopite - 

 

Table 1 - Petrographic summary of the rock types in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. 

 



26 
 

 

Figure 10 - Photographs and photomicrographs of representative rock textures of orthopyroxenite, 

magnetite orthopyroxenite and magnetitite in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. A) Contact 

of orthopyroxenite (Opxt) and magnetitite (Mag); B) Orthopyroxenite consisting mainly of cumulus 

orthopyroxene (Opx) and Fe-Ti oxides (opaque minerals); C) Fe-Ti oxides (opaque mineral) enclosed 

in orthopyroxene (Opx) or associated with interstitial plagioclase (whitish mineral) in 

orthopyroxenite; D) Detail of corona of garnet between orthopyroxene (Opx) crystals. Note also 

green spinel (hercynite) associated with magnetite (Mag) crystal; E) Fe-Ti oxides (Mag/Ilm) 

enclosed in or interstitial to orthopyroxene in magnetite orthopyroxenite; F) Irregular magnetite-

rich domains (Mag) in orthopyroxenite. 



27 
 

Norite and gabbronorite are the common plagioclase-bearing rocks in the Serrote da Laje 

and Caboclo deposits. Norite is closely associated with orthopyroxenite and the progressive 

transition of orthopyroxene cumulates with intercumulus plagioclase with meso- to 

orthocumulate textures to orthopyroxene-plagioclase adcumulates are common. Norite is a 

medium-grained orthopyroxene-plagioclase cumulate (Fig. 11A) commonly with accessory FeTi-

oxides and apatite, as well as minor interstitial phlogopite. Gabbronorite is a medium-grained 

orthopyroxene-clinopyroxene-plagioclase cumulate commonly with accessory apatite (Fig. 11E) 

and minor interstitial phlogopite. Accessory Fe-Ti oxides in norite consist of magnetite and 

ilmenite with minor associated dark green spinel (hercynite). Apatite is a common accessory 

mineral in both norite and gabbronorite and occurs as fine- to medium-grained euhedral crystals 

or aggregates (Fig. 11B). 

 Primary igneous minerals and textures are commonly partially modified by post-magmatic 

processes including high-grade metamorphism (granulite facies) as well as hydrothermal 

alteration. Gabbroic rocks (i.e., norite and gabbronorite) are usually more extensively deformed 

and recrystallized during metamorphism than orthopyroxenites and associated rocks with 

abundant Fe-Ti oxides. High-grade metamorphism and associated ductile deformation include 

common minor bending and rim recrystallization of igneous minerals, as well as discrete zones 

where igneous rocks were completely transformed into fine- to medium-grained rocks with 

granoblastic textures and metamorphic assemblages. Garnet is a common mineral associated with 

orthopyroxene, clinopyroxene and plagioclase in these metamorphic assemblages. In partially 

recrystallized rocks, garnet occurs in corona around orthopyroxene and/or Fe-Ti oxides, usually 

formed at the expense of plagioclase (Fig. 10D). Discrete zones of highly transformed rocks may 

have unusual mineralogical compositions associated with metassomatic processes. These up to 1 

meter-thick zones include garnet-rich rocks (&gt; 50 vol. %) and phlogopite-rich rocks (&gt; 75 vol. %). 

 



28 
 

 

Figure 11 – Photographs and photomicrographs of representative rock textures of norite and 

gabbronorite in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. A) Photomicrograph of norite with 

adumulus texture; B) Photomicrograph of norite with abundant apatite. C) Core sample of banded 

norite. The intercalated white bands are composed by plagioclase; D) Core sample of leuconorite. 

The dark brown minerals are orthopyroxene with dark green alteration rim of talc. E) 

Photomicrograph of gabbronorite consisting of cumulus orthopyroxene, clinopyroxene, plagioclase 

and apatite. Hornblende occurs as an alteration of pyroxenes.  F) Core sample showing veins and 

bag-like bodies of magnetite in leuconorite.  

 



29 
 

5.4 - Whole-rock geochemistry  

Two representative drill holes were used to illustrate the lithogeochemical variations of 

the host rocks of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits (drill holes SLJE-272 and CBCR-71). Each 

sample represents an approximately 1-m interval of variably layered mafic-ultramafic rocks, such 

that variable amounts of different rock types may be included in several samples. Because the 

Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are hosted by mafic-ultramafic cumulate rocks, major and 

minor elements contents are mainly controlled by the type and relative proportion of cumulus 

minerals. The distribution of FeO, Ti, CaO, Cr, V and Ni in mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote da 

Laje (Fig. 12A) and Caboclo (Fig. 12B) deposits indicates the predominance of orthopyroxene, Fe-

Ti oxides, plagioclase and clinopyroxene cumulates. Orthopyroxenite and magnetitite (i.e., 

orthopyroxene + Fe-Ti oxide cumulates) have higher contents of FeO and lower contents of CaO 

compared to plagioclase-bearing cumulates (norite and gabbronorite). The plots of FeO vs Ti, Cr, 

V and Ni show a positive correlation (Fig. 13) indicating that these minor elements are mainly 

hosted in Fe-Ti oxides and orthopyroxene. The close match in the distribution of V, Ni and Cr 

indicates that their contents are mainly controlled by magnetite (Fig. 12 and 13). The plot of FeO 

vs CaO shows a negative correlation proportional to the abundance of plagioclase and 

clinopyroxene in these rocks (Fig. 13). The distribution of major and minor elements in the mafic-

ultramafic rocks hosting the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are remarkably similar. 

 



30 
 

 

Figure 12 – Stratigraphic variations of selected major and minor elements. A) Drill hole SLJE-0272 

in the Serrote da Laje Deposit. B) Drill hole CBCR-0071 in the Caboclo Deposit.  

Drill Hole 
SLJE-0272 

0 (m) 

50 

100 

150 

200 

250 

V (ppm) 

0 20 40 60 

Cr (ppm) CaO (wt. %) Ti (wt. %) FeO (wt. %) Ni (ppm) 
A 

0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 8 12 16 0 0 0 0 4 2 4 6 8 10 12 1 2 3 1 2 3 
(x 10

3
) (x 103) (x 103) 

gneiss magnetitite norite, 
gabbronorite 

orthopyroxenite, 
magnetitite, norite 

0 20 40 60 0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 8 12 16 0 0 0 0 4 2 4 6 8 10 12 1 2 3 2 6 10 
(x 10

3
) (x 103) (x 103) 

gneiss magnetitite norite, 
gabbronorite 

orthopyroxenite, 
magnetitite, norite 

Drill Hole 
CBCR-0071 

67 
(m) 

100 

150 

175 

192 

V (ppm) Cr (ppm) CaO (wt. %) Ti (wt. %) FeO (wt. %) Ni (ppm) 

B 

4 8 



31 
 

A B 

  

  

  

  

 

Fe (wt. %) 

 

Fe (wt. %) 

Figure 13 – Plot of FeO content versus major oxides and selected minor elements. A) Drill hole SLJE-

0272 in the Serrote da Laje Deposit. B) Drill hole CBCR-0071 in the Caboclo Deposit. 

0.0

0.5

1.0

1.5

2.0

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

Ti (wt. %)

0

0.4

0.8

1.2

1.6

0 10 20 30 40 50

Ti (wt. %)

0

4

8

12

16

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

CaO (wt. %)

0

4

8

12

16

0 10 20 30 40 50

CaO (wt. %)

0

2000

4000

6000

8000

10000

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

Cr (ppm)

0

2000

4000

6000

8000

10000

12000

0 10 20 30 40 50

Cr (ppm)

0

1000

2000

3000

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

V (ppm)

0

1000

2000

3000

0 10 20 30 40 50

V (ppm)

0

1000

2000

3000

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

Ni (ppm)

0

2000

4000

6000

8000

10000

0 10 20 30 40 50

Ni (ppm)



32 
 

5.5 - Mineral chemistry  

Systematic studies of mineral chemistry were limited to orthopyroxene (Opx) analyses in 

15 samples (~ 90 analyses) of mafic and ultramafic cumulates from drill hole SLJE-0272 (see 

Appendix 1 for the complete dataset). Orthopyroxene compositions range from En65.49 to 

En79.22 mol % through the thickest interval of ultramafic cumulates in drill hole SLJE-0272 (Fig. 

14). Results indicate no base-to-top systematic variation in Opx composition along with significant 

variation in En mol % (up to 5-9 mol. %) for adjacent samples. The later possibly indicates 

compositional shifts due to different amounts of intercumulus minerals (Barnes, 1986). Although 

the average En content for orthopyroxene in gabbroic rocks (i.e., norite and gabbrobonite) is lower 

than in ultramafic rocks (i.e., orthopyroxenite and magnetite orthopyroxenite), the range in En 

contents does not separate gabbroic (En65.49 to 79.22 mol. %) and ultramafic rocks (En71.95 to 

77.26 mol. %). The later have En contents close 75 mol. % through the interval. Contents of minor 

elements in Opx are scattered due to abundant exsolution of Fe-Ti minerals (i.e., scattered Ti, Cr, 

Ni) and clinopyroxene (i.e., scattered Ca). Al2O3 content in Opx is higher in ultramafic rocks (4.12-

8.52 wt. %; average of 6.46 wt. %) than in mafic rocks (0.88-6.64 wt. %; average of 3.27 wt. %). 



33 
 

 

 

Figure 14 – Stratigraphic variation of En content in orthopyroxene through drill hole SLJE-0272. 

 

5.6 - Petrography, mineralogy and geochemistry of the sulfide ore 

Two distinct types of sulfide ore occur in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. The 

first type (indicated as type 1), associated with orthopyroxenite, magnetite and norite, encompass 

the bulk of the Cu-Au resources. The second type (indicated as type 2), associated with sulfide 

veins and/or extensively altered rocks, is just important in the hydrothermally altered central 

domain of the Serrote da Laje deposit located between the fault zones (Fig. 4 and 7). Type 2 ore 

commonly overprints type 1 ore in both deposits. While type 1 ore is restricted to orthopyroxenite, 

magnetite and norite, type 2 ore may also occur in gabbronorite and host gneissic rocks adjacent 

to the mafic-ultramafic bodies. 

Drill Hole 
SLJE-0272 

0 (m) 

50 

100 

140 

180 

220 

260 
60 65 70 75 80 85 

En (%) 

Norite/ gabbronorite 
Orthopyroxenite/ Mag orthopyroxenite 



34 
 

Sulfides in type 1 ore of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits consist mainly of 

disseminated chalcopyrite and bornite (Fig. 15A) with minor associated chalcocite. Disseminated 

sulfides are abundant (5-10 vol. %) in magnetitite and orthopyroxenites, becoming less abundant 

in norite (1-5 vol. %) and gabbronorite (&amp;lt;1 vol. %). Sulfides are interstitial to magnetite and 

orthopyroxene and net-texture characterizes the ore in sulfide-rich samples (Fig. 15B). The relative 

modal proportion of chalcopyrite and bornite is highly variable within a meter scale, such that 

samples consisting mainly of bornite are closely associated with those consisting mainly of 

chalcopyrite. Bornite and chalcopyrite occur either as fine-grained (&amp;lt;1 mm) polycrystalline 

granular aggregates or complex intergrowth of both minerals (Fig. 15B). Rounded sulfide blebs (&amp;lt;

0.5 mm diameter) consisting of variable modal proportions of bornite and chalcopyrite are 

enclosed in orthopyroxene (Fig. 15D) or Fe-Ti oxides. Gold occurs as fine-grained crystals enclosed 

in chalcopyrite and/or bornite, as well as filling fractures within sulfides.  

Sulfides in type 2 ore of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits occur in veins associated 

with hydrothermally altered rocks (Fig. 15C), as well as disseminated (up to 5-10 vol. %) adjacent 

to highly veined rocks or within highly altered rocks. Sulfides consist mainly of pyrite, pyrrhotite 

and chalcopyrite of variable grain size. Coarse- to medium-grained sulfides occur within veins 

while fine-grained sulfides prevail in disseminated ore.  

Drill hole SLJE-0272 was used to illustrate the geochemical features associated with 

different ore types of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. This drill core intersected a 

representative interval of type 1 ore hosted by orthopyroxenite/magnetite/norite, and an interval 

of type 2 ore hosted by gabbronorite (Fig. 16).  

The distribution of FeO, S, Cu, Au and Pd through drill core SLJE-0272 (Fig. 16) indicates 

that type 1 ore is associated with rocks enriched in magnetite and orthopyroxene, as indicated by 

high FeO contents (see also Fig. 12A and 13A for positive correlation of FeO with Ti-V-C-Ni). Type 

2 ore in drill core SLJE-0272 is hosted by gabbronorite and, therefore, not associated with FeO-

rich rocks. The plot of S vs Cu for the interval hosting type 1 ore indicates a strong positive 

correlation (Fig. 17). Type 1 ore samples plot between Cu/S ratios of bornite and chalcopyrite as 

expected based upon petrographic studies of the sulfide ore, which indicate highly variable modal 

proportions of bornite and chalcopyrite. The plot of S vs Au and S vs Pd for the interval hosting 

type 1 ore indicate a weak positive correlation and low contents for Au (&amp;lt;0.5 ppm) and Pd (&amp;lt;300 

ppm, but mainly &amp;lt;100 ppm).  

 The plot of S vs Cu for the interval hosting type 2 ore does not indicate a positive 

correlation (Fig. 17). Type 2 ore samples plot mainly between Cu/S ratios of chalcopyrite and Cu/S 



35 
 

equal zero as expected based upon petrographic studies of the sulfide ore, which indicate variable 

modal proportions of pyrite, pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite. Compared to type 1 ore, Cu-Au-Pd 

contents in type 2 ore much lower. 

 

 

Figure 15 – Representative sulfide textures of ore. A) Disseminated sulfides (mainly chalcopyrite) 

in a magnetitite core sample (typical type 1 ore). B) Photomicrograph of sulfides interstitial to Fe-

Ti oxides and orthopyroxene (type 1 ore). Sulfides consist of an intergrowth of bornite and 

chalcopyrite. C) Sulfide vein cross cutting a hydrothermally altered gabbroic rock (typical type 2 

ore). Sulfides consist mainly of pyrite (yellow) and pyrrhotite (bronze color). D) Photomicrograph 

of a bornite-rich sulfide bleb enclosed in an orthopyroxene crystal. The rock is a magnetite 

orthopyroxenite. 

 

 

 

 

 

 



36 
 

 

Figure 16 – Stratigraphic variations of FeO, S, Cu, Au and Pd through drill hole SLJE-0272 in the 

Serrote da Laje Deposit.  

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Pd (ppb) 

Drill Hole 
SLJE-0272 

  0 (m) 

50 

100 

150 

200 

250 

Au (ppm) Cu (wt. %) S (wt. %) FeO (wt. %) 

gneiss magnetitite norite, 
gabbronorite 

orthopyroxenite, 
magnetitite, norite 



37 
 

 

 

 

Figure 17 – Plot of S content versus Cu, Au and Pd for type 1 (blue) and type 2 (red) ore intervals in 

drill hole SLJE-0272 in the Serrote da Laje Deposit (see Fig. 16 for location of indicated ore intervals). 

Cu/S ratios for bornite (Bn) and chalcopyrite (Cpy) in the S-Cu plot are based on average microprobe 

analyses of sulfides (Aura Minerals internal report). 

 

5.7 - Sulfur isotopes 

Sulfur isotopic analyses were obtained in disseminated chalcopyrite and bornite in samples 

of ultramafic rocks (type 1 ore), and in pyrite, pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite that occurs in veinlets 

in samples of altered mafic rocks (type 2 ore). The sulfides were analysed in a LA-MC-ICPMS and 

the ?34S results were related with the Cañon Diablo Troilite (V-CDT). The sulfur isotopic 

compositions obtained are listed in the Table 2. 

Results for disseminated chalcopyrite and bornite in type 1 ore hosted by ultramafic rocks 

have a narrow range of values from -1.0 to 2.5 ?34S ‰ (Fig. 18). The results are the same for 

chalcopyrite and bornite and indicate an isotopic composition similar to mantle-derived sulfur. 

0.0

0.5

1.0

1.5

2.0

2.5

3.0

3.5

0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 3.5 4

Cu (wt. %)

Cpy

0

0.1

0.2

0.3

0.4

0.5

0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 3.5 4

Au (ppm)

0

50

100

150

200

250

300

0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 3.5 4

S (wt. %)

Pd (ppb)

Bn 



38 
 

Pyrite, chalcopyrite and pyrrhotite in type 2 ore hosted by hydrothermally altered gabbroic rocks 

have isotopic values from 7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰ (Fig. 18). The higher values of ?34S ‰ indicate values 

distinct from mantle-derived sulfur, thus suggesting that sulfides in type 2 ore may partially 

originate from hydrothermal fluids from the host rocks (paragneiss). 

 

 

Figure 18 – Histogram of ?34S ‰ V-CDT values of sulfides from ultramafic rocks (type 1 ore) and 

hydrothermally altered gabbroic rocks (type 2 ore) of the Serrote da Laje deposit. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

0

1

2

3

4

5

6

7

8

-3.0 -2.0 -1.0 0.0 1.0 2.0 3.0 4.0 5.0 6.0 7.0 8.0 9.0 10.0 11.0 12.0 13.0 14.0

F
re

q
u

e
n

cy

?34S ‰ V-CDT

Mantle Range

Py-Po-Cpy in
Hydrotermal rocks

Cpy-Bn in
Ultramafic rocks



39 
 

Sample Litology Mineral ‰ V-CDT Depth (m) Ore Type 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite cpy 0.61 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite cpy 0.39 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite bn 2.36 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite bn 2.1 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite cpy 1.1 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-25 Orthopyroxenite cpy 1.26 129.8 Type 1 

SLJE-21 Orthopyroxenite cpy -0.12 143.7 Type 1 

SLJE-21 Orthopyroxenite cpy -0.74 143.7 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy+bn 0.63 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy+bn -0.13 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy+bn 0.25 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy+bn -0.51 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy -0.5 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy -0.36 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn -0.51 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-18 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn -0.22 149.6 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn 0.43 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn 0.15 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn 0.42 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite bn 0.52 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy 0.18 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-16 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy 0.12 155.1 Type 1 

SLJE-10 Magnetitite bn 0.85 189.2 Type 1 

SLJE-10 Magnetitite bn 0.55 189.2 Type 1 

SLJE-10 Magnetitite cpy 0.79 189.2 Type 1 

SLJE-10 Magnetitite cpy 0.63 189.2 Type 1 

SLJE-04 Gabbro cpy 11.16 224.2 Type 2 

SLJE-04 Gabbro py 10.61 224.2 Type 2 

SLJE-04 Gabbro py 10.86 224.2 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro po 12.86 231 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro po 12.69 231 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro po 13.23 231 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro po 13.29 231 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro py 13.42 231 Type 2 

SLJE-02 Gabbro py 13.28 231 Type 2 

SLJE-28 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy 9.17 69.5 Type 2 

SLJE-28 Mag Orthopyroxenite cpy 8.69 69.5 Type 2 

SLJE-12 Garnetitite cpy 8.05 182.6 Type 2 

SLJE-12 Garnetitite cpy 7.95 182.6 Type 2 

SLJE-12 Garnetitite cpy 8.5 182.6 Type 2 

SLJE-12 Garnetitite cpy 8.49 182.6 Type 2 

 

Table 2 - Sulfur isotope data for sulfide minerals of the Serrote da Laje deposit 

 



40 
 

5.8 – U-Pb and Sm-Nd isotopes 

Two samples from mafic-ultramafic intrusion of the Serrote da Laje deposit produced 

appropriated concentrate of zircons for U-Pb geochronology. The results are presented in table 3. 

Sample SLJE-17 is a leuconorite and U-Pb isotopic analyses of zircon crystals render several 

concordant to slightly discordant U-Pb dates (Fig. 19A). Twenty-five spot analyses define a 

Discordia line with an upper intercept age of 1982±17 Ma (MSWD=13). Sample SLJE-28 is a 

magnetite orthopyroxenite and U-Pb isotopic analyses of zircon crystals render several concordant 

to slightly discordant U-Pb dates (Figure 19B). Twenty-nine spot analyses define a Discordia line 

with an upper intercept age of 1997±20 Ma (MSWD=20). These ages overlap at ca. 1.99 Ga and 

are interpreted as the crystallization age of magmatic zircons and, therefore, the age of magmatic 

crystallization of the mafic-ultramafic intrusion of the Serrote da Laje deposit. 

 

Spot U(ppm) Th(ppm) Th/U 206Pb/204Pb Ratio 7/6* 2s (%) Age 7/6 2s (Ma) Ratio 7/5* 2s (%) Age 7/5 2s (Ma) Ratio 6/8* 2s (%) Age 6/8 2s (Ma) 

23-Z14 492.81 139.43 0.28 761672.97 0.11052 0.6 1808.1 11.3 3.67098 3.1 1565.1 24.7 0.24089 3.1 1391.3 38.3 

33-Z19 769.62 221.53 0.29 842537.72 0.11700 0.9 1910.9 16.5 5.56815 1.7 1911.2 14.7 0.34516 1.4 1911.5 23.8 

28-Z17 391.83 71.12 0.18 794354.57 0.11727 0.5 1915.0 8.5 5.54879 1.5 1908.2 12.8 0.34318 1.4 1901.9 23.4 

04-Z2 476.61 143.65 0.30 979111.41 0.11983 0.7 1953.7 11.7 6.28138 1.5 2015.9 13.2 0.38017 1.4 2077.1 24.1 

40-Z24 159.36 23.72 0.15 141388.89 0.12129 0.6 1975.3 10.3 5.87446 2.3 1957.5 20.1 0.35127 2.3 1940.7 38.0 

18-Z11 239.09 45.25 0.19 510934.70 0.12153 0.7 1978.8 12.9 5.28647 2.3 1866.7 19.7 0.31549 2.2 1767.7 34.2 

22-Z13 158.23 26.64 0.17 326075.78 0.12169 0.6 1981.1 10.3 6.09580 1.5 1989.6 12.9 0.36331 1.4 1997.9 23.5 

11-Z7 155.34 25.33 0.16 345657.04 0.12191 0.8 1984.4 14.3 6.77298 1.8 2082.2 15.4 0.40293 1.6 2182.5 28.9 

29-Z18 87.23 13.91 0.16 206553.71 0.12200 0.8 1985.7 14.6 6.23006 1.6 2008.7 14.1 0.37037 1.4 2031.2 24.3 

27-Z16 130.10 19.01 0.15 375336.74 0.12230 0.8 1990.1 14.1 6.38126 2.1 2029.7 18.0 0.37842 1.9 2068.9 33.6 

34-Z20 173.36 21.29 0.12 323359.52 0.12246 0.6 1992.3 10.4 6.42184 1.4 2035.3 12.2 0.38035 1.3 2077.9 22.4 

09-Z5 147.05 26.09 0.18 283391.53 0.12291 1.1 1998.9 18.8 6.26559 1.7 2013.7 15.0 0.36972 1.4 2028.1 23.6 

24-Z15 290.66 43.58 0.15 680187.76 0.12296 0.5 1999.6 9.2 6.60615 2.5 2060.2 21.9 0.38965 2.5 2121.2 44.3 

03-Z1 113.74 15.91 0.14 284476.56 0.12296 1.1 1999.6 19.8 6.42528 1.6 2035.7 13.7 0.37899 1.1 2071.5 19.3 

05-Z3 150.89 20.26 0.13 117986.45 0.12302 1.4 2000.5 23.9 6.54024 2.6 2051.3 22.6 0.38559 2.2 2102.3 39.7 

06-Z4 124.63 23.47 0.19 340095.64 0.12312 0.8 2001.9 13.8 6.64450 1.7 2065.3 15.3 0.39142 1.6 2129.4 28.2 

35-Z21 131.24 18.43 0.14 330942.39 0.12339 0.8 2005.9 13.3 6.50514 1.2 2046.6 10.3 0.38235 0.9 2087.3 16.0 

17-Z10 90.48 15.20 0.17 268378.65 0.12341 0.7 2006.2 12.8 6.86002 1.2 2093.5 11.0 0.40314 1.0 2183.5 18.8 

15-Z8 157.47 25.05 0.16 360385.15 0.12366 1.0 2009.7 18.0 6.58332 1.5 2057.1 13.5 0.38610 1.2 2104.7 20.7 

16-Z9 108.06 15.27 0.14 117815.81 0.12388 0.8 2012.8 13.9 6.29857 1.4 2018.3 12.0 0.36876 1.1 2023.6 19.6 

39-Z23 173.96 24.44 0.14 386730.51 0.12413 0.7 2016.4 12.4 6.43384 1.5 2036.9 13.0 0.37593 1.3 2057.2 23.0 

10-Z6 105.49 15.97 0.15 274212.48 0.12411 0.8 2016.2 14.9 7.00321 1.4 2111.8 12.5 0.40924 1.1 2211.4 21.3 

21-Z12 86.18 13.28 0.15 270578.07 0.12459 1.0 2023.0 17.7 5.77286 2.3 1942.3 19.5 0.33605 2.0 1867.6 33.0 

41-Z25 136.44 26.26 0.19 2872.05 0.11951 1.4 1949.0 24.1 5.78630 2.4 1944.4 20.8 0.35114 2.0 1940.0 33.5 

36-Z22 66.30 9.00 0.14 123048.54 0.12613 0.8 2044.7 14.3 6.68886 1.8 2071.2 15.5 0.38462 1.6 2097.8 28.0 

 

Table 3 - U-Pb LA-MC-ICPMS data for sample SLJE-17. 

 

 

 

 



41 
 

Spot U(ppm) Th(ppm) Th/U 206Pb/204Pb Ratio 7/6* 2s (%) Age 7/6 2s (Ma) Ratio 7/5* 2s (%) Age 7/5 2s (Ma) Ratio 6/8* 2s (%) Age 6/8 2s (Ma) 

38-Z24 512.65 25.63 0.05 31082.79 0.09405 1.1 1509.1 19.8 2.08732 2.1 1144.6 14.5 0.16097 1.8 962.2 16.4 

23-Z14 362.68 27.40 0.08 7219.26 0.10034 1.2 1630.4 21.5 1.95618 4.5 1100.6 29.8 0.14140 4.3 852.6 34.7 

53-Z34 173.82 32.30 0.19 74365.47 0.10811 1.7 1767.8 30.8 3.86135 6.6 1605.6 51.6 0.25905 6.3 1485.0 83.5 

46-Z29 261.55 40.09 0.15 252977.02 0.10890 0.9 1781.0 15.7 3.48020 3.0 1522.7 23.2 0.23179 2.8 1343.9 34.4 

52-Z33 202.80 63.23 0.31 243640.69 0.11024 1.2 1803.3 21.6 3.76399 4.1 1585.1 32.2 0.24764 3.9 1426.3 49.7 

45-Z28 456.28 57.36 0.13 303354.49 0.11312 0.8 1850.1 14.1 3.90480 1.7 1614.7 13.4 0.25037 1.5 1440.4 19.0 

24-Z15 226.93 24.48 0.11 268588.05 0.11668 0.7 1906.0 12.0 4.54381 2.3 1739.0 18.6 0.28243 2.2 1603.6 30.6 

33-Z20 193.53 41.01 0.21 321313.34 0.11767 0.8 1921.1 13.7 3.99936 2.2 1634.1 17.6 0.24651 2.0 1420.5 26.0 

10-Z6 553.40 52.60 0.10 441312.64 0.11824 0.6 1929.8 11.3 5.63080 6.0 1920.8 50.9 0.34538 6.0 1912.5 98.8 

16-Z9 247.69 46.28 0.19 562338.96 0.11849 1.0 1933.5 18.5 5.43885 1.7 1891.0 14.4 0.33292 1.3 1852.5 21.4 

22-Z13 685.54 46.38 0.07 13608.43 0.11799 0.7 1926.0 11.8 4.85881 1.5 1795.1 12.9 0.29866 1.4 1684.7 20.6 

39-Z25 292.17 37.33 0.13 302947.74 0.11986 0.9 1954.2 15.4 4.67780 2.0 1763.3 16.7 0.28305 1.8 1606.7 25.8 

51-Z32 280.56 37.38 0.13 18445.07 0.11932 0.6 1946.0 10.9 5.99311 2.0 1974.8 17.0 0.36429 1.9 2002.5 32.2 

47-Z30 679.02 24.73 0.04 734922.78 0.12041 0.9 1962.3 16.6 6.45874 2.2 2040.3 19.1 0.38903 2.0 2118.3 35.8 

34-Z22 231.28 31.05 0.13 288710.09 0.12054 0.8 1964.3 14.0 5.53424 1.2 1905.9 10.7 0.33298 1.0 1852.8 15.5 

17-Z10 321.68 42.53 0.13 822439.72 0.12131 1.0 1975.6 18.0 6.25195 1.4 2011.7 12.4 0.37378 1.0 2047.2 17.5 

27-Z16 129.16 26.58 0.21 281577.40 0.12169 0.6 1981.2 10.8 5.78966 1.7 1944.9 14.5 0.34506 1.6 1911.0 26.0 

03-Z1 405.10 39.16 0.10 11095.96 0.12096 0.5 1970.4 9.1 4.91688 1.5 1805.2 12.3 0.29482 1.4 1665.6 20.1 

06-Z4 287.78 59.13 0.21 383093.47 0.12252 0.3 1993.3 5.9 5.90594 3.2 1962.1 27.0 0.34960 3.1 1932.7 52.2 

29-Z18 144.78 20.23 0.14 531717.99 0.12266 0.9 1995.3 15.2 5.69006 1.4 1929.9 12.4 0.33645 1.2 1869.6 18.7 

30-Z19 111.85 25.71 0.23 275621.69 0.12315 0.7 2002.3 11.6 5.90792 2.0 1962.4 17.2 0.34794 1.9 1924.8 31.2 

05-Z3 180.81 28.15 0.16 525318.09 0.12336 0.4 2005.4 6.7 6.00820 1.8 1977.0 15.4 0.35324 1.7 1950.0 29.2 

09-Z5 193.92 128.93 0.66 188881.31 0.12338 0.6 2005.7 10.6 6.40078 3.6 2032.4 30.9 0.37624 3.5 2058.7 61.7 

40-Z26 266.56 46.87 0.18 221017.95 0.12354 0.9 2008.0 15.7 5.62573 1.3 1920.0 11.5 0.33026 1.0 1839.7 15.9 

33-Z21 136.85 83.71 0.61 274669.61 0.12421 0.6 2017.5 11.5 6.21464 1.5 2006.5 12.6 0.36288 1.3 1995.8 22.3 

11-Z7 156.65 43.80 0.28 9973.39 0.12317 1.4 2002.7 25.2 6.91662 5.6 2100.8 48.3 0.40726 5.4 2202.4 99.7 

18-Z11 258.38 41.77 0.16 548644.71 0.12497 0.9 2028.4 15.0 5.98504 1.7 1973.7 14.9 0.34734 1.5 1921.9 24.9 

28-Z17 128.82 53.21 0.41 6156.59 0.12334 0.6 2005.1 10.9 5.22993 1.4 1857.5 11.9 0.30753 1.3 1728.5 19.0 

50-Z31 715.42 236.23 0.33 24067.53 0.12591 0.9 2041.6 16.1 6.44323 3.2 2038.2 27.5 0.37114 3.0 2034.8 52.7 

 

Table 4 - U-Pb LA-MC-ICPMS data for sample SLJE-28. 

 

  

The Sm-Nd isotopic data of the Serrote da Laje Complex are listed in Table 5. Nd isotopic 

data obtained for mafic and ultramafic lithotypes render Nd model ages between 1.92 and 3.01 

Ga, with highly variable ?Nd (T = 1.99 Ga) values (-4.33 to 3.87). Plotted against the stratigraphy, 

the Sm-Nd data are scattered and do not correlate with the layering sequence. 

 

 

 



42 
 

 

 

 

Figure 19 – Concordia diagram of U-Pb analyses of zircons. A) Sample SLJE-17 (leuconorite). B) 

Sample SLJE-28 (magnetite orthopyroxenite). 

 

 

 

1800

1900

2000

2100

0.28

0.30

0.32

0.34

0.36

0.38

0.40

0.42

0.44

4.6 5.0 5.4 5.8 6.2 6.6 7.0 7.4

2
0

6
P

b
/2

3
8

U

207Pb/235U

A

Intercepts at 
535±330 &amp;amp; 1982±17   [±18]  Ma

MSWD = 13

data-point error ellipses are 2s

600

1000

1400

1800

2200

0.05

0.15

0.25

0.35

0.45

0 2 4 6 8

2
0

6
P

b
/2

3
8

U

207Pb/235U

B

Intercepts at 
520±100 &amp;amp; 1997±20   [±21]  Ma

MSWD = 20

data-point error ellipses are 2s



43 
 

Sample Sm(ppm) Nd(ppm) 147Sm/144Nd 143Nd/144Nd (± 2SE) ??? (0) TDM (Ga) ENd(t) 

SRLJ 01 4,984 36,346 0,0829 0,511367+/-18 -24,80 1,94 +4,09 

SRLJ 07 8,131 39,781 0,1233 0,511461+/-12 -22,96 2,67 -4,33 

SRLJ 09 1,079 4,112 0,1587 0,512341+/-57 -5,79 1,92 +3,87 

SRLJ 17 0,826 4,272 0,1169 0,511558+/11 -21,07 2,34 -0,81 

SRLJ 25 0,121 0,292 0,2497 0,513330+/-31 13,50 - +0,05 

SRLJ 27 0,527 2,972 0,1073 0,511281+/-9 -26,47 2,52 -3,78 

SRLJ 28 1,801 7,069 0,1540 0,511876+/-17 -14,87 3,01 -4,03 

        

Table 5 - Sm-Nd isotopic data for the Serrote da Laje Complex (t=1.99 Ga). 

 

6 - Discussion 

6.1 - Magmatic structure and composition of mafic-ultramafic bodies 

 The mafic-ultramafic bodies hosting Cu-Au mineralization in the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo deposits consist of small bodies partially obliterated by regional tectonism and 

metamorphism. These irregular bodies of mafic-ultramafic rocks are interpreted as small dikes 

and/or pipes consisting of restricted rock types consisting mainly of orthopyroxenite, magnetitite, 

norite and gabbronorite. Orthopyroxene is the most prominent mineral and is commonly 

associated with Fe-Ti oxides, plagioclase, clinopyroxene, as well as minor apatite and phlogopite. 

Primary magmatic compositions and textures are highly variable, a feature consistent with small 

size irregular intrusions. Interlayered orthopyroxenite, an orthopyroxene cumulate with variable 

proportions of intercumulus plagioclase (i.e., adcmulate to orthocumulate textures), and 

norite/leuconorite, a plagioclase + orthopyroxene cumulate, occurs in metric to centimetric scale. 

Similar features characterize interlayered magnetitite, magnetite orthopyroxenite and 

orthopyroxenite. The crystallization sequence consists of orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides followed 

by plagioclase and then by clinopyroxene. Magnetitite are mainly interlayered with 

orthopyroxenite and minor norite but very rare in association with gabbronorite. Apatite is a 

common cumulus mineral in norite and gabbronorite but very rare in association with magnetitite 

and orthopyroxenite. Systematic interlayering of these rock types are consistent with all rock types 

resulting from fractionation from a parental magma, either in situ or due to successive pulses of 

variably fractionated magma. Orthopyroxene compositions ranging from En65.49 to En79.22 mol 

% indicate moderately primitive to fractionated compositions for the parental magma. The 

average En content for orthopyroxene in gabbroic rocks is lower but not significantly different 

from ultramafic rocks, which is consistent with progressive fractionation of a parental magma that 

crystallize Fe-Ti oxides.  



44 
 

 Unusual rock types with abundant phlogopite and/or garnet are commonly associated 

with mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. Rocks consisting largely 

of phlogopite (&gt; 50 %) were considered as glimmerites in the Koperberg Suite that host the Okiep 

deposit in South Africa (Clifford and Barton, 2012), or as the result of post-magmatic K 

metasomatism of the mafic-ultramafic rocks that host the Caraíba deposit in Brazil (Garcia, 2013). 

Although we don't intend to address in detail the processes associated with the origin of 

phlogopite-rich rocks in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits, it is worth to point out that such 

rocks are usually located in the contact of mafic-ultramafic bodies and host gneissic rocks. This 

close association may result from the assimilation of country gneissic rocks during magmatic 

emplacement. Assimilation of older crustal rocks is also consistent with Sm-Nd isotopic data of the 

Serrote da Laje Complex, as indicated by highly variable and scattered ?Nd (T = 1.99 Ga) values (-

4.33 to 3.87).  

 

6.2 - The origin of magnetitite 

 The origin of magnetite in mafic-ultramafic intrusions remains controversial (see Maier et 

al., 2013 for a review of proposed models). While some studies proposed that the Fe-Ti oxide-rich 

rocks formed by accumulation of cumulus minerals from basaltic magmas (e.g., Ganino et al., 

2008; Maier et al., 2013) others propose an origin by silicate-oxide liquid immiscibility (e.g., 

Naslund, 1983; Zhou et al., 2005). Some textural features described in this study suggest that Fe-

Ti-rich melts intruded norite or leuconorite (Fig. 11F). These contacts are characterized by a halo 

of altered plagioclase and highly altered plagioclase enclosed into ilmenite-magnetite rich veins. 

However, within the predominant orthopyroxenite and magnetitite association, textures typical 

of cumulate rocks, including euhedral Fe-Ti oxides enclosed in cumulus orthopyroxene prevail (Fig. 

10). Independent of the favored model for the origin of magnetitites, higher oxidation states are 

known to promote the crystallization of Fe-Ti oxides in mafic magmas (Toplis and Carrol, 1995; 

Ganino et al., 2008). However, the abundance of magmatic sulfides (i.e., type 1 ore) in both Serrote 

da Laje and Caboclo deposits indicates that the oxidation state should be below the FMQ-+1.5 

buffer (Jugo et al., 2005). In fact, Fe-Ti oxides and Cu sulfides in type 1 ore are closely associated 

in these deposits, as indicated by interstitial sulfides enclosing cumulus oxides (Fig. 15B) and 

sulfide blebs enclosed in oxides (Fig. 15D). The association of magmatic sulfides and Fe-Ti oxides 

suggests that their origin is closely related, as will be discussed in the following discussion. 

 



45 
 

6.3 - How Cu-Au magmatic sulfides are formed? 

 Magmatic Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide deposits are formed as the result of the segregation and 

concentration of droplets of liquid sulfide from mafic or ultramafic magma (e.g., Naldrett, 2004; 

Barnes and Lightfoot, 2005). The origin of Cu-rich sulfide deposits hosted in mafic-ultramafic 

intrusions remains however a controversial issue. The composition of Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide deposits 

are determined by the composition of the associated silicate magma (i.e., the magma that 

segregated the sulfide liquid), and the relative volumes of silicate and sulfide liquid (i.e., the "R" 

factor, Campbell and Naldrett, 1979). The compositions of the segregated Ni-Cu-PGE sulfide melts 

are controlled by the fractionation of monosulfide solid solution (mss, Naldrett, 2004), such that 

the last sulfide composition before complete crystallization takes place should be close to the 

intermediate solid solution (iss, Naldrett 2004). The bulk sulfide assemblage would consist 

essentially of pyrrhotite, pentlandite and chalcopyrite. The fractionation of the sulfide liquid 

coupled with the migration of the most fractionated fraction from residual mss explains the origin 

of Cu-Pt-Pd-rich liquids and Cu/Fe ratios up to values close to 1. This explanation has been used 

for the origin of Cu-Pt-Pd rich sulfide bodies closely associated with larger Ni-Cu deposits (e.g., Li 

et al., 1996). However, this is likely to be a more localized process, and not appropriate for deposits 

consisting entirely of Cu-rich sulfide assemblages, especially when bornite is a significant sulfide 

and Cu/Fe ratios are well above 1 (e.g., Caraíba deposit, Oliveira and Tarney, 1995; Serrote da Laje 

and Caboclo deposits, this study). 

 Textural and chemical features described in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits 

support the interpretation that Cu-rich sulfides are magmatic and closely associated with 

magnetite-rich rocks. In both deposits disseminated sulfides are interstitial to or enclosed into 

cumulus orthopyroxene and Fe-Ti oxides (Fig. 15A-B-D), as commonly described in typical 

magmatic Ni-Cu-PGE deposits (e.g., Limoeiro Ni-Cu-PGE deposit, Mota-e-Silva et al., 2013; several 

deposits described in Naldrett 2004), where sulfides are interstitial to or enclosed into cumulus 

silicates (usually olivine, pyroxenes and/or plagioclase). The close association of magnetite and 

sulfides in the Serrote da Laje deposit is indicated by positive correlations of FeO and Ti-V in hosted 

mafic-ultramafic rocks (Fig. 12A and 13A) matched with positive correlations of FeO and S-Cu-Au 

(Fig. 16 and 17) in sulfide ore. The sulfide assemblages in both deposits consist mainly of bornite 

and chalcopyrite (Fig. 17), with Cu/Fe ratio in sulfides ranging from about 1 in chalcopyrite-rich 

ore samples to about 5 in bornite-rich samples. Sulfur isotope results for chalcopyrite and bornite 

in type 1 ore indicate a narrow range of values from -1.0 to 2.5 ?34S ‰ (Fig. 18), thus supporting 

a magmatic origin for the ore. The close association of magnetite and sulfides in the Serrote da 



46 
 

Laje and Caboclo deposits suggests that sulfide oxidation may be an appropriate mechanism to 

increase the Cu content and Cu/Fe ratio of a sulfide melt. Experimental study of the phase 

relations in the Fe-Ni-Cu-PGE indicates that higher Cu contents of a sulfide melt increases the bulk 

metal/S ratios and lower its liquidus and solidus temperatures (Ballhaus et al., 2001). The same 

study indicates that relatively Cu-rich and S-rich sulfide melts (i.e., metal/S &amp;lt;1) will solidify in the 

iss stability field, while S-poor sulfide melts (i.e., metal/S &gt; 1) can fractionate past the iss stability 

field up to bornite crystallization. Experimental work by Wohlgemuth-Ueberwasser et al. (2013) 

has shown that a combination of fractional crystallization with magmatic oxidation is an 

appropriate mechanism to generate Cu-rich magmatic sulfides with high Cu/Fe ratios. The authors' 

results also indicate that the timing and magnitude of sulfide oxidation will determine the extent 

of the increase in Cu/Fe ratio, such that sulfide melts oxidized above the mss liquidus would 

fractionated to higher Cu/Fe ratios. These results may be applied to the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo ores considering that magnetite crystallized due to the oxidation of the magma, thus 

leading to Cu/Fe increase in sulfides due to strong partition of Ni and Fe to magnetite. 

 

6.4 - Classification of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo Cu-Au deposits 

 Magmatic nickel-copper-PGE sulfide deposits form as the result of the segregation and 

concentration of droplets of liquid sulfide from mafic or ultramafic magma and the partitioning of 

chalcophile elements into these droplets from the silicate magma (e.g., Naldrett, 2004). The 

deposits are grouped into those that are mined primarily for their Ni and Cu contents and those 

for their PGE contents (Fig. 20). The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are mined for their Cu-

Au contents and plot outside the compositional range of Ni-Cu-PGE deposits (Fig. 20). Magmatic 

Cu-Au deposits, such as Serrote da Laje, Caboclo, Okiep and Caraíba are not considered into the 

different classes proposed for magmatic sulfides (e.g., Naldrett, 2004; 2010; Barnes and Lightfoot, 

2005) and should be considered as a different class of a broader group of Ni-Cu-PGE-Au magmatic 

deposits. The origin of Cu-rich sulfide deposits hosted in mafic-ultramafic intrusions remains a 

controversial issue (i.e., they were interpreted in different studies either as primary magmatic, or 

metamorphic transformed magmatic deposits, or as well as a member of IOCG-type hydrothermal 

deposits) and genetic classifications are consequently compromised. The main features described 

in magmatic Cu sulfides (i.e., type 1 ore) in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits that are 

considered significant for a descriptive classification of these deposits are listed below.  

a) Host rocks consist essentially of orthoyroxenite, magnetitite and norite.  

b) Cu-Au contents have strong positive correlation with FeO contents and modal Fe-Ti oxides. The 



47 
 

latter also reflects a strong positive correlation of Cu-Au contents with Ti, V, Cr and Ni 

(predominantly hosted in Fe-Ti oxides). 

c) Sulfide minerals consist mainly of chalcopyrite and bornite. 

d) Cu/Ni ratio in the sulfide fraction is very high (&gt; 100). 

e) Cu/Fe ratio ranges from ~ 1 (chalcopyrite-rich ore) to ~ 4 (bornite-rich ore). 

f) Isotopic compositions of sulfides are similar to mantle-derived sulfur.  

 

 

 

 

Figure 20 – Relative value of the contributions of Ni, Cu, and PGE to magmatic sulfide deposits. 

Modified from Naldrett (2004).  

 

6.5 - Implications for exploration 

Copper mineralization in the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits is restricted to mafic-

ultramafic rocks. Although two distinct types of ore were recognized in both deposits, just the 

primary magmatic mineralization (i.e., type 1 ore; Fig. 16) is significant for the reserves (&gt; 70 vol. 

%) and Cu-Au supply for the system. Type 1 ore has a strong positive correlation with FeO contents 

and modal magnetite. This association has important implications for exploration in the region, 

once magnetic anomalies characterize mineralized ultramafic bodies in the Serrote da Laje and 

Caboclo deposits. Due to the small size and poor outcropping of these irregular bodies of mafic-

M 
Z 

L 
Po 

PR 

N 

U 

D 
R 

V S 
K T P J 

0.2 

0.4 

0.6 

0.8 

1 

Ni+Co Cu 

PGE 

Relative value of Ni+Co 

V 
D 
K 
M 
N 
P 
S 
T 
J 
L 

PR 
Po 
R 
U 
Z 

- Voisey´s Bay (Canada) 
- Duluth Complex (USA) 
- Kambalda (Australia) 
- Merensky Reef (Bushveld) 
- Noril´sk region (Russia) 
- Pechenga (Russia) 
- Sudbury (Canada) 
- Thompson (Canada) 
- Jinchuan (China) 
- Lac des lles (Canada) 
- Platreef (Bushveld) 
- Portimo Complex (Finland) 
- Raglan (Canada) 
- UG-2 chromitite (Bushveld) 
- Great Dyke of Zimbabwe 
- Mt Keith (Australia) 
- Perseverance (Australia) 
- Stillwater (USA) 
  Serrote da Laje/Cabloclo (Brazil) 
  Okiep (South Africa) 
  Caraiba (Brazil) 



48 
 

ultramafic rocks, magnetic surveys provide a prime target selecting criteria in the region. The close 

association of Cu-Au sulfides and Fe-Ti oxides also reflects in combined Cu-Ti-V-Cr-Ni anomalies in 

geochemical surveys.  

The subordinated mineralization that occurs in veins and/or breccia in altered mafic-

ultramafic rocks (i.e., type 2 ore; Fig. 16) has been used to suggest the potential for hydrothermal 

Cu-Au deposits in the region. However, type 2 ore is always closely associated with type 1 ore and 

does not extend beyond the mafic-ultramafic bodies. Sulfur isotope results for sulfides (pyrite, 

pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite) in type 2 ore range from 7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰ (Fig. 18). This range of 

values is remarkably different from the one obtained in type 1 ore and suggests a hydrothermal 

origin for type 2 ore. Although minor sulfide-rich veins or disseminated sulfides are commonly 

intersected in drill cores of gneissic host rocks, they consist mainly of pyrite and/or pyrrhotite and 

bear no economic importance. In this study we interpret the type 2 ore as the result of sulfides 

from hydrothermal fluids that percolate the Cu-Au mineralized mafic-ultramafic rocks and 

partially remobilized the primary ore (i.e., type 1 ore). Our interpretation suggests that 

hydrothermal fluids percolated from host rocks through the mafic-ultramafic bodies, but their Cu-

Au-Pd contents were remobilized from primary ore. This interpretation implies that type 2 ore 

does not indicate the existence of a robust Cu-Au hydrothermal mineralization that may lead to 

different exploration targets than those investigated in this study.   

LA-ICPM U-Pb data of zircons from two samples of mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote 

da Laje deposit indicate a crystallization age at ca. 1.99 Ga for the intrusion. This age close to but 

younger than the 2056±9.2 Ma SHRIMP U-Pb zircon age of a pyroxenite associated with Cu 

mineralization in the Caraíba deposit (Garcia et al., 2016). These results suggest that significant Cu 

deposits are associated with Paleoproterozoic mafic-ultramafic intrusions in the region located 

close to the northern border of the São Francisco Craton in Brazil.  

 

7 - Conclusions 

The principal conclusions of this study are as follows:  

a) The Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits are hosted in irregular dikes and/or pipes consisting 

mainly of orthopyroxenite, magnetitite, norite and gabbronorite. Orthopyroxene compositions 

ranging from En65.49 to En79.22 mol % indicate moderately primitive to fractionated 

compositions for the parental magma.  

 



49 
 

b) Textural and chemical features support the interpretation that Cu-Au mineralization is 

magmatic and closely associated with magnetite-rich rocks. 

 

c) Sulfide minerals in Cu-Au ore consist mainly of chalcopyrite and bornite, reflecting very high 

Cu/Ni (&gt; 100) and Cu/Fe ratios (from 1~ 1 to ~5) in the sulfide fraction.  

 

d) Isotopic compositions of sulfides are similar to mantle-derived sulfur (-1.0 to 2.5 ?34S ‰), 

except for minor remobilized hydrothermal ore associated with altered mafic-ultramafic rocks (7.5 

to 13.0 ?34S ‰). 

 

e) A combination of fractional crystallization of the parental magma combined with magmatic 

oxidation is an appropriate mechanism to generate the Cu-rich magmatic sulfides with high Cu/Fe 

ratios of the Serrote da Laje and Caboclo deposits. 

 

f) Subordinated mineralization that occurs in veins and/or breccia in altered mafic-ultramafic 

rocks, consisting of pyrite, pyrrhotite and chalcopyrite, have isotopic composition ranging from 

7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰. This mineralization does not indicate the existence of a robust Cu-Au 

hydrothermal system that may lead to different exploration targets than those investigated in this 

study. 

 

g) Magmatic ages of mafic-ultramafic rocks of the Serrote da Laje deposit (ca. 1.99 Ga) and a 

pyroxenite associated with Cu mineralization in the Caraíba deposit (ca. 2.05; Garcia et al., 2016) 

suggest that significant Cu deposits are associated with Paleoproterozoic mafic-ultramafic 

intrusions in the region located close to the northern border of the São Francisco Craton in Brazil. 

 

8 - Acknowledgements  

This study was supported by CNPq (Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e 

Teconológico) and Aura Minerals Inc. Analytical facilities of the Instituto de Geociências of the 

University of Brasília (UnB) provided additional support for this research. The authors 

acknowledge Aura Mineral Exploration Managers (Carlos Bertoni and Jorge Tachibana) for field 

support and access to exploration data. We thank geologist Marcos Deus (former employee at 

Aura Minerals) for his contribution in the initial stages of this project. Cesar F. Ferreira Filho is a 

Research Fellow of CNPq and acknowledges the continuous support through research grants and 



50 
 

scholarships for the "Metalogenênese de Depósitos Associados ao Magmatismo Máfico-

Ultramáfico" Research Group. Guilherme Ferreira Canedo was supported by CNPq (Conselho 

Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Teconológico) and this study is part of his M.Sc. thesis 

developed at the Instituto de Geociências (Universidade de Brasília). 

 

9 - References 

Almeida, F.F.M., Hasui, Y., Brito Neves, B.B., and Fuck, R.A., 1981. Brazilian structural provinces: 

An introduction. Earth Science Reviews, v. 17, p. 1?29. 

 

Amcoff, O., Figueiredo, B.R., 1990. Mechanisms of retrograde changes in oxide minerals from 

Proterozoic Serrote da Laje deposit, northeastern, Brazil. Mineralium Deposita, v. 25, p. 313-322. 

 

Arndt, N.T., Czamanske, G.K., Walker, R.J., Chauvel, C., and Fedorenko, V.A., 2003. Geochemistry 

and origin of the intrusive hosts of the Noril’sk-Talnakh Cu-Ni-PGE sulfide deposits: Economic 

Geology, v. 98, p. 495?515. 

 

Ballhaus C., Tredoux M., Spaeth A., 2001. Phase relations in the Fe-Ni-Cu-PGE-S system at 

magmatic temperature and application to massive sulfide ores of the Sudbury Igneous Complex.  

Journal of Petrology, v. 42, p. 1911-1926. 

 

 

Barnes, S-J., 1986. The effect of trapped liquid crystallization on cumulus mineral compositions in 

layered intrusions. Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology v. 93, p. 524–531. 

 

Barnes, S.-J., Lightfoot, P.C., 2005. Formation of magmatic nickel sulfide ore deposits and 

processes affecting their copper and platinum group element contents. Economic Geology 100th 

Anniversary Volume, p. 179–213. 

 

Bender, K.M., Buhn, B.M., Mota-e-Silva, J., Chaves, J.G.S., 2007. 32S/34S isotope analyses by 

laser ablation MC–ICPMS: method and application. VI South American Symposium on Isotope 

Geology, San Carlos de Bariloche [CD-ROM]. 

 



51 
 

Brito Neves, B.B., Santos, E.J., and Van Schmus, W.R., 2000. Tectonic history of the Borborema 

province, northeast Brazil. International Geological Congress, 31st, 2000, Rio de Janeiro, 

Proceedings, p. 151–182. 

 

Brito Neves, B.B., Sial, A.N., Albuquerque, J.P.T., 1977. Vergência centrífuga residual no sistema 

de dobramentos Sergipano. Revista Brasileira de Geociências, v. 7, p. 102–114. 

 

Buhn, B., Pimentel, M.M., Matteini, M., Dantas, E.L., 2009. High spatial resolution analysis of Pb 

and U isotopes for geochronology by laser ablation multicollector inductively coupled plasma mass 

spectrometry (LA-MC-ICP-MS). Anais Academia Brasileira de Ciências, v. 81, p. 1-16. 

 

Caby, R., Sial, A.N., Arthaud,M.H., Vauchez, A., 1991. Crustal evolution and the Brasiliano 

orogeny in northeast Brazil. In: Mariano, G., Guimarães, I. P., Silva Filho, A.F., Melo, S.C., Neves, 

S.P., 2000. Intralithospheric differentiation and crustal growth: Evidence from the Borborema 

province, northeastern Brazil. Geology , Estados Unidos, v. 28, n.6, p. 519-522. 

 

Campbell, I.H., Naldrett, A.J., 1979. The influence of silicate:sulphide ratios on the geochemistry 

of magmatic sulphides. Economic Geology, v. 74, p. 1503–1506. 

 

Cawthorn, R.G., Meyer, F.M., 1993. Petrochemistry of the Okiep cooper district basic intrusive 

bodies, northwestern Cape province, South Africa. Economic Geology, v. 88, p. 590-605 

Clifford, T.N., Barton, E.S., 2012. The O'okiep Copper District, Namaqualand, South Africa: a 

review of the geology with emphasis on the petrogenesis of the cupriferous Koperberg Suite. 

Mineralium Deposita, v. 47, p. 837-857. 

 

Davison, I., Santos, R.A., 1989. Tectonic evolution of the Sergipano Belt, NE of Brazil, during 

brasilian orogeny.  Precambrian Research, v. 45, p. 319-342. 

 

DePaolo, D.J., 1981. Neodymium isotopes in the Colorado Front Range and implications for crust 

formation and mantle evolution in the Proterozoic. Nature, v. 291, p. 193-197. 

 

Ding, T., Valkiers, S., Kipphardt, H., De Biève, P., Taylor, P.D.P., Gonfiantini, R., Krouse, R., 2001. 

Calibrated sulfur isotope abundance ratios of three IAEA sulfur isotope reference materials and V-



52 
 

CDT with a reassessment of the atomic weight of sulfur. Geochim Cosmochim Acta, v. 65, p. 2433–

2437. 

 

Ferreira Filho, C.F., Nilson, A.A., Naldrett, A.J., 1992. The Niquelândia Mafic-Ultramafic Complex, 

Goias, Brazil: A contribution to the ophiolite vs. stratiform controversy based on new geological 

and structural data. Precambrian Research, v. 59, p. 125?143. 

 

Ferreira Filho, C.F., Pimentel, M.M., Araujo, S.M., Laux, J.H., 2010. Layered intrusions and volcanic 

sequences in Central Brazil: Geological and geochronological constraints for Mesoproterozoic 

(1.25 Ga) and Neoproterozoic (0.79 Ga) igneous associations. Precambrian Research, v. 183, p. 

617?634. 

 

Fetter, A.H., Van Schmus, W.R., Santos, T.J.S., Neto, J.A.N., Arthaud, M.H., 2000. U-Pb e Sm-Nd 

Geochronological Constrains on the Crustal Evolution and Basement Architecture of Ceará State, 

NW Borborema Province, NE Brazil: Implications for the Existence of the Paleoproterozoic 

Supercontinent "Atlantica". Revista Brasileira de Geociências, v. 30, nº 1, p.102-106. 

 

Garcia, P.M.P., 2013. Metalogênese dos depósitos cupríferos de Caraíba, Surubim, Vermelhos e 

Sussuarana, Vale do Curaçá, Bahia, Brasil. Dissertação de Mestrado, Instituto de Geociências, 

Universidade Federal da Bahia, Salvador, 225 p. 

 

Garcia, P.M.P., Misi, A., Sá, J.H.S., Teixeira, J.B.G., Olivo, G.R., Marques, J.C., 2016. Geology, new 

geochronological and isotopic data for the Curaçá Valley Copper Deposits, Bahia, Northeastern 

Brazil. In: Simpósio Brasileiro de Exploração Mineral (SIMEXMIN), Ouro Preto, Brazil, poster 

session. 

 

Gioia, S.M.C.L., Pimentel, M.M., 2000. The Sm-Nd isotopic method in the geochronology 

laboratory of University of Brasilia. Anais da Academia Brasileira de Ciências, v. 72, p. 219-245. 

 

Gao, J-F., Zhou, M-F., Lightfoot, P.C., Wang, C.Y., Qi, L., 2012. Origin of PGE-poor and Cu-rich 

magmatic sulfides from the Kalatongke deposit, Xinjiang, northwest China. Economic Geology, v. 

107, p. 481–506.  

 



53 
 

Ganino, C., Arndt, N.T., Zhou, M.F., Gaillard, F., and Chauvel, C., 2008. Interaction of magma with 

sedimentary wall rock and magnetite ore genesis in the Panzhihua mafic intrusion, SW China. 

Mineralium Deposita, v. 43, p. 677?694.  

 

Groves, D.I.P., Bierlein, F.P., Meinert, L.D., Hitzman, M.W., 2010. Iron oxide copper–gold (IOCG) 

deposits through Earth history; implications for origin, lithospheric setting, and distinction from 

other epigenetic iron oxide deposits. Economic Geology, v. 105, p. 641–654. 

 

Horbach, R., Marimon, M. P. C., 1988. O Depósito de Cobre do Serrote da Laje, em Arapiraca, 

Alagoas. XXXV Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, Belém, SBG, Anais, v. 1, p. 01- 15. 

 

Jugo, P.J., Luth, R.W., and Richards, J.P., 2005. Experimental data on the speciation of sulfur as a 

function of oxygen fugacity in basaltic melts. Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, v. 69, p. 497–503.  

 

Lazarin, F.A., 2011, Geologia, Petrologia e Estudos Isotópicos dos Depósitos de Níquel-Cobre 

Sulfetados Santa Rita e Peri-Peri, Nordeste do Brasil. Dissertação de Mestrado, Instituto de 

Geociências, Universidade de Brasilia, Brasilia, 109 p. 

 

Li, C., Barnes, S-J., Makovicky, E., Rose-Hansen, J., Makovicky, M., 1996. Partitioning of Ni, Cu, Ir, 

Rh, Pt and Pd between monosulfide solid solution and sulfide liquid: effects of composition and 

temperature. Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, v. 60, p. 1231–1238.  

 

Lima, H.A.F., Ferreira Filho, C.F., Pimentel, M.M., Dantas, E.L., Araújo, S.M., 2008. Geology, 

petrology and geochronology of the layered mafic-ultramafic intrusions in the Porto Nacional area, 

central Brazil. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, v. 26, p. 300?317. 

 

Maier, W.D., Andreoli, M.A.G, Groves, D.I., Barnes, S-J., 2012. Petrogenesis of Cu-Ni sulphide ores 

from Okiep and Kliprand, Namaqualand, South Africa: Constraints from chalcophile metal 

contents. South African Journal of Geology, v. 114.4, p. 499-514.  

 

Maier, W.D., Barnes, S-J., 1999. The origin of Cu sulfide deposits in the Curaca Valley, Bahia, Brazil; 

evidence from Cu, Ni, Se, and platinum-group element concentrations. Economic Geology, v. 94, 

p.165-183 



54 
 

Maier, W.D., Barnes, S-J., Arindam, S., Ripley, E., Li, C., and Livesey, T., 2010, The Kabanga Ni sulfide 

deposit, Tanzania: I. Geology, petrography, silicate rock geochemistry, and sulfur and oxygen 

isotopes. Mineralium Deposita, v. 45, p. 419?441. 

 

Maier, W.D., Barnes, S-J., Groves, D.I., 2013. The Bushveld Complex, South Africa: formation of 

platinum–palladium, chrome- and vanadium- rich layers via hydrodynamic sorting of a mobilized 

cumulate slurry in a large, relatively slowly cooling, subsiding magma chamber. Mineralium 

Deposita, v. 48, p. 1–56. 

 

Mendes V.A., Brito  M.F.L., Paiva I.P., 2009. Programa Geologia do Brasil - PGB. Arapiraca. Folha 

SC.24-X-D. Estados de Alagoas, Pernambuco e Sergipe. Mapa Geológico. Recife: CPRM, 2009. 

Escala - 1:250.000 

 

Mota-e-Silva, J., Ferreira Filho, C.F., Bühn, B., Dantas, E.L., 2011. Geology, petrology and 

geochemistry of the “Americano do Brasil” layered intrusion, central Brazil, and its Ni-Cu sulfide 

deposits. Mineralium Deposita, v. 46, p. 57–90. 

 

Mota-e-Silva, J., Ferreira Filho, C.F., Giustina, M.E.S.D., 2013 . The Limoeiro Deposit: Ni-Cu-PGE 

Sulfide Mineralization Hosted Within an Ultramafic Tubular Magma Conduit in the Borborema 

Province, Northeastern Brazil. Economic Geology, v. 108, p. 1753-1771. 

Naldrett, A.J., 1992. A model for the Ni-Cu-PGE ores of the Noril’sk region and its application to 

other areas of flood basalts. Economic Geology, v. 87, p. 1945?1962. 

 

Naldrett, A.J., 2004. Magmatic sulfide deposits: Geology, Geochemistry and Exploration. 

Heidelberg, Springer Verlag, 728 p.  

 

Naldrett, A.J., 2010. Secular Variation of Magmatic Sulfide Deposits and Their Source Magmas. 

Economic Geology, v. 105, p. 669-688. 

 

Naslund, H.R., 1983. The effect of oxygen fugacity on liquid immiscibility in iron-bearing silicate 

melts. American Journal of Science, v. 283, p.1034–1059. 

 

Oliveira, E.P., Tarney, J., 1995. Genesis of the precambrian copper-rich Caraiba hypersthenite-



55 
 

norite complex, Brazil. Mineralium Deposita, v. 30, p. 351-373. 

 

Silva Filho, M.A., Accioly, A.C.A., Torres, H.H.F., Araujo, R.V., 2003. O Complexo Jaramataia no 

Contexto do Sistema Sergipano. Revista de Geologia, v. 16, p. 99-110. 

 

Silva Filho, M.A.; Torres, H.H.F., 2002. A new interpretation on the Sergipano belt domains. An. 

Acad. Bras. Cienc. Anais 74, p. 556-557. 

 

Silva Filho, M.A., Torres, H.H.F., Brito, R.S.C., 2002. Mapa Geológico de Alagoas. Brasília ; CPRM, 

2002, Escala : 1: 250 000. 

 

Santos, E.J. 1996. Ensaio preliminar sobre terrenos e tectônica acrescionária na Província 

Borborema. in: Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, 39, 1996, Salvador. anais. Salvador: SBG, 7v., il., 

v.6, p.47- 50.  

 

Santos, E.J., 1998. Integração geológica e metalogenética, escala 1:250.000, Folha SC.24-X-A 

Belém do São Francisco, Província Borborema, NE do Brasil. Recife: CPRM. 

Santos, E.J.; Brito Neves, B.B.; Van Schmus, W.R.; Oliveira, R.G.; Medeiros, V.C., 2000. An overall 

view on the displaced terrane arrangement of the Borborema Province, NE-Brazil. In: 31st 

International Geological Congress, 2000, Rio de Janeiro. Proceedings, in CD-ROM. 

 

Santos, E.J., Van Schmuss, W.R., Kozuch, M., Brito Neves, B.B., 2010. The Cariris Velhos tectonic 

event in northeast Brazil. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, v. 29, p. 61-76.  

 

Toplis, M.J., and Carroll, M.R., 1995. An experimental study of the influence of oxygen fugacity on 

Fe-Ti oxide stability, phase relations, and mineral-melt equilibria in ferro-basaltic systems. Journal 

of Petrology, v. 36, p. 1137?1170.  

 

Van Schmus, W.R.; Kozuch, M.; Kozuch, B.B.; de Brito Neves, B.B., 2011. Precambrian history of 

the Zona Transversal of the Borborema Province, NE Brazil: Insights from Sm-Nd and U-Pb 

geochronology. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, v. 31, p. 227-252. 

 



56 
 

Williams, P.J., Barton, M.D., Fontbote´ L, 2005. Iron-oxide–copper–gold deposits: Geology, space–

time distribution, and possible modes of origin. Economic Geology 100th Anniversary Volume, p. 

371–406. 

 

Wohlgemuth-Ueberwasser, C.C., Fonseca, R.O.C., Ballhaus, C., Berndt, J., 2013. Sulfide oxidation 

as a process for the formation of copper-rich magmatic sulfides. Mineralium Deposita, v. 48, p. 

115-127.  

 

Zhou, M.F., Robinson, P.T., Lesher, C.M., Keays, R.R., Zhang, C.J., and Malpas, J., 2005. 

Geochemistry, petrogenesis and metallogenesis of the Panzhihua gabbroic layered intrusion and 

associated Fe-Ti-V oxide deposits, Sichuan province, SW China. Journal of Petrology, v. 46, p. 

2253?2280. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



57 
 

CONCLUSÕES 

As principais conclusões do estudo foram:   

1) Os depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo são hospedados em diques e/ou pipes irregulares, 

consistindo principalmente de ortopiroxenitos, magnetititos, noritos e gabronoritos. As 

composições dos ortopiroxênios variam entre En65.49 to En79.22 mol % indicando 

composições moderadamente primitivas a mais fracionadas para o magma parental. 

 

2) Características texturais e químicas suportam a interpretação de que a mineralização de 

Cu-Au é magmática e fortemente associada com rochas ricas em magnetita. 

 

 

3) Os minerais de sulfeto da mineralização de Cu-Au consistem principalmente de calcopirita 

e bornita, refletindo alta razão Cu/Ni (&gt;100) e Cu/Fe (entre 1 e 5) na fração sulfeto. 

 

4) As composições isotópicas dos sulfetos são similares às composições de enxofre derivado 

do manto (-1.0 a 2.5 ?34S ‰), exceto no minério remobilizado hidrotermal associado com 

rochas máfica-ultramáficas alteradas (7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰). 

 

 

5) A combinação de cristalização fracionada do magma parental com a oxidação do magma 

é um mecanismo apropriado para a geração de sulfetos magmáticos ricos em Cu, com alta 

razão Cu/Fe, dos depósitos Serrote da Laje e Caboclo. 

 

6) A mineralização subordinada que ocorre em veios e/ou brechas nas rochas máfica-

ultramáficas alteradas consiste em pirita, pirrotita e calcopirita, tem composição isotópica 

variando entre 7.5 to 13.0 ?34S ‰. Esta mineralização não indica a existência de um 

sistema robusto de Cu-Au hidrotermal, que poderia indicar diferentes alvos além dos 

investigados neste estudo. 

 

7) A idade magmática das rochas máfica-ultramáficas hospedeiras dos depósitos Serrote da 

Laje (ca. 1,99 Ga) e Caraíba (ca. 2.05; Garcia et al., 2016) sugerem que importantes 

depósitos de Cu localizados próximos a borda norte do Craton do São Francisco estão 

associados a intrusões máfica-ultramáficas Paleoproterozóicas.  



I 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

ANEXOS 

Resultados de química mineral – microssonda - ortopiroxênios  

Depósito Serrote da Laje



II 
 

Sample Rock Depth (m) SiO2 TiO2 Al2O3 Fe2O3 Cr2O3 FeO MnO MgO CaO Na2O K2O BaO NiO Total 

SRLJ05 2C  Leuconorite 219.85 52.84 0.04 0.98 0.00 0.01 21.44 0.97 23.05 0.48 0.04 0.01 0.00 0.02 99.87 

SRLJ05 2C  Leuconorite 219.85 52.97 0.05 0.88 0.00 0.06 21.32 0.89 22.88 0.45 0.04 0.00 0.07 0.00 99.61 

SRLJ05 1C  Leuconorite 219.85 53.43 0.00 0.94 0.00 0.02 21.33 0.88 23.38 0.48 0.00 0.00 0.02 0.12 100.59 

SRLJ05 1C  Leuconorite 219.85 53.38 0.06 0.94 0.00 0.05 21.00 0.78 23.37 0.39 0.01 0.02 0.00 0.09 100.09 

SRLJ05 1C  Leuconorite 219.85 52.47 0.03 0.98 0.00 0.05 20.83 0.88 23.06 0.44 0.04 0.00 0.00 0.01 98.80 

SRLJ07 2C  Gabbronorite 198.10 52.54 1.30 1.28 0.00 0.04 20.69 0.58 23.62 0.42 0.02 0.00 0.05 0.05 100.57 

SRLJ07 2C  Gabbronorite 198.10 53.10 0.00 1.14 0.00 0.01 21.91 0.81 23.08 0.42 0.01 0.01 0.00 0.08 100.57 

SRLJ07 2C  Gabbronorite 198.10 53.24 0.09 1.36 0.00 0.02 21.05 0.57 23.63 0.38 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.08 100.46 

SRLJ07 1C OPXN  Gabbronorite 198.10 52.86 0.02 1.43 0.00 0.00 21.31 0.73 23.03 0.67 0.02 0.00 0.12 0.07 100.25 

SRLJ07 1C OPXB  Gabbronorite 198.10 52.86 0.00 1.38 0.00 0.05 21.34 0.76 23.06 0.39 0.03 0.01 0.00 0.02 99.92 

SRLJ07 1C OPXN  Gabbronorite 198.10 52.50 0.11 1.55 0.00 0.01 21.38 0.73 22.78 0.50 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.13 99.70 

SRLJ09 1C OPXN 1.1  Norite 190.90 51.40 0.00 5.32 0.00 0.02 17.35 0.25 25.10 0.08 0.03 0.00 0.00 0.30 99.86 

SRLJ09 1C OPXN 1.2  Norite 190.90 51.52 0.09 5.15 0.00 0.02 18.12 0.29 25.15 0.08 0.00 0.01 0.03 0.09 100.56 

SRLJ09 1C OPXN 1.3  Norite 190.90 50.51 0.44 5.65 0.00 0.04 19.34 0.24 24.10 0.06 0.00 0.00 0.04 0.16 100.58 

SRLJ09 2C OPXN 1.1  Norite 190.90 51.16 0.03 5.75 0.00 0.00 18.13 0.18 24.46 0.09 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.10 99.92 

SRLJ09 2C OPXN 1.2  Norite 190.90 50.87 0.05 5.88 0.00 0.04 18.35 0.27 24.29 0.06 0.04 0.00 0.06 0.19 100.10 

SRLJ09 2C OPXB 1.3  Norite 190.90 50.42 0.01 5.61 0.00 0.06 18.31 0.25 24.48 0.08 0.03 0.00 0.07 0.31 99.63 

SRLJ11 1C OPXN 1.1  Opxt 186.45 49.11 0.04 8.35 0.00 0.13 18.27 0.22 23.83 0.03 0.01 0.02 0.02 0.20 100.22 

SRLJ11 1C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 186.45 49.85 0.00 7.48 0.00 0.04 18.23 0.28 23.83 0.05 0.00 0.01 0.02 0.15 99.92 

SRLJ11 1C OPXN 1.3  Opxt 186.45 49.37 0.09 8.26 0.00 0.15 17.80 0.16 23.94 0.03 0.06 0.00 0.00 0.10 99.96 

SRLJ11 2C OPXB 1.1  Opxt 186.45 50.73 0.01 5.81 0.00 0.09 18.29 0.17 24.33 0.05 0.00 0.01 0.00 0.19 99.69 

SRLJ11 2C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 186.45 50.41 0.04 6.48 0.00 0.07 18.41 0.26 24.18 0.00 0.02 0.01 0.00 0.22 100.10 

SRLJ11 2C OPXB 1.3  Opxt 186.45 49.87 0.07 6.53 0.00 0.06 18.54 0.20 24.34 0.03 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.19 99.85 

SRLJ13 1C OPXB 1.1  Norite 172.80 52.69 0.03 3.40 0.00 0.33 15.98 0.34 27.00 0.18 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.22 100.17 

SRLJ13 1C OPXB 1.2  Norite 172.80 52.69 0.02 3.59 0.00 0.46 15.50 0.31 26.82 0.17 0.05 0.01 0.03 0.20 99.83 

SRLJ13 1C OPXB 1.3  Norite 172.80 52.10 0.04 3.87 0.00 0.48 15.44 0.28 26.46 0.21 0.00 0.00 0.03 0.20 99.09 

SRLJ13 2C OPXN 1.1  Norite 172.80 52.42 0.00 3.83 0.00 0.46 15.10 0.30 26.41 0.22 0.04 0.00 0.00 0.27 99.05 

SRLJ13 2C OPXN 1.2  Norite 172.80 52.46 0.06 3.95 0.00 0.44 15.57 0.27 26.77 0.09 0.01 0.00 0.00 0.20 99.83 

SRLJ13 2C OPXN 1.3  Norite 172.80 52.39 0.15 3.95 0.00 0.44 15.52 0.25 26.52 0.16 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.32 99.70 

SRLJ14 1C OPXN 1.1  Opxt 169.25 50.58 0.07 5.28 0.00 0.10 19.11 0.38 24.18 0.09 0.01 0.00 0.03 0.04 99.88 

SRLJ14 1C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 169.25 50.40 0.05 5.36 0.00 0.13 18.63 0.36 24.35 0.11 0.02 0.01 0.01 0.27 99.71 

SRLJ14 1C OPXN 1.3  Opxt 169.25 52.06 0.05 4.54 0.00 0.08 19.01 0.36 24.88 0.09 0.00 0.01 0.00 0.16 101.25 

SRLJ14 2C OPXB 1.1  Opxt 169.25 51.36 0.06 4.89 0.00 0.14 18.30 0.37 24.28 0.08 0.00 0.03 0.07 0.07 99.65 

SRLJ14 2C OPXB 1.2  Opxt 169.25 51.95 0.01 4.12 0.00 0.09 18.58 0.38 24.71 0.10 0.00 0.01 0.03 0.13 100.12 



III 
 

Sample Rock Depth (m) SiO2 TiO2 Al2O3 Fe2O3 Cr2O3 FeO MnO MgO CaO Na2O K2O BaO NiO Total 

SRLJ14 2C OPXN 1.3  Opxt 169.25 50.74 0.00 6.02 0.00 0.16 18.97 0.33 23.68 0.10 0.00 0.00 0.07 0.25 100.32 

SRLJ15 1C OPXB 1.1  Magnetitite 162.90 51.28 0.04 5.29 0.00 0.08 16.73 0.41 25.53 0.08 0.00 0.00 0.04 0.10 99.58 

SRLJ15 1C OPXN 1.2  Magnetitite 162.90 49.98 0.06 7.58 0.00 0.10 17.65 0.38 24.73 0.08 0.00 0.03 0.00 0.16 100.75 

SRLJ15 1C OPXN 1.3  Magnetitite 162.90 50.28 0.08 4.97 0.00 0.10 18.15 0.36 24.90 0.12 0.02 0.00 0.07 0.15 99.18 

SRLJ15 2C OPXB 1.1  Magnetitite 162.90 50.80 0.01 6.36 0.00 0.10 17.59 0.28 24.89 0.10 0.00 0.01 0.00 0.10 100.24 

SRLJ15 2C OPXB 1.2  Magnetitite 162.90 50.85 0.04 6.52 0.00 0.07 16.98 0.31 25.14 0.08 0.00 0.01 0.00 0.13 100.13 

SRLJ15 2C OPXN 1.3  Magnetitite 162.90 50.82 0.03 6.38 0.00 0.08 16.99 0.32 24.71 0.04 0.06 0.03 0.07 0.12 99.67 

SRLJ16 1C OPXN 1.1  Mag-Opxt 155.10 50.84 0.03 5.90 0.00 0.14 18.44 0.25 24.26 0.06 0.08 0.01 0.00 0.13 100.14 

SRLJ16 1C OPXN 1.2  Mag-Opxt 155.10 50.15 0.02 6.38 0.00 0.16 18.66 0.29 24.38 0.07 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.26 100.40 

SRLJ16 1C OPXN 1.3  Mag-Opxt 155.10 51.57 0.05 4.92 0.00 0.08 18.20 0.28 24.81 0.10 0.01 0.00 0.02 0.04 100.08 

SRLJ16 2C OPXN 1.1  Mag-Opxt 155.10 51.28 0.02 5.46 0.00 0.08 18.04 0.33 24.65 0.07 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.24 100.18 

SRLJ16 2C OPXN 1.2  Mag-Opxt 155.10 50.72 0.00 6.03 0.00 0.10 18.80 0.32 24.32 0.08 0.03 0.02 0.00 0.16 100.58 

SRLJ16 2C OPXN 1.3  Mag-Opxt 155.10 50.43 0.07 6.62 0.00 0.10 18.35 0.22 24.41 0.08 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.17 100.45 

SRLJ17 2C OPXN 1.1  Leuconorito 153.30 49.97 0.04 5.67 0.00 0.04 21.14 0.24 22.00 0.12 0.03 0.04 0.00 0.25 99.54 

SRLJ17 2C OPXB 1.2  Leuconorito 153.30 51.75 0.02 3.36 0.00 0.06 20.94 0.26 23.22 0.09 0.00 0.02 0.06 0.09 99.87 

SRLJ17 2C OPXB 1.3  Leuconorito 153.30 50.41 0.00 4.87 0.00 0.02 21.23 0.23 22.64 0.13 0.01 0.01 0.01 0.22 99.77 

SRLJ17 1C OPXB 1.1  Leuconorito 153.30 51.77 0.02 2.74 0.00 0.05 20.56 0.31 23.66 0.06 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.16 99.35 

SRLJ17 1C OPXN 1.2  Leuconorito 153.30 52.27 0.00 2.36 0.00 0.03 20.73 0.31 23.75 0.19 0.00 0.01 0.07 0.16 99.89 

SRLJ17 1C OPXN 1.3  Leuconorito 153.30 52.18 0.02 2.57 0.00 0.03 20.61 0.34 23.88 0.11 0.00 0.04 0.03 0.23 100.05 

SRLJ18 1C OPXN 1.1  Mag-Opxt 149.60 49.37 0.08 6.64 0.00 0.14 20.02 0.26 24.58 0.06 0.04 0.01 0.00 0.22 101.42 

SRLJ18 1C OPXB 1.2  Mag-Opxt 149.60 50.01 0.10 6.56 0.00 0.09 17.60 0.26 24.70 0.06 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.09 99.50 

SRLJ18 1C OPXB 1.3  Mag-Opxt 149.60 51.91 0.00 4.60 0.00 0.05 17.66 0.32 24.98 0.05 0.04 0.02 0.00 0.18 99.80 

SRLJ18 2C OPXB 1.1  Mag-Opxt 149.60 50.85 0.00 6.04 0.00 0.06 17.82 0.20 24.84 0.12 0.02 0.01 0.01 0.19 100.17 

SRLJ18 2C OPXN 1.2  Mag-Opxt 149.60 50.52 0.00 6.70 0.00 0.13 17.79 0.23 24.42 0.13 0.02 0.02 0.00 0.00 99.97 

SRLJ18 2C OPXB 1.3  Mag-Opxt 149.60 51.25 0.08 5.82 0.00 0.10 18.25 0.21 24.84 0.12 0.04 0.02 0.00 0.20 100.93 

SRLJ20 1C OPXB 1.1  Gabronorite 144.32 52.91 0.09 1.59 0.00 0.06 20.92 0.32 22.67 1.18 0.04 0.02 0.00 0.04 99.85 

SRLJ20 1C OPXN 1.2  Gabronorite 144.32 52.93 0.00 1.49 0.00 0.10 21.78 0.34 23.32 0.43 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.06 100.46 

SRLJ20 1C OPXB 1.3  Gabronorite 144.32 52.54 0.00 1.57 0.00 0.02 22.17 0.37 22.80 0.38 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.02 99.89 

SRLJ20 2C OPXB 1.1  Gabronorite 144.32 52.60 0.08 1.37 0.00 0.07 21.91 0.40 22.73 0.40 0.04 0.00 0.00 0.08 99.70 

SRLJ20 2C OPXN 1.2  Gabronorite 144.32 53.02 0.01 1.57 0.00 0.09 21.30 0.32 23.48 0.47 0.00 0.00 0.03 0.07 100.34 

SRLJ20 2C OPXB 1.3  Gabronorite 144.32 52.94 0.06 1.31 0.00 0.06 21.79 0.42 23.41 0.36 0.02 0.03 0.02 0.12 100.53 

SRLJ21 1C OPXB 1.1  Opxt 143.70 48.97 0.06 8.52 0.00 0.05 18.51 0.35 22.78 0.16 0.00 0.03 0.00 0.13 99.57 

SRLJ21 1C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 143.70 48.54 1.08 7.58 0.00 0.05 19.64 0.24 23.06 0.06 0.01 0.03 0.06 0.08 100.44 

SRLJ21 1C OPXB 1.3  Opxt 143.70 49.94 0.08 7.07 0.00 0.02 18.44 0.23 24.07 0.04 0.08 0.01 0.00 0.15 100.15 



IV 
 

Sample Rock Depth (m) SiO2 TiO2 Al2O3 Fe2O3 Cr2O3 FeO MnO MgO CaO Na2O K2O BaO NiO Total 

SRLJ21 2C OPXB 1.1  Opxt 143.70 49.70 0.00 7.39 0.00 0.04 18.84 0.24 23.68 0.09 0.04 0.00 0.00 0.13 100.15 

SRLJ21 2C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 143.70 49.11 0.09 8.43 0.00 0.06 18.59 0.33 22.73 0.17 0.03 0.03 0.04 0.15 99.76 

SRLJ21 2C OPXB 1.3  Opxt 143.70 48.17 0.05 7.16 0.00 0.11 19.75 0.20 22.85 0.09 0.04 0.03 0.00 0.07 98.50 

SRLJ22 1C OPXN 1.1  Norite 139.10 50.03 0.00 5.99 0.00 0.01 20.27 0.21 22.85 0.10 0.00 0.00 0.03 0.12 99.61 

SRLJ22 1C OPXB 1.2  Norite 139.10 50.55 0.00 5.96 0.00 0.05 20.46 0.18 23.02 0.09 0.02 0.00 0.00 0.22 100.54 

SRLJ22 1C OPXB 1.3  Norite 139.10 50.02 0.03 6.40 0.00 0.00 20.21 0.18 23.20 0.14 0.00 0.00 0.00 0.17 100.38 

SRLJ22 2C CPXN 1.2  Norite 139.10 49.62 0.00 6.38 0.00 0.02 20.18 0.18 22.64 0.10 0.03 0.00 0.00 0.12 99.26 

SRLJ22 2C CPXB 1.3  Norite 139.10 49.70 0.03 6.64 0.00 0.05 20.84 0.17 22.94 0.09 0.02 0.02 0.00 0.16 100.66 

SRLJ23 1C OPXN 1.1  Opxt 136.10 49.39 0.11 7.32 0.00 0.06 19.06 0.34 23.13 0.14 0.02 0.00 0.11 0.18 99.84 

SRLJ23 1C OPXB1.2  Opxt 136.10 50.16 0.10 6.48 0.00 0.10 18.77 0.25 24.19 0.08 0.01 0.04 0.04 0.16 100.38 

SRLJ23 1C OPXB1.3  Opxt 136.10 48.22 0.00 6.80 0.00 0.13 21.58 0.27 23.28 0.08 0.02 0.00 0.08 0.16 100.62 

SRLJ23 2C OPXN 1.1  Opxt 136.10 49.94 0.01 7.19 0.00 0.07 18.27 0.28 23.54 0.03 0.04 0.03 0.00 0.03 99.44 

SRLJ23 2C OPXN 1.2  Opxt 136.10 48.61 0.89 6.29 0.00 0.06 19.40 0.24 23.37 0.03 0.00 0.00 0.07 0.14 99.11 

SRLJ23 2C OPXB 1.3  Opxt 136.10 50.05 0.04 6.90 0.00 0.04 18.31 0.29 24.10 0.03 0.03 0.03 0.00 0.09 99.91 

SRLJ25 1C OPXB 1.1  Mag-Opxt 129.80 50.88 0.07 5.94 0.00 0.05 17.58 0.24 24.64 0.06 0.01 0.01 0.04 0.12 99.65 

SRLJ25 1C OPXN 1.2  Mag-Opxt 129.80 49.51 0.05 7.39 0.00 0.04 18.07 0.25 23.99 0.08 0.02 0.01 0.00 0.08 99.49 

SRLJ25 1C OPXB 1.3  Mag-Opxt 129.80 49.52 0.18 7.22 0.00 0.03 18.14 0.24 24.17 0.00 0.01 0.00 0.06 0.17 99.75 

SRLJ25 2C OPXB 1.1  Mag-Opxt 129.80 51.15 0.00 5.62 0.00 0.06 17.86 0.26 25.03 0.08 0.00 0.03 0.09 0.17 100.36 

SRLJ25 2C OPXN 1.2  Mag-Opxt 129.80 49.61 0.08 7.38 0.00 0.07 18.87 0.33 23.53 0.20 0.04 0.04 0.08 0.14 100.35 

SRLJ25 2C OPXN 1.3  Mag-Opxt 129.80 49.80 0.04 7.53 0.00 0.02 18.44 0.33 23.88 0.04 0.03 0.02 0.00 0.07 100.20 

 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>