<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.14452</field>
		<field name="filename">20791_S0036-46652010000300007.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo
52(3):151-156, May-June, 2010
doi: 10.1590/S0036-46652010000300007

(1) Superintendência de Controle de Endemias-SUCEN/SES/São Paulo, SP, Brasil. 
(2) Centro de Vigilância Epidemiológica Dr. Alexandre Vranjac-SES/São Paulo,SP, Brasil. 
(3) Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde-SVS/MS, Brasil. 
(4) Grupo Técnico de Vigilância XVI/SES/ São Paulo, Brasil.
(5) Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu, UNESP, Botucatu, SP, Brasil. 
(6) Faculdade de Medicina USP, São Paulo, SP, Brasil.
Correspondence to: Dalva M.V. Wanderley, SUCEN, Rua Paula Souza 166, 01027-000 São Paulo, SP, Brasil. E-mail: dalva.wanderley@gmail.com 

ON AN ACUTE CASE OF CHAGAS DISEASE IN A REGION UNDER VECTOR CONTROL  
IN THE STATE OF SÃO PAULO, BRAZIL

Dalva M.V. WANDERLEY(1), Vera L.C.C. RODRIGUES(1), Ruth Moreira LEITE(2), Sueli Yasumaro DIAZ(1), Maria Esther de CARVALHO(1), 
Soraya O. SANTOS(3), Érica TATTO(3), Maria Salete CARLI(4), Kunie I.R. COELHO(5), Paulo Ribeiro da SILVA(1), Sandra Aparecida TÚLIO(4), 

Isaias Ribeiro da SILVA(1) &amp;amp; Maria A. SHIKANAI-YASUDA(6)

SUMMARY

No vector transmitted cases of Chagas disease had been notified in the state of São Paulo since the 1970s. However, in March, 
2006, the death of a six-year-old boy from the municipality of Itaporanga was notified to the Center for Epidemiological Survey of the 
São Paulo State Health Secretariat: an autochthonous case of acute Chagas disease. The postmortem histopathological examination 
performed in the Hospital das Clínicas of the Botucatu School of Medicine confirmed the diagnosis. Reference to hospital records, 
consultation with the health professionals involved in the case and interviews with members of the patient’s family supplied the basis 
for this study. We investigated parasite route of transmission, probable local reservoirs and vectors. No further human cases of acute 
Chagas disease were diagnosed. No locally captured vectors or reservoirs were found infected with Trypanosoma cruzi. Alternative 
transmission hypotheses - such as the possible ingestion of foods contaminated with vector excreta - are discussed, as well as the need 
to keep previously endemic regions and infested houses under close surveillance. Clinicians should give due attention to such signs 
as uni- or bilateral palpebral edema, cardiac failure, myocarditis, pericarditis, anasarca and atypical signs of nephrotic syndrome or 
nephritis and consider the diagnostic hypothesis of Chagas disease. 

KEYWORDS: Acute Chagas disease; Clinical features; State of São Paulo, Brazil.

INTRODUCTION

No vector transmission of Chagas disease (CD) had been notified 
to the health authorities of the state of São Paulo since the mid 1970s9. 
Over the last thirty years the Control Program of the Superintendência 
de Controle de Endemias - SUCEN (Superintendency for the Control 
of Endemic Diseases) has been adjusting its actions according to the 
extent of home triatomine infestation. Thus, the areas marked out for 
active vector search had been gradually restricted. Active vector search 
was finally discontinued in the year 2002. At the same time investment 
in the educational part of the Control Program was supplemented, aiming 
to stimulate residents in rural zones and the outskirts of cities under 
surveillance to notify the occurrence of suspected insects in their homes. 
Accordingly, they are now partaking in the work of CD prophylaxis. 
Surveillance posts were installed to collect and identify the insects 
captured by local residents13. 

As it has been a rare occurrence in the state of São Paulo for at least 
three decades, acute Chagas disease (ACD) can now be a diagnostic 
challenge for those general medical practitioners who are not familiar 
with its signs and symptoms. Indecision and the consequent lack of 

prompt diagnosis tend to delay or even prevent the prescription of specific 
treatment. Concerning epidemiological surveillance, the identification 
of an isolated occurrence is as important as that of an outbreak or an 
accidental laboratory contamination: immediate control measures are 
required. 

In March 2006 a lethal case of ACD - a six-year-old boy from 
the municipality of Itaporanga - was notified to the Center for 
Epidemiological Surveillance of the São Paulo State Health Secretariat, 
or Centro de Vigilância Epidemiológica da Secretaria de Estado da Saúde 
de São Paulo (CVE-SP). Postmortem examination had established the 
diagnosis of his condition. The municipality of Itaporanga is included 
in the XVIth Botucatu Regional Health Section. An investigation into the 
case was initiated by a team which included epidemiological surveillance 
technicians from: the municipality of Itaporanga, branches of SUCEN 
based in the municipalities of Sorocaba, Itararé, São Paulo and Mogi 
Guaçu, XVIth Botucatu Health Regional Section, Epidemiological 
Surveillance Group based in the municipality of Avaré, and CVE-SP. 
The task of investigating mode of transmission, reservoirs, and vectors 
involved was assigned to a multi-professional team from central and 
local administrative levels. 



WANDERLEY, D.M.V.; RODRIGUES, V.L.C.C.; LEITE, R.M.; DIAZ, S.Y.; CARVALHO, M.E.; SANTOS, S.O.; TATTO, E.; CARLI, M.S.; COELHO, K.I.R.; SILVA, P.R.; TÚLIO, S.A.; 
SILVA, I.R. &amp;amp; SHIKANAI-YASUDA, M.A. - On an acute case of Chagas disease in a region under vector control in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 
52(3):151-6, 2010. 

152

MATERIALS AND METHODS

We analyzed information kept in the records of the institutions where 
the patient had received medical care, both as an outpatient and as an 
inpatient, in Itaporanga, Avaré and Botucatu. We describe the consequent 
epidemiological and entomological investigation, which involved a 
search for triatomine vectors and potential vertebrate reservoirs in the 
area. We made house calls and had talks with members of the patient’s 
family. From his parents, both his brothers and his grandmother (who 
lives in another house) blood samples were collected for the serological 
tests: immunofluorescent antibody test (IFAT) and Enzyme-Linked 
ImmunoSorbent Assay (ELISA) for the diagnosis of Chagas disease, 
which were performed as specified by the kit manufacturers (Immuno-
com, WAMA diagnóstica and Test ELISA para Chagas – BIOSChile 
respectively). Triatomines and vertebrate reservoirs were searched for 
inside and outside the house and in the annexes. Dislodging agents 
were applied before insecticide spraying. Light traps7 to capture adult 
triatomines and traps intended for synanthropic as well as wild potential 
vertebrate Trypanosoma cruzi reservoirs were also set up on the 
premises10. Fluid extracted by abdominal compression from the captured 
triatomines was used to prepare both May-Grünwald/Giemsa stained 
smears to be examined for trypanosomes10 and precipitin blood meal 
identification tests12. Giemsa stained10 blood smears from the captured 
synanthropic and wild animals were also examined for trypanosomes. 
Xenodiagnosis, using 10 insect specimens (Triatoma infestans and 
Panstrongylus megistus 4th and 5th nymphal stages) was another diagnostic 
technique applied to this case. 

RESULTS

1. Clinical investigation: A six-year-old male was taken to an 
out-patient clinic in Itaporanga on February 8th, 2006. He had nausea, 
hyporexia, and cephalea. Diagnostic hypotheses: upper respiratory tract 
infection (URTI) and helminthiasis. Ceftriaxone was prescribed and 
administered accordingly. February 11th, 2006: new consultation, this 
time at Nossa Senhora das Graças Hospital in Itaporanga. Observed: 
fever, edema, and abdominal pain. Prescribed: Dipirone and Dimethicone. 
February 13th, 2006: no health improvement. The patient was taken for 
further consultation. Diagnosis: pharyngitis. Chest radiography failed 
to show any heart or lung problem (eventually identified in Avaré and 
Botucatu). February 15th, 2006: emergency consultation in Itaporanga. 
Requested: chest radiography. Diagnosis: pneumonia. The patient was 
febrile; chest radiography showed a paracardiac effusion on the right 
side and enlargement of the cardiac area. Treatment with Ceftriaxone 
was maintained. 

Thirteen days after the first consultation (February 21, 2006) 
emergency attention was required. Observed: facial edema and persistent 
fever (38.6 ºC). Body weight was increased by 2.0 kg (edema). Urinalysis, 
normal. Hospitalization in Itaporanga: diagnostic hypotheses, nephritis 
and bronchopneumonia. Chest radiography showed progressive 
enlargement of the cardiac area. Hemogram: moderate anemia without 
leukocytosis. According to the laboratory examinations, renal function 
was normal: BUN = 19.0 mg/dL; creatinine = 0.6 mg/dL. Antistreptolysin 
O titer (ASO) = 800 UI/mL (negative &amp;lt;299 UI/mL). Three days 
afterwards (February 24th, 2006): urinalysis, normal. BUN increased to 
23.2 mg/dL; creatinine, 0.7 mg/dL (still within normal limits). The patient 
was transferred to the Santa Casa hospital in Avaré. Here, laboratory 

test results diverged from those previously obtained elsewhere. Now 
severe anemia (Hb = 9.1g/dL) and left shift leukocytosis (18 600/mm³) 
(9.0%) were detected. Diagnosis: pneumonia with pleural effusion and 
respiratory failure. Abdominal pain increased in intensity; the hypothesis 
of acute abdomen was formulated. Chest radiography: interstitial opacity 
of the right lung base (paracardiac), homogeneous opacity of the right 
lung base (pleural effusion), accentuation of the right lung hilum, and 
enlargement of the cardiac area. A routine radiography of the abdomen 
showed a normal aspect of bone structures, anatomical images preserved, 
intestinal gases distributed as usual and no pathological calcifications 
observed, the hypothesis of acute abdomen was ruled out.

On February 25th, 2006: thoracic fluid drainage (thoracentesis) on 
the right side. No acid-fast or other bacilli were found in the pleural 
fluid. Oxacillin, Amicacin and Ceftriaxone were prescribed. On this 
day, the X-ray picture showed small subcutaneous emphysema and a 
thoracic tube on the right side; interstitial opacity on the right lung base 
and enlarged cardiac area. Laboratory test results on February 26th, 2006 
showed: creatinine = 0.8 mg/dL; BUN = 26 mg/dL; total serum protein 
= 4.2 g/dL; serum albumin = 1.7 g/dL; serum globulin = 2.5 g/dL;  
A/G ratio = 0.7; amylase = 11U/L. According to the nurse’s report, the 
patient had diarrhea and oliguria; the pleural fluid was “purulent”. On 
the following day his condition worsened: he had oliguria and dyspnea, 
was anorectic, crying and moaning with intense abdominal pain. On 
February 28th, 2006, the patient’s condition was declared critical, he was 
transferred to the Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de 
Botucatu - Universidade Estadual Paulista - UNESP, where hypotension 
was observed (P

sys
 = 90 mm Hg; P

dias
 = 60 mm Hg).

Cultures of pleural fluid, blood, urine, and feces showed negative 
results. March 2nd, 2006: the echocardiogram showed slight hypertrophy 
and moderate systolic dysfunction of the left ventricle (LV); pericardial 
effusion and moderate to serious mitral insufficiency. Treatment for heart 
failure was started. An investigation was initiated into the etiology of 
the myocarditis. The child was pronounced dead on March 7th, 2006, 27 
days after the first consultation. 

Necroscopical examination established the diagnosis of ACD. 
Consequential causes: cardiomegaly, pleural effusion, ascitis (200 mL, 
citrine-yellow), chronic passive pulmonary congestion. Terminal cause: 
heart failure. Serological tests (ELISA and passive hemagglutination 
for the diagnosis of ACD) performed postmortem (on March 14th, 
2006) were positive. The results of the same tests, applied to relatives 
of the patient (mother, father, grandmother, and two brothers) were 
negative. Heart histological sections showed T. cruzi amastigote “nests”, 
inflammatory mononuclear infiltrate and sparse granulomatous structures 
in the interstitial spaces. The cardiac fibers showed diffuse alteration, 
vascular congestion interstitial and interfibrillar edema; agglomeration of 
amastigotes. Mononuclear infiltration, mainly composed of lymphocytes 
and plasma cells. Myofibers, predominantly dissociated were observed 

2. Epidemiological investigation: Our epidemiological investigation 
included domiciliary visits to the relatives of the deceased patient. 
According to them, he was delivered normally in a hospital maternity 
ward. His height and weight had been normal for his age and he was 
periodically examined at a public Health Center in the municipality, 
regularly receiving milk. There were no records of past illness, blood 
transfusion or hospitalization. 



WANDERLEY, D.M.V.; RODRIGUES, V.L.C.C.; LEITE, R.M.; DIAZ, S.Y.; CARVALHO, M.E.; SANTOS, S.O.; TATTO, E.; CARLI, M.S.; COELHO, K.I.R.; SILVA, P.R.; TÚLIO, S.A.; 
SILVA, I.R. &amp;amp; SHIKANAI-YASUDA, M.A. - On an acute case of Chagas disease in a region under vector control in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 
52(3):151-6, 2010. 

153

His family had been living for seven months in a wooden house 
with poor standards of hygiene and frequent contact with animals in 
its periphery. It was impoverished and dysfunctional (a chronically 
alcoholic father and a mother suffering from depression). In addition to 
the deceased, his parents and two brothers, aged one and seven, occupied 
the family house. They had previously lived on a farm in the municipality 
of Salto de Pirapora. No records of blood transfusion or hospitalization 
of this patient could be found in the Health Centers of Salto de Pirapora 
or Votorantim, which his family had access to. 

As stated by the deceased patient’s father, a “barbeiro” (“cone-
nosed bug”, Hemiptera: Reduviidae), which had fallen from the roof 
of the family house during the day, was captured at the beginning of 
February, 2006, and duly notified to the health authorities on February 
20th, 2006. According to the patient’s mother, she had, less than 30 days 
earlier, captured another “barbeiro” specimen in his bed. That insect was 
eventually destroyed. In spite of his age, the boy still sucked a pacifier 
and remained frequently in bed for long periods and complained of leg 
pain. He liked to eat raw vegetables, but had been losing his appetite for 
about a year, was rather aggressive, introverted, and easily tired when 
playing with other children. His grandfather died of CD more than 20 
years ago and one of his uncles has also been infected. 

Xenodiagnosis was applied to three members of the family (with the 
exception of the one-year-old child) which came out negative.

A nationwide serologic survey is now applied to children five-years-
old or younger in the state of São Paulo. It includes the municipality of 
Itaporanga. One of the localities selected is in the proximity of that where 
the family of the deceased patient lived. From a sample of 356 sera, none 
produced positive results (personal communication, Prof. Alejandro O. 
Luquetti-UFGO, Goiânia, GO, Brazil). 

3. Entomological investigation: The triatomine specimen captured 
by the deceased boy’s family and notified to the local health authorities on 
February 20th, 2006, was identified as Panstrongylus megistus, negative 
for T. cruzi. A consequence of this finding was an exhaustive search for 
triatomines inside the house and in the surrounding area; no triatomines 
were found. 

The family house is made of wooden planks (Fig. 2), and has marks 
of the permanence of such domestic animals as poultry, ducks, pigs, 
dogs, and cows in its periphery, where their feces accumulated. Inside 
the house mice tracks were visible. The family declared that, after the 
death of their child, the Social Promotion Sector of the Municipality 
assisted them in cleaning the house and clearing the surrounds of weeds. 
They have also sprayed insecticides as recommended. A new exhaustive 
entomological investigation included spraying the house with alpha-
Cypermethrin preceded by the application of a dislodging agent (Pirisa). 
Another investigation was made in this area after a period of three months. 
Light traps were set up to capture triatomines in the surrounds of a house 
where the deceased boy’s family had stayed for about 30 days during the 
month of August 2005. No triatomines were found.

4. Situation of the entomological surveillance for Chagas disease 
in the municipality of Itaporanga, state of São Paulo: The municipality 
of Itaporanga is located in the Southwest of the state of São Paulo, Brazil 
(23°42’24”S, 49°29’24”W). It is included in the Governmental Region 
of Avaré (an administrative subdivision of the state), in the homogeneous 
Micro-Region of Campos de Itapetininga, a subdivision of the former. 
Five infected specimens of Triatoma infestans had been captured here 
in the year 1978, while the last capture of T. infestans (one specimen) in 
the Municipality of Itaporanga dates back to 1974. Since then, very few 
specimens of P. megistus have been found in human domiciles, some of 
them naturally infected. During the 1980s, triatomine infestation reached 
extremely low levels in Itaporanga. The year 1988 marked the last 
extensive search for triatomines in houses and their surroundings. Not a 
single specimen was captured during that year. Since then, entomological 
surveillance has been maintained by encouraging local people to notify 
the health authority or the local school, of the presence of any insect 
suspected of being a “barbeiro”. It should be emphasized that, in the 
locality where the deceased patient had his residence, the capture of a 
female specimen of P. megistus (negative for T. cruzi infection) had been 
notified. On March 8, 2006 the consequent search for triatomines was 
negative. No triatomine species were found.

From the year 2000 onwards, P. megistus has been the only species 
captured in the municipality of Itaporanga (95.2% inside houses), 

Fig. 1 - Intracellular Trypanosoma cruzi (amastigota “nest”) inside myocardial fibers. 
Inflammatory reaction.

Fig. 2 - Home of the deceased ACD patient, in the rural zone of Itaporanga, SP, Brazil.



WANDERLEY, D.M.V.; RODRIGUES, V.L.C.C.; LEITE, R.M.; DIAZ, S.Y.; CARVALHO, M.E.; SANTOS, S.O.; TATTO, E.; CARLI, M.S.; COELHO, K.I.R.; SILVA, P.R.; TÚLIO, S.A.; 
SILVA, I.R. &amp;amp; SHIKANAI-YASUDA, M.A. - On an acute case of Chagas disease in a region under vector control in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 
52(3):151-6, 2010. 

154

infected (15.5%); these have been isolated specimens, without formation 
of colonies (Table 1). 

The two triatomine specimens captured inside houses during the 
period from 2001 to 2003 had precipitin tests positive for human blood. 
Those specimens captured more recently had only bird and dog blood 
identified as ingested. According to the entomological norms in force 
at that occasion in the Control Program of Chagas disease - Programa 
de Controle da Doença de Chagas - PCDCh, all the residents of a 
house where an infected triatomine had been captured should undergo 
serological tests for T. cruzi infection, to ascertain the consequences of the 
occurrence of infected vectors in a human dwelling. Serological tests of 
the inhabitants of the municipality of Itaporanga, during the periods from 
1984 to 1988 and from 1990 to 1993, showed a total of 12.06% positive 
results. Remarkably, none of the positive tests were observed in people 
aged 15 years or younger2. The serological data in the later years 2001 
and 2002, consisted of, respectively, six and 10 blood samples and one 
seropositive in each year, both belonging to the age group 51 to 60 years. 

5. Reservoir investigation: Before spraying the place with dislodging 
agents, a comprehensive investigation into the possible occurrence of 
vertebrate animal reservoirs was made in the area. Traps were installed for 
the capture of wild animals known to be potential reservoirs of T. cruzi. 
This resulted in the capture of two specimens of Didelphis albiventris. 
Fresh and stained blood smears, in addition to xenodiagnosis, were all 
negative for flagellate forms of T. cruzi. A specimen of Rattus rattus was 
shown to be positive for Trypanosoma (Herpetosoma) lewisi, observed 
in fresh blood smears. This protozoon strain was isolated by inoculation 
in laboratory mice (Wistar).

6. General orientation: The Health Service personnel were 
instructed to keep a record of every bit of information about cases of 
fever in the families when collecting insects reported by householders of 
Itaporanga inhabitants. Notifiers were told to be alert to the emergence 
of symptoms (especially fever) in any member of their families during 
the 90 days following notification. Furthermore, they should look for 
medical service and make known the discovery of blood-sucking insect/s 
in their homes. 

DISCUSSION

Following the Control Program of the State of São Paulo (PCDCh) 
norms, the specific duties under the responsibility of SUCEN should 
be aimed at the control of vector triatomines. Upon the detection of T. 
infestans specimens in the human domicile, a serological investigation 
of the local residents should be made. Regarding the occurrence of 
other vector species, this investigation will depend only on the indoor 
detection of vectors with ingesta identified as human blood and infected 
with T. cruzi. In the high plateau of the state of São Paulo, as a whole, 
no reagent cases have been found among young people4, considering 
the current conditions for performing serological tests in population 
samples. The same is not true for the littoral5. In the neighborhood of 
Itaporanga CD was still prevalent in the six years or over age group in 
1976. This explains the concern for diagnosing congenital CD infection 
in the female seroreagent group3. 

Serological tests for CD applied to the inhabitants of Itaporanga 
between the years 1976 and 1978 produced 19.22% positives - confidence 
interval 95% of the

 
positives = 17.27 to 21.34 out of a total of 1,441 

samples from four localities2. In the 2-to-29-year-old age-group 42.23% 
of the cases are clustered, which indicates a problem of CD transmission 
in this area. It is important to note that Itaporanga was included in the 
project of serological survey among school-children in the first series 
of the fundamental classes. That survey, made between 1973 and 1983, 
comprised 54 municipalities of different regions of the state of São Paulo. 
The proportions of positives were 14.0% and 8.4% in 1973 and 1974 
respectively, and decreased with the passage of time until they reached 
the values of 0.9% and zero per cent in 1982 and 1983, respectively2. 

In Itaporanga, seroreactivity results have now reached values 
comparable to those characteristic of past infection, in spite of the fact 
that infected P. megistus specimens have been observed. The occurrence 
of this species infected with T. cruzi has been detected6; thus, vigilance is 
maintained in many areas of the state13. On every occasion that an insect 
is notified, SUCEN promotes cautious observation of the area mentioned, 
(attendance to notification) in search of vector foci and colonies11. 

In spite of all caution we were compelled to report the occurrence of 
an ACD case in the state of São Paulo, Brazil: a previously healthy six-
year-old child, resident in the rural zone of Itaporanga, manifested clinical 
signs and symptoms compatible with those of ACD, such as continuous 
fever, leg and face edema, intense abdominal pain, myocardiopathy, and 
eventually heart failure. 

As the semiological techniques used failed to identify the etiology 
of the disease, the patient did not receive the specific treatment. 
The etiological diagnosis of this case was the result of postmortem 
histopathological and parasitological examinations performed at least 
27 days after the first medical consultation. 

Probable contact with the triatomine specimen found by the patient’s 
mother on his bed (destroyed without having been examined), could 
possibly have caused the infection through his eyelid mucosa or small 
quantities of triatomine excreta might have been ingested, accepting the 
hypothesis that the insect was, in fact, infected. According to estimates 
of incubation periods of Chagas disease (three to 22 days for oral 
transmission, and five to 15 days for vectorial transmission), contact 

Table 1
Triatomine capture in the municipality of Itaporanga, SP, Brazil,  

from 2000 to 2006

YEAR Panstrongylus megistus 
collected

Panstrongylus megistus 
infected

Intra Peri Intra Peri

2000 12 - 1 -

2001 9 - 1 -

2002 14 2 5 -

2003 19 - 3 -

2004 8 - 1 -

2005 8 1 1 -

2006 14 1 1 -

Source: SUCEN/DCV/NIT, 2009.



WANDERLEY, D.M.V.; RODRIGUES, V.L.C.C.; LEITE, R.M.; DIAZ, S.Y.; CARVALHO, M.E.; SANTOS, S.O.; TATTO, E.; CARLI, M.S.; COELHO, K.I.R.; SILVA, P.R.; TÚLIO, S.A.; 
SILVA, I.R. &amp;amp; SHIKANAI-YASUDA, M.A. - On an acute case of Chagas disease in a region under vector control in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 
52(3):151-6, 2010. 

155

with the triatomine specimen which was notified could have caused the 
infection. However, in this case the route of infection of T. cruzi would 
be difficult to trace. Vectorial transmission should not be ruled out 
altogether, as an infected specimen of P. megistus had been captured in 
the municipality of Itaporanga in the year 2006. However, this hypothesis 
is based on the slimmest evidence. The hypothesis of oral contamination 
was considered remote as the other members of the patient’s family, who 
shared the same sources of nutrients (father, mother, and brothers), were 
not demonstrated to be infected. 

This case history exposes the difficulty that a clinician may 
experience in trying to act promptly to diagnose a case of ACD, even in 
the environment of a tertiary-level hospital. Recent and well documented 
outbreaks of trypanosomiasis resulting from oral contamination, exhibited 
some manifestations which until recently would have been considered 
unusual. It is evidently necessary to adopt new definitions for suspected 
cases of ACD to enable clinicians to reach without delay the correct 
diagnosis, so that the specific treatment can be promptly started. 

In addition to the classic definitions of the acute disease1, fever 
persisting for more than five days, adenomegaly with hepatosplenomegaly, 
bilateral edema of the eyelids, edema of the extremities, exanthema, 
myocarditis and meningoencephalitis, the inclusion of such signs 
as suspected glomerulonephritis with a normal urinary sediment, 
pericarditis, cardiac failure with or without pleural effusion, icterus 
without apparent cause, associated with fever; anasarca without urinary 
or cardiac dysfunction, associated with fever; fever without any apparent 
focus in patients with such positive epidemiological data as direct contact 
with triatomines or with food contaminated with their excreta should 
be investigated. 

Although associated with a great number of symptoms, ACD has 
not been a diagnostic hypothesis as frequently as should be reasonably 
expected. Now, the most important vector of CD is under control 
in Brazil8, but there have been many recent reports of probable oral 
transmission. The acute phase of CD is characterized by very high 
concentrations of trypomastigotes in the peripheral blood. Thus, the live 
parasite is readily identified in fresh blood samples. This is a simple, 
efficient, rapid and inexpensive means, highly recommended for the 
identification of the etiological agent of CD. In case of positive result, 
immediate specific treatment should be prescribed. This case history 
emphasizes the importance of the maintenance of the program of active 
surveillance and the inclusion of areas where the vector is already under 
control. We suggest the creation of two levels of control. Level One: 
control of triatomines, which will count upon the cooperation of the 
community and surveillance institutions; selection of techniques sensitive 
enough to detect new, scarcely evident triatomine colonies. Immediate 
notification of positive cases to the Health Units. Level Two: training 
of Health Teams should be adequately updated to permit a prompt 
identification of suspected cases of ACD, even when the patients are 
coming from a region where the vector control has been considered 
successful for the last decades. We aim to avoid misdiagnosis and the 
worsening of a patient’s condition towards an otherwise avoidable death.

AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS

Dalva Marli V. Wanderley: first draft of the manuscript, supervision 
of field surveillance and control of CD vector activity, text writing; Vera 

Lúcia C.C. Rodrigues: field supervision of vector triatomine control and 
potential vertebrate T. cruzi reservoirs, in addition to laboratory work, T. 
cruzi detection and histopathological identification; Ruth M. Leite, Kunie 
I. R. Coelho and Sueli Y. Diaz: support for the epidemiological as well 
as entomological surveillance work in the Region of Sorocaba, where 
the case under study occurred; Maria Esther de Carvalho: execution of 
serological tests, analysis of laboratory data concerning the epidemiological 
history of the area under study; Soraya O. Santos, Érica Tatto and Maria 
Salete Carli: epidemiological investigation support in the XVI Botucatu 
Health Division; Paulo Ribeiro da Silva and Sandra Aparecida Túlio: 
epidemiological investigation support in Avaré, Isaias Ribeiro da Silva and 
Maria A Shikanai-Yasuda: clinical investigation and text writing.

RESUMO

Sobre caso de doença de Chagas aguda em região de vetores 
controlados no Estado de São Paulo, Brasil

Desde a década de 1970 não se notificavam casos autóctones de 
doença de Chagas aguda em São Paulo. Em março de 2006 a Vigilância 
Epidemiológica registrou óbito por doença de Chagas aguda, em 
Itaporanga, de paciente de seis anos de idade. Exame histopatológico post 
mortem realizado no Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de 
Botucatu confirmou o diagnóstico. Consultamos prontuários de hospitais 
e entrevistamos profissionais de saúde envolvidos além de familiares do 
paciente. Descrevemos medidas adotadas in loco para identificar a via 
de transmissão, reservatórios e vetores. Discutimos as possíveis fontes 
de infecção. Na região não foram identificados outros casos humanos, 
vetores ou reservatórios vertebrados infectados por Trypanosoma cruzi. 
Salientamos a importância de manter a vigilância, mesmo em áreas onde 
a transmissão de doença de Chagas está interrompida e naquelas ainda 
infestadas por triatomíneos. Deve-se admitir a hipótese diagnóstica de 
doença de Chagas quando observados: edema palpebral (uni ou bilateral), 
insuficiência cardíaca, miocardite, pericardite, anasarca, quadros 
similares aos de síndrome nefrótica ou glomerulonefrite sem causas 
outras aparentes, em pacientes com dados epidemiológicos positivos. 
Encontro, mesmo em raras ocasiões, de triatomíneos na região ou ainda 
contato com alimento contaminável com formas infectantes de T. cruzi. 

REFERENCES

 1.  Amato Neto V, Shikanai-Yasuda MA, Sabbaga Amato V. Doença de Chagas aguda. In: 
Dias JCP, Coura JR, orgs. Clínica e terapêutica da doença de Chagas: uma abordagem 
prática para o clínico geral. Rio de Janeiro: Fiocruz; 1997. p. 227-34.

 2.  Carvalho ME. Sorologia da infecção chagásica no Programa de Controle do Estado 
de São Paulo, Brasil. [Tese]. São Paulo: Universidade de São Paulo, Faculdade de 
Saúde Pública; 2000.

 3.  Carvalho ME, Latorre MRDO, Ferreira CS, Mello CS, Barata JMS. Soroprevalência 
de infecção chagásica em área de Triatoma infestans após medidas de controle. Rev 
Saúde Pública. 2000;34:15-20.

 4.  Carvalho ME, Silva RA, Rodrigues VLCC, Oliveira CD. Programa de Controle da 
Doença de Chagas no Estado de São Paulo: sorologia de moradores como parte de 
investigação de unidades domiciliares com presença de triatomíneos vetores na década 
de 1990. Cad Saúde Pública. 2002;18:1695-703.

 5.  Carvalho ME, Silva RA, Barata JMS, Domingos MF, Ciaravolo RMC, Zacharias F. 
Soroepidemiologia de tripanosomíase americana na região do litoral sul, São Paulo. 
Rev Saúde Pública. 2003;37:49-58.



WANDERLEY, D.M.V.; RODRIGUES, V.L.C.C.; LEITE, R.M.; DIAZ, S.Y.; CARVALHO, M.E.; SANTOS, S.O.; TATTO, E.; CARLI, M.S.; COELHO, K.I.R.; SILVA, P.R.; TÚLIO, S.A.; 
SILVA, I.R. &amp;amp; SHIKANAI-YASUDA, M.A. - On an acute case of Chagas disease in a region under vector control in the State of São Paulo, Brazil. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 
52(3):151-6, 2010. 

156

 6.  Nascimento C, Marassá AM, Curado I, Piazza RMF. Encontro de Panstrongylus 
megistus em ecótopo artificial: domiciliação ou mera visitação? Rev Soc Bras Med 
Trop. 1997;30:333-6.

 7.  Noireau F, Abad-Franch F, Valente SA, Dias-Lima A, Lopes CM, Cunha V, et al. 
Trapping Triatominae in sylvatic habitats. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz. 2002;97:61-3.

 8.  Organización Panamericama de la Salud. OPS/HDM/CD. XV Reunión de la Comisión 
Intergubernamental del Cono Sur para la eliminación de Triatoma infestans y la 
interrupción de la transmisión de la tripanosomiasis transfusional. Validación de la 
interrupción de la transmisión vectorial de Trypanosoma cruzi por T. infestans en 
Brasil. Brasília; 2006.

 9.  Rocha e Silva E, Guarita OF, Ishihata GK. Doença de Chagas: atividades de controle 
dos transmissores no Estado de São Paulo, Brasil. Rev Bras Malariol. 1979;31:99-119.

 

 10.  Rocha e Silva EO, Rodrigues VLCC, Reyes S. Manual de normas sobre organização 
e funcionamento de laboratórios de diagnóstico da doença de Chagas. Brasília: 
Ministério da Saúde; 1980.

 11.  Secretaria de Estado da Saúde de São Paulo. Superintendência de Controle de 
Endemias. Vigilância entomológica da doença de Chagas no Estado de São Paulo. 
Diretrizes Técnicas. São Paulo; 2003. 

 12.  Siqueira AF. Estudos sobre a reação de precipitina aplicada na identificação do sangue 
ingerido por triatomíneos. Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo. 1960;2:41-53.

 13.  Wanderley DMV, Silva RA, Carvalho ME, Barbosa GL. Doença de Chagas: 
a vigilância entomológica no Estado de São Paulo. Bol Epidemiol Paulista. 
2007;4(38):10-14.

Received: 27 March 2009
Accepted: 8 March 2010

 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>