<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.24445</field>
		<field name="filename">8830_ulfc105435_tm_Yiyi_Ji.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Universidade de Lisboa 

Faculdade de Ciências 

Departamento de Física 

 

 

 

 Dual tuned 
19

F/
1
H Multichannel Coil for Magnetic Resonance 

Imaging of Human Knee at 7.0 Tesla 

Yiyi Ji 

 

Dissertação 

Mestrado Integrado em Engenharia Biomédica e Biofísica 

Perfil em Engenharia Clínica e Instrumentação Médica   

 

 

2013 



 



Universidade de Lisboa 

Faculdade de Ciências 

Departamento de Física 

 

 

 Dual tuned 
19

F/
1
H Multichannel Coil for Magnetic Resonance 

Imaging of Human Knee at 7.0 Tesla 

Yiyi Ji 

 

Dissertação 

Mestrado Integrado em Engenharia Biomédica e Biofísica 

Perfil em Engenharia Clínica e Instrumentação Médica   

 

Orientador interno: Professor Doutor Alexandre Andrade 

Orientador externo: Professor Doutor Thoralf Niendorf 

 

2013 



 



i 

 

RESUMO 
 

Anti-inflamatórios não esteróides (NSAIDs) tópicos foram introduzidos no tratamento da 

artrite reumatóide, de forma a evitar os efeitos secundários da administração oral destes 

medicamentos. Embora seja conhecido que os NSAIDs de aplicação tópica são capazes de 

penetrar na pele humana, não existem estudos com humanos in vivo que mostrem a 

eficiência de penetração e o percurso do medicamento até ao local de inflamação. 

O in vivo tracking do medicamento deve ser efectuado por um método eficaz e não 

invasivo. A ressonância magnética (MRI) e espectroscopia por ressonância magnética 

(MRS) do flúor (
19

F) são de maior interesse para este propósito, dado que a MRI oferece 

um excelente contraste de tecidos, elevada resolução espacial e temporal e, a ausência de 

flúor nos tecidos biológicos faz do núcleo deste átomo um probe ideal para fazer tracking e 

quantificação in vivo de NSAIDs que contenham flúor. 

A baixa resolução espacial e temporal de 
19

F MRI/MRS, devido a baixas concentrações 

deste átomo nas regiões de interesse, pode ser aumentada nos campos magnéticos ultra 

elevados (UHF) pelo aumento da razão sinal-ruído (SNR) que acompanha o aumento da 

intensidade do campo do magneto estático. Porém, o aumento do campo magnético acarreta 

desvantagens como o aumento da não homogeneidade do campo de excitação   
  e da 

absorção da energia de radio frequência (RF), que causa o aquecimento indesejável dos 

tecidos. RF array coils de superficie com um design ideal e com os parâmetros RF 

refinados podem usufruir da elevada SNR de UHF e, ao mesmo tempo reduzir a não 

homogeneidade do   
  e evitar a elevada deposição de energia de RF de modo a que esta 

não exceda os limites de taxa de absorção específica (SAR). 

Neste projecto foi desenvolvida uma coil de superfície de frequência dual (
1
H e 

19
F) para 

registo de imagens anatómicas com protões, assim como de imagens e espectroscopia de 

flúor no tracking e quantificação deste átomo num creme de NSAID com flúor (ácido 

flufenâmico) num joelho humano a 7.0 Tesla.  

A coil construída consiste em três partes, contendo quatro canais de protão e quatro canais 

de flúor, que abrangem toda a área de interesse. As duas partes anteriores, com dois canais 



ii 

 

de flúor e um de protão cada, cobrem a parte anterior do joelho, onde o creme de NSAID é 

aplicado. A parte posterior, formada por dois canais de protão, é curvada convexamente 

para suportar confortavelmente o joelho durante os exames de MRI. 

O circuito do condutor da coil foi imprimido numa folha de cobre através de um sistema de 

controlo numérico por computador. Vários condensadores foram soldados ao longo do 

condutor de modo a diminuir o seu comprimento, assim são evitadas as fases zero da onda 

sinusoidal, onde não há sinal, na medida em que o comprimento de onda em 7.0 T é 

aproximadamente o comprimento dos condutores. Foram colocados condensadores 

ajustáveis nos locais de circuito reservados ao tuning, matching e decoupling dos elementos 

da coil. Desde modo, a coil pode ser ajustada a diferentes loads (fantomas ou humanos) 

conforme o necessário. Além disso, ainda foram colocadas cable traps nos cabos de 

alimentação de cada canal, para evitar as correntes instáveis dos respectivos cabos que 

podem influenciar a performance da coil. 

A performance da coil foi avaliada através de S-parameters, mais especificamente através 

do coeficiente de reflexão (Sii), que indica a porção da energia que é reflectida quando ela é 

imposta no canal i, e através do coeficiente de transmissão (Sij), que indica que porção da 

energia imposta no canal i é transmitida e perdida para o canal j. Os resultados obtidos 

mostraram que os coeficientes de reflexão de todos os canais se encontravam abaixo de  

-30 dB, ou seja, na pior das hipóteses, apenas 0.1% da energia emitida para um canal é 

reflectida para trás, o que mostra que quase toda a energia é recebida pelos canais para 

produzir o campo de excitação   
 . Os coeficientes de transmissão variavam entre -16 dB a 

-25 dB, revelando que as perdas de energia de um canal para outro podem de ser até 2.5%, 

ou seja, a perda não é significativa.  

O factor Q também foi medido para verificar a performance da coil. A razão entre Q com 

load e Q sem load de todos os canais apresentou-se menor que 0.5. Este resultado mostra 

que o ruído vem maioritariamente do load e não do circuito da coil em si, o que é desejável, 

uma vez que nestas condições uma melhor razão sinal-ruído pode ser obtida. 

A intensidade e a fase dos campos de radiofrequência variam dentro do objecto conforme a 

sua forma, permitividade e condutividade eléctricas. Em campos maiores que 3.0 T, o 



iii 

 

comportamento das ondas electromagnéticas torna-se difícil de prever com métodos 

simples e quási-estáticos, tanto que é necessário recorrer à simulação completa de campos 

electromagnéticos. As simulações oferecem um conhecimento antecipado do 

comportamento de   
 , assim como da deposição da energia RF nos tecidos, que é mais 

elevada nos campos magnéticos ultra elevados, como no caso de 7.0 T. Deste modo, o 

sobreaquecimento dos tecidos pode ser previamente visualizada e evitada. 

Neste projecto, as simulações foram efectuadas com o software SEMCAD X que se baseia 

no método das diferenças finitas no domínio temporal (FDTD) para resolver as equações 

diferenciais de Maxwell.  

De forma a mostrar a credibilidade das simulações, uma simulação da coil com um fantoma 

foi efectuada de modo a obter mapas de   
 , usados para comparar os mapas de   

  obtidos 

experimentalmente. Como resultado, os mapas simulados e medidos apresentavam uma 

semelhança significativa em termos qualitativos. Ao nível quantitativo, estes apresentavam 

uma diferença de 21.5 ± 7.6% para os canais de protão e de 47.8 ± 9.2% para os canais de 

flúor, apesar das correcções de perdas de energia em hardware nas medições. A diferença 

quantitativa nos canais de protão pode dever-se a perdas extras desconhecidas no scanner. 

A significativa diferença presente nos canais de flúor pode ser explicada pelo facto dos 

mapas experimentais serem obtidos na frequência de protão e extrapolados através dos S-

parameters, uma vez que não existia nenhum fantoma que contivesse flúor no momento da 

experiência. Adicionalmente, os S-parameters foram adquiridos fora do scanner, sendo por 

isso apenas uma aproximação dos S-parameters reais durante as medições. Contudo, pode 

afirmar-se que a validação das simulações é credível pela significativa semelhança 

qualitativa dos mapas em todos os canais, e da semelhança quantitativa entre os canais de 

protão. 

Os valores de SAR médio de 10 g, obtidos por simulação para as configurações de fase 3 

utilizadas nos scans reais, foram encontrados como sendo 0.306 W/kg para a frequência de 

flúor (279.5 MHz) e 0.375 W/kg para a frequência de protão (297.0 MHz). Estes valores 

encontram-se muito abaixo do limite estabelecido pelas directrizes da IEC, 20.0 W/kg para 

as extremidades do corpo. É de notar também que, os valores de SAR obtidos pela 



iv 

 

simulação não têm em conta as perdas de energia existentes na realidade, por isso, num 

scan real, o valor de SAR não iria exceder os valores simulados. 

Os valores de T1 e T2 para o creme de NSAID com ácido flufenâmico a usar nas 

experiências in vivo foram encontrados através de espectroscopia, através da variação de 

TR para o T1 e de TE para o T2. Foi também elaborada uma curva de concentração, onde 

para cada quantidade de creme de NSAID existe a correspondente intensidade de sinal.  

As imagens de ressonância obtidas com a coil construída mostram um bom contraste e 

homogeneidade na área de interesse. A homogeneidade foi conseguida por uma sessão de 

  
  shimming in vivo. A resolução espacial foi de 0.7 × 0.7 mm

2
 no plano e 5 mm para a 

espessura de fatia para imagens de protão e, de 2 × 2 mm
2
 no plano e 5 mm para a 

espessura de fatia para imagens de flúor. 

Os estudos in vivo foram conduzidos em dois voluntários saudáveis, na ausência de 

voluntários com reumatóide artrite. Os voluntários aplicaram o creme que contém NSAID 

sobre o joelho. Foram efectuadas espectroscopias não-localizadas a intervalos regulares de 

modo a verificar a existência da alteração do sinal inicial que pudesse indicar a absorção do 

creme na pele. Os resultados, porém, não se mostraram conclusivos, uma vez que a 

espectroscopia efectuada abrangia as regiões no exterior e no interior do corpo. Foi 

efectuada, adicionalmente, uma espectroscopia localizada com o método SPECIAL dentro 

do joelho de um dos voluntários, após 172 minutos do primeiro scan, contudo nenhum sinal 

foi detectado. A inexistência do sinal pode dever-se à não penetração do creme na região 

onde o voxel SPECIAL foi colocado, ou contrariamente, ter ocorrido a penetração do 

creme mas numa quantidade demasiada baixa para poder ser detectada. 

Nos trabalhos futuros, devem-se ser incluídos outros métodos para detecção do creme de 

NSAID in vivo com a coil desenvolvida, como espectroscopias localizadas dentro e fora do 

joelho, com tempos mais longos de scan, e com pacientes que tenham reumatóide artrite e 

voluntários saudáveis, de modo a comparar a eficiência da absorção do medicamento. 

Palavras chave: MRI, campos magnéticos ultra elevados, RF coil, array coil de suferfície, 

RF coil de dual frequência, imagiologia de 
19

F, espectroscopia de 
19

F, simulações de 

campos EM, SAR, Artrite Reumatóide, NSAIDs.  



v 

 

ABSTRACT 

Topical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) have been introduced to treat 

rheumatoid arthritis condition in order to avoid side effects from its oral form. Although it 

is known that topical NSAIDs are able to penetrate the human skin, no human in vivo 

studies were carried out to show the penetration efficiency and the drug delivering path at 

the site of inflammation.   

In vivo drug tracking should be carried out by a non-invasive and effective method. A good 

candidate is fluorine (
19

F) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and spectroscopy (MRS), 

since MRI offers excellent tissue contrast and high spatial and temporal resolutions. The 

absence of fluorine in biological tissue makes it an ideal probe to track and quantify 

fluorine containing NSAIDs in vivo.  

In this project, a dedicated 
1
H/

19
F dual tuned surface coil with eight channels was 

constructed to register proton anatomical images and fluorine images/spectroscopy to track 

and quantify a fluorine containing NSAID ointment in human knee at 7.0 tesla. The 

constructed coil showed low reflection and transmission coefficients (&lt;-30 dB and&amp;lt;-16 dB 

respectively) and noise dominant Q ratio, which enounces SNR gain. 

Electromagnetic field (EMF) simulations were carried out to visualize RF field patterns and 

SAR values for safety. Comparison between simulated and measured   
  maps showed 

reasonable qualitative and quantitative agreement, validating the SAR simulations, which 

give an estimation of the deposited RF power in the tissue in a real MRI scan. 

In vivo 
19

F spectroscopy, aimed to observe and quantify the skin absorption of flufenamic 

acid contained NSAID, showed inconclusive results. The spectroscopy performed with a 

SPECIAL voxel placed inside the knee did not show any fluorine signal, either due to non-

absorption of the NSAID or the absorbed quantity was too low to be detected. Further 

improved in vivo experiments should be carried out with RA patients. 

Keywords: MRI, ultrahigh magnetic field, surface array RF coil, dual tuned RF coil, 
19

F 

imaging, 
19

F spectroscopy, EMF simulations, SAR, Rheumatoid Arthritis, NSAIDs. 



vi 

 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS   
 

This thesis would not have been possible without the help of many people and here I would 

like to express my gratitude.  

First of all, I would like to express my gratitude to Professor Thoralf Niendorf and Dr. 

Sonia Waiczies for the opportunity to work at Berlin Ultrahigh Field Facility (B.U.F.F.), 

Max-Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine (MDC), Berlin, Germany and especially for 

their encouragement, guidance and support. 

I would like to thank Dr. Helmar Waiczies, who have been closely supervising my work. I 

highly appreciate his guidance, support and patience through this ultrahigh magnetic 

imaging experience, from which I have learnt a lot. 

I’m very grateful to whole B.U.F.F. team which forms a very nice and cooperative work 

environment. A special thanks to Celal Özerdem, who has always been ready for my 

questions, to Andreas Gräßl, Matthias Dieringer and Lukas Winter for their help with many 

technical aspects of the coil. 

I would like to thank all the professors of the Institute of Biophysics and Biomedical 

Engineering of the Faculty of Sciences of the University of Lisbon for their dedication and 

encouragement, without them this experience abroad would not have been possible. A 

special thanks to Professor Alexandre Andrade for his support and supervision. 

I would like to thank my flat mates and also colleagues João Fernandes and João Periquito 

for their friendship, patience and joyful moments that we passed together in Berlin. I’m 

very grateful to Carolina Galvão who took the time to help me with my English. 

At last but not at least, I would like to thank my family and all my friends for all their 

encouragement, support and love. To my parents, Zhengrong Ji and Weifen Xia, my 

brother Pusheng Ji, and Tiago Silva for their love, encouragement and support in my 

studies and decisions, and everything else they have given me over the years.  

I dedicate this work to the memory of my grandfather Yongqing Ji, who taught me since 

little that the education is the best tool to achieve success.  



vii 

 

CONTENTS 
 

RESUMO ................................................................................................................................ i 

ABSTRACT ........................................................................................................................... v 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS .................................................................................................. vi 

LIST OF FIGURES ................................................................................................................ x 

LIST OF TABLES ............................................................................................................... xii 

ABBREVIATIONS AND SYMBOLS ............................................................................... xiii 

1. INTRODUCTION ........................................................................................................... 1 

1.1. Objective .............................................................................................................. 2 

2. BACKGROUND ............................................................................................................. 3 

2.1. Basics of Magnetic Resonance Imaging .................................................................. 3 

2.1.1. The Nuclear Spin .................................................................................................. 3 

2.1.2. Protons in a Static Magnetic Field ....................................................................... 5 

2.1.3. Magnetic Resonance Signal ................................................................................. 6 

2.1.4. Magnetic Resonance Imaging ............................................................................ 11 

2.1.5. Basic Pulse Sequences ....................................................................................... 14 

2.2. MRI at Ultrahigh Fields ......................................................................................... 18 

2.3. Fluorine (
19

F) imaging ........................................................................................... 20 

3. RADIOFREQUENCY (RF) COILS ............................................................................. 21 

3.1. RLC circuit ............................................................................................................ 22 

3.2. Tuning and Matching ............................................................................................. 22 

3.3. Decoupling ............................................................................................................. 23 

3.4. Cable Trap .............................................................................................................. 24 

3.5. Scattering-Parameters (S-Parameters) ................................................................... 25 

3.6. Quality factor ......................................................................................................... 27 

4. MATERIALS AND METHODS .................................................................................. 28 

4.1 Coil Construction ................................................................................................... 28 

4.1.1. Casing .................................................................................................................. 30 



viii 

 

4.1.2. Cable trap ............................................................................................................ 30 

4.2. Electromagnetic field (EMF) simulations .............................................................. 31 

4.2.1. Phantom simulation ............................................................................................ 33 

4.2.2. Human model simulation ................................................................................... 33 

4.3. RF Bench analysis ................................................................................................. 35 

4.3.1. Tuning, Matching and Decoupling..................................................................... 36 

4.3.2. Q factor measurement ........................................................................................ 36 

4.4. Measurements ........................................................................................................ 36 

4.4.1. Coil interface ...................................................................................................... 37 

4.4.2. B1
+
 mapping ........................................................................................................ 38 

4.4.3. Determination of T1 and T2 ................................................................................ 38 

4.4.4. Calibration curve ................................................................................................ 40 

4.4.5. In vivo Imaging................................................................................................... 40 

4.4.6. In vivo 
19

F Spectroscopy .................................................................................... 40 

5. RESULTS...................................................................................................................... 42 

5.1. Coil Layout ............................................................................................................ 42 

5.1.1. Cable traps .......................................................................................................... 43 

5.2. RF Bench Analysis ................................................................................................ 43 

5.2.1. S-Parameters....................................................................................................... 43 

5.2.2. Q-factor .............................................................................................................. 45 

5.3. Simulated and measured B1
+
 maps ........................................................................ 45 

5.4. SAR evaluation ...................................................................................................... 48 

5.5. T1 measurement ..................................................................................................... 50 

5.6. T2 measurement ..................................................................................................... 52 

5.7. Calibration Curve ................................................................................................... 53 

5.8. In vivo Imaging ...................................................................................................... 54 

5.8.1. B1
+
 Shimming ..................................................................................................... 54 

5.1.1. Proton and fluorine imaging ............................................................................... 56 



ix 

 

5.9. In vivo 
19

F Spectroscopy ........................................................................................ 56 

6. DISCUSSION ............................................................................................................... 58 

6.1. Coil performance ................................................................................................... 58 

6.2. B1
+
 mapping comparison ....................................................................................... 59 

6.3. SAR evaluation ...................................................................................................... 61 

6.4. T1, T2 and concentration curve............................................................................... 61 

6.5. In vivo imaging and 
19

F spectroscopy .................................................................... 61 

7. CONCLUSION ............................................................................................................. 63 

8. REFERENCES .............................................................................................................. 64 

 

 
 

 

  



x 

 

LIST OF FIGURES 

 

Figure 1 – The nuclear spin ................................................................................................... 3 

Figure 2 – The behavior of the nuclear spin in the absence and in the presence of an 

external magnetic field ....................................................................................... 5 

Figure 3 - Precession of a nuclear magnetic moment about an externally applied 

magnetic field ..................................................................................................... 6 

Figure 4 – Behavior of the net magnetization vector in the presence of B1+ field ............... 7 

Figure 5 – Spin-lattice and spin-spin relaxations. ................................................................. 8 

Figure 6 – T1 and T2 relaxation times  ................................................................................... 9 

Figure 7 – The signal processing chain in an NMR experiment ......................................... 10 

Figure 8 – Magnetic field gradients’ influence on main static field strength ...................... 11 

Figure 9 – An illustration of slice selection ......................................................................... 12 

Figure 10 – Spatial encoding: phase encoding and frequency enconding ........................... 13 

Figure 11 – K-space and correspondent reconstructed images by 2D Fourier transform ... 14 

Figure 12 – Free induction decay ........................................................................................ 15 

Figure 13 – T1 recovery curve by repeating 90º RF pulses. ................................................ 15 

Figure 14 – Spin echo sequence .......................................................................................... 16 

Figure 15 - Spin echo signal and exponential decay ........................................................... 16 

Figure 16 – Gradient echo sequence.................................................................................... 17 

Figure 17 – Effects of RF field inhomogeneities on MRI ................................................... 19 

Figure 18 – An RLC resonant circuit in series .................................................................... 22 

Figure 19 – Equivalent serial RLC circuit of an MRI coil with tuning-matching circuit ... 23 

Figure 20 – Element coupling and frequency shift ............................................................. 23 

Figure 21 – Decoupling capacitor CD. ................................................................................. 24 

Figure 22 – Coaxial cable – cut away view ......................................................................... 25 

Figure 23 – A two-port component with transmitted and reflected waves ai and bi ........... 25 

Figure 24 – S-parameters of a coil with 2 elements at 297 MHz ........................................ 26 

Figure 25 – 
1
H/

19
F dual tuned knee coil overview .............................................................. 28 

Figure 26 – Illustration of the anterior parts of coil ............................................................ 29 

Figure 27 – Illustration of the posterior part of the coil ...................................................... 29 

Figure 28 – Cable trap used in the coil ................................................................................ 30 



xi 

 

Figure 29 – Simulation steps ............................................................................................... 31 

Figure 30 – ADS circuit design environment ...................................................................... 32 

Figure 31 – ADS S-parameter visualization environment................................................... 32 

Figure 32 – The EMF simulation model of the phantom with the coil ............................... 33 

Figure 33 – Voxelized lower member of “Duke” with the coil........................................... 34 

Figure 34 – ZVT8 (Rhode &amp;amp; Schwarz GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG, Munich, Germany) .................. 35 

Figure 35 – 7.0 T whole-body scanner (Siemens Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany) ........... 36 

Figure 36 – Tx/Rx switch box ............................................................................................. 37 

Figure 37 – 1 to 4 power splitter ......................................................................................... 37 

Figure 38 – Coil interface box specialized for 1H/19F dual tuned knee coil ...................... 37 

Figure 39 – 
19

F GRE image of a sample filled with NSAID ointment ................................ 39 

Figure 40 – SPECIAL voxel placement inside the knee ..................................................... 41 

Figure 41 – Coil elements numbering ................................................................................. 42 

Figure 42 – PCB circuit and capacitors of the coil. ............................................................. 42 

Figure 43 – Placement of the coil in its casing on a volunteer ............................................ 42 

Figure 44 – Print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for left anterior part of 

the coil .............................................................................................................. 44 

Figure 45 – Print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for left anterior part of 

the coil .............................................................................................................. 44 

Figure 46 – Print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for right anterior part 

of the coil .......................................................................................................... 45 

Figure 47 – Relative B1 map of simulation and measurement............................................ 46 

Figure 48 – 10 g averaged SAR distribution at 279.5 MHz for phase setting 3 ................. 49 

Figure 49 - 10 g averaged SAR distribution at 297.0 MHz for phase setting 3 .................. 50 

Figure 50 – Fitted T1 recovery curve from acquired data.................................................... 51 

Figure 51 – Fitted T2 recovery curve from acquired data ................................................... 53 

Figure 52 – Concentration curves for 100% NSAID ointment and for 50% NSAID 

ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment ............................................................ 54 

Figure 53 – GRE images of a knee using different phase setting ........................................ 55 

Figure 54 – Destructive interference of RF field and its correction .................................... 55 

Figure 55 – High resolution proton and fluorine images..................................................... 56 

Figure 56 – In vivo spectroscopy graphic results ................................................................ 57 

Figure 57 – B1
+
 map of channel 1 and maximum value correction. .................................... 60 

  



xii 

 

LIST OF TABLES 

 

Table 1 – Spin, gyromagnetic ratio, isotopic composition and abundance in biological 

tissues of some elements of mr interest .............................................................. 4 

Table 2 – RF wavelength in air and in water for proton at different field strengths ........... 18 

Table 3 – ICE and FDA guidelines for SAR and heating in human MRI studies ............... 19 

Table 4 – Capacitors used for cable traps ............................................................................ 43 

Table 5 – Sii and Sij of the coil elements ............................................................................. 43 

Table 6 – Ql, Qul and Ql/Qul of each coil channels. ............................................................. 45 

Table 7 – Correction factors of measured B1
+
 maps ........................................................... 47 

Table 8 – Simulated and measured b1
+ 

values and their comparison. ................................. 48 

Table 9 – Peak averaged SAR at 279.5 MHz and 297.0 MHz ............................................ 48 

Table 10 – The phase and amplitude of worst case SAR at 
19

F and 
1
H frequencies ........... 49 

Table 11 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies of 100% NSAID ointment sample and 

50% NSAID ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment sample at different 

TRs. ................................................................................................................... 51 

Table 12 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies of 100% NSAID ointment sample and 

50% NSAID ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment sample at different 

TEs. ................................................................................................................... 52 

Table 13 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies and amount of flufenamic acid present 

at different SPECIAL voxel sizes for 100% NSAID ointment sample ............ 53 

Table 14 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies and amount of flufenamic acid present 

at different special voxel sizes for 50% nsaid ointment + 50% fluorine free 

ointment sample ................................................................................................ 53 

Table 15 – Phase settings for B1
+
 homogeneity experiment. .............................................. 54 

Table 16 – In vivo 
19

F spectroscopy of applied fluorine containing topical NSAID 

ointment. ........................................................................................................... 57 

 

 

  



xiii 

 

ABBREVIATIONS AND SYMBOLS 

  – Gyromagnetic ratio 

 ??  – Magnetic  moment 

? – frequency (rads/s), usually Larmor 
frequency 

1
H – Proton  

19
F – Fluorine  

ADS – Advanced Design System 

B0 – External static magnetic field  

  
  – Excitation radio frequency field 

EMF – Electromagnetic Field 

FDA – Food and Drug Administration 

FID – Free Induction Decay 

FOV – Field of View 

FWHM – Full Width at Half Maximum 

GRE – Gradient Recalled Echo 

IEC – International Electrotechnical 

Commission 

 ???  – Net magnetization  

 ???   – Thermal-equilibrium net 
magnetization 

 ???    – Transversal component of net 

magnetization  

 ???   – Longitudinal component of net 
magnetization  

MRI – Magnetic Resonance Imaging 

MRS – Magnetic Resonance 

Spectroscopy 

NMR – Nuclear Magnetic Resonance 

NSAID – Non-Steroidal Anti-

Inflammatory Drug 

PCB – Printable Circuit Board 

RA – Rheumatoid Arthritis 

RF – Radio Frequency 

ROI – Region of Interest 

Rx – Receive  

SAR – Specific Absorption Rate 

SE – Spin Echo 

Sii – Reflection coefficient of S-parameter 

Sij - Transmission coefficient of S-

parameter 

SNR – Signal to Noise Ratio 

SPECIAL – SPin ECho full Intensity 

Acquired Localized 

T – Tesla  

Tx – Trasnmit  

UHF – Ultra High Field 

VNA – Vector Network Analyzer 

 



1 

 

1. INTRODUCTION 
 

Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is an autoimmune disease that causes long-term joints and 

surrounding tissues inflammation. It affects usually joints on both sides of the body equally. 

Wrists, fingers, knees, feet, and ankles are the most commonly affected, though it can also 

affect another body parts such as eyes, mouth and lungs [1].  

RA treatment includes non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), which are known 

for their anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antipyretic and antithrombotic effects [2]. Despite 

their beneficial proprieties for RA, conventional oral form of NSAIDs present side effects 

such as irritation and bleeding of gastrointestinal mucosa, heart burn and nausea, thus  

topical NSAIDs were introduced as an alternative to avoid these side effects and also to 

minimize the overall required dosage [3].  

However, to be effective, topical NSAIDs have to penetrate the skin and reach the joints in 

a sufficient concentration. Although many studies have shown overall therapeutic active 

effects of topical NSAIDs [4–7] and effective skin penetration [8,9] it is still not shown 

how nor how much of the drug reaches the site of inflammation to exert their therapeutic 

effect. This in vivo drug tracking should be carried out by a non-invasive and effective 

method, and fluorine (
19

F) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and spectroscopy (MRS) are 

of major interest. 

MRI provides an excellent tissue contrast and high spatial and temporal resolutions, and the 

fluorine with a high gyromagnetic ratio and high signal sensitivity, about 83% of 

hydrogen’s; together with its absence background in biological tissue [10] form an ideal 

probe to track and quantify NSAIDs in vivo. MRI at ultrahigh fields (7.0 T) benefits from 

the increased signal to noise ratio (SNR) which can be translated into higher spatial and 

temporal resolutions [11], which is of high interest of 
19

F MRI and MRS due to low 

concentration of fluorine nuclei in region of interest [12].  

But on the other hand, higher fields lead to more   
  excitation field inhomogeneities and to 

more radio frequency (RF) power absorption, which can cause undesirable tissue heating 

[13]. RF surface array coils with an optimum design and refined RF parameters can get use 



2 

 

of the high SNR of the ultrahigh magnetic fields and at same time reduces the   
  non-

homogeneities and avoid high RF power absorption in order to stay within the limits of 

specific absorption rate (SAR). This limits are established by authority entities such as 

Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and International Electrotechnical Commission 

(IEC), concerning patient safety [14,15].  

Typical approach for 
19

F studies combines proton images containing anatomical 

information and fluorine images that contain study aimed information. This can be 

performed either by a single tuned RF coil, which can have a sufficient bandwidth to 

accommodate both nuclei or a smaller bandwidth that needs to be constantly tuned and 

matched between 
1
H and 

19
F frequencies, or by a dual tuned RF coil tuned and matched to 

both frequencies. Dual tuned RF coils are preferred rather than single tuned coils, since a 

large bandwidth needed to cover both frequencies of the later ones leads to significant noise 

increase and signal sensitivity drop, or in the other case, the constant manipulation between 

frequencies can change image registration between one nuclei scan to the other, besides, the 

sensitivity profile also varies from one frequency to the other [16]. 

 

1.1. Objective 
 

The purpose of the present thesis is to develop a dual tuned array coil for proton and 

fluorine magnetic resonance imaging and spectroscopy at 7.0 T for human knee. The 

developed coil will be used to register 
1
H anatomical images and 

19
F images and 

spectroscopy to track and quantify a fluorine containing NSAID ointment (flufenamic acid 

(2-{[3-(Trifluoromethyl) phenyl]amino}benzoic acid) in vivo. 

 

  



3 

 

2. BACKGROUND 

2.1. Basics of Magnetic Resonance Imaging 
 

Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is a relatively recent medical imaging modality as its 

first practical medical application was performed in 1973 [17]. It has shown to be a 

powerful imaging modality due to its flexibility and sensitivity to a wide range of tissue 

properties and most importantly to the noninvasive nature of the magnetic fields. MRI is 

based on the principle of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) [18], which is explained 

below.  

 

2.1.1. The Nuclear Spin 
 

Nuclear Magnetic resonance is based upon the interaction between an applied external 

magnetic field and atoms that possess nuclear magnetic moment, or more generally referred 

as nuclear spin [15].   

Protons and neutrons of nucleus possess intrinsic angular momentum as they rotate around 

an axis at constant rate. In classical-physics view, protons and neutrons can be regarded as 

rotating mass with charge, therefore giving rise to a magnetic moment which behaves like 

small magnets (Figure 1). A neutron has no net charge but it is composed of charged 

particles (two down-Quarks and one up-Quark) possessing an intrinsic spin of 1/2 and 

therefore belongs to the group of Fermions, like the protons [19,20]. 

                                 
 
Figure 1 - A: A rotating proton or neutron can classically be represented with a dipole magnetic 

field. B: The magnetic moment vector indicates direction and magnitude of the magnetic field 

induced by a spinning proton or neutron and behaves like a small magnet. Adapted from [21]. 



4 

 

Pairing phenomenon occurs within the nucleus, where the magnetic moments of proton-

proton or neutron-neutron pairs tend to align in opposition canceling each other. Thus, 

nuclear spin can be zero if the nucleus has an even number of protons and neutrons which 

pair up, resulting in a zero net magnetic moment. Such nucleus does not interact with an 

external magnetic field. On the other hand, nuclear spin can be multiples of 1/2 if a nucleus 

has an odd number of protons or neutrons, in this case there are unpaired protons or 

neutrons that produce a non-zero net magnetic moment, and therefore  this nucleus will 

interact with an external field [19,21,22]. Almost all atoms have at least one naturally 

occurring isotope that possesses spin, therefore nearly every element is examinable in MRI 

[15].  

An important physical quantity for MRI is the ratio of the magnetic moment to the angular 

momentum, called gyromagnetic ratio ( ) [19]. Table 1 shows information about spin, 

gyromagnetic ratio, isotropic composition and abundance in biological tissues of some 

selected elements of the MRI interest. It is also notable that hydrogen has a very high 

concentration in the body, due to its presence in water, fat and other organic molecules, and 

a relatively high gyromagnetic ratio, which makes these nuclei, composed only by a single 

proton, the source of signal for nearly all clinical MRI exams. This fact leads to the general 

description of MRI effects made with term “proton” (also used in the next sections of this 

work), although these effects are same for other nuclei [19].  

Element Symbol Net Spin 
  

(MHz/T) 

Natural 

abundance 

Biological 

abundance 

Hydrogen 

1
H ½ 42.58 0.99985 

0.63 
2
H 1 6.54 0.00015 

Fluorine 
19

F ½ 40.08 1 0.00001 

Carbon 

13
C ½ 10.71 0.11 

0.094 
12

C 0 0 0.89 

Sodium 
23

Na 3/2 11.27 1 0.00041 

Phosphorus 
31

P ½ 17.25 1 0.0024 

Table 1 - Spin, gyromagnetic ratio ( ), isotopic composition and abundance in biological tissues of 

some elements of MR interest. Adapted from [22,23]. 



5 

 

2.1.2. Protons in a Static Magnetic Field 
 

Without an external magnetic field, protons spins in random directions, which results in a 

null net magnetic moment, also called net magnetization  ??? , illustrated in Figure 2 A. On 

the other hand, when the protons are placed inside a static magnetic field  ??  , they 

experience two quantized energy states (2 × spin + 1) with energy difference of   , which 

is proportional to external magnetic strength. Protons in the lower energy level, called spin 

up, align parallel to  ??   (conventionally set as z direction) and protons in the higher energy 

level, called spin down, align antiparallel to  ??  , as shown in Figure 2 B.  At thermal 

equilibrium state a number of protons in higher energy state transits to lower energy state 

by exchanging energy with their surroundings, and vice versa, but the mean number of 

protons in each energy state remains constant. The parallel alignment cancels out the 

antiparallel alignment, and as there are more protons in the lower energy state than in the 

higher energy state, the excess of parallel alignment results in a measurable net 

magnetization vector  ???   aligned with  ??   which is called thermal-equilibrium magnitization 

[19,21].  ???   increases proportionally with   , and the MRI signal is directly proportional to 

 ???  . This increase of signal with increase of    explains one of the motivations for 

development of higher magnetic field systems [19]. 

 

                     

Figure 2 – A: in absence of an external magnetic field, nuclei spins are in random directions, 

resulting in a zero net magnetization.  B: in presence of an external magnetic field  ??  , protons 

align parallel (lower energy state) or antiparallel (higher energy state) to the  ??  , the excess of 

parallel alignment results in a measurable net magnetization. Adapted from [21]. 

 

 ???   

 ???    



6 

 

Besides magnetic alignment, an external magnetic field exerts a torque on the magnetic 

moment causing the proton to precess around z direction, as shown in Figure 3. The 

frequency of precession, also known as the Larmor frequency (?0), is proportional to the 

strength of  ??   and is influenced by gyromagnetic ratio of the element. It is described by 

Larmor equation (Eq. 1) [15,19]: 

 

        Eq. 1 

 

   

 
Figure 3 - Precession of a nuclear magnetic moment ( ?? ) about an externally applied magnetic field 

with  ??   with angular frequency of ?0 [19]. 

 

2.1.3. Magnetic Resonance Signal 
 

Excitation of the spins 

At equilibrium, the longitudinal magnetization (aligned with  ??  ) of  ???   is maximal and is 

denoted as  ???  . However, compared to the strength of   ???? ,  ???   (in order of ?T) is too small, 

making it impossible to be directly detected. Therefore, it is necessary to tip  ???   into the 

transversal xy plane in order to gain a measurable signal [21]. 

To tip the thermal-equilibrium magnetization vector  ???  , it is necessary to disturb the 

equilibrium state of the protons. This can be done by an additional time-varying magnetic 

field perpendicular to  ??  , called  ??  , through application of a radiofrequency (RF) excitation 

pulse at Larmor frequency on a transmit (Tx) RF coil. The generated  ??   consists of two 



7 

 

circular polarized fields:  ??  
 , which can excite the spin as it has the same sense of rotation 

as the precessing spins, and  ??  
 , which has an opposite direction of rotation and does not 

contribute for excitation, however it is decisive for signal reception.  

Now  ???  (called  ???  instead of  ???   once the system is no longer in equilibrium state) has to 

precess about  ??   while continuing to precess at the same time about  ??  , as result, in a 

stationary frame (x y z)  ???  will spiral towards xy plane as shown in Figure 4 A. In a rotating 

frame (xrot yrot zrot), where zrot (parallel to  ??  ) is the axis of rotation, while xrot and yrot axes 

rotates at the Larmor frequency,  ???  will tip at an angle, the flip angle ?, about xrot and a 

transversal component of net magnetization  ??? ,  ???   , is originated, as can be observed in 

Figure 4 B [15,24].  

                          

Figure 4 – Behavior of the net magnetization vector  ???  in presence of a circular polarized and 

perpendicular to  ??   magnetic field   ??   in A) a stationery frame and on B) a rotational frame. [19] 

 

The flip angle ? depends on the gyromagnetic ratio ( ), the strength of  ??   and on the 

duration   of the RF field, as described by the following equation [19]: 

        Eq. 2 
 

By an appropriate choice of    and   any flip angle ? can be obtained. A 90º flip angle is 

caused by a 90º pulse, also called an excitation pulse, and moves the net magnetization 

from longitudinal axis into transverse plane. The RF pulse also induces phase coherence to 

all individual spins, that is why the net magnetization vector can have a transverse 

component in non-equilibrium conditions [17]. 

 

 



8 

 

Relaxation 

When the RF pulse is turned off,  ??   vanishes and the relaxation occurs as the protons 

returns to equilibrium state. This process is called free induction decay (FID).  The 

relaxation can be divided into spin-lattice relaxation and spin-spin relaxation. In the first 

one, the longitudinal component of  ???  becomes  ???   again, and in the latter one, the 

transverse component of  ???  returns to zero [17], as shown in Figure 5. 

 
Figure 5 – schematic overview of free induction decay process. The RF pulse creates a net 

transverse magnetization due to energy absorption and phase coherence. After RF pulse, spin-

lattice and spin-spin relaxations occur [17]. 

 

Spin-lattice relaxation  

In the absence of  ??  , the previous excited protons, in order to return to the lowest energy 

state, tends to re-align their magnetic moment to  ??  . Therefore the longitudinal component 

of  ???  becomes maximum again, thus the spin-lattice relaxation is also called longitudinal 

relaxation. The energy difference is transferred to the lattice of nearby atoms and is 

transformed into heat. The process of this relaxation can be described by follow equation. 



9 

 

   ( )    (   )     
        (   

     ) Eq. 3 

where   ( ) is the longitudinal component of net magnetization vector  ??? ( ),   (  

 )     is the value of longitudinal component immediately after RF pulse and    is the 

spin-lattice relaxation time – the time taken for the net magnetization to recover to 63% of 

   or   (   
  )  – which differs from tissue to tissue and increases with the strength of 

 ??   [11,17]. 

 

Spin-spin relaxation  

Physically, each spin vector experiences a slightly different magnetic field because of the 

different chemical environment. As a result of these spin–spin interactions, the spins rotate 

at slightly differing angular frequencies, which results in a loss of the phase coherence and 

a decrease of the transverse component    ( ). This spin-spin relaxation, also called 

transversal relaxation, is described by 

    ( )     (   )     
      Eq. 4 

where    (   )     is the value of the transverse component immediately after the RF 

pulse, and     –  the spin-spin relaxation time – takes place when    ( ) has decayed to 37%  

of its original value or    (   ) 
   and it depends considerably on the tissue.  In this 

mechanism of dephasing, no energy is lost, but since it also includes the spin-lattice 

interaction related to   ,    has to be shorter than   , and it is rather independent of    

[11,17]. 

   
Figure 6 – A: The longitudinal relaxation and relaxation time T1. B: The transversal relaxation 

and relaxation time T2. [8] 

      

A B 



10 

 

The longitudinal and transversal relaxations are illustrated in Figure 6, with their 

correspondent relaxation times. 

There is an additional dephasing caused by  ??   inhomogeneities which contributes to an 

even faster signal decay. This type of decay occurs with the time constant T2
*
, typically 

shorter than T2 [20]. 

 

Signal reception 

 

By placing a receive (Rx) RF coil near to the sample, the precessing transversal 

magnetization     ( ) will induce an alternating voltage at the ends of the loop due to 

Faraday's Law of induction. The intensity of the detected signal is connected to the 

magnetic field of the loop via the principle of reciprocity [25,26]. 

After its detection, the signal is first amplified and then mixed with a frequency ?, which 

slightly differs from Larmor frequency. After the demodulation, the signal is sampled by an 

Analogue-Digital-Converter (ADC) and finally transferred to the computer for post-

processing, as illustrated in Figure 7 [18]. 

 

 
 

Figure 7 – Block diagram of the signal processing chain in an NMR experiment with PA being the 

power amplifier, M the mixer for demodulation and ADC the Analogue-Digital-Converter [18]. 

 

 

R
x
 



11 

 

2.1.4. Magnetic Resonance Imaging 
 

Magnetic resonance imaging is based on determination of spatial location of NMR signals 

to create an image. This is possible by introduction of magnetic field gradients that produce 

a small variation on the strength of the main magnetic field  ??   [15]. 

 

Magnetic Field Gradients 

Magnetic field gradients consist of three magnetic fields that add or subtract a small amount 

of field strength from the main static magnetic field  ??  , linearly proportional to the distance 

from the isocenter in x, y and z direction. This spatial variation of the strength of  ??   results 

on different Larmor frequencies on protons located at different positions along the applied 

gradient in a known way, as shown in Figure 8 [19]. 

 

 

Figure 8 – Total magnetic field strength along position when a magnetic gradient field is applied to 

the main static field. This variation causes protons in different positions to spin at different but 

known Larmor frequencies [21]. 

 

Slice Selection 

The first step to acquire a MRI image is the slice selection. The slice-select gradient (GSS) 

creates a linear correspondence between the Larmor frequency and the position, a desired 

slice can be obtained by applying an RF pulse with selected center frequency (? ), thus, 

only the protons in the position corresponded to center frequency (  ), called slice position, 

can be excited, as shown in Figure 9 [19]. 



12 

 

 

Figure 9 – An illustration of slice selection [19]. 

 

Spatial encoding 

 

After the slice selection, e.g., in z direction, all the protons within the slice precess at same 

frequency. To obtain an image from it, it is necessary to proceed spatial encoding. Spatial 

encoding comprises two steps, phase encoding and frequency encoding [20,24]. 

For phase encoding, a gradient in y direction is switched on immediately after the RF pulse 

of the slice selection and before the signal acquisition. This gradient modifies the Larmor 

frequency of the protons along y direction (Figure 10 A). As result, the protons in a higher 

field strength gain phase relative to the protons in a lower field strength. In this way, each 

line of protons within the slice can be identified by its unique phase.  



13 

 

For frequency encoding, a frequency-enconding gradient is applied in x direction during 

acquisition time. This gradient causes different Larmor frequencies of the protons along x-

axis, thus each column of protons within the slice can be characterized by its specific 

frequency (Figure 10 B).  

In this way, each volume element (voxel) of the slice will have unique frequency and phase 

allowing its spatial identification. 

 

      
 

Figure 10 – Spatial encoding. A: Phase encoding – a y-gradient causes unique phase shifts within 

lines of the selected slice. B: Frequency enconding – an x-gradient causes specific Larmor 

frequencies within columns of the selected slice. [20] 

 

 

K-space  
 

K-space is where the collected encoded data from the MR signals are stored, corresponding 

to the inverse Fourier transform of the image space. It has two axes, the horizontal axis kx 

stores the frequency information, and the vertical axis ky stores the information about the 

phase. Each k-space line corresponds to one measurement and it is acquired for each phase-

encoding step. An MR image is created from raw data by application of 2D Fourier 

transform after the scan is over and k-space is filled.  

K-space lines do not correspond to the resulting image lines. Rather, the data from center of 

k-space mainly determines contrast in the image while the outer lines primarily contain 

spatial information (Figure 11). [20] 

A B 



14 

 

 

       
Figure 11 – K-space and correspondent images by 2D Fourier transform (FT) of k-space. A: 

reconstruction from full k-space, B: reconstruction from only the centre of k-space results in an 

image with good contraste but lacking in detail, C: reconstruction from only the edges of k-space 

results in an image where only the edges and detail of the imaged object. [15] 

 

2.1.5. Basic Pulse Sequences 
 

A pulse sequence is a set of RF pulses applied to a sample to produce a specific form of 

NMR signal [22]. 

 

One pulse sequence 

 

A single 90º RF pulse is applied uniformly to the sample in an associated static magnetic 

field and the net magnetization is tipped into the transverse plane. After the pulse, as the 

spins begin to realign themselves and return to equilibrium orientation in z-direction, the 

net magnetization begins to precess freely about  ??  , emitting energy. This energy is 

captured, resulting in an MR signal known as free induction decay (FID). The initial 

K-space 

Image 

      2D-FT 2D-FT 2D-FT 

A B C 



15 

 

magnitude of FID signal depends on the value of    prior to the 90º RF pulse. The FID 

decays with time as relaxation occurs [15].  

               
 

Figure 12 – Free induction decay. A: oscillating FID recorded within stationary frame of 

reference. B: non-oscillating FID recorded within rotating frame of reference. [24] 

 

The FID experiment is used in MR spectroscopy where different nuclei with different 

Larmor frequencies can be differentiated within a sample [18]. 

 

 

Figure 13 – T1 recovery curve by repeating 90º RF pulses [21]. 

 



16 

 

Additionally, repeated 90º pulses can be conducted to determine T1 time. The initial 90º 

pulse, which takes the    to zero, is followed by a recovery time and then a second 90º 

pulse is applied to examine the longitudinal recovery by displacing it into the transverse 

plane. By repeating the sequence with different repetition times (TR) a T1 recovery curve – 

  (   
      ) – can be determined and T1 value can be estimated [18,21], as shown in 

Figure 13. 

 

Spin Echo (SE) sequence 
 

In spin echo sequence, a 90º RF pulse is first applied to rotate the net magnetization into the  

transversal plane. After this pulse, dephasing occurs as the precessing of some spins are 

faster than others due to  ??   inhomogeneities. Faster spins acquire positive phase (running 

clockwise), while slower ones lag behind and acquire negative phase (running 

counterclockwise). Dephasing occurs during the first half echo time (TE), then a 180º RF 

pulse is delivered to reverse or refocus the spins. As consequence the spins that were ahead 

before are now behind and vice versa, only the spins that are now behind will catch up as 

their respective speeds remain the same. Thus, after second half TE all spins will meet once 

again in phase forming the echo signal [20,24], Figure 14. 

 

 

 

   

 

Figure 14 – Spin echo sequence [17]. Figure 15 - Spin echo signal 

and exponential decay [17]. 



17 

 

The maximal echo amplitude depends on T2 and not in T2
*
 since spin echo only affects 

dephasing caused by field inhomogeneities and has no effect on spin-spin interaction 

dephasing, Figure 15. Therefore, an exponential decay curve   ( 
      ) can be 

determined by multiple experiments at different echo times, and T2 can be estimated [24]. 

 

Gradient Recalled Echo (GRE) sequence 

In gradient recalled echo sequences, or simply gradient echo, the echo is produced by 

magnetic field gradients rather than pairs of RF pulses. This is done by first applying a 

frequency-encoding gradient with negative polarity to induce dephasing of precessing spins 

and then the gradient is reversed and the spins rephase forming a gradient echo (Figure 16). 

Since gradient echoes do not need 180º refocusing pulse, very short repetition times (TR) 

can be achieved. The repetition time is determinant in overall scan time of most sequences 

which makes GRE sequence much faster than spin echo sequence [20]. Another advantage 

of GRE by not using a 180º pulse is that less total RF power is applied to the patient and 

thus less total RF energy is deposited within the tissue [15]. 

 

 

Figure 16 – Gradient echo sequence [20].  



18 

 

2.2. MRI at Ultrahigh Fields  

 
A continuous increasing of MRI field strength can be observed alongside its development. 

More and more 3.0 T high field systems have been placed in clinical use beside 1.5 T 

conventional systems, and ultrahigh field (4 – 9.4 T) systems have been installed at a 

number of research sites for human studies [27]. One of the reasons for the rise of field 

strength is the increasing difference between spin up and spin down population with field 

strength. This leads to a higher signal, and thus, a higher signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) can be 

obtained [13]. A higher SNR can be traded for increasing spatial resolution or for 

decreasing imaging time [11].  

Despite increased SNR at ultrahigh field (UHF) systems, several drawbacks are present. An 

increased    inhomogeneities due to magnetic susceptibility differences between air and 

tissue [28] causes varying precession frequencies of the spins, which diminishes a 

homogeneous excitation and leads to a faster dephasing of the spins resulting in a shorter 

T2
*
 [13]. However,    inhomogeneities can be reduced by    shimming.  

The Larmor frequency of the RF field (  
 ) applied, increases with the field strength, and 

higher the frequency shorter becomes the RF wavelength (Table 2). At 7.0 T, with 

frequencies near 300 MHz, the RF wavelength for protons in water is about 11cm, which 

leads regionally to negative interferences of superimposed RF waves. This creates 

inhomogeneities of the RF field in the body, which results in signal drop off in MR images, 

Figure 17 [13]. This constrain can be overcame by using surface array coils, by regulating 

the amplitude and the phase of each array channel [29]. 

 

Field 

strength 

Proton wavelength 

in air (cm) 

Proton wavelength 

in water (cm) 

1.5 T 470 52 

3.0 T 235 26 

7.0 T 100 11 

 

Table 2 – RF wavelength in air and in water for proton at different field strengths [13]. 



19 

 

 

Figure 17 – A: Effects of RF field inhomogeneities on MRI. B: MRI with corrected RF field 

inhomogeneities. [30] 

 

RF power deposition is another concern when referring to ultrahigh fields, as the RF field 

does not only affect the orientation of the net magnetization but also interacts with ions and 

molecules in the tissue [13]. The absorbed energy results in temperature rise that is higher 

for higher frequencies [13]. Thus, at UHF the risk of tissue heating and burning are 

increased. To avoid excessive tissue heating, regulatory organizations, such as Food and 

Drug Administration (FDA) and International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC), restricts 

the maximum input power of RF field in order to not exceed the specific absorption rate 

(SAR) limit (Table 3) [15,31]. The evaluation of SAR values is an important procedure at 

UHF MRI to assure patient safety [31].  

 

Limit 
Whole-Body 

Average 

Heat 

Average 

Head, Trunk 

Local SAR 

Extremities 

Local SAR 

IEC (6-minute average) 
    

Normal (all patients) 2 W/kg (0.5°C) 3.2 W/kg 10 W/kg 20 W/kg 

First level (supervised) 4 W/kg (1°C) 3.2 W/kg 10 W/kg 20 W/kg 

Second level (IRB approval) 4 W/kg (&gt;1°C) &gt;3.2 W/kg &gt;10 W/kg &gt;20 W/kg 

Localized heating limit 39°C in 10 g 38°C in 10 g 
 

40°C in 10 g 

FDA 
4 W/kg for 

  15 min 

3 W/kg for 

10 min 

8 W/kg in 1g 

for 10 min 

12 W/kg in 1g 

for 5 min 

Table 3 –International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC 60601-2-33:2010) and Food and US 

Drug Administration (FDA) guidelines on SAR and heating in human MRI studies. [32]  

A B 



20 

 

2.3. Fluorine (19F) imaging 
 

The feasibility of 
19

F MRI was first demonstrated by Holland et al. [10] four years after the 

development of 
1
H MRI. 

19
F has 100% natural abundance, a spin of 1/2, and a 

gyromagnetic ratio of 40.08 MHz/T (see Table 1) and 83% of the sensitivity of 
1
H.  

The use of 
19

F MRI also benefits from the similarity of gyromagnetic ratios of 
19

F and 
1
H 

(differs about 6%) which allows the use of the same equipment for both nuclei. The 

absence of 
19

F background in biological tissue (trace amounts of 
19

F present in teeth and 

bones are negligible) [10] makes this nuclei a good probe to assess the structure, function 

and molecular display of various diseases [12]. 

The 
19

F MRI was usually performed at relatively low spatial (millimeters) and temporal 

(minutes to hours) resolution because of low concentration of 
19

F atoms in region of 

interest, though, these limitations can be overcame by the increased SNR at higher field 

strength (e.g., 7T) and dedicated RF coils [12].  

 

  



21 

 

3. RADIOFREQUENCY (RF) COILS  

 
As referred before, RF coils are used to excite the spins in order to produce a measurable 

transversal signal (in transmission (Tx) mode) and to receive this signal (in receive (Rx) 

mode). An RF coil can be characterized as transmit only, receive only or both transmit and 

receive (transceiver Tx/Rx) [33].  

There are two types of RF coils, volume coil and surface coil. Volume coils surround either 

the whole body or a specific part of a body and are often carried out as birdcage coils. They 

consist of wires arranged like rungs of a birdcage along the z-axis of the scanner. Due to 

their predetermined structure, it is not possible to position the coil to an arbitrarily position 

on the patient and hence the typical applications of birdcage coils are the body coil, a head 

coil or extremity coils These coils have the capability to generate a homogenous   
  field 

over a large volume within the coil, however in higher magnetic fields the volume coils 

have some   
  homogeneity constraints. [21] 

Surface RF coils are RF coils placed directly on surface of the sample, which can be single 

or multiple turns of wire. This type of RF coil has an increased signal to noise ratio (SNR) 

due to its very close placement on the patient, and as it generally comprises a smaller 

imaging volume, less noise is present, since the major source of noise is usually the tissue. 

One drawback of this type of coils is its limited penetration depth, possible   
  

inhomogeneities and a reduced field-of-view (FOV) (the imaged area is more or less the 

size of the coil) [11,18]. 

A way to overcome reduced FOV is the application of a coil array, which consists of 

numerous single elements placed near each other. Therefore, the FOV can be increased and 

simultaneously benefits from the good SNR of surface coils [14]. Coil arrays can also  be 

used to compensate for   
  inhomogeneities by adapting the amplitude and phase of each 

transmitter independently to reduce the negative interferences of the RF waves [34]. These 

advantages made surface array coils preferred RF coils for UHF use, rather than volume 

coils. 

The next sections describe general aspects of a surface coil. 



22 

 

3.1. RLC circuit  
 

A simple loop surface coil can be described as a resonant RLC-circuit. This consists of 

inductance L, capacity C and resistance R representing the electrical losses, as illustrated in 

Figure 18. When connected to an alternating power source, the electrical energy is stored 

periodically within the magnetic field of the inductance or the electrical field of the 

capacitance. The resonant frequency of the RLC circuit is [14] 

 
  

 

  ?  
 Eq. 5 

 

 
Figure 18 – An RLC resonant circuit in series [35]. 

 

When building RF surface coils for MRI, the inductance is determined by the geometry of 

the copper conductors. Therefore, the resonance frequency can only be changed by 

adjusting the value of the capacitors within the circuit. Inserting multiple capacitors has 

another purpose. As the wavelength at ultrahigh fields approaches the length of the 

conductors, there would be sites with no signal due to the zero phase of the sinusoidal 

wave. By inserting capacitors, they partition the RF coil, keeping the conductors short 

compared to the wavelength avoiding the zero phases. But each inserted capacitor increases 

the total loss within the RF coil and thus worsens the RF coils performance. By choosing a 

suitable number of capacitors, both effects can be balanced [36]. 

3.2. Tuning and Matching 

The resonant circuit described previously needs to be tuned to the Larmor frequency of the 

protons in order to successfully excite them. Therefore, a tuning capacitor Ct is inserted in 



23 

 

the circuit. On the other hand the resonant circuit also needs to be matched to the 

impedance of the MR scanner and the coaxial cables, which is typically 50 ?, in order to 

achieve optimal signal transfer from the power source to the RF coil avoiding reflections 

that occur when the impedances differ. The matching can be handled by adding a matching 

capacitor Cm to the circuit. The Figure 19 shows an RLC circuit with additional tuning and 

matching capacitors [14]. 

 

 
 

Figure 19 – Equivalent serial RLC circuit of an MRI coil with tuning-matching circuit [35]. 

 

3.3. Decoupling 

When two loops are tuned to the same resonant frequency and placed near each other, their 

mutual inductance causes the resonances to split as shown in Figure 20. This results in a 

loss of sensitivity of the two coils. Therefore the neighboring elements have to be 

decoupled [34]. 

 

Figure 20 – Element coupling and frequency shift [34]. 



24 

 

 

One of the decoupling methods is the overlap decoupling. It can be performed by moving 

two neighboring elements one upon the other so that they partially overlap. The magnetic 

flux, caused by one of the elements, is penetrating its neighboring element as well as the 

overlapping area, but in both cases with a different direction. Hence, their mutual 

inductance can be canceled out and the magnetic flux in the second element can be zeroed 

by adjusting the size of the overlap area. The drawbacks of this method are the geometrical 

constraints that go along with it. By partially overlapping two elements, the next-

neighboring elements are automatically closer to each other and can therefore potentially 

couple stronger [37]. 

The Other way of how to decouple elements is the inductive or capacitive decoupling [38]. 

Two elements can be arranged so that they share a common conductor, illustrated in Figure 

21, and an inductive or capacitive element can be brought into it. By adjusting the value of 

these elements, the mutual inductance of the elements can be cancelled out. As the losses of 

capacitive elements are usually lower, primarily capacitors are used for this purpose. One 

great advantage of this method is the possibility to decouple even non-adjacent element by 

connecting them with coaxial cables with two capacitors in between [37]. 

 
Figure 21 – Addition of a capacitor CD between two elements that share a common conductor to 

avoid mutual inductance [35]. 

 

3.4. Cable Trap 

Coaxial cables (Figure 22) are used to feed each element of the coil. On this type of cable, 

the current on the inner conductor and on the shield are equal and opposite so there is no 

energy to be radiated. However unbalanced current can be induced on the shield due to 



25 

 

unsymmetrical feeding of RF coil or from a near electromagnetic field, such as RF field. 

Under this situation, it can lead to increased power requirements, stronger coupling 

between the elements and cable heating in transmit mode, and also to significant decreased 

SNR in receive mode. A cable trap is a specialized circuit to suppress induced unbalanced 

current on the shield [34]. 

 

 

 
Figure 22 – Coaxial cable – cut away view [39]. 

 

3.5. Scattering-Parameters (S-Parameters) 

The S-parameters describe the power transmission and reflection in a given system without 

knowledge about its components, and are therefore, used to quantify tuning, matching and 

decoupling. S-parameters are usually expressed in dB and organized in an S-parameter 

matrix. A network with N ports will have an N x N dimension S-matrix [40]. 

  

Figure 23 – A two-port component indicating the transmitted and reflected waves ai and bi [35]. 

 

Assuming a network with 2 ports, signals can be fed in (described by the parameter ai) and 

read out (described by the parameter bi) at 2 locations, as shown in Figure 23. The S-matrix 

will have the size of 2 x 2 and its entries are 



26 

 

    
  
  
|
    

 
Eq. 6.1 

 

    
  
  
|
    

 
Eq. 6.3 

    
  
  
|
    

 
Eq. 6.2 

    
  
  
|
    

 
Eq. 6.4 

 

Sii is called the reflection coefficient, giving information about the fraction of the signal 

which is reflected at the port i and did not propagate through the component. On the other 

hand, the parameters Sij, with i ? j, represent the transmission coefficient, providing how 

much of the signal, inserted at port j, is transferred and lost into port i [40]. An example of a 

coil with two elements is shown on Figure 24.  

 

Figure 24 – S-parameters of a coil with 2 elements at 297 MHz. The reflection coefficient S11 and 

S22 are approximately -50 dB, which means only 0.00001 of the power transmitted is reflected 

back. The transmission coefficient S12 is -30 dB shows that 0.001 of the power inserted at element 1 

is transmitted into element 2.  

 

 

?S11 

?S22 

?S12 



27 

 

3.6. Quality factor 
 

Quality factor or Q measures the performance of the coil (a tuned circuit) and is the ratio of 

stored energy to dissipated energy in the system. Equivalently, it can be seen as the ratio of 

the reactive impedance to the resistive impedance 

  
  

 
      Eq. 7 

Quality factor is also a measure of the current or voltage magnification achieved by the 

coil. A higher Q means a narrower frequency response and the coil behaves like a band-

pass filter, eliminating noise from outside the bandwidth of interest, and an improved SNR 

can be obtained  [11].  

The SNR is proportional to the square root of the loaded Q (QL – loaded to a sample such as 

a patient or a phantom) and an optimum SNR results when the sample noise is dominant, 

that is when the ratio of QL and unloaded Q (QuL – without any sample loaded) is less than 

0.5 [19]. 

A practical way to calculate Q is using linear S11 curve of the coil tuned at f0 and the 

bandwidth of Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) shown by Eq. 8 [41] 

   
  

    
  Eq. 8 



28 

 

4. MATERIALS AND METHODS 

4.1 Coil Construction  

In order to detect at 7.0 T both proton (f = 297 MHz) and fluorine (f = 279.5 MHz) signals a 

dual tunable transceiver array coil with eight elements was constructed. The coil was made 

of three parts, two identical anterior parts and one posterior part to fit the anatomy of an 

average knee, Figure 25.  

 

Figure 25 – 
1
H/

19
F dual tuned knee coil made of three parts: two identical anterior parts and one 

posterior part to fit the anatomy of an average knee. 

 

Each of the anterior sections consists of three elements, each one with a size of 5 × 5 cm, 

were arranged in a triangular form in order to facilitate the decoupling of neighboring 

elements and bent to better cover the region of interest. As the short wavelength of RF field 

at 7.0 T leads to significant phase variations along the conductor, high Q ceramic capacitors 

were equally placed around the loop to shorten the conductor length. Decoupling between 

adjacent elements was allowed by a common conductor with a sharing decoupling capacitor 

with high Q. For tuning and matching trim capacitors (1-13 pF) with high Q were used. On 

right side of the Figure 26 trim and non-trim capacitor placements can be found. 

Two of those elements placed above the knee were tuned to fluorine frequency and the 

lateral one to proton frequency, Figure 26 left.  



29 

 

  

Figure 26 – Left: anterior part of the coil consisted by two identical 3 loop elements sections. Two 

of these loops, placed above the knee, were tuned to 
19

F and the lateral one to proton frequency. 

Right: detail of one of the anterior section’s circuit, where capacitors to shorten the conductor 

length and tuning, matching and decoupling capacitors are shown. 

 

The posterior part of the coil consists of two elements with a size of 180 × 95 mm tuned to 

proton frequency. It was bended to fit the knee fold, serving as a comfortable support while 

measurements occur. Tuning, matching, decoupling capacitors and capacitors shortening 

the conductor length can be seen on Figure 27.  

   

Figure 27 – Left: posterior part of the coil consisted by 2 loop elements tuned to proton 

frequency. Right: detail the posterior section’s circuit, where capacitors to shorten the 

conductor length and tuning, matching and decoupling capacitors are shown. 



30 

 

The coils were manufactured from printed circuit board (PCB) using a computer numerical 

control (CNC) machine Promat S100 (LpKF, Garbsen, Germany). The width of the 

conductor was 10 mm to minimize ohmic losses. 

 

4.1.1. Casing 

A solid casing was designed to meet safety and comfort (Autodesk Inventor 2010, San 

Rafael, CA). It was built with the rapid prototyping system BST 1200es (Dimension, Eden 

Prairie, MN) using ABS (acrylonitrile butadiene styrene). The casing prevents a direct 

contact between the tissue and the coil, and thus avoiding tissue heating caused by high 

electric fields in the conductors and capacitors.  

 

4.1.2. Cable trap 

Cable traps were placed in the feeding coaxial cable of each element to suppress induced 

unbalanced current on the outer conductor at 279.5 MHz and 297.0 MHz for fluorine and 

proton cables, respectively. The cable trap was made out of two turns of the feeding cable 

with an adequate capacitor soldered to the outer conductor to adjust the frequency, Figure 

28. The capacitor value was found using a pick-up loop. 

 

 

Figure 28 – Cable trap used in the coil. It consists of two turns of the feeding cable with a capacitor 

soldered to the shield. 

 

 



31 

 

4.2. Electromagnetic field (EMF) simulations 
 

At    higher than approximately 3.0 T, quasistatic solutions may no longer be employed, 

and the propagation of the magnetic field through the object has to be considered. The 

strength and phase of the RF field vary as function of position within the object, and 

determined by its form, permittivity, and conductivity. Even for simple geometrical 

configurations analytical solutions are difficult to obtain [42]. Hence, full wave simulation 

of the electromagnetic field is necessary to obtain complex behavior of RF field and RF 

power deposition in the tissues. 

EMF simulations were carried out by the software SEMCAD X (Schmid &amp;amp; Partner 

Engineering AG, Zurich, Switzerland) based on finite-difference time-domain (FDTD) 

method that uses the differential form of Maxwell’s equations for the discretization and 

computation of EM fields in a gridded 3D volume [43]. 

In order to find right capacitor values for capacitive shortening of the conductor and tuning, 

matching and decoupling of the elements, capacitors of the coil were modeled and 

simulated as 50 ? ports. The resulting S-Parameters (saved as a touchstone file) were 

exported into an S-parameter simulator, Advanced Design System (ADS) (Agilent 

Technologies, Santa Clara, California, USA), where the optimal values were found. With 

these capacitors values, another EM simulation in SEMCAD X was carried out to obtain 

the correct electromagnetic field responses of the coil. Figure 29 shows SEMCAD X 

environment and Figure 30 and Figure 31 show ADS environment. 

   

Figure 29 – Left: all capacitors were modeled and simulated as 50 ? ports (in red) in order to be 

exported to ADS to be find optimal capacitive values. Right: the ports were replaced by capacitors 

(in blue) when their values were found on ADS. 



32 

 

 

Figure 30 – ADS circuit design environment. The touchstone file of ports EMF simulations are 

imported, the ports representing capacitors are replaced by capacitors and S-parameter simulation is 

simulated in order to find optimal capacitor values. 

 

Figure 31 – ADS S-parameter visualization environment. The option “Tune” permits to change 

capacitor values at real time and by visualizing the S-parameters, optimal capacitor values are found. 

This environment is similar to real-life vector network analyzer (VNA) to tune, match and decouple the 

coil elements. 



33 

 

4.2.1. Phantom simulation 

 

EMF simulation of the coil was performed with the coil loaded to a phantom to access   
  

field patterns that would be compared to the measurements in order to validate the 

simulations (Figure 32 left). The phantom was modeled after a cylindrical phantom 

available at B.U.F.F. with similar tissue properties as an average knee (?r = 65, ? = 0.72 

S/m). 

To balance accuracy and simulation time, the resolution of the mesh was set as 3 mm in all 

3 dimensions over the phantom. Grid refinement was necessary to properly discretize the 

conductors and lumped elements (Figure 32 right) in order to produce realistic paths for the 

currents. The resulting grid had 3.06 million cells (135 × 154 × 147). 

   

Figure 32 – Left: EM Simulation model of the phantom with the coil placed in a manner similar as 

in real-life measurements on the scanner. Right: Voxelized model. 

 

4.2.2. Human model simulation 
 

Human model simulations were performed with the posable human body model “Duke” 

(virtual family, IT’IS Foundation, Zurich, Switzerland). “Duke” model (male, age 34 years 

old, height 1.77 m, weight 72.4 kg) was developed from high resolution MRI scans of a 

healthy volunteer, and reconstructed as a 3D CAD object with approximately 80 high 

resolution organs and tissues [44].  



34 

 

To save simulation and post-processing time, only the lower part of the model was used, 

Figure 33. This was possible due to the local performance of surface coils.  

The resolution of the mesh was set as 3 mm in all 3 dimensions over the region of interest. 

Grid refinement was conducted to proper discretization of the conductors and lumped 

elements. The resulting grid had 10.48 million cells (232 × 139 × 325). 

 

Figure 33 – Voxelized lower member of “Duke” with the coil. 

 

SAR evaluation 

Part of the energy carried by a time-harmonic EMF is deposited in lossy objects by induced 

conduction currents, which may result into local heating [43]. 

As mentioned before, SAR measures the energy absorbed by the biological tissues. The 

local SAR can be calculated with Eq. 9 when a specific location is given 

   (  )  
 

  
     Eq. 9 

 

  is the electrical conductivity,    equals  ?   ?  , the squared magnitude of the induced 

electric field, and   is the mass density. Local SAR is not always useful, as it is too 

sensitive to approximation in the computational methods. Therefore, averaged SAR in a 

region R with mass M is mostly used for safety concerns [43]. 

According to IEEE/IEC62704-1, R is recommended to be a cube aligned to the 

computational grid and sized to contain a specific M of lossy tissue (normally 1 g or 10 g). 



35 

 

The cube can also contain background material (air or other non-conductive tissues), 

however, it should not exceed more than 10% of the volume occupied by the cube. The 

cube is expanded at each location to compute the average SAR, resulting in a distribution of 

averaged SAR values along the entire region of interest.  

The SAR evaluation was performed by post processing tool of SEMCAD X, MRI toolkit. 

This tool is able to combine magnetic and electric field of all or selected coil elements, and 

displays the result at selected frequencies.  

The averaged SAR for the coil was calculated at 279.5 MHz and 297.0 MHz, by computing 

IEEE/IEC62704-1 constant mass cube of 10 g without any phase setting and with phase 

setting 3 (Table 15), which showed good   
  homogeneity in the region of interest in vivo. 

The overall delivered power, which is the power delivered to all channel without losses, 

was set as 1 W, and equally distributed to each channel. The worst case SAR was also 

computed. The worst SAR is calculated by MRI toolkit of SEMCAD X by analyzing all 

possible phases and amplitudes for all active transmission ports, and then displays the 

setting that produces more SAR in the sample [43]. 

 

4.3. RF Bench analysis 

For a circuit analysis of the coil an 8-channel vector network analyzer (VNA) ZVT8 

(Rhode &amp;amp; Schwarz GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG, Munich, Germany), with a frequency range of 3 kHz 

to 8 GHz, was used to assess the S-parameters.  

 

Figure 34 – ZVT8 (Rhode &amp;amp; Schwarz GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG, Munich, Germany). 



36 

 

4.3.1. Tuning, Matching and Decoupling 
 

By connecting the coil directly to the VNA, the tuning, matching and decoupling of 

elements were possible by real-time assessment of the S-parameters. 

 

4.3.2. Q factor measurement 
 

The unloaded Q of each element of the coil was obtained using Eq. 8, with S-parameters 

acquired by VNA in unloaded conditions.  

The loaded Q of each element was obtained with the coil loaded to a subject with 25 years 

old and 55 kg. It was also calculated with Eq. 8 using S-parameters obtained by the VNA. 

 

4.4. Measurements 
 

All images and spectroscopies were acquired on a 7.0 T whole-body scanner (Siemens 

Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany), Figure 35, equipped with an Avanto gradient system 

capable to achieve a slew rate of up to 200 mT/m/ms, maximum gradient strength of 40 

mT/m (Siemens Medical Solutions, Erlangen, Germany) and an 8 kW RF amplifier 

(Stolberg HF-Technik, Stolberg-Vicht, Germany).  

 

 

Figure 35 – 7.0 T whole-body scanner (Siemens Healthcare, Erlangen, Germany). 



37 

 

4.4.1. Coil interface 
 

The connection between the coil and the scanner is carried out by the coil interface. It 

consists of a Tx/Rx switch box (Figure 36) with integrated low impedance preamplifiers, 

two 1 to 4 power splitter boxes (one for proton channels (Figure 37) and one for fluorine 

channels), and the coil plug with a coil file associated that bears the coil parameters, such as 

which nuclei is been scanned and RF power limitations. The power splitters were necessary 

since the power plug for the coil provided by the Siemens scanner consisted only in a single 

transmit plug.  

 
   Figure 36 – Tx/Rx switch box. 

 

Figure 37 – 1 to 4 power splitter. 

 

The coil interface described above, was used for the measurements of T1, T2, concentration 

curve and   
  mapping measurements. Later, a specialized coil interface box (Figure 38) 

was constructed for 
1
H/

19
F dual tuned knee coil with integrated power splitters. This new 

coil interface was used for in vivo imaging and spectroscopy. 

 

 
Figure 38 – Coil interface box specialized for 

1
H/

19
F dual tuned knee coil with integrated power 

splitters. 



38 

 

4.4.2.   
  mapping 

 

To validate the EMF simulations a comparison between simulated individual element and 

MR measured individual element   
  maps were performed with a cylindrical phantom (?r = 

65, ? = 0.72 S/m) free of fluorine components. 

The transmission field of each element was acquired with Bloch-Siegert implementation 

[45].  Each evaluated element was directly connected to the single power transmit plug of 

the scanner, while the remaining elements were connect to 50 ? power loads in order to 

absorb any power received through mutual coupling.  

  
  maps were done offline using Bloch simulations in Matlab (MathWorks Inc., Natick, 

Massachusetts, USA). The resulting maps were giving in arbitrary units (a. u.), hence, in 

order to allow the comparison between measured and simulated   
  maps, a unit conversion 

to    ?   was performed using Eq. 10. 

 

   
 [   ?  ]    

 [    ]
          

      
?    ?    Eq. 10 

 

 

The           is the achieved approximate flip angle and        is the required voltage, 

both given by Siemens scanner raw data. As the simulation does not have losses, the 

measurements were corrected to the hardware losses, Q-factors and S-parameters. The 

correction with S-parameters was necessary as the phantom did not contain fluorine, which 

made the maps for the fluorine channels be acquired at 
1
H frequency, therefore, the losses 

originated by not matched and tuned fluorine channels to 
1
H frequency could be corrected. 

 

4.4.3. Determination of T1 and T2 
 
19

F spectroscopy was performed in order to determine T1 and T2 of fluorine containing 

NSAID ointment (flufenamic acid (2-{[3-(Trifluoromethyl) phenyl]amino}benzoic acid) 

used in this project. The measured samples were two cylindrical MR probes (inner diameter 

= 4.52 mm, height = 50 mm) filled with NSAID ointment, and 50% NSAID ointment plus 



39 

 

50% fluorine free ointment. In order to cover only one MR probe for each measurement, 

SPin ECho full Intensity Acquired Localized (SPECIAL) [46]  technique was used (Figure 

39). This technique allows data acquisition only in the ROI enclosed by a predefined voxel. 

For a more accurate position of the voxel, 
19

F gradient-echo (GRE) images were acquired 

for orientation (TR = 90 ms, TE = 1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 

mm, matrix: 128 × 128).  

 

Figure 39 – 
19

F GRE image (TR = 90 ms, TE = 1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice 

thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 128 × 128) of a sample filled with NSAID ointment. Left: sagittal view of 

SPECIAL voxel. Right: transversal view of SPECIAL voxel. 

 

A voxel of size 7 × 7 × 40 mm was placed around the MR probe. 
19

F spectroscopy for T1 

measurements was performed with 128 averages, TE of 5.5 ms and different TR durations. 

19
F spectroscopy for T2 measurements were performed with 128 averages, TR of 4000 ms 

and different TE durations. The obtained data were processed in Matlab (MathWorks Inc., 

Natick, Massachusetts, USA) and fitted to T1 and T2 equations, described in section 2.1.5, 

in order to determine T1 and T2 relaxation times.  

 



40 

 

4.4.4. Calibration curve 
 

For the calibration curve, which is the relationship between the amount of fluorine 

contained in the sample and the respect signal magnitude, spectroscopies were performed 

with TR of 2000 ms. TE of 5.5 ms, and different voxel sizes to limit different amount of the 

samples. The number of averages varies according to the voxel size to assure the same SNR 

for all measurements.  

 

4.4.5. In vivo Imaging 
 

High resolution GRE proton images (TR = 12 ms, TE = 3.4 ms, in plane resolution: 0.7 × 

0.7 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 384 × 384) and fluorine images (TR = 90 ms, TE = 

1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 128 × 128) were 

acquired.  

In vivo   
  shimming was performed using different phase settings to obtain a more 

homogeneous   
  distribution over the region of interest.  

 

4.4.6. In vivo 19F Spectroscopy  
 

As there were no volunteers with active inflammation on the knee available at moment of 

this study, two healthy subjects were asked to apply topically the flufenamic acid 

containing NSAID ointment on the skin surrounding the knee, in order to detect eventual 

ointment absorption. For this purpose unlocalized 
19

F spectroscopy using FID was regularly 

performed, and any change of initial signal magnitude can be used to trace substance 

absorption.  

Subject 1 applied topically 5.82 g of the NSAID ointment, corresponding to 0.621 mmol of 

flufenamic acid, and was monitored approximately 70 minutes without leaving the scanner.  

Subject 2 was asked to apply 9.65 g of the NSAID ointment, containing 1.03 mmol of 

flufenamic acid, and was monitored 172 minutes in two scan sessions, with each one not 

exceeding 50 minutes. At end of the session, after 172 minutes of the first spectroscopy, a 



41 

 

SPECIAL voxel spectroscopy was performed. The voxel was placed inside the knee under 

NSAID ointment application as shown in Figure 40. 

 

Figure 40 – SPECIAL voxel placement inside the knee under NSAID ointment application. Left: 

sagittal view of GRE 
1
H image (TR = 12 ms, TE = 3.4 ms, in plane resolution: 0.7 × 0.7 mm

2
, slice 

thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 384 × 384). Center: axial view of GRE 
1
H image (TR = 12 ms, TE = 3.4 

ms, in plane resolution: 0.7 × 0.7 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 384 × 384). Right: axial view 

of 
19

F GRE image (TR = 90 ms, TE = 1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, 

matrix: 128 × 128). 

  



42 

 

5. RESULTS 

 

To facilitate description of the results, the coil elements were numbered in Figure 41. 

 

Figure 41 – Elements numbering. Channels 1-4 are 
1
H channels and 5-8 are 

19
F channels. 

5.1. Coil Layout 
 

The constructed coil is shown in figures below. On Figure 42, the coil PCB circuits, 

soldered capacitors and cable traps for each channel can be observed. Figure 43 shows how 

the coil in its casing is placed on a volunteer. 

 

Figure 42 – PCB circuit and 

capacitors of the coil. Cable 

traps for each channel can 

be also observed. 

 

Figure 43 – placement of the coil in its casing on a volunteer. 

 



43 

 

5.1.1. Cable traps 
 

The performance of the cable traps associated to each channel as well as the capacitor value 

used are described in Table 4. 

Associated channel Capacitor value S11 

1 4.7 -13 

2 4.3 -20 

3 3.9 -18 

4 4.3 -20 

5 4.7 -14 

6 5.4 -13 

7 4.5 -20 

8 4.7 -16 

Table 4 – capacitors used for cable traps of associated channels and their performance. 

 

5.2. RF Bench Analysis      

5.2.1. S-Parameters 

Each of coil elements were tuned to their respective 279.5 MHz (
19

F frequency) or 297.0 

MHz (
1
H frequency) loaded on the knee of a subject (female, 1.63 m, 55 kg).  

Reflection and transmission coefficients of each of three parts of the coil are presented in 

table below. Respective S-parameters visualizations on VNA can be found on Figure 44 to 

Figure 46. 

Coil part Sii 279.5 MHz 297.0 MHz Sij 279.5 MHz 297.0 MHz 

Posterior 

part 

S11 - -32 dB S12 -  

S22 - -35 dB    

Left 

anterior 

part 

S66 -39 dB - S63 -20 dB -19 dB 

S33 - -39 dB S35 -17 dB -16 dB 

S55 -34 dB - S65 -25 dB - 

Right 

anterior 

part 

S77 -46 dB - S74 -19 dB -18 dB 

S44 - -39 dB S48 -19 dB -19 dB 

S88 -50 dB - S78 -20 dB - 

Table 5 – Sii and Sij of coil elements. Note that the S-parameter acquirement was made for each 

coil part. 



44 

 

 

Figure 44 – print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for left anterior part of the coil. 

 

 

Figure 45 - print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for right anterior part of the coil. 



45 

 

 

Figure 46 - print of VNA screen while measuring S-parameters for the posterior part of the coil. 

 

5.2.2. Q-factor 

Loaded and unloaded Q as well as the ratio of loaded Q to unloaded Q is presented in the 

table below. 

channels QL QuL QL/QuL 

1 6.5 29.7 0.22 

2 8.9 18.6 0.48 

3 7.7 31.3 0.25 

4 7.7 49.5 0.16 

5 12.7 46.6 0.27 

6 14.7 111.8 0.13 

7 13.6 124.2 0.11 

8 13.6 62.1 0.22 

Table 6 – QL, QuL and QL/QuL of each coil channels. 

5.3. Simulated and measured   
  maps 

The measured   
  maps corrected to hardware losses (from the Tx/Rx switch box, scanner 

power transmit plug and feeding cables), to Q-factors and to S-parameters are shown in 

Table 7. 



46 

 

Simulated and measured   
  maps are compared on Table 8 and displayed in Figure 47 

together with the maximum   
  value of each channel. The   

  maps are shown by their 

relative values to simulated and measured maximum values, respectively.  

 

Figure 47 – Relative   
  map of simulation and measurement. The maximum   

  value of each 

channel is shown below its map.



47 

 

 

channel Hardware 

losses 

(linear) 

QL/QuL Sii 
(linear) 

Measure

d   
  

(a.u.) 

Measured 

  
  

(   ?  ) 

Measured   
   

corrected 

with 

hardware loss 

(   ?  ) 

Measured   
   

corrected 

with hard. 

Loss + Q 

(   ?  ) 

Measured   
  

correc. with 

hard. Loss + 

Q + S-param 

(   ?  ) 

1 0.54 0.22 - 0.9619 25.25823 34.27617579 38.74828847 38.74828847 

2 0.54 0.48 - 0.8299 21.79208 29.79315268 41.23286951 41.23286951 

3 0.55 0.25 0.000622 2.9868 78.42944 105.6703619 121.7556467 121.7935426 

4 0.56 0.16 0.001709 3.1213 81.96123 109.6794355 119.3690178 119.4711279 

5 0.55 0.27 0.440018 2.0864 54.78612 73.81883746 86.55561424 115.6666174 

6 0.54 0.13 0.3926 1.5818 41.53599 56.46822568 60.59513996 77.74998318 

7 0.55 0.11 0.402949 1.5564 40.86902 55.24755848 58.55323896 75.77835632 

8 0.56 0.22 0.416045 1.5732 41.31016 55.28071251 62.57099931 81.88102884 

 

Table 7 – Correction factors of measured   
  maps – hardware losses, QL/QuL and Sii, the obtained measured   

  maps (a. u.) and after correction 

factors. Sii of channels 1 and 2 was not registed before   
  mapping experiment, but as they are proton channels and they were well tuned and 

matched to proton frequency, hence, the S-parameter correction of these channels would be negligible.  



48 

 

channel 
Simulated   

  

(   ?  ) 

Measured 

  
  

(   ?  ) 

Simulated   
  

   Measured 
  
  

(   ?  ) 

        

         
   

        

         
 

1 32.4 38.7 -6.3 1.20 -0.20 

2 49 41.2 7.8 0.84 0.15 

3 157 121.8 35.2 0.78 0.22 

4 175 119.5 55.5 0.68 0.32 

5 174 115.7 58.3 0.66 0.34 

6 159 77.7 81.3 0.49 0.51 

7 161 75.8 85.2 0.47 0.53 

8 176 81.9 94.1 0.47 0.53 

Table 8 – Simulated and measured   
  values and their comparison. 

5.4. SAR evaluation 

Peak averaged SAR at 279.5 MHz and 297.0 MHz, computed with IEEE/IEC62704-1 

constant mass cube of 10 g with total input power of 1 W for no phase setting and for phase 

setting 3 is shown in Table 9, as well as worst the case SAR. This worst case scenario is 

calculated by MRI toolkit of SEMCAD X for all possible phase settings and amplitudes of 

the transmission power in each port, with 1 W as total input power. The resulting phases 

and amplitudes of worst case SAR are shown in Table 10. 

SAR distribution over the region of interest is shown for phase setting 3 at 279.5 MHz in 

Figure 48 and at 279.0 MHz in Figure 49. 

 

 no phase settings 

(1 W input power) 

phase setting 3 

(1 W input power) 

Worst case SAR 

(1 W input power) 

Peak 10 g averaged 

SAR at 279.5 MHz 
0.495 W/kg 0.306 W/kg 3.033 W/kg 

Peak 10 g averaged 

SAR at 297.0 MHz 
0.475 W/kg 0.375 W/kg 1.769 W/kg 

Table 9 - Peak averaged SAR at 279.5 MHz and 297.0 MHz computed with IEEE/IEC62704-1 

constant mass cube of 10 g for no phase setting, for phase setting 3 and worst case SAR. 



49 

 

Worst case SAR (for 1 W input power) 

Channel 279.5 MHz 297.0 MHz 

Phase Amplitude Phase Amplitude 

1 105.12º 0.0007 W 79.75º 0.1052 W 

2 55.35º 0.0003 W 118.25º 0.1123 W 

3 122.70º 0.0016 W -157.36º 0.7661 W 

4 -10.02º 0.0233 W -153.97º 0.0041 W 

5 -128.24º 0.0142 W 157.17 0.0045 W 

6 42.81º 0.0221 W 91.01º 0.0070 W 

7 -180.00º 0.5069 W -180.00º 0.0002 W 

8 -1.15º 0.4309 W 122.53º 0.0005 W 

Table 10 – The phase and amplitude of worst case SAR at 
19

F and 
1
H frequencies. 

 

 
Figure 48 – 10 g averaged SAR distribution at 279.5 MHz for phase setting 3. 



50 

 

 

 
Figure 49 - 10 g averaged SAR distribution at 297.0 MHz for phase setting 3. 

 

 

5.5. T1 measurement 

 

Signal magnitude of FID of different samples at different TRs was registered in Table 11. 

The acquired data was plotted and fitted to the T1 equation, shown in Figure 50. T1 was 

found as 673 ms for 100% NSAID ointment and 616 ms for 50% NSAID ointment + 50% 

fluorine free ointment. 

 

 



51 

 

TR (ms) 

Signal magnitude a.u. (×10
-6

) 

100% NSAID ointment 

(65 ?mol of flufenamic acid) 

Signal magnitude a.u. (×10
-6

) 

50% NSAID ointment + 

50% fluorine free ointment 

(32 ?mol of flufenamic acid) 

260 3.650414713 1.857248084 

500 6.619002951 3.623145289 

750 8.555848297 4.43542712 

1000 9.585644839 5.140411854 

1250 10.71735259 5.371996585 

1500 11.21005678 5.659231852 

1750 11.37189668 5.757178825 

2000 11.90929343 6.118101368 

3000 12.34120536 6.136087312 

4000 12.42318758 6.189797488 

5000 12.47302942 6.307514114 

Table 11 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies of 100% NSAID ointment sample and 50% NSAID 

ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment sample at different TRs. 

 
Figure 50 – Fitted T1 recovery curve from acquired data. 

          (   
 

 
     ) 

 

         (   
 

 
     ) 

 



52 

 

5.6. T2 measurement 

Signal magnitude of FID for the different samples at different TEs was registered in Table 

12. The acquired data was plotted and fitted to the T2 equation shown in Figure 51. T2 was 

found as 31.07 ms for 100% NSAID ointment and 25.87 ms for 50% NSAID ointment + 

50% fluorine free ointment. 

 

TE (ms) 

Signal magnitude a.u. (×10
-6

) 

100% NSAID ointment 

(65 ?mol of flufenamic acid) 

Signal magnitude a.u. (×10
-6

) 

50% NSAID ointment + 

50% fluorine free ointment 

(32 ?mol of flufenamic acid) 

5.5 12.49374738 6.82736343 

8 11.89928515 
 

9 
 

5.41190389 

10 11.21772892 
 

12 10.47904098 
 

15 9.295233851 3.947644809 

20 
 

3.444100231 

30 5.833485836 2.429228108 

40 4.098662036 1.790736375 

50 
 

1.562887196 

60 2.287997288 0.737952665 

70 
  

80 0.995964142 
 

100 0.611352291 
 

120 0.436143606 
 

Table 12 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies of 100% NSAID ointment sample and 50% NSAID 

ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment sample at different TEs. 



53 

 

  
Figure 51 – Fitted T2 recovery curve from acquired data. 

 

5.7. Calibration Curve 

Signal magnitude of the spectroscopy and amount of flufenamic acid present at different 

SPECIAL voxel sizes for 100% NSAID ointment can be found in Table 13 and, for 50% 

NSAID ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment is registered in Table 14. The concentration 

curves are plotted in Figure 52. 

Voxel size 

(mm
3
) 

Amount of 

Fluf. Acid 

(?mol) 

Signal 

magnitude 

a.u. (×10
-6

) 

7 x 7 x 30 51.1 10.84 

7 x 7 x 27 46.0 10.12 

7 x 7 x 24 40.8 9.44 

7 x 7 x 21 35.7 8.30 

7 x 7 x 18 30.6 7.19 

7 x 7 x 15 25.5 6.09 

7 x 7 x 12 20.4 4.91 

7 x 7 x 9 15.3 3.84 

Table 13 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies 

and amount of flufenamic acid present at 

different SPECIAL voxel sizes for 100% 

NSAID ointment sample. 

voxel size 

(mm
3
) 

Amount of 

Fluf. Acid 

(?mol) 

Signal 

magnitude 

a.u. (×10
-6

) 

7 x 7 x 30 25.5 6.42 

7 x 7 x 27 23.0 5.64 

7 x 7 x 24 20.4 5.02 

7 x 7 x 21 17.9 4.43 

7 x 7 x 18 15.3 3.92 

7 x 7 x 15 12.8 3.10 

7 x 7 x 12 10.2 2.61 

7 x 7 x 9 7.7 1.86 

Table 14 - Signal magnitude of spectroscopies 

and amount of flufenamic acid present at 

different SPECIAL voxel sizes for 50% NSAID 

ointment + 50% fluorine free ointment sample.

          ( 
 

 
     ) 

 

         ( 
 

 
     ) 

 



54 

 

 

Figure 52 – Concentration curves for 100% NSAID ointment and for 50% NSAID ointment + 

50% fluorine free ointment. 

5.8. In vivo Imaging 

5.8.1.   
  Shimming 

 

Phase setting 1 
Ch1: 0º 

Ch2: 180º 

Ch3: 90º 

Ch4: 0º 

Ch5: 180º 

Ch6: 0º 

Ch7: 90º 

Ch8: 0º 

Phase setting 2 
Ch1: 0º 

Ch2: 180º 

Ch3: 0º 

Ch4: 90º 

Ch5: 0º 

Ch6: 180º 

Ch7: 90º 

Ch8: 0º 

Phase setting 3 
Ch1: 0º 

Ch2: 90º 

Ch3: 0º 

Ch4: 90º 

Ch5: 0º 

Ch6: 0º 

Ch7: 0º 

Ch8: 0º 

Phase setting 4 
Ch1: 0º 

Ch2: 180º 

Ch3: 0º 

Ch4: 90º 

Ch5: 0º 

Ch6: 0º 

Ch7: 0º 

Ch8: 0º 

Phase setting 5 
Ch1: 90º 

Ch2: 0º 

Ch3: 90º 

Ch4: 0º 

Ch5: 0º 

Ch6: 0º 

Ch7: 0º 

Ch8: 0º 

Phase setting 6 
Ch1: 0º 

Ch2: 90º 

Ch3: 0º 

Ch4: 180º 

Ch5: 0º 

Ch6: 0º 

Ch7: 0º 

Ch8: 0º 

Table 15 – phase settings used in order to achieve a more homogeneous   
  field. 

                             

 

                             

 



55 

 

Images of the region of interest resulting from in vivo   
  shimming using phase settings 

described in Table 15 are shown in Figure 53 (TR = 8.6  ms, TE = 4 ms, in plane 

resolution: 0.4 × 0.4 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 512 × 512). The phase setting 3 

showed an overall better SNR (brighter image) and less RF destructive interference. 

 

 

Figure 53 – GRE images from the region of interest using different phase setting of Table 15. 

 

Using the phase sitting 3, the image quality is also improved for other knee anatomies as 

can be seen on Figure 54, comparing a scan without phase setting and a scan with phase 

setting 3. 

     

Figure 54 – The left image was acquired without any phase setting and destructive interference of 

short wavelength of the RF field can be observed. The right image used phase setting 3 and a more 

homogeneous   
  distribution can be observed.  

Phase setting 1 Phase setting 2 Phase setting 3 

Phase setting 4 Phase setting 5 Phase setting 6 



56 

 

5.1.1. Proton and fluorine imaging  
 

A slice of high resolution proton images (TR = 12 ms, TE = 3.4 ms, in plane resolution: 0.7 

× 0.7 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 384 × 384), and fluorine images (TR = 90 ms, 

TE = 1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 128 × 128)  of 

a subject’s knee with topical applied flufenamic acid containing NSAID ointment on the 

nearby skin are shown on Figure 55. 

 

 

Figure 55 – A: High resolution proton image (0.7 × 0.7 × 5 mm). B: high resolution fluorine image 

(2 × 2 × 5 mm). C: combined 
1
H/

19
F image. 

 

5.9. In vivo 19F Spectroscopy 
 

Results of in vivo unlocalized 
19

F spectroscopy of the flufenamic acid contained NSAID 

ointment topically applied to volunteers’ skin near by the knee are shown in Table 16 and 

plotted on Figure 56. 

There was no signal on the spectrogram of the spectroscopy performed with SPECIAL 

voxel placed inside the knee beneath the skin where the NSAID was topically applied. 

 

 

A B C 



57 

 

Subject 1 (0.621 mmol of fluf. acid) Subject 2 (1.028 mmol of fluf. acid) 

Time (min) 
Signal magnitude 

a.u. (×10
-5

) 
Time (min) 

Signal magnitude 

a.u. (×10
-5

) 

0 1.31 0 1.93 

16 1.46 31 2.06 

28 1.61 132 1.80 

46 1.68 155 1.84 

65 1.75 172 1.93 

Table 16 – 
19

F spectroscopy over time of the two subjects who applied topically the fluorine 

containing ointment on the skin near the knee.  

 

 

Figure 56 – graphic visualization of data of the Table 16.  



58 

 

6. DISCUSSION 

 

In this project, a knee coil tuned to proton and to fluorine frequencies was constructed in 

order to access the dynamics of a fluorine contained NSAID ointment, from its application 

in the skin to the site of inflammation in knees suffering from rheumatoid arthritis. In this 

section, results obtained in the previous section are discussed. 

6.1. Coil performance 
 

The coil consisted of two bent anterior parts that easily cover the anterior part of an average 

knee and one lower part that was designed to support an average knee in a bent position; 

this offers better comfort than a plane design for MRI examining subjects. The three parts 

of the coils are made by eight loop elements to cover all the region of interest, since surface 

coils have reduced field of view of approximately its diameter. 

Cable traps built to suppress the induced unbalanced currents in the feeding coaxial cables 

of each channel show a performance ranged from -13 dB to -20 dB. In the worst case, 5% 

of the unbalanced shield current is not attenuated, hence the cable traps can be considered 

to have a reasonable performance. 

The reflection coefficients (Sii) of each coil element were situated below -30 dB, which 

means that only 0.1% of the power is reflected back. This result show that tuning and 

matching of the coil was well performed and little loss occurs. This is important for coil 

performance since loss in reflection will result in less available power to generate the   
  

field to excite the spins. On the other hand, the transmission coefficients (Sij) of the 

elements of the same coil parts showed a variation from -16 dB to -25 dB meaning that in 

the worst case 2.5% of the power delivered to an element is lost into another. This is an 

acceptable result since it does not translate into a significant loss. By changing the 

capacitance of the tuning, matching and decoupling of the trim capacitors, the coil could be 

easily adapted to various subjects and to the phantom without further capacitance changes 

in the conductor shortening capacitors. 



59 

 

The ratio between loaded and unloaded Q, of all coil elements, lies below 0.5. This is a 

desired result since QL/QuL below 0.5 indicates the dominance of sample noise, and under 

this situation an optimum SNR could be achieved. 

6.2.   
  mapping comparison 

 

The simulated and measured   
  maps patterns showed a significant agreement. It is 

important to refer that the phantom used in the measurements was constructed by 

colleagues at B.U.F.F. and was aimed to measure temperature changes in RF heating 

experiments, thus it has three holes along its extension for the insertion of thermometers. 

This fact caused artifacts in   
  patterns of elements 1 and 2, since the holes are considered 

singularities in the Bloch algorithm when unwrapping phase.  

The comparison of maximum values of the measured and the simulated   
  (Table 8), 

revealed that the measurements are 15% to 53% less than the simulations, with a higher 

loss at fluorine channels. An unexpected gain of 20% in   
  value was found in channel 1 

which led to a further analysis of   
  map of this channel. It was found that the maximum 

measured   
  value of channel 1 was located in a region far away from the coil, where a 

hole for a thermometer is located, Figure 57. The actual maximum   
  value produced by 

the coil is approximately 27    ?  , which compared to simulated   
 , is 17% less. 

With the corrected value for channel 1, the measured maps for proton channels showed an 

extra loss of 21.5 ± 7.6% compared to simulated maps, despite the loss correction made in 

Table 7. On this table Sii values for channels 1 and 2 were not registered, but since these 

channels were tuned and matched to the proton frequency, Sii should not be higher than -15 

dB, thus the   
  value correction with S-parameters should not produce significant 

difference. The extra losses could be explained by further unknown losses in the MR 

system.  

The phantom used in the   
  mapping measurements did not contain fluorine compounds, 

thus, the   
  maps of fluorine elements were acquired in proton frequency and then 

extrapolated to fluorine frequency by correcting with S-parameters. Also, the S-parameters 

were acquired in the laboratory and not inside the scanner; therefore they are just an 



60 

 

approximation of the actual S-parameters values of the mapping measurement. This fact, 

plus further losses that occur in the MR system could explain the relatively high difference, 

47.8 ± 9.2%, between measured and simulated 
19

F channels.  

In this experiment, the validity of the simulation could be accepted by reasonable 

qualitative and quantitative agreement between measured and simulated   
  maps of the 

proton channels. On the other hand, despite the qualitative agreement, relatively higher 

quantitative difference was found in fluorine channels, due to the fact that there was no 

fluorine containing phantom available to make a proper 
19

F   
  mapping, this fact should 

not deter the validation of the simulations, which gives credibility of SAR simulations.  

A more accurate   
  mapping for the dual tuned knee coil could be made, by using a 

uniform proton containing phantom for 
1
H channels and a uniform fluorine containing 

phantom for 
19

F measurements. Also, the simulations should reproduce the exact 

positioning, size and dielectric properties of the phantom in MR experiments to achieve a 

better comparison. 

 

 

Figure 57 – Left:   
  map of channel 1 scaled from 0 to 39    ?  . Right:   

  map of channel 1 

scaled from 27 to 39    ?  , it shows that the maximum   
  value is not located in the expected 

region next to the channel 1, instead it is located in a far region from the channel 1 where a hole 

for insertion of a thermometer is placed. At approximately 27    ?   there is no signal left in 

the region next to channel 1, thus this value can be said to be the actual maximum   
  value 

produced by channel 1. 

Channel 1 scaled from 0 to 39 ?? ??? Channel 1 scaled from 27 to 39 ?? ??? 

Location of 

maximum  
Location of 

maximum  



61 

 

6.3. SAR evaluation 
 

For input power of 1 W to all the channels, 10 g averaged SAR for phase setting 3 was 

found to be 0.306 W/kg at 279.5 MHz (fluorine frequency) and 0.375 W/kg at 297.0 MHz 

(proton frequency). As the limit defined by IEC for 10g SAR at body extremity is 20 W/kg, 

a power increase until as high as 53 W for the coil at this phase setting (resulting in SAR 

value of 19.9 W/kg) will still stay within the limit of IEC guidelines.  

Since different phase and amplitude settings of the power at each port affects the SAR, the 

worst case SAR given by MRI toolkit of SEMCAD X could be used, for safety issues, as 

reference for delimitation of the RF power in the coil plug.  

It is also important to refer that the SAR calculations are made without power loss that 

occurs in real MR scans, thus, in real-life, the SAR values would not exceed the expected 

value from the simulations. 

6.4. T1, T2 and concentration curve 
 

Different T1 and T2 values were found for 100% flufenamic acid containing NSAID 

ointment sample and 50% flufenamic acid containing NSAID ointment + 50% non-fluorine 

containing ointment sample. This is an expected result, since the molecular environment 

was modified with the introduction of non-fluorine containing ointment. This also explains 

different concentration curve slops of these two samples. 

6.5. In vivo imaging and 19F spectroscopy 
 

In vivo high spatial resolution proton images (TR = 12 ms, TE = 3.4 ms, in plane 

resolution: 0.7 × 0.7 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 384 × 384) with phase setting 3 

showed homogenous image quality and contrast. The Overlapping of 
19

F image (TR = 90 

ms, TE = 1.3 ms, in plane resolution: 2 × 2 mm
2
, slice thickness: 5 mm, matrix: 128 × 128) 

and 
1
H image allows visualization and localization of fluorine contained NSAID ointment. 

This is of a major importance for in vivo drug tracking, which permits the sight of 
19

F 



62 

 

contained NSAID localization within the body, if drug penetration occurs and if the 

penetrated quantity allows the detection. 

In vivo 
19

F spectroscopy performed with two healthy subjects with topically applied 

flufenamic acid contained NSAID in the skin near the knee didn’t show signal decrease 

compared to the initial signal (Table 16 and Figure 56), which was originally expected to 

occur if any quantity of NSAID would be skin absorbed. In fact, non-localized 

spectroscopy excites all the 
19

F nuclei within the FOV, which included regions outside and 

inside the body, in this way the spectroscopy made is inconclusive.  

On the other hand the spectroscopy performed to subject 2 with SPECIAL voxel placed 

inside the knee beneath skin area where topical NSAID was applied did not show presence 

of fluorine after 172 minutes of beginning of the scanning session. This result shows that 

either it did not occurred any skin absorption of the topically applied NSAID at depth of the 

placed SPECIAL voxel within the scanning time, or the absorption occurred, but the 

absorbed quantity could be too low to be detected. 

Further in vivo studies could be performed using voxel spectroscopies, one placed outside 

the knee on top of the area where NSAID is applied and other placed inside the knee 

beneath application area. This should be performed with patients with rheumatoid arthritis 

in the knee and also with health volunteers. In this way, the absence of fluorine signal in the 

in vivo experiment performed for this work could also be checked if was due to the 

inexistence of the inflammation site for NSAID penetration. The absorption of NSAID 

could also be monitored for longer periods, such as days, instead of just a few hours, as it 

was used in this study. Therefore, an accumulative absorption of the NSAID could be 

evaluated.  

  



63 

 

7. CONCLUSION 

 

The eight channel dual tuned knee array coil constructed for the present thesis for the use at 

7.0 T ultrahigh magnetic field showed good performance evidenced by its low reflection 

and transmission coefficients (&lt;-30 dB and&amp;lt;-16 dB respectively) and noise dominant Q 

ratio,  which enounces SNR gain. 

The performed EM simulations with a phantom showed reasonable qualitative and 

quantitative agreement with the experiment results for proton channels validating the 

reliability of the SAR calculations for a human model, which give an estimation of the 

deposited RF power in the tissue. 

High spatial resolution images were acquired with this coil for proton (0.7 × 0.7 mm
2
 in 

plane resolution and 5 mm slice thickness) and for fluorine (2 × 2 mm
2
 in plane resolution 

and 5 mm slice thickness × 5 mm). After an in vivo   
  shimming session, images presented 

an increased quality since the RF destructive interference was attenuated. These parameters 

are important for knee imaging due to small structures around this joint.  

In vivo unlocalized 
19

F spectroscopy that aimed to observe and to quantify the skin 

absorption of flufenamic acid contained NSAID showed inconclusive results. And the 

spectroscopy performed with a SPECIAL voxel placed inside the knee did not show any 

fluorine signal, either due to non-absorption of the NSAID or the absorbed quantity was too 

low to be detected. 

Further improved in vivo experiments could be carried out using the dual tuned 
1
H/

19
F knee 

coil in the study of the effectiveness of penetration and action of NSAIDs within patients 

with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) in the knee. These experiments could be performed using 

two voxel, one inside and one outside the knee, for 
19

F spectroscopy, in healthy and RA 

patients for longer monitoring times.  



64 

 

8. REFERENCES 

[1] Rheumatoid arthritis, (2012). 

[2] S.B. Abramson, Mechanisms of action of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and 
therapeutic considerations., Bulletin of the Hospital for Joint Diseases Orthopaedic 
Institute. 50 (1990) 107–15. 

[3] C.A. Heyneman, C. Lawless-Liday, G.C. Wall, Oral versus topical NSAIDs in rheumatic 
diseases: a comparison., Drugs. 60 (2000) 555–74. 

[4] A.R. Brewer, B. McCarberg, C.E. Argoff, Update on the use of topical NSAIDs for the 
treatment of soft tissue and musculoskeletal pain: a review of recent data and 
current treatment options., The Physician and Sportsmedicine. 38 (2010) 62–70. 

[5] R. Buchbinder, Topical NSAIDs provide effective relief of acute musculoskeletal pain 
compared to placebo, with no increase in risk of adverse effects., Evidence-based 
Medicine. 15 (2010) 177–8. 

[6] L.S. Simon, Do topical NSAIDs work?, Nature Clinical Practice. Rheumatology. 4 
(2008) 458–9. 

[7] L. Mason, R.A. Moore, J.E. Edwards, S. Derry, H.J. McQuay, Topical NSAIDs for 
chronic musculoskeletal pain: systematic review and meta-analysis., BMC 
Musculoskeletal Disorders. 5 (2004) 28. 

[8] J.J. Escobar-Chávez, V. Merino-Sanjuán, M. López-Cervantes, Z. Urban-Morlan, E. 
Piñón-Segundo, D. Quintanar-Guerrero, et al., The tape-stripping technique as a 
method for drug quantification in skin., Journal of Pharmacy &amp;amp; Pharmaceutical 
Sciences?: a Publication of the Canadian Society for Pharmaceutical Sciences, 
Société Canadienne Des Sciences Pharmaceutiques. 11 (2008) 104–30. 

[9] A. Zesch, H. Schaefer, Penetration kinetics of four drugs in the human skin. 
Influences of various pharmaceutical vehicles on penetration in vitro., Acta 
Dermato-venereologica. 54 (1974) 91–7. 

[10] G.N.HOLLAND, P.A.B.W.S. HINSHAW, COMMUNICATIONS 19F Magnetic Resonance 
Imaging, Journal of Magnetic Resonance. 136 (1977) 133–136. 

[11] D.W. McRobbie, E.A. Moore, M.J. Graves, M.R. Prince, MRI from Picture to Proton, 
Cambridge University Press, 2007. 



65 

 

[12] J. Chen, G.M. Lanza, S. a Wickline, Quantitative magnetic resonance fluorine 
imaging: today and tomorrow., Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews. Nanomedicine and 
Nanobiotechnology. 2 (2010) 431–40. 

[13] F. Schick, Whole-body MRI at high field: technical limits and clinical potential., 
European Radiology. 15 (2005) 946–59. 

[14] J. Mispelter, M. Lupu, A. Briguet, Nmr Probeheads for Biophysical And Biomedical 
Experiments: Theoretical Principles And Practical Guidelines, Imperial College Press, 
2006. 

[15] M.A. Brown, R.C. Semelka, MRI: Basic Principles and Applications, Wiley, 2003. 

[16] F.D. Hockett, K.D. Wallace, A.H. Schmieder, S.D. Caruthers, C.T.N. Pham, S.A. 
Wickline, et al., Simultaneous dual frequency 1H and 19F open coil imaging of 
arthritic rabbit knee at 3T., IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging. 30 (2011) 22–7. 

[17] P. Suetens, Fundamentals of Medical Imaging, Cambridge University Press, 2009. 

[18] E.M. Haacke, R.W. Brown, M.R. Thompson, R. Venkatesan, Magnetic Resonance 
Imaging: Physical Principles and Sequence Design, Wiley, 1999. 

[19] R.R. Edelman, J. V. Crues, J.R. Hesselink, M.B. Zlatkin, Clinical Magnetic Resonance 
Imaging Online: Access to Continually Updated Online Reference, Elsevier Science 
Health Science Division, 2005. 

[20] D. Weishaupt, V.D. Köchli, B. Marincek, How does MRI work?: An Introduction to 
the Physics and Function of Magnetic Resonance Imaging, Springer, 2008. 

[21] J.T. Bushberg, J.A. Seibert, E.M. Leidholdt, J.M. Boone, The Essential Physics for 
Medical Imaging, (2002) 933. 

[22] J.P. Hornak, The Basics of MRI, Interactive Learning Software, Henietta, NY, n.d. 

[23] WebElements: the periodic table on the web, (n.d.). 

[24] R.Y. Kwong, Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging, Springer, 2008. 

[25] J.D. Jackson, Classical Electrodynamics, Wiley, 1998. 

[26] D.I. Hoult, The principle of reciprocity in signal strength calculations - A 
mathematical guide, Concepts in Magnetic Resonance. 12 (2000) 173–187. 

[27]  a M. Blamire, The technology of MRI--the next 10 years?, The British Journal of 
Radiology. 81 (2008) 601–17. 



66 

 

[28] M. V Knopp, Ultra-High Field Clinical Brain MR Imaging?: Challenge and Excitement, 
Proc. Intl. Soc. Mag. Reson. Med. 17 (2009) 2009. 

[29] R. Burgess, Magnetic Resonance Imaging at Ultrahigh Field: Implications for Human 
Neuroimaging, (2004) 237. 

[30] A. Lutti, F. Dick, M.I. Sereno, N. Weiskopf, Using high-resolution quantitative 
mapping of R1 as an index of cortical myelination., NeuroImage. (2013). 

[31] IEC 60601-2-33 ed3.0 - Medical electrical equipment - Part 2-33: Particular 
requirements for the basic safety and essential performance of magnetic resonance 
equipment for medical diagnosis, (2010). 

[32] P.A. Bottomley, Turning up the heat on MRI., Journal of the American College of 
Radiology?: JACR. 5 (2008) 853–5. 

[33] S. Webb, The Physics of Medical Imaging, CRC Press, 2010. 

[34] P.B. Roemer, W.A. Edelstein, C.E. Hayes, S.P. Souza, O.M. Mueller, The NMR phased 
array., Magnetic Resonance in Medicine?: Official Journal of the Society of Magnetic 
Resonance in Medicine / Society of Magnetic Resonance in Medicine. 16 (1990) 
192–225. 

[35] A. Ok, Design, Construction and Evaluation of a Flexible Carotid Coil for MRI at 7.0 T, 
2012. 

[36] A. Hassan, I. Elabyed, J. Mallow, T. Herrmann, J. Bernarding, A. Omar, Optimal 
geometry and capacitors distribution of 7T MRI surface coils, Microwave 
Conference (EuMC), 2010 European. (2010) 1437–1440. 

[37] M.A. Lopez, E. Al., Overlap Decoupling in Hole-Slotted Arrays, Int. Soc. Mag. Reson. 
Med. (2010). 

[38] J. Wang, A novel method to reduce the signal coupling of surface coils for MRI., 
Proc. Int. Soc. Mag. Reson. Med. 3 (1996) 1434. 

[39] J.J. Carr, Secrets of RF Circuit Design (Tab Electronics), McGraw-Hill/TAB Electronics, 
2000. 

[40] S.J. Orfanidis, Electromagnetic Waves and Antennas, (2008). 

[41] Building RF Surface Coils for MRI, (n.d.). 

[42] X. Hu, D.G. Norris, Advances in high-field magnetic resonance imaging., Annual 
Review of Biomedical Engineering. 6 (2004) 157–84. 



67 

 

[43] SPEAG, SEMCAD X Manual, 14.8.3 ed., Schmid &amp;amp; Partner Engineering AG, 2012. 

[44] I. Foundation, Virtual Family flyer, (n.d.). 

[45] L.I. Sacolick, F. Wiesinger, I. Hancu, M.W. Vogel, B1 mapping by Bloch-Siegert shift., 
Magnetic Resonance in Medicine?: Official Journal of the Society of Magnetic 
Resonance in Medicine / Society of Magnetic Resonance in Medicine. 63 (2010) 
1315–22. 

[46] V. Mlynárik, G. Gambarota, H. Frenkel, R. Gruetter, Localized short-echo-time 
proton MR spectroscopy with full signal-intensity acquisition., Magnetic Resonance 
in Medicine?: Official Journal of the Society of Magnetic Resonance in Medicine / 
Society of Magnetic Resonance in Medicine. 56 (2006) 965–70.  

 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>