<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.08545</field>
		<field name="filename">13389_Vasconcelos%2c%202016_Tese.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">iie^ lifelife-
i » »
UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE PERNAMBUCO CENTRO DE TECNOLOGIA E GEOCIÊNCIAS DEPARTAMENTO DE OCEANOGRAFIA PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM OCEANOGRAFIA
MACROALGAS MARINHAS COMO FERRAMENTA DE AVALIAÇÃO DO ESTADO DE CONSERVAÇÃO DE AMBIENTES RECIFAIS EM PERNAMBUCO
EDSON RÉGIS T. P. PINHO DE VASCONCELOS
MACROALGAS MARINHAS COMO FERRAMENTA DE AVALIAÇÃO DO ESTADO DE CONSERVAÇÃO DE AMBIENTES RECIFAIS EM PERNAMBUCO
EDSON RÉGIS T. P. PINHO DE VASCONCELOS
Tese de Doutorado apresentada ao Programa de Pós-graduação em Oceanografia da Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, como parte dos requisitos necessários à obtenção do título de Doutor em Oceanografia.
Orientadora: Dra. Mutue Toyota Fujii Co-orientador: Dr. Arsenio J. Areces Mallea
Catalogação na fonte Bibliotecária Valdicea Alves, CRB-4 / 1260
V331m Vasconcelos, Edson Régis T. P. Pinho de.
Macroalgas marinhas como ferramenta de avaliação do estado de conservação de ambientes recifais em Pernambuco / Edson Régis t. P. Pinho de Vasconcelos. - 2016.
133 folhas, il., e tabs.
Orientadora: Profa. Dra. Mutuê Toyota Fuji.
Coorientador: Prof. Dr. Arsenio José Areces-Mallea.
Tese (Doutorado) - Universidade Federal de Pernambuco. CTG. Programa de Pós-Graduação em Oceanografia, 2016.
Inclui Referências e Anexos.
1. Oceanografia. 2. Bentos. 3. Biodiversidade. 4. Índice de distúrbio ambiental. 5. Macroalgas. 6. Recifes costeiros. I. Fuji, Mutuê Toyota. (Orientadora). II. Areces-Mallea, Arsenio José (Coorientador). III. Título.
UFPE
551.46 CDD (22. ed.)
BCTG/2017-32
MACROALGAS MARINHAS COMO FERRAMENTA DE AVALIAÇÃO DO ESTADO DE CONSERVAÇÃO DE AMBIENTES RECIFAIS EM PERNAMBUCO
Tese apresentada ao Programa de Pós-Graduação em Oceanografia (PPGO), da Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, como parte dos requisitos para obtenção do grau de Doutor em Oceanografia na Área de Oceanografia Biológica.
Aprovada em 27/10/2016
BANCA EXAMINADORA
Dra. Mutue Toyota Fujii
(Instituto de Botânica - IBt-SP)
Dr. Fernando Antonio do Nascimento Feitosa
(Departamento de Oceanografia - UFPE)
Dr. José Souto Rosa Filho
(Departamento de Oceanografia - UFPE)
Dr. George Emmanuel Cavalcanti de Miranda (Departamento de Sistemática e Ecologia - UFPB)
Dr. Múcio Luiz Banja Fernandes
(Departamento de Ciências - UPE/FFPNM)
“Se vi mais longe foi por estar de pé sobre ombros de gigantes”
(Isaac Newton)
•y
A minha família e amigos
Agradecimentos
Ainda que o título de Doutor seja um título individual e as madrugadas de redação tenham sido longas e muitas vezes solitárias, esse trabalho não foi esforço apenas do autor, longe disso. Assim, tenho o prazer em reconhecer os preciosos colaboradores que contribuíram direta e indiretamente para a conclusão desse projeto.
Agradeço a Deus, por me dar condições de chegar onde estou, por ter uma família e amigos os quais posso contar em qualquer momento.
Aos funcionários do Departamento de Oceanografia - UFPE, em especial a Myrna, pela boa amizade e por resolver todas as "broncas" na secretaria. Aos coordenadores do PPGO, Dr. Jesser Fidelis Souza Filho e Dra. Tereza Araújo, pela oportunidade de realização do doutorado e doutorado sanduíche no exterior. Aos professores do PPGO, por ministrarem os conteúdos mais importantes da oceanografia, de uma forma amigável e didática. Em especial aos Professores Fernando Feitosa, Sigrid Neumann-Letão, José Souto e Jesser Fidelis, por acompanharem a evolução do projeto em avaliações de seminários e banca de qualificação. Aos demais servidores, que tornam o Departamento e o Museu de Oceanografia um bom local de trabalho.
Aos órgãos financiadores: FACEPE pela concessão da bolsa de Doutorado durante o período de trabalho. A CAPES pelo custeio do Doutorado Sanduíche no Exterior (PDSE). Ao CNPq pelo finamciamento dos trabalhos de campo através do Edital Universal.
Agradeço a disponibilidade dos Doutores titulares e suplentes que irão formar a banca de avaliação.
À orientadora Dra. Mutue Toyota Fujii, pela amizade, apoio e confiança em me orientar mais uma vez, nunca estando ausente ou omissa. Agradeço ao apoio e atenção na reta final, principalmente quando pensei estar à deriva. Gostaria de agradecer aos atos de cobrança e aos bons momentos tanto no ambiente de trabalho quanto fora dele. Foi um prazer colaborar com o grupo e que a parceria continue.
Aos amigos do laboratório. À Dra. Adilma, pelos momentos de alegria no laboratório, pelas dicas nos trabalhos e acima de tudo pela amizade e confiança. Ao Thiago, por todas as dicas de trabalho, ajuda nas coletas e pela boa amizade construída.
Ao Co-orientador e amigo Dr. Arsenio Areces, os anos que passou como professor visitante foram os mais proveitosos e divertidos, tanto no aspecto científico quanto no pessoal. Espero um dia desenvolver um pensamento científico crítico e profissional como o seu. Agradeço pela idealização do projeto e as preciosas colaborações nos trabalhos.
Aos colegas do lado de lá (Universidade dos Açores), que me receberam com muita atenção e carinho no perído do doutorado sanduíche no exterior. Agradeço a professora Dra. Ana Isabel Neto e ao Dr. Gustavo Martins por me orientarem nesse período e por se disponibilizarem em dar o curso aqui no DOCEAN.
Aos meus pais Reginaldo e Bertine, minha irmã Rochelly e a minha tia Glória (tia Gró), por serem pessoas que estiveram presentes nos momentos doces da conquista e nos momentos amargos da tristeza, por sempre acreditarem no meu potencial até quando eu mesmo desconfiava. Especialmente a minha mãe, Bertine, por ser um exemplo de fibra, dedicação e cumplicidade, tornando todo sacrifício válido para garantir o melhor para a nossa família.
Aos meus “irmãos” Emerson e Henrique, por suas inestimáveis amizades, companheirismo e bons momentos e aventuras que passamos juntos desde a saudosa infância.
À Juliane Bernardi, pela companhia, por toda cumplicidade, por todo amor que compartilhamos. Por sua colaboração em todas as fases dessa áruda caminhada, sem seu apoio durante os momentos difíceis não seria possível a conclusão deste trabalho.
A todos que ajudaram direta e indiretamente a realização e conclusão deste trabalho.
Resumo
Um dos ambientes marinhos mais estudados são as comunidades de recifes costeiros, pois possuem uma alta contribuição para a riqueza de espécies e, consequentemente, para a biodiversidade estrutural e funcional do ambiente marinho. No entanto, as atividades como pesca predatória, empreendimentos costeiros, turismo e crescimento urbano desordenado, podem levar à perda de espécies e simplificação do ambiente recifal. Assim, o objetivo desta tese foi aplicar o conhecimento da biodiversidade de macroalgas e a relação dos componentes dominantes como base para indicação do estado de conservação das macroalgas marinhas bentônicas e dos ambientes recifais no litoral do estado de Pernambuco. O trabalho foi realizado na região entremarés de 12 estruturas recifais (areníticas e coralíneos-algáceos) em um gradiente de urbanização do litoral de Pernambuco, com amostragens não destrutivas, no período entre novembro de 2013 a agosto de 2014. A tese foi dividida em quatro capítulos, de acordo com os seus respectivos objetivos e se encontram formatados na forma de publicações. O Capítulo I é uma análise das comunidades de macroalgas dos ambientes recifais da costa pernambucana, identificando os padrões de distribuição frente a gradiente de urbanização. O Capítulo II é uma classificação dos habitats recifais representativos da costa pernambucana através de variáveis em escala paisagística e geomorfológica, correlacionando com a comunidade fitobentônica. No Capítulo III descreveu-se a influência do nível de urbanização na modificação da estrutura (composição taxonômica, abundância, riqueza, diversidade, dominância e diversidade morfofuncional) das comunidades bentônicas na zona entremáres em Pernambuco. O Capítulo IV é um estudo de caso utilizando um índice numérico de distúrbio ambiental (IDA), como ferramenta de análise da qualidade dos ambientes costeiros, baseado nas frequências teóricas de macroalgas indicadoras, representativas dos respectivos habitats. Os recifes de Pernambuco foram classificados, segundo o grau de impacto antrópico nos seguintes status de conservação: Pristinos (São José da Coroa Grande, Campas, Serrambi, Paiva e Toquinho), Baixo Impacto (Enseada dos Corais, Mamucabas e Suape), Impactado (Boa Viagem e Piedade) e Muito Impactado (Pina). A urbanização tem um forte efeito sobre a estrutura de assembleias de macroalgas da região entremarés, destacando as espécies bioindicadoras Palisada perforata, Gelidiella acerosa e Caulerpa spp. como dominantes em locais Não Urbanizados (NU) e em Processo de Urbanização (UP), enquanto Chondracanthus acicularis, Bryopsis sp. e Ulva spp. dominaram locais com Urbanização Consolidada (UC). A classificação dos ambientes recifais levou à formação de três grupos de recifes baseados em atributos geomorfológicos, paisagísticos e cobertura vegetal (Biótopos), sendo eles: recifes de arenito com três subgrupos (Pina-Boa Viagem-Piedade; Toquinho-Enseada dos Corais; Suape); recifes coralíneos-algáceos com dois subgrupos (Campas-Serrambi-Mamucabas-Paiva; São José da Coroa Grande) e recifes mistos com um subgrupo (Carneiros). Considerando o gradiente de urbanização nos recifes de arenito, uma vez que a urbanização aumenta os impactos na região costeira, há a diminuição ou ruptura de padrões como a zonação vertical e suas interações ecológicas. Em conclusão, os ambientes recifais de Pernambuco são distintos, tanto em nível morfológico quanto paisagístico e as macroalgas respondem de forma diferente a essa variação, sendo os impactos causados pela urbanização fatores preponderantes na distribuição e estrutura da comunidade desses organismos, que podem ser representados numericamente através de um índice biótico, como o IDA.
Palavras-chave: bentos, biodiversidade, índice de distúrbio ambiental, macroalgas, recifes costeiros, zonação.
Abstract
One of the most studied marine environments is coastal reef communities, since they have a high contribution to the species richness and, consequently, to the structural and functional biodiversity of the marine environment. However, activities such as predatory fishing, coastal developments, tourism and disorderly urban growth can lead to loss of species and simplification of the reef environment. Thus, the objective of this thesis was to apply the knowledge of macroalgal biodiversity and their relation of the dominant components as a basis for indicating the state of conservation of the benthic marine macroalgae and the reef environments on the coast of Pernambuco state. This work was carried out in the intertidal region of 12 reef structures (sandstone and coralline-algal) at an urbanization gradient of the Pernambuco coastline, with non-destructive samplings between November 2013 and August 2014. This thesis was divided into four chapters, according to their respective objectives and writen in the form of scientific pappers. The Chapter I is an analysis of macroalgae communities of the Pernambuco coast reef environments, identifying the patterns of distribution relative to the urbanization gradient. Chapter II is a representative reef habitats classification of the Pernambuco coast through variables in landscape and geomorphological scale, correlating with the phytobenthic community. In Chapter III, the influence of urbanization level on the structure modification (taxonomic composition, abundance, richness, diversity, dominance and morphofunctional diversity) of benthic communities in the intertidal zone of Pernambuco reefs was described. Chapter IV is a study case using a numeric environmental disturbance index (IDA), as a tool for analyzing the environments coastal quality, based on the theoretical frequencies of indicator macroalgae, representative of the respective habitats. The Pernambuco reefs were classified according to the anthropic impact degree in the following conservation status: Pristine (São José da Coroa Grande, Campas, Serrambi, Paiva and Toquinho), Low Impact (Enseada dos Corais, Mamucabas and Suape), Impacted (Boa Viagem and Piedade) and Heavely Impacted (Pina). Urbanization has a strong effect on the structure of macroalgae assemblages of the intertidal region, highlighting the bioindicator species Palisada perforata, Gelidiella acerosa and Caulerpa spp. as dominant in Non Urbanized (UN) and Urbanization Process (UP), while Chondracanthus acicularis, Bryopsis spp. and Ulva spp. dominated sites with Consolidated Urbanization (UC). Reef environments classification led the formation of three reef groups based on geomorphological, landscape and vegetation cover (biotopes), being: sandstone reefs with three subgroups (Pina-Boa Viagem-Piedade; Toquinho-Enseada dos Corais; Suape); Coral-algal reefs with two subgroups (Campas-Serrambi-Mamucabas-Paiva; São José da Coroa Grande) and mixed reefs with one subgroup (Carneiros). Considering the urbanization gradient in sandstone reefs, since urbanization increases impacts on the coastal region, there is a decrease or rupture of patterns such as vertical zonation and its ecological interactions. In conclusion, the Pernambuco reef environments are distinct, both at the morphological and landscape level, macroalgae respond differently to this variation, and the urbanization impacts are predominant factors in the distribution and structure of the community of these organisms, which can be represented numerically through a biotic index, such as the IDA.
Keywords: Benthos, biodiversity, environmental disturbance index, macroalgae, coastal reefs, zonation.
Lista de Figuras
_	, | | Macroalgal responses to coastal urbanization: relative abundance of indicator
p________species_______________________________________________________________________
Sampling sites along with metropolitan and south sectors of coast of Pernambuco.
Relative abundance of macroalgae phyla. A: Macroalgae phyla relative abundance at different urbanization degrees: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC). B: Morpho-funtional groups and feed guilds relative abundance at different urbanization degrees: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC).
Abundance of Morfo-Functional Groups and feed guilds in response to urbanization degree: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC).
Principal Coordinates (PCO) plot. O Non Urbanized, ■ Urbanization Process and * Consolidated Urbanization. The vectors correspond to a multiple correlation &gt; 0.6 of macroalgae taxa: Ulv: Ulva spp., Chon: Chondracanthus acicularis, C.rac: Caulerpa recemosa and Sar: Sargassum sp; and Morpho-functional group and feed guilds: SI: Siphonous; FO: Foliose; CA: Canopy; CR: Cnidaria.
Figure 1
Figure 2
Figure 3
Figure 4
31
36
36
38
Capítulo II	Caracterização de topos recifais no litoral de Pernambuco, Brasil, a partir de atributos paisagísticos, variáveis geomorfológicas e composição da ficoflora intermareal	
Figura 1	Localização das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco, Nordeste do Brasil.	49
Figura 2	Agrupamento mostrando afinidades entre 20 formações recifais de Pernambuco com topos emersos atendendo a seis atributos paisagísticos. Média entre Grupos e Índice de Similaridade de Bray-Curtis. (PI = Pina; BO = Boa Viagem; EN = Enseada dos Corais; PIE = Piedade; PA = Paiva; MU = Muro Alto; ToI = Toquinho (interior); JA = Janga; CAM = Campas, Tamandaré; MAR = Maria Farinha; GU = Guadalupe; CAR = Carneiros; BA = Barra Sirinhaem; ToE = Toquinho (exterior); MAM = Mamucabas, Tamandaré; SU = Suape; SJ =São José da Coroa Grande; CU = Cupe; PO = Porto Galinhas; SE = Serrambi).	52
Figura 3	Distribuição e valores da carga fatorial correspondente aos atributos paisagísticos e às variáveis geomorfológicas nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco nos dois primeiros eigenvectors. INCL = Inclinação; ALT = Altura; RUG = Rugosidade; COMP = Comprimento; LARG = Largura; ORIENT = Orientação; DIST = Distância.	54
Figura 4	Distribuição no plano cartesiano de 36 transectos amostrados em doze formações recifais de Pernambuco. A separação mais significativa entre grupos foi determinada pelas variáveis Altura e Inclinação.	55
Figura 5	Distribuição no plano cartesiano segundo os dois primeiros eigenvectors de uma função discriminante dos grupos formados, atendendo ao fator Influência do aporte fluvial nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	57
Figura 6	Distribuição no plano cartesiano segundo os dois primeiros eigenvectors de uma função discriminante dos grupos formados, atendendo ao fator Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	58
Figura 7	Representação do escalonamento multidimensional (MDS) da comunidade algal presente em nove topos recifais de Pernambuco, de acordo com suas afinidades florísticas. Dados de frequência relativa transformados em Raiz quarta, Matriz de similaridade com índice de Bray-Curtis.	60
Figura 8
Figura 9
Figura 10
Figura 11
Figura 12
Figura 13
Figura 14
Influência da rugosidade sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.	62
Influência da inclinação da face externa do recife sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.	63
Influência da altura do recife em relação ao ponto zero da maré sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.	63
Influência da largura do recife sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.	64
Influência da Orientação dos transectos sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.	65
Afinidades existentes entre formações recifais do litoral pernambucano, em relação a elementos da estrutura física e a composição e abundância relativa da cobertura algal. GEO = Variáveis geomorfológicas; InfRios = Influência de aportes fluviais; Orient. = Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico.Denominação recifal segundo a Figura 2	66
Dissimilaridade entre 9 formações recifais de Pernambuco com topos emersos atendendo a cobertura fitobentônica. Média entre Grupos e Índice de Similaridade de Bray-Curtis. (EN = Enseada dos Corais; PA = Paiva; MU = Muro Alto; TO = Toquinho; CAM = Campas; CAR = Carneiros; MA = Mamucabas, Tamandaré; SU = Suape; SJ =São José da Coroa Grande; SE = Serrambi).	67
Capítulo III
Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco, Brasil
Representação gráfica do PCO. A) Análise baseada no descritor Grupo morfofuncional (GMF). B) Análise baseada no descritor Frequência dos táxons (TAX). Os diagramas em círculos representam vetores de correlação de Pearson (r&gt;0,04) para as variáveis. Filtrador (FL), Canópia (CA), Corticado folioso (CF), Calcário articulado (AC), Sifonáceo (SI) e Folioso (FO) para os grupos morfofuncionais. Palisada perforata (Pal), Laurencia dendroidea (Lau), Sargassum sp (Sar), Ulva
Figura 1 sp. (Ulv), Chondracanthus acicularis (Chon) e Bryopsis sp. (Bry).	83
Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) baseado na frequência de macroalgas
Capítulo IV indicadoras de processos antrópicos em regiões entremarés de estruturas recifais: estudo de caso no Nordeste brasileiro
Figura 1	Locais de amostragem na costa de Pernambuco (Nordeste do Brasil).	96
Figura 2	A. Praia de Enseada dos Corais, em detalhe a formação do tipo Recife de Arenito (RA). B. Praia de Campas (Tamandaré), em detalhe o recife com formação Coralíneo-Algáceo (CA).	99
Figura 3	Média do Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) de onze estruturas recifais no estado de Pernambuco (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).	103
Figura 4	Dissimilaridade representada no Cluster das localidades testadas com o IDA. (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).	104
Figura 5	Escalonamento multidimensional dos centroides dos fatores Tipo de recife e Nível de Urbanização. RA (Recife de Arenito), CA (Coralíneo-Algáceo), UC (Urbanização Consolidada), PU (Processo de Urbanização) e NU (Não Urbanizado).	105
Lista de Tabelas
Capítulo I	Macroalgal responses to coastal urbanization: relative abundance indicator species	of
Table 1	Types of urbanization degree according to proxy variables. and variables used to classify the locations near the reefs into Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC) in Brazilian Northeastern reef environments	33
Table 2	Macroalgae and their respective morphofunctional group and sessile animal feeding guild identified recorded at each reef urbanization category: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC)). The simbols (♦) and (-) denote presence and absence.	34
Table 3	Summary of PERMANOVA results for Pairwise test of Morpho-Functional Group and feed guilds that shown significant differences in abundance by urbanization degree levels.	37
Table 4	Results from the Permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA) between factors Time, Reef Formation, Urbanization Degree (NU = Non Urbanized, UP = Urbanization Process and UC = Consolidated Urbanization), that affect the macroalgae community on the Brazilian Northeastern reefs.	37
Table 5	Differences in abundance of major macroalgal species based on SIMPER analysis. The similarity amongst and dissimilarity among the analyzed factors (NU = Non Urbanized, UP = Urbanization Process and UC = Consolidated Urbanization).	38
Caracterização de topos recifais no litoral de Pernambuco, Brasil, a partir Capítulo II de atributos paisagísticos, variáveis geomorfológicas e composição da ficoflora intermareal
Formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco. Em negrito os recifes selecionados para análises em diversas escalas e em negrito e com asterisco (*), os escolhidos para associar a cobertura algal a diferentes características		
Tabela 1	paisagísticas e geomorfológicas	50
Tabela 2	Correlações significativas e valores de p associados a cada um, entre dois atributos paisagísticos e cinco variáveis geomorfológicas quantificadas em formações recifais da costa de Pernambuco.	53
Tabela 3	Análise de Componentes Principais das estruturas recifais. Eigenvalues de cada vetor e variabilidade acumulada.	53
Tabela 4	Estatísticas descritivas e matriz de confusão gerada por uma função discriminante empregada para a estimativa de elementos em cada uma das categorias dos atributos paisagísticos Influência do aporte fluvial (InfluRios) e Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico (Orientação) das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	56
Tabela 5	Verossimilhança estatística em pares (Distância de Fisher) e global (Prova de Lambda de Wilks com aproximação de Rao) na discriminação das quatro categorias do atributo paisagístico Influência do aporte fluvial das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	56
Tabela 6	Verossimilhança estatística em pares (Distância de Fisher) e global (Prova de Lambda de Wilks com aproximação de Rao) na discriminação das quatro categorias do atributo paisagístico Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico, das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	56
Tabela 7	Táxons de macroalgas bentônicas identificadas nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.	58
Tabela 8	Resultados da análise de Correspondência Fatorial para a distribuição das macroalgas das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco, de acordo com 22 condições diferentes de cinco variáveis geomorfológicas. A porcentagem de inércia refere-se ao primeiro vetor no caso da Orientação, e o acumulado dos dois primeiros vetores às variáveis restantes. Em destaque, as categorias mais influentes na distribuição das macroalgas. As espécies que	61
Análise de porcentagem de similaridade (SIMPER) evidenciando as algas que mais contribuem para formação dos biótopos nas formações recifais
Tabela 9 estudadas de Pernambuco.	67
Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades Capítulo III bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco,
Brasil		
Tabela 1	Grau de urbanização de acordo com variáveis usadas para as localidades próximas aos recifes amostrados. Não urbanizado (NU), Processo de urbanização (PU) e Urbanização Consolidada (UC).	78
Tabela 2	Lista dos organismos e os respectivos grupos morfofuncionais registrados na região entremarés dos recifes de arenito da costa de Pernambuco.	80
Tabela 3	Resumo da ANOVA considerando os fatores e níveis de urbanização (URB) e zonas entremarés (ZON).	81
Tabela 4	Resumo da PERMANOVA e PERMDISP considerando os fatores urbanização e zonas entre marés. Abundância relativa dos táxons (TAX) e Grupo morfofuncional (GMF).	82
Tabela 5	Correlação de (r) Pearson &gt;0,4 dos táxons de algas de Grupo morfofuncional (GMF) e os principais eixos da PCO.	84
Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) baseado na frequência de macroalgas
Capítulo IV indicadoras de processos antrópicos em regiões entremarés de estruturas recifais: estudo de caso no Nordeste brasileiro
Grau de urbanização de acordo com variáveis proxy usadas para classificar os locais adjacentes aos recifes em: Não urbanizada (NU), Em Processo de urbanização (PU) e Urbanização consolidada (UC) nos ambientes recifais do	
Tabela 1 Nordeste do Brasil.	95
Macroalgas conspícuas da zona entremarés de regiões recifais no Nordeste do Brasil. (+): táxons indicadores de regiões impactadas (Souza e Cocentino, 2004; Santos et al., 2006; Simões et al., 2009; Scherner et al., 2013; Tabela 2 Guimaraens et al., 2014; Portugal et al., 2016).	97
Valores de indicação (IndVal) para os táxons de macroalgas presentes em recifes de Urbanização Consolidada (UC) de Pernambuco. Em negrito, os Tabela 3 táxons indicadores de impactos, escolhidos para formação do índice.	100
Valores de indicação (IndVal) para os táxons de macroalgas presentes em recifes de arenito (RA) e coralíneos-algáceos (CA), existentes em zonas Não Urbanizadas (NU) e em Processo de Urbanização (PU) de Pernambuco. Em negrito, os táxons indicadores de ambientes com baixo impacto escolhidos Tabela 4 para formação do índice.	100
Frequência teórica dos táxons de regiões pristinas da costa de Pernambuco. Tabela 5 Em A recifes Coralíneos-Algáceos (CA), B recifes de Arenito (RA).	101
Resumo das Análises de variância (one way ANOVA), evidenciando as diferenças entre as localidades (LO) estudadas de acordo com o índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA). (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; Tabela 6 CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).	103
Sumário
Introdução geral.......................................................15
Ambientes recifais...................................................15
Impactos na região costeira..........................................17
Índices de Integridade...............................................17
Macroalgas e bioindicação............................................18
Hipótese...............................................................22
Objetivos..............................................................22
Geral................................................................22
Específico...........................................................22
Estrutura da tese......................................................22
ÁREA DE ESTUDO.........................................................23
Referências............................................................24
Capítulo I - Macroalgal responses to coastal urbanization: relative abundance
OF INDICATOR SPECIES...................................................28
1.	Introduction.....................................................30
2.	Material and Methods.............................................31
2.1.	Study area...................................................31
2.2.	Sa mpling design.............................................32
2.3.	Urbanization scale...........................................32
2.4.	Data analysis................................................33
3.	Results..........................................................34
4.	Discussion.......................................................39
References.............................................................40
Capítulo Il - Caracterização de topos recifais no litoral de Pernambuco, Brasil, a partir de atributos paisagísticos, variáveis geomorfológicas e composição da ficoflora intermareal............................................................44
1.	Introdução.......................................................45
2.	Materiais e Métodos..............................................47
2.1.	ÁREA DE ESTUDO...............................................47
2.2.	Localidades e características da amostragem..................47
2.3.	Processamento numérico da informação.........................50
3.	RESULTADOS...................................................... 51
3.1.	Características paisagísticas e morfológicas.................51
3.2.	Influência da estrutura física sobre a cobertura algal.......57
3.3. OS HABITATS E BIÓTOPOS PRESENTES NOS AMBIENTES RECIFAIS ESTUDADAS DE Pernambuco...............................................................65
4.	Discussão..............................................................68
Referências..................................................................70
Capítulo III - Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco, Brasil.74
1.	Introdução.............................................................76
2.	Materiais e Métodos....................................................77
2.1.	ÁREA DE ESTUDO.....................................................77
2.2.	Desenho amostral...................................................77
2.3.	Nível de urbanização...............................................78
2.4.	Análise dos dados..................................................79
3.	Resultados.............................................................79
4.	Discussão..............................................................84
Referências..................................................................87
Capítulo IV - Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) baseado na frequência de macroalgas indicadoras de processos antrópicos em regiões entremarés de estruturas recifais: estudo de caso no Nordeste brasileiro........................................91
1.	Introdução.............................................................93
2.	Materiais e Métodos....................................................94
2.1	Descrição da área..................................................94
2.2	Grau de urbanização................................................94
2.3	Desenho amostral...................................................95
2.4	IDA - ÍNDICE DE DISTÚRBIO AMBIENTAl................................96
3.	Resultados............................................................100
4.	Discussão.............................................................105
Referências.................................................................109
Conclusão Geral.............................................................114
ANEXOS......................................................................115
ANEXO I - DADOS...........................................................116
Anexo II - Normas editorias das revistas..................................120
Introdução geral
Ambientes recifais
A zona costeira é uma região ativa onde as ondas geradas pelo vento quebram-se e dissipam a sua energia. As marés arrastam a água sobre a orla dos continentes e os rios lançam mais sedimentos na costa. Por causa de sua proximidade tanto do oceano como da terra, essa região está sujeita a eventos naturais comuns a ambos os domínios (Garrison, 2015).
Por ser um local tão dinâmico e complexo, onde diversos fatores atuam sinergicamente influenciando os processos em diversas escalas, os ecossistemas existentes nessa região, como dunas, falésias, praias, estuários e recifes que possuem, em geral, uma alta biodiversidade (Beatley, 1991; Amaral &amp;amp; Jablonski, 2005; Garrison, 2015) que prestam diversos serviços ecológicos (Granek et al., 2010). Ao se tratar da zona costeira, a diversidade biológica de seus recursos tem importância não apenas na sua exploração direta com a finalidade de produção de alimentos, mas também em sua biodiversidade enquanto patrimônio cultural, genético, químico e ecológico, além da sua influência no clima do planeta (Norse, 1993).
Dentro dessa enorme diversidade de ecossistemas costeiros, os habitats bentônicos estão entre os mais produtivos do planeta, possuindo uma elevada biomassa e produção primária, pois recebem grande quantidade de nutrientes provenientes dos sistemas terrestres (Coutinho &amp;amp; Zalmon, 2009). Na região tropical se destacam cinco comunidades bentônicas: as praias, as restingas, os manguezais, os bancos de fanerógamos e os recifes (Barbier et al., 2011).
As comunidades marinhas bentônicas são caracteristicamente associadas à heterogeneidade dos substratos em variadas escalas. Muitas espécies estão associadas a um tipo particular de substrato (móvel ou fixo) em seus distintos estágios de vida, e as próprias comunidades podem produzir uma variedade de habitats (Munguia et al., 2011). Ao exemplo dos ambientes marinhos consolidados, os recifes são caracterizados por uma alta complexidade de substratos, importante principalmente para organismos fitais e sésseis (Danovaro &amp;amp; Fraschetti, 2002).
Os recifes podem ser concreções biogênicas ou ter origem geogênica. São substratos duros e compactos que se desenvolvem sobre fundos sólidos ou moles e se elevam do leito do mar nas zonas sublitorais e litorais. Os recifes podem sustentar uma estratificação das comunidades bentônicas de algas e de animais, bem como
concreções, que podem ser ou não coralogênicas (EC, 2013). Os ambientes recifais correspondem a cerca de 15% do fundo marinho entre 0 e 30 metros de profundidade, distribuídos por todo o planeta, entre a isoterma de 20°C dos hemisférios norte e sul (Villaça, 2002).
No Brasil, temos a ocorrência de ambientes recifais distintos, com destaque para os recifes da região Nordeste, que podem ser: de corais, de arenito ou os resultantes da erosão de falésias (Manso et al., 2006). Comunidades recifais coralíneas foram registradas no Brasil desde o Parcel de Manuel Luís, no Maranhão (cerca de 0°53’S, 44°16’W) até os recifes de Viçosa, na área de Abrolhos (cerca de 18°01’S, 39°17’W), além de ilhas oceânicas como Atol das Rocas e Fernando de Noronha. (Ferreira e Maida, 2006). Concomitante a esses recifes de corais, se encontram os recifes de arenito, situados entre os estados do Piauí e Sul da Bahia (Leão &amp;amp; Dominguez, 2000; Villaça, 2002; Baptista &amp;amp; Filho, 2014).
Diferentes dos recifes de corais do Caribe e da Grande barreira de coral australiana, os recifes de arenito do Nordeste do Brasil possuem características distintas quanto a gênese e estrutura. Laborel (1970) cita em seu trabalho sobre os recifes do Nordeste: a) diferenças entre recifes de arenito e de coral são claras e evidentes, uma vez que os primeiros têm uma formação distinta em fileiras paralelas, ligadas à evolução costeira no Holoceno; b) formações recifais observadas nos anos 60 já eram pobres, principalmente devido ao baixo número de espécies de corais hermatípicos e corais de fogo envolvidos na construção dos recifes; c) os recifes brasileiros destacam-se pelas espécies endêmicas de gorgônias, esponjas e corais (gênero Mussismilia) e, por outro lado, ausência de gêneros importantes no Caribe, como Acropora, Diploria, Colpophyllia, Solenastrea, Dendrogyra, Mussa, Mycetophyllia e outros; d) no Nordeste, a cobertura viva de corais era, na década de 60, em geral menor que 50%. O restante da superfície era principalmente coberto de algas coralíneas incrustantes, esponjas, gorgônias e densos tapetes de Halimeda. Em síntese, nunca foram observadas coberturas maiores que 50% nos recifes rasos do Nordeste (desde a superfície até profundidades de 20 m), nos quais a cobertura média de coral era de 25% (esta percentagem foi estimada, não calculada). As principais espécies construtoras, em ordem de importância são: algas coralíneas, Millepora alcicornis (Linneaus, 1758), Mussismilia hartii (Verril, 1868), Siderastrea (Blainville, 1830), Montastrea cavernosa (Linneaus, 1767) e Porites astreoides (Lamarck, 1816), com folhas de Halimeda (J.V. Lamouruoux, 1812) sendo a principal fonte de sedimento (Ferreira &amp;amp; Maida, 2006).
A importância dos recifes brasileiros, que ocupam uma área extensa ao longo de 3000 km da costa e são os únicos recifes de coral do Atlântico Sul, é tão grande quanto as ameaças que estes ecossistemas vêm sofrendo. No mundo todo, estima-se que a principal causa da degradação dos recifes de coral é o desenvolvimento crescente e acelerado das zonas costeiras e o excesso de exploração de seus recursos (Maida &amp;amp; Ferreira, 1997; Cesar et al., 2003; Ferreira &amp;amp; Maida, 2006).
Impactos na região costeira
A biodiversidade dos ecossistemas costeiros nas proximidades de grandes centros urbanos vem sendo ameaçada por tensores de origem antrópica, como sobre-exploração e destruição de habitat (Johnston &amp;amp; Roberts, 2009; Martins et al., 2012; Scherner et al., 2013). A região costeira está sujeita a uma infinidade de impactos antrópicos atribuídos à elevada ocupação da linha de costa, reduzindo a saúde dos ecossistemas presentes (Shanmugam et al., 2007; Halpern et al., 2012; Turra et al., 2013).
Esses ambientes, quando encontrados em regiões de crescimento urbano, são impactados, principalmente, pela alta taxa de sedimentação e o excesso de nutrientes que modificam a estrutura e a biodiversidade desses ambientes (Airoldi, 1998, Worm et al., 1999; 2003; Connell et al., 2008; Krause-Jensen et al., 2008). Muitas vezes, esses impactos levam à dominância de espécies oportunistas (Borowitzka, 1972), que colonizam o ambiente e acabam diminuindo a biodiversidade de uma área.
No Brasil, cerca de um quarto da população vive na região costeira, sendo a região Nordeste uma das mais densamente ocupadas. No estado de Pernambuco, aproximadamente 45% da população encontra-se no litoral (IBGE, 2011). Esta região é rica em substratos consolidados como recifes de arenito e recifes coralíneos-algáceos (Branner, 1904; Laborel, 1970; Dominguez et al., 1990; Castro &amp;amp; Pires, 2001;), abrigando elevada diversidade de organismos. Por essas características, as formações recifais constam como áreas estratégicas em programas de conservação e proteção ambiental (Roberts et al., 2002; Prates, Gonçalves &amp;amp; Rosa, 2012;).
Índices de Integridade
Há mais de três décadas, quando o monitoramento da qualidade da água era feito principalmente através de parâmetros físico-químicos, Karr (1981) desenvolveu um Índice de Integridade Biótica (Index of Biotic Integrity - IBI). Este índice era designado
para quantificar características das comunidades de peixes para avaliar a integridade biótica de rios. A “integridade biótica” pode ser definida como “a capacidade de manter uma comunidade de organismos equilibrada, integrada e adaptativa, possuindo diversidade e organização funcional semelhantes às áreas que conservam o habitat natural da região” (Karr &amp;amp; Dudley, 1981).
Os índices multimétricos constituem atualmente as ferramentas de avaliação biológica da integridade ecológica mais utilizados em programas de monitoramento de ecossistemas aquáticos em países como EUA, Alemanha, França e Áustria (Oberdorff et al, 2002; Haase et al, 2004; Whittier et al, 2007). A força da abordagem multimétrica está na habilidade de integrar informações dos vários aspectos de uma comunidade biológica para fornecer uma classificação geral da degradação, sem perder a informação proveniente das métricas individuais. O desenvolvimento desse tipo de índice é baseado na comparação entre áreas livres de influência humana, consideradas como referências, e áreas sujeitas a impactos da atividade humana (Oliveira, Castro &amp;amp; Baptista, 2008).
Como consequência do sucesso dos índices como o IBI, programas de biomonitoramento foram bastante empregados por órgãos governamentais em diversas regiões do mundo (Norris, 1995; Karr &amp;amp; Chu, 1999). Tais programas podem fornecer informações sobre regiões que necessitam maior fiscalização (ou proteção) e avaliar o quanto instrumentos de conservação (e.g. leis, programas de recuperação ambiental) estão produzindo resultados positivos (Melo &amp;amp; Hepp, 2008).
Os índices multimétricos são amplamente utilizados em diversos programas de biomonitoramento e vêm sendo adaptados e desenvolvidos em pequena escala em diversos locais que ainda não possuem programas efetivos de bioavaliação. Um bom índice multimétrico pode ser desenvolvido no tempo hábil de uma dissertação de mestrado e pode representar um princípio da iniciativa de programas de monitoramento e conservação da integridade de ecossistemas aquáticos (Oliveira, Castro &amp;amp; Baptista, 2008).
Macroalgas e bioindicação
Dentre a grande diversidade de organismos dos ambientes recifais, as macroalgas destacam-se por sua diversidade, cobertura e abundância. Estas possuem importância ecológica fundamental como produtoras primárias, fazendo parte da base da cadeia alimentar, além de fornecer habitat; refúgio e local de reprodução para
diversos organismos da biota marinha e desempenham o papel de bioconstrutores nas formações recifais (Pereira et al., 2002)
As macroalgas marinhas pertecem a três diferentes grupos, empiricamente diferenciados desde o século XIX de acordo com a coloração do talo: algas pardas (filo Ochrophyta, classe Phaeophyceae), algas vermelhas (filo Rhodophyta) e algas verdes (Filo Chlorophyta). No entanto, as diferenças desses filos envolvem características mais substanciais do que a cor do talo. Em adição a pigmentação, elas diferem consideravelmente em características ultraestruturais e bioquímicas, incluindo pigmentos fotossintetizantes, tipo de material de reserva, composição da parede celular, presença/ausência de flagelo, conexões entre células adjacentes e na estrutura do cloroplasto. Elas originam-se de diferentes processos evolutivos, endossimbiose primária em Rhodophyta e Chlorophyta (Reino Plantae) e endossimbiose secundária em Ochrophyta (Reino Chromista) (Delwiche, 2007; Reviers, 2010; Guiry &amp;amp; Guiry, 2015).
As macroalgas bentônicas interagem com outros organismos marinhos e com o ambiente físico-químico que as cercam. A sua distribuição consiste entre o topo da zona entremarés até a máxima profundidade adequada para fotossíntese. Os principais fatores ambientais que afetam diretamente as macroalgas são a luz, temperatura, salinidade, hidrodinamismo e disponibilidade de nutrientes. Entre as interações biológicas estão a competição com outras plantas e animais sésseis, herbivoria e predação. Os fatores individuais de crescimento, morfologia e reprodução são consequências resultantes de todos estes fatores combinados. Outros parâmetros biológicos como idade, fenótipo e genótipo, bem como sua história evolutiva, podem afetar a resposta desses organismos ao meio abiótico (Lobban e Harrison, 1994).
Independente do nível de complexidade ou posição na escala evolutiva, os integrantes da ficoflora expressam uma alta conectividade com o meio, gerando uma grande variedade de respostas a qualquer mudança ambiental. Por constituírem os primeiros níveis da cadeia trófica, tem importância adicional por representar a interface entre as comunidades biológicas e o meio físico-químico onde vivem. Uma vez que através de sua biomassa, transferem energia à toda teia trófica, os metais pesados e poluentes orgânicos persistentes (Areces et al., 2015).
A ampla gama de respostas que as macroalgas oferecem tem permitido usa-las como biomonitores de compostos tóxicos e elementos traços (González et al., 2005; Hédouin et al., 2011), de qualidade ambiental (Borowitzka, 1972; Fairweather, 1990; Soltan et al., 2001; Hillebrand et al., 2007), e inclusive para modelar as variações de biomassa de diferentes grupos funcionais diante das mudanças ambientais (Biber et al.,
2004). Nas últimas décadas houve um uso generalizado desses organismos em estudos de processos de eutrofização (Collado-Vides et al., 2007), e análise da tendência evolutiva de diversos ecossistemas marinhos (Gorostiaga &amp;amp; Diez, 1996; Curiel et al., 2004).
Partindo de um ponto de vista conceitual onde: 1) há aumento da riqueza e cobertura frente a distúrbios de moderada intensidade segundo Connell (1978); 2) ocorre a substituição de espécies sensíveis por outras oportunistas em comunidades bentônicas submetidas à contaminação orgânica (Pearson e Rosenberg, 1978); 3) há desaparecimento ou extinção local das macrófitas do habitat e substituição por outras espécies “oportunistas” melhores adaptadas às novas condições, a medida que se aumentam os distúrbios ambientais (Littler &amp;amp; Littler, 1984; Steneck e Dethier, 1994; Littler, Littler &amp;amp; Brooks, 2006;), têm-se a comprovação experimental que permite concluir que a eutrofização pode culminar em uma dominância desproporcionada de algumas espécies de macroalgas (Soltan et al., 2001). Outros distúrbios como sedimentação, turbidez, e aumento no nível de toxicidade presente na água, também constituem fatores significativos na desestabilização das comunidades fitobentônicas (Gorostiaga e Diez, 1996).
Baseado no contraste entre áreas pristinas, sem distúrbios antrópicos, e áreas com variados graus de impactos, o Quadro de Diretivas da Água europeu (WFD) demandou estudos em manejo de sistemas costeiros nos últimos 15 anos. Este conceito gerou expectativas de trabalho estimulando a formulação e criação de diversos índices quali-quantitativos (Juanes et al., 2008; Orfanidis, Panayotidis, Stamatis, 2001; 2003, Panayotidis, Montesanto, Orfanidis, 2004; Pinedo et al., 2007; Wells et al., 2007), baseados na composição e abundância do macrofitobentos (Schramm e Nienhuis, 1996).
Todos esses índices foram propostos como indicadores de estado para o monitoramento ambiental. Eles se baseiam nas mudanças das proporções relativas de grupos de organismos constituídos de acordo com a sua sensibilidade diante do gradiente de distúrbio (Grall e Glémarec, 1997). As estratégias adaptativas se manifestam de três maneiras distintas: 1) espécies r-estrategistas de curto ciclo de vida e pioneiras em sucessão ecológica; 2) espécies K-estrategistas competidoras de estágios sucessionais tardios com baixa taxa de crescimento e ciclos de vida mais longos; 3) espécies T - tolerantes ao distúrbio (Grime, 1977). Quando ocorre um distúrbio agudo, como durante um processo de contaminação orgânica severa, ocorre a transformação progressiva de uma determinada condição inicial, geralmente
caracterizada por alta biodiversidade, abundância e presença de espécies bentônicas bem adaptadas ao seu habitat, em uma conversão para um substrato homogêneo quase sem vida (Salen-Picard, 1983). Durante essa transformação os grupos altamente sensíveis são substituídos por r-estrategistas e/ou espécies tolerantes de primeira ou segunda ordem (Grall e Glémarec, 1997). Em geral, para macroalgas os estudos têm-se baseado na mudança das frequências relativas quando existem distúrbios de diferentes intensidades em seus habitats.
As mudanças ambientais ou as variações climáticas em uma escala de tempo grande, apesar de ocorrer em longo prazo e sem condições finais tão extremas, podem ser documentadas a partir da dinâmica anterior. Para isso, o local selecionado deverá constituir um habitat representativo ou distinto, sem tensores antrópicos aparentes, e o monitoramento deverá pressupor utilização de métodos preditivos, usados para detectar tendências e ciclos naturais (Areces et al., 2015).
A peculiaridade da costa pernambucana em possuir diversos habitats recifais com uma boa representatividade de ambientes, em um gradiente de urbanização bem definido, torna essa região propícia a estudos sobre os impactos da urbanização. Estes estudos podem ser feitos através da utilização de diversos modelos bioindicadores. Devido às características ecofisiológicas, as macroalgas foram concebidas como ótimos modelos para estudar o efeito da urbanização sobre as comunidades recifais em Pernambuco, ressaltando a importância do conhecimento dos grupos de estudo em ficologia na região (Laboratório de Macroalgas do Departamento de Oceanografia da Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, Laboratório de Ficologia do Departamento de Biologia da Universidade Federal Rural de Pernambuco e Departamento de Biologia da Universidade de Pernambuco).
Hipótese
A variabilidade natural da comunidade fitobentônica é alterada ao longo de um gradiente de urbanização.
Objetivos
GERAL
Aplicar o conhecimento da biodiversidade e a relação dos componentes dominantes como base para indicação do estado de conservação das macroalgas marinhas bentônicas e dos ambientes recifais do litoral do estado de Pernambuco.
ESPECÍFICO
•	Identificar os padrões de distribuição das macroalgas em um gradiente de urbanização;
•	Classificar os recifes do litoral pernambucano segundo variáveis geomorfológicas e paisagísticas correlacionando a comunidade fitobentônica;
•	Descrever a influência do nível de urbanização na modificação da estrutura (composição taxonômica, abundância, riqueza, diversidade, dominância e diversidade morfofuncional) das comunidades bentônicas dominadas por macroalgas na zona entremáres e evidenciar o efeito dos níveis de urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades;
•	Propor e validar o índice de distúrbio ambiental (I DA) como ferramenta de análise da qualidade dos ambientes costeiros recifais de Pernambuco.
Estrutura da tese
De acordo com os objetivos e os resultados obtidos ao longo da realização do presente estudo, esta tese foi dividida em quatro capítulos. Cada capítulo se refere a artigos científicos e seguem as normas de publicação das revistas escolhidas para publicação.
O Capítulo I é uma análise das comunidades algais dos ambientes recifais da costa pernambucana. Esse capítulo demonstra como o grau de urbanização pode afetar a distribuição das comunidades de macroalgas recifais.
O Capítulo II é uma classificação dos habitats recifais representativos da costa pernambucana através de variáveis em escala paisagística e geomorfológica, bem como as correlações dessas variáveis com o fitobentos.
O Capítulo III é a descrição da influência do nível de urbanização no padrão de distribuição vertical do fitobentos da zona entremarés em Pernambuco.
O Capítulo IV é um estudo de caso utilizando um índice numérico, baseado nas frequências teóricas de macroalgas indicadoras, representativo dos respectivos habitats.
ÁREA DE ESTUDO
O litoral pernambucano possui, aproximadamente, 187 km de linha de costa, limitando-se ao norte pela praia de Carne de Vaca, no município de Goiana, e ao sul pela praia de São José da Coroa Grande, no município de Barreiros, e está localizado entre as coordenadas 07°15’45’’ - 09°28’18’’S e 34°48’35’’ - 41°19’54’’O. A área estudada situa-se na faixa de clima Tropical Úmido do tipo As’ de acordo com a classificação de Koppen (1948). A área apresenta temperatura média do ar de cerca de 24°C, com mínima de 18°C e máximas de 32°C (CPRH, 2003). A precipitação média anual é em torno de 1720 mm, com precipitações abaixo de 100 mm, entre os meses de setembro e fevereiro (período seco) e acima de 100 mm, entre os meses de março a agosto (período chuvoso), sendo os meses de maio-junho-julho o trimestre mais úmido, e o mês de junho, comumente, o mais frio (FINEP/UFPE, 1990).
Na costa do estado ocorrem extensas formações recifais constituídas por embasamentos arenítico e arenítico ferruginoso, que afloram na maré baixa ou podem estar ligeiramente expostos acima do nível médio do mar, podendo em alguns locais, aparecer diretamente na face da praia (Dominguez et al., 1990; Pereira et al., 2002). Os recifes costeiros de Pernambuco ocorrem em faixas paralelas à linha de costa funcionando como um sistema natural de proteção e como substrato para macroalgas e diversos outros organismos marinhos (Guerra &amp;amp; Manso, 2004).
Referências
Airoldi, L. (1998). Roles of Disturbance, Sediment Stress, and Substratum Retention on Spatial Dominance in Algal Turf. Ecology, 79 (8), 2759-2770.
Airoldi, L. (2003). The effects of sedimentation on rocky coast assemblages. Oceanography and Marine Biology: an Annual Review, 41, 161-236.
Amaral, A.C.Z. &amp;amp; Jablonski S., (2005). Conservation of marine and coastal biodiversity in Brasil. Conservation Biology, 19 (3), 625-631.
Areces A.J., Cocentino, A.L.M., Reis, T.N.V., Vasconcelos, E.R.T.P.P., Guimarães-Barros, N.C. &amp;amp; Fujii, M.T. (2015). Las Macroalgas como Bioindicadoras da Calidad Ambiental y Cambios Climáticos. Guia Prática. Braz'lian Journal of Ecology, v. Especial, 1-64
Baptista, E.M.C., &amp;amp; FIlho, N.O.H. (2014). Relação dos recifes de arenito com a geomorfologia costeira do Litoral piauiense. Revista Geonorte, Ed. especial 4, 10, 140-145.
Barbier, E. B., Hacker, S. D., Kennedy, C., Koch, E. W., Stier, A. C., &amp;amp; Silliman, B. R. (2011). The value of estuarine and coastal ecosystem services. Ecological monographs, 81 (2), 169-193.
Beatley, T. (1991). Protecting biodiversity in coastal environments: introduction and overview. Coastal Management, 19(1), 1-19.
Biber, P. D., Harwell, M. A., &amp;amp; Cropper, W. P. (2004). Modeling the dynamics of three functional groups of macroalgae in tropical seagrass habitats. Ecological Modelling, 175(1), 25-54.
Borowitzka, M. A. (1972). Intertidal algal species diversity and the effect of pollution. Marine and Freshwater Research, 23(2), 73-84.
Branner J. C. (1904). The stone reefs of Brazil, their geological and geographical relations, with a chapter on the coral reefs. Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology, 44, 1-285.
Castro, C. B., &amp;amp; Pires, D. O. (2001). Brazilian coral reefs: what we already know and what is still missing. Bulletin of Marine Science, 69(2), 357-371.
Cesar, H., Burke, L., &amp;amp; Pet-Soede, L. (2003). The economics of worldwide coral reef degradation. Cesar Environmental Economics Consulting (CEEC). 24 p. Disponível em:&amp;lt;http://eprints.eriub.org/48/&gt;.
Collado-Vides, L., Caccia, V. G., Boyer, J. N., &amp;amp; Fourqurean, J. W. (2007). Tropical seagrass-associated macroalgae distributions and trends relative to water quality. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 73(3), 680-694.
Connell, J. H. (1978). Diversity in tropical rain forests and coral reefs. Science, 199(4335), 1302-1310.
Connell, S., Russell, B., Turner, D., Shepherd, A., Kildea, T., Miller, D., ... &amp;amp; Cheshire, A. (2008). Recovering a lost baseline: missing kelp forests from a metropolitan coast. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 360, 6372
Coutinho, R., &amp;amp; Zalmon, I.R. (2009). Bentos de costões rochosos. In: Pereira RC, Soares-Gomes A. (Orgs.). Biologia marinha. 2. ed. Rio de Janeiro: Interciência, 281-297.
CPRH. (2003). Companhia Pernambucana do Meio Ambiente. Diagnóstico Socioambiental Litoral Sul De Pernambuco. Recife.
Curiel, D., Rismondo, A., Bellemo, G., &amp;amp; Marzocchi, M. (2004). Macroalgal biomass and species variations in the Lagoon of Venice (Northern Adriatic Sea, Italy): 1981-1998. Scientia Marina, 68(1), 57-67.
Danovaro, R., &amp;amp; Fraschetti, S. (2002). Meiofaunal vertical zonation on hard-bottoms: Comparison with soft-bottom meiofauna. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 230, 159-169.
Delwiche, C. F. 2007. Algae in the warp and weave of life: bound by plastids. In: Brodie J, Lewis J (Orgs.). Unrevealing the algae: the past, the present and future of algal systematics. Boca Raton, FLorida: CRC Press, 7-20.
Dominguez, J.M.L., Bittencourt, A.C.S.P., Leão, Z.M.A.N. &amp;amp; Azevedo, A.E.G. (1990). Geologia do quaternário costeiro do Estado de Pernambuco. Rev. Brasil. Geociênc. 20: 208-215.
EC. (2003). Interpretation Manual of European Union Habitats, Version EUR25. EC, DGEnvironment, Brussels. Available Online: http://ec.europa.eu/environment/nature/info/pubs/paper_en.htm.
Fairweather, P. G. (1990). Sewage and the biota on seashores: assessment of impact in relation to natural variability. Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 14(2-3), 197-210.
Ferreira, B. P., &amp;amp; Maida, M. (2006). Monitoramento dos recifes de coral do Brasil. MMA, Secretaria de Biodiversidade e Florestas. 250p.
FINEP/UFPE, (1990). Carta geotécnica da cidade do Recife (sub-área Geologia/ Geologia de Engenharia), Relatório Final de Atividades. Recife.
Garrison, T. S. (2015). Oceanography: an invitation to marine science. Nelson Education.
González, M. E. C., Sosa, L., Moreira, A. R., Maya, H., Pérez, S., León, A. R., &amp;amp; Gómez, M. (2005). Concentración de arsénico en macroalgas de la Bahía De Cienfuegos, Cuba. Rev. Invest. Mar, 26(1), 2126.
Gorostiaga, J. M., &amp;amp; Diez, I. (1996). Changes in the sublittoral benthic marine macroalgae in the polluted area of Abra de Bilbao and proximal coast (Northern Spain). Marine Ecology Progress Series, 130, 157-167.
Grall, J., &amp;amp; Glémarec, M. (1997). Using biotic indices to estimate macrobenthic community perturbations in the Bay of Brest. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 44, 43-53.
Granek, E. F., Polasky, S., Kappel, C. V., Reed, D. J., Stoms, D. M., Koch, E. W., ... &amp;amp; Aswani, S. (2010). Ecosystem services as a common language for coastal ecosystem-based management. Conservation Biology, 24(1), 207-216.
Grime, J. P. (1977). Evidence for the existence of three primary strategies in plants and its relevance to ecological and evolutionary theory. American naturalist, 1169-1194.
Guerra, N.C. &amp;amp; Manso, V.A.V. (2004). Beachrocks (Recifes de Arenito). In: Eslinazi-Leça E, Neumann-Leitão S, Costa MF (Orgs.). Oceanografia um cenário tropical. Recife: Bagaço p. 109-130.
Guiry, M.D., &amp;amp; Guiry, G.M. (2015). AlgaeBase. Disponível em:&amp;lt;http://www.algaebase.org&gt;. Acesso em: 12 nov. 2015.
Haase, P.; Lohse, S.; Pauls, S.; Schindehütte, K.; Sundermann, A.; Rolauffs, P. &amp;amp; Hering, D. (2004). Assessing streams in Germany with benthic invertebrates: Development of a practical standardised protocol for macroinvertebrate sampling and sorting. Limnologica, 34 p. 349-365.
Halpern, B. S., Longo, C., Hardy, D., McLeod, K. L., Samhouri, J. F., Katona, S. K., ... &amp;amp; Rosenberg, A. A. (2012). An index to assess the health and benefits of the global ocean. Nature, 488(7413), 615-620.
Hédouin, L., Pringault, O., Bustamante, P., Fichez, R., &amp;amp; Warnau, M. (2011). Validation of two tropical marine bivalves as bioindicators of mining contamination in the New Caledonia lagoon: Field transplantation experiments. Water research, 45(2), 483-496.
Hillebrand, H., Gruner, D. S., Borer, E. T., Bracken, M. E., Cleland, E. E., Elser, J. J., ... &amp;amp; Smith, J. E. (2007). Consumer versus resource control of producer diversity depends on ecosystem type and producer community structure. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 104(26), 10904-10909.
IBGE (2010). Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística. Produção da Pecuária Municipal. Censo Demográfico 2010 - Características da População e dos Domicílios. 39, 1 - 63.
Johnston, E. L., &amp;amp; Roberts, D. A. (2009). Contaminants reduce the richness and evenness of marine communities: a review and meta-analysis. Environmental Pollution, 157(6), 1745-1752.
Juanes, J. A., Guinda, X., Puente, A., &amp;amp; Revilla, J. A. (2008). Macroalgae, a suitable indicator of the ecological status of coastal rocky communities in the NE Atlantic. Ecological indicators, 8(4), 351-359.
Karr, J. R. (1981). Assessment of biotic integrity using fish communities. Fisheries, v. 6, p. 21-27.
Karr, J. R. &amp;amp; Dudley, D. R. (1981). Ecological perspective on water quality goals. Environmental Management, v. 5, p. 55-68.
Karr, J. R. &amp;amp; Chu, E. W. (1999). Restoring life in running waters: better biological monitoring. Island Press. Washington, DC, USA. p. 206.
Koppen, W. (1948). Climatologia: con un estudio de los climas de la tierra. Fondo de Cultura Econômica. México. p 479.
Krause-Jensen, D., Sagert, S., Schubert, H., &amp;amp; Bostrom, C. (2008). Empirical relationships linking distribution and abundance of marine vegetation to eutrophication. Ecological Indicators, 8(5), 515-529.
Laborel, J. (1970). Les peuplements de madréporaires des cotes tropicales du Brésil. Annales de LUniversité d'Abidjan, 2 (3), 260.
Leão, Z.M.A.N., &amp;amp; Dominguez, J.M.L. (2000). Tropical coast of Brazil. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 41(1), 112122.
Littler, M. M., &amp;amp; Littler, D. S. (1984). Relationships between macroalgal functional form groups and substrata stability in a subtropical rocky-intertidal system. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 74(1), 13-34.
Littler, M. M., Littler, D. S., &amp;amp; Brooks, B. L. (2006). Harmful algae on tropical coral reefs: bottom-up eutrophication and top-down herbivory. Harmful algae,5(5), 565-585.
Lobban, C.S., &amp;amp; Harrison, P.J. (1994). Morphology, life histories and morphogenesis. In: Lobban CS, Harrison PJ (Orgs.). Seaweed ecology and physiology. Cambridge University Press. p. 68.
Maida, M. &amp;amp; Ferreira, B.P. (1997). Coral reefs of Brazil an overview. 263-274.
Manso, V. A. V., Coutinho, P. N., Guerra, N.C., &amp;amp; Soares, C. F. A. (2006). Pernambuco. In: D. Muehe (Ed), Erosão e Progradação no Litoral Brasileiro (pp.179-196), Ministério do Meio Ambiente Brasil, Brasília.
Martins, C. D., Arantes, N., Faveri, C., Batista, M. B., Oliveira, E. C., Pagliosa, P. R., &amp;amp; Horta, P. A. (2012). The impact of coastal urbanization on the structure of phytobenthic communities in southern Brazil. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 64(4), 772-778.
Melo, A. S. &amp;amp; Hepp, L. U. (2008). Ferramentas estatísticas para análise de dados provenientes de biomonitoramento. Oecologia, 12(3), 463-486.
Munguia, P., Osman, R. W., Hamilton, J., Whitlatch, R., &amp;amp; Zajac, R. (2011). Changes in habitat heterogeneity alter marine sessile benthic communities. Ecological Applications, 21(3), 925-935.
Norris, R. H. (1995). Biological monitoring: the dilemma of data analysis. Journal of the North American Benthological Society, 14, 440-450.
Norse, E.A. (1993). Global marine diversity: a strategy for buidilng conservation. Washington: Island Press. p 383.
Oberdorff, T.; Pont, D.; Hugueny, B. &amp;amp; Porcher, J. P. (2002). Development and validation of a fish-based index for the assessment of 'river health' in France. Freshwater Biology, 47, 1720-1734.
Oliveira, R. B. S.; Castro, C. M. &amp;amp; Baptista, D. F. 2008. Desenvolvimento de índices multimétricos para utilização em programas de monitoramento biológico de integridade de ecossistemas aquáticos. Oecologia brasiliensis, 12 (3), 487-505.
Orfanidis, S., Panayotidis, P., &amp;amp; Stamatis, N. (2001). Ecological evaluation of transitional and coastal waters: a marine benthic macrophytes-based model. Mediterranean Marine Science, 2(2), 45-66.
Orfanidis, S., Panayotidis, P., &amp;amp; Stamatis, N. (2003). An insight to the ecological evaluation index (EEI). Ecological indicators, 3(1), 27-33.
Panayotidis, P., Montesanto, B., &amp;amp; Orfanidis, S. (2004). Use of low-budget monitoring of macroalgae to implement the European Water Framework Directive. Journal of Applied Phycology, 16(1), 49-59.
Pearson, T. H., &amp;amp; Rosenberg, R. (1978). Macrobenthic succession in relation to organic enrichment and pollution of the marine environment. Oceanogr. Mar. Biol. Ann. Rev, 16, 229-311.
Pereira, S. M. B.; Oliveira-Carvalho, M. F.; Angeiras, J. A. P; Bandeira-Pedrosa, M. E.; Oliveira, N. M. B.; Torres, J, Gestinari, L. M. S.; Cocentino, A. L. M., Santos, M. D, Nascimento, P. R. F. &amp;amp; Cavalcanti D. R. (2002). Algas marinhas bentônicas do Estado de Pernambuco. In: M. Tabarelli &amp;amp; J. M. C. Silva (Ed.). Diagnóstico da Biodiversidade de Pernambuco (pp. 97-124). Recife: Editora Massangana.
Pinedo, S., García, M., Satta, M. P., De Torres, M., &amp;amp; Ballesteros, E. (2007). Rocky-shore communities as indicators of water quality: a case study in the Northwestern Mediterranean. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 55(1), 126-135.
Prates, A.P.L., Gonçalves, M.A., &amp;amp; Rosa, M.R. (2012). Panorama da Conservação dos Ecossistemas Costeiros e Marinhos no Brasil. 2. ed. Brasília: MMA. 152 p.
Reviers, B. (2010). Natureza e posição das “algas” na árvore filogenética do mundo vivo. In: Franceschini IM et al. (Orgs.). Biologia e Filogenia das Algas. Porto Alegre: Artmed. 19-57.
Roberts, C. M., McClean, C. J., Veron, J. E., Hawkins, J. P., Allen, G. R., McAllister, D. E., ... &amp;amp; Vynne, C. (2002). Marine biodiversity hotspots and conservation priorities for tropical reefs. Science, 295(5558), 12801284.
Salen-Picard, C. (1983). Schémas d'évolution d'une biocénose macrobenthique de substrat meuble. Comptes rendus des seances de l'Academie des Sciences. Serie III. Sciences de la Vie, 296, p. 587-590.
Scherner, F., Horta, P.A., de Oliveira, E.C., Simonassi, J.C., Hall-Spencer, J.M., Chow, F., Nunes, J.M.C. &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B. (2013). Coastal urbanization leads to remarkable seaweed species loss and community shifts along the SW Atlantic. Marine Pollution Bulletin 76, 106-115.
Schramm, W., &amp;amp; Nienhuis, P. (Eds.). (1996). Marine benthic vegetation: recent changes and the effects of eutrophication (No. 123). Springer Science &amp;amp; Business Media, Germany. 480p.
Shanmugam, P., Neelamani, S., Ahn, Y. H., Philip, L., &amp;amp; Hong, G. H. (2007). Assessment of the levels of coastal marine pollution of Chennai city, Southern India. Water Resources Management, 21(7), 1187-1206.
Soltan, D., Verlaque, M., Boudouresque, C. F., &amp;amp; Francour, P. (2001). Changes in macroalgal communities in the vicinity of a Mediterranean sewage outfall after the setting up of a treatment plant. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 42(1), 59-70.
Steneck, R. S., &amp;amp; Dethier, M. N. (1994). A functional group approach to the structure of algal-dominated communities. Oikos, 476-498.
Turra, A., Croquer, A., Carranza, A., Mansilla, A., Areces, A. J., Werlinger, C., ... &amp;amp; Scarabino, F. (2013). Global environmental changes: setting priorities for Latin American coastal habitats. Global change biology, 19(7), 1965-1969.
Villaça, R. (2002). Recifes Biológicos. In: Pereira RC, Soares-Gomes A (Orgs.). Biologia marinha. Rio de Janeiro: Interciência, 1, 229-248.
Wells, E., Wilkinson, M., Wood, P., &amp;amp; Scanlan, C. (2007). The use of macroalgal species richness and composition on intertidal rocky seashores in the assessment of ecological quality under the European Water Framework Directive. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 55(1), 151-161.
Whittier, T. R.; Hughes, R. M.; Stoddard, J. L.; Lomnicky, G. A.; Peck, D. V.; Herlihy, A. T. (2007). A structured approach for developing indices of biotic integrity: Three examples from streams and rivers in the western USA. Transactions of the American Fisheries Society, 136 p. 718-735.
Worm, B., Lotze, H. K., Bostrom, C., Engkvist, R., Labanauskas, V., &amp;amp; Sommer, U. (1999). Marine diversity shift linked to interactions among grazers, nutrients and propagule banks. Marine Ecology Progress Series,185, 309-314.
Capítulo I - Macroalgal responses to coastal urbanization:
RELATIVE ABUNDANCE OF INDICATOR SPECIES
A SER SUBMETIDO À REVISTA MARINE ENVIRONMENTAL RESEARCH (ISSN: 0141 -1136)
Abstract
This study aimed to evaluate and compare the intertidal macroalgae community from reef structures, subject to different urbanization degrees. Samplings were made in 11 beaches from the Pernambuco coast, northeastern Brazil. The sites were classified according to the level of urbanization into three classes of increasing urbanization pressure: Non Urbanized (NU), in Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC). Macroalgae were identified in situ non-destructively. A total of 53 taxa were identified, 41 of these were macroalgae. Significant differences were observed in the composition of macroalgae according to the urbanization levels, with Palisada perforata, Gelidiella acerosa and Caulerpa spp. dominating NU and UP sites, whereas Chondracanthus acicularis, Bryopsis sp. and Ulva spp. dominated UC sites. This work shows that urbanization can have a strong effect on the structure of rocky intertidal macroalgal assemblages and highlights some macroalgae species that can be used as bioindicators for assessing the impact of urbanization on coastal shores.
Keywords: Coast occupation, bioindicators, phytobenthos, coastal reefs.
1.	Introduction
Nearly a quarter of the Brazilian population lives on the coastal zone, being the Northeastern region one of the most densely occupied. This region is rich in consolidated substrates (Branner, 1904; Laborel, 1969; Dominguez et al., 1990; Castro &amp;amp; Pires, 2001), supporting a rich benthic biodiversity. The reefs in urban areas are highly susceptible to anthropogenic impacts such as elevated sedimentation rates and nutrient run-off that can modify the structure and diversity of these ecosystems (Worm et al., 1999; Airoldi, 2003; Connell et al., 2008; Krause-jensen et al., 2008; Goatley &amp;amp; Bellwood, 2013). These impacts generally lead to the establishment and dominance of opportunistic species (Borowitzka, 1972), which may boost low levels of diversity.
Biodiversity of coastal ecosystems close to large urban centers is often affected by several anthropic pressures, like pollution (Johnston &amp;amp; Roberts, 2009; Martins et al., 2012), overexploitation, habitat destruction and climate change (Scherner et al., 2013) which, cumulatively, can lead to the degradation of these productive ecosystems Shanmugam et al., 2007; Halpern et al., 2012; Turra et al., 2013). For instance, there is great concern about the widespread loss of canopy-forming algae from many rocky coastlines and how it may be related to urbanization (Benedetti-Cecchi et al., 2001, Airoldi &amp;amp; Beck, 2007; Connell et al., 2008).
Macroalgae play a fundamental ecological role as primary producers, by providing sheltering, nursery grounds and substrate for a diverse assemblage of species (Schiel, 2006). Many algal species (i.e. canopy-forming algae) are commonly recognized as key for ecosystem engineers as they play an important structuring role in intertidal communities (Davison &amp;amp; Pearson, 1996). As many other organisms, however, macroalgae are exposed to several disturbances of both natural and human origins. Intertidal macroalgal assemblages generally respond rapidly to those disturbances, as they are regularly exposed to potential stressful conditions, such as nutrient limitation, temperature range, desiccation, osmotic pressure variations and anthropic contaminants (Areces, 2001; Scherner et al., 2013).
The effects of anthropogenic disturbances on the phycoflora can result in changes of dominance, specific composition of assemblages, and variations in the distribution patterns. Some macroalgal groups are particularly susceptible to anthropogenic disturbances. For instance, the canopy-forming Cystoseira spp. has been shown to decline and replaced by turf-forming species with increasing anthropogenic pressure along the Mediterranean (i.e. Benedetti-Cecchi et al., 2001). Canopies are important macroalgae and their loss has led to long-term changes in structure and functioning of benthic communities, with consequences reaching far up the food chain
(Tait &amp;amp; Schiel, 2011). Thus, this study aimed to evaluate and compare the structure of intertidal reef macroalgal assemblages affected by different levels of coastal urbanization.
2.	Material and M ethods
21. Study area
The Pernambuco coast comprises 187 km long (7°32’52” S 34°50’27” W and 8°54’57” S, 35°09’76” W) and it is located in the Tropical Southwest Atlantic biogeographic province and Brazil’s Northeastern ecoregion (Fig. 1) (Spalding et al.,
2007). The local climate is classified as humid tropical (As’) (Koppen, 1948), with average annual temperatures ranging between 25°C (minimum) and 30°C (maximum) (CPRH, 2003). The region has a semidiurnal tidal regime, with a predominant E-SE swell, and an average superficial sea temperature between 27-29°C (Manso et al.,
2006). The Pernambuco coastal area represents only 4% of the state territory; however, it hosts 46% of the Pernambuco population, figuring the second most densely populated city of the Brazilian coast (IBGE, 2010). The Pernambuco coastal reefs are basically rocky bodies composed mostly by quartz sand grains, cemented by calcium carbonate. These reef formation are abundant in the northeastern Brazilian coast (Branner, 1904; Laborel, 1969; Dominguez et al., 1990).
8° 06' S
8° 24' S
São José da Coroa Grande
(Praia do Paiva
'Enseada dos Corais
Suape
8° 42' S
20
i s
oww
íwíé
^^FToquinho
-------
^^^^¿Tamandaré
^w(Campas)
Tamandaré
(Mamucabas)
w
Figure. 1. Sampling sites along with metropolitan and south sectors of coast of Pernambuco.
2.2.	Sampling design
Non-destructive samplings were performed in 11 sampling sites, all reefs located on the metropolitan and south sectors of Pernambuco coast (8°5'18.14"S, 34°52'44.31" W and 8°54'16.59"S, 35° 8'16.26"W) (ITEP, 2012). (Authorization for activities with scientific purpose, number 44046-2, emitted by the Federal agency, Ministério do Meio Ambiente, Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade).
The 11 reefs were classified according to the human occupation levels and population density based on urbanization criteria (Projeto Orla, 2002). This classification was achieved using a combination of field visits and consulting demographic data (IBGE, 2010), local technical reports (SNIS, 2011) and processing remote sensing images (Google Earth®, 2013). Demographic surveys were made in each sector until one kilometer away of the sampling site in both directions parallel to the shore, and locations were accordingly classified into three levels of urbanization: non urbanized coast (NU), coast in urbanization process (UP) and consolidated urbanization coast (UC).
The “Line Point Transect” (Ambrose, 2002) was the method used to quantify the relative abundance of species in the macroalgae community. In this non-destructive method, the observer records in situ the species present in previously defined points at the lowest level (naked eye). Macroalgae were later assigned to a morpho-functional group (MFG) (adapted from Steneck &amp;amp; Dethier, 1994; Benedetti-Cecchi, 2001; Balata et al., 2011), to each sessile invertebrate a feeding guild (FG) was assigned (Paine, 1980). A total of seven transects of 10 m each, perpendicular to the coastline were done in each reef, starting at the lowest shore levels of the intertidal region. In each transect, we recorded the benthic sessile organism present every 10 cm.
To assess temporal generality of the results, each reef was sampled twice (November 2013 until February 2014 and between May 2014 and August 2014).
2.3.	Urbanization scale
The variables used to classify the scale of environmental stress in the sampling sites are in according to the urbanization degrees and they are listed on Table 1. The beaches Pina, Boa Viagem and Piedade were classified as UC urbanization degree, due to its high demographic density, with over than 500 inhab.km-2, over 85% of occupied residences and, in Piedade, only 6.9% of the sewage are collected. Enseada dos Corais, Suape, Serrambi, Tamandaré (Campas) and São José da Coroa Grande beaches were classified as UP for its urbanization degree. Those beaches had demographic densities
Table 1. Types of urbanization degree according to proxy variables. and variables used to classify the locations near the reefs into Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC) in Brazilian Northeastern reef environments.
Location	Urbanization degree	Demographic density (inhab.km-2)1	Population (inhab.)i	Occupied residences	Sewage collected 2	Coordinates
Pina	UC	&gt;500	29,176	86.4%	35.5 %	(8.08804 S, 34.87887 W)
Boa Viagem	UC	&gt;500	122,922	86%	35.5 %	(8.12451 S, 34.89583 W)
Piedade	UC	&gt;500	64,503	89.4%	6.9%	(8.17715 S, 34.91479 W)
Paiva	NU	10.1 to 15	421	22.1%	8.8%	(8.27993 S, 34.94484 W)
Enseada dos	UP	250.1 to 500	3,700	29.1%	8.8%	(8.31891 S,
Corais						34.94822 W)
Suape	UP	100.1 to 250	1,631	54.9%	8.8%	(8.37005 S, 34.94938 W)
Serrambi *	UP	20.1 to 50	80,637	76.8%	-	(8.56313 S, 35.00510 W)
Toquinho *	NU	100.1 to 250	80,637	76.8%	-	(8.56885 S, 35.03069 W)
Tamandaré	UP	100.1 to 250	20,715	47.4%	3.9%	(8.74357 S,
(Campas) 3 *						35.07965 W)
Tamandaré	NU	5.1 to 10	20,715	47.4%	3.9%	(8.78626 S,
(Mamucabas) 3 *						35.09741 W)
São José da	UP	250.1 to 500	18.18	60.8%	-	(8.90432 S,
Coroa Grande 3 *						35.1377 1W)
1	Source: Atlas from 2010 Demographic Census (IBGE, 2010).
2	Source: 2011 Water and Sewage Services Diagnosis (SNIS, 2011).
3	Environmental Protection Areas.
* Demographic data from all city sectors (IBGE, 2010).
2.4.	Data analysis
Prior to analyses, data were transformed into relative abundance (Ra® = N(i)/Ta), were Ra© is the taxa frequency, N® is the number of times the taxa showed up on the sample and Ta is the amount of points occupied by macroalgae on the transect. The tested hypothesis was: macroalgae dominance patterns differs and varies according to the level of urbanization.
A 2-way permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA) with the factors: “Urbanization” (fixed, 3 levels) and “Time” (random, 2 levels) was performed. The morpho-functional group/feeding guild (MFG/FG) was used as an indicator (10 levels) and was compared using PERMANOVA with the factor urbanization (3 levels). Analyses were performed on fourth-root transformed data by using the Bray-Curtis similarity coefficient. The similarity percentage analysis (SIMPER) was used to highlight
3.	Results
A total of 100 transects were obtained across the 11 sampled reefs, where 51 taxa were identified including 24 Rhodophyta, 11 Chlorophyta and 6 Ochrophyta, and sessile animals as Porifera, Annelida, Mollusca (2), Cnidaria (3), Echinodermata and Arthropoda. The macroalgae and their respective MFG/FG identified according to the degree of urbanization are shown in Table 2.
Table 2. Macroalgae and their respective morphofunctional group and sessile animal feeding guild identified recorded at each reef urbanization category: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC)). The simbols (♦) and (-) denote presence and absence.
Macroalgae		Morpho-Functional Group	MFG/FG	Non Urbanized	Urbanization Process	Consolidated Urbanization
	Anadyomene J.V.Lamouroux	Foliose	FO	♦	♦	-
	Bryopsis sp. J.V.Lamouroux	Siphonous	SI	♦	♦	♦
	Caulerpa racemosa (Forsskal) J.Agardh	Siphonous	SI	-	♦	♦
	Caulerpa cupressoides (Vahl) C.Agardh	Siphonous	SI	♦	-	♦
-2 _c Q_ O O _c Q	Chaetomorpha antennina (Bory de Saint-Vincent)	Filamentous	FI	♦	♦	
	Kutzing Cladophora Kutzing	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
	Dictyosphaeria Decaisne	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	-
	Halimeda J.V.Lamouroux	Articulated Calcareous	AC	♦	♦	-
	Rhizoclonium Kutzing	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
	Ulva lactuca Linnaeus	Foliose	FO	♦	♦	♦
	Ulva lingulata A.P.de Candolle	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
	Chnoospora J.Agardh	Canopy	CA	-	♦	-
	Dictyopteris delicatula	Corticated	CF		♦	♦
ro _c Q_ O _C O o	J.V.Lamouroux	Foliose				
	Dictyota J.V.Lamouroux	Corticated Foliose	CF	-	♦	♦
	Ectocarpales C.E.Bessey	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
	Padina Adanson	Corticated Foliose	CF	♦	♦	-
	Sargassum C.Agardh	Canopy	CA	♦	♦	♦
Rhodophyta	Acanthophora spicifera (M.Vahl) Borgesen	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
	Amansia J.V.Lamouroux	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
	Bryothamnion seaforthii (Turner) Kutzing	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Bryothamnion triquetrum (S.G.Gmelin) M.A.Howe	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	-
Corallinaceae J.V.Lamouroux	Articulated Calcareous	AC	-	♦	♦
Centroceras clavulatum (C.Agardh) Montagne	Filamentous	FI	♦	♦	♦
Ceramiaceae Dumortier	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	♦
Chondracanthus acicularis (Roth) Fredericq.	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Corallina Linnaeus	Articulated Calcareous	AC	♦	-	♦
Cryptonemia seminervis (C.Agardh) J.Agardh	Corticated	CO	-	♦	♦
Digenea simplex (Wulfen) C.Agardh	Corticated	CO	-	♦	-
Gelidiella acerosa (Forsskál) Feldmann &amp;amp; G.Hamel	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Gelidiopsis F.Schmitz	Corticated	CO	♦	-	♦
Gelidium J.V.Lamouroux	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Gracilaria Greville	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Hypnea musciformis (Wulfen) J.V.Lamouroux	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Jania J.V.Lamouroux	Articulated Calcareous	AC	♦	♦	-
Laurencia dendroidea	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
J.Agardh Laurencia translucida	Corticated	CO		♦	
M.T.Fujii &amp;amp; Cordeiro-Marino					
Palisada flagellifera (J.Agardh) K.W.Nam	Corticated	CO	♦	-	-
Palisada furcata (Cordeiro- Marino &amp;amp; M.T.Fujii) Cassano &amp;amp; M.T.Fujii	Corticated	CO	-	♦	♦
Palisada perforata (Bory de Saint-Vincent) K.W.Nam	Corticated	CO	♦	♦	♦
Polysiphonia Greville	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
Wrangelia C.Agardh	Filamentous	FI	-	♦	-
“Turf”	Filamentous	FI	♦	♦	-
Brachidontes Swainson	Filter	FL	-	-	♦
Zoantharia (Class)	Coral	CN	♦	-	-
Cirripedia (infra-Class)	Filter	FL	♦	♦	♦
Porifera (Phylum)	Filter	FL	-	-	♦
Echinometra lucunter Linneaus	Herbivores	HE	♦	♦	♦
Palythoa Lamoroux	Coral	CN	♦	♦	♦
Petaloconchus Lea	Filter	FL	♦	-	-
Polychaeta	Filter	FL	♦	-	-
Protopalythoa Verril	Coral	CN	♦	-	♦
Regarding to the urbanization degree, identified macroalgae are distributed into the three phyla in this way: 19 Rhodophyta, 7 Chlorophyta and 3 Ochrophyta at the NU environment; 22 Rhodophyta, 10 Chlorophyta and 6 Ochrophyta at the UP environment and 16 Rhodophyta, 4 Chlorophyta and 3 Ochrophyta at the UC environment (Table 2). Their relative frequencies were: 63% Rhodophyta, 21% Chlorophyta and 16% Ochrophyta at NU environment; 62% Rhodophyta, 22% Chlorophyta and 16% Ochrophyta at UP environment and 64% Rhodophyta, 32% Chlorophyta and 4% Ochrophyta at UC environment (Fig. 2).
Figure. 2. Relative abundance of macroalgae phyla. A: Macroalgae phyla relative abundance at different urbanization degrees: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC). B: Morpho-funtional groups and feed guilds relative abundance at different urbanization degrees: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC).
The red macroalga Palisada perforata was abundant at all studied sites but decreased in abundance with increasing of urbanization levels whereas other macroalgae, such as green Ulva spp., Bryopsis sp. and the red Chondracanthus acicularis became the dominant taxa with increasing of urbanization levels. Concerning the MFG, the Foliose, Siphonous, Canopy and Cnidaria groups presented responses in abundance when compared at different levels of urbanization (Fig. 3, Table 3).
Figure. 3. Abundance of Morfo-Functional Groups and feed guilds in response to urbanization degree: Non Urbanized (NU), Urbanization Process (UP) and Consolidated Urbanization (UC).
Table 3. Summary of PERMANOVA results for Pairwise test of Morpho-Functional Group and feed guilds that shown significant differences in abundance by urbanization degree levels.
Urbanization Degree	Foliose		Siphonous		Canopy		Cnidaria	
	t	P	t	P	t	P	t	P
UC - NU	12.8	0.01	2.45	0.01	4.15	0.01	2.52	0.01
UC - UP	9.87	0.01	2.56	0.01	5.29	0.01	0.41	0.68
NU - UP	1.62	0.13	0.22	0.8	1.37	0.18	1.89	0.05
Macroalgae community structure significantly varied among levels of urbanization (Fpseudo = 12.89; p = 0.003, which were consistent in time (Time x Urbanization Fpseudo = 1.08; p = 0.37). There were significant differences in the structure of macroalgal assemblages between UP and UC (t = 3.52 and p = 0.014), and between NU and UC (t = 4.49 and p = 0.004), but not between NU and UP (t = 1.78 and p = 0.12) (Fig. 4, Table 4).
Table 4. Results from the Permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA) between factors Time, Urbanization Degree (NU = Non Urbanized, UP = Urbanization Process and UC = Consolidated Urbanization), that affect the macroalgae community on the Brazilian Northeastern reefs.
Permanova		
Factor	FPseudo	P
Time	2.537	0.055
Urbanization	12.894	0.003
Ti x Urb	1.083	0.341
	Pairwise test	
Factor levels	t	P
UC, NU	4.498	0.004
UC, UP	3.526	0.014
NU, UP	1.783	0.124
The PCO and SIMPER analyses (Table 5) revealed that in UC there was generally a greater dominance of filamentous (i.e. Bryopsis sp.), turf-forming (i.e. Chondracanthus sp.) and foliose (i.e. Ulva spp.) algae. In contrast, the canopy algae Sargassum sp. was completely absent from UC, but dominated assemblages.
Urbanization Degree
Average abundance (%)	Contribution dissimilarity (%)
	NU	UP	UC	NU x UP	UP x UC	NU x UC
Bryopsis sp.	37	43	84	4.2	4	4.7
Caulerpa spp.	54	59	-	4.2	5.3	4.8
Chondracanthus sp.	-	-	88	1.5	7.6	7
Dictyosphaeria sp.	45	45	-	4.1	4	4.2
Gelidiella acerosa	75	68	64	3.3	3.2	3
Gelidium sp.	47	41	64	4.2	3.8	3.8
Gracilaria sp.	56	50	81	3.8	3.3	3.3
Hypnea musciformis	48	54	55	4.2	3.5	3.8
Palisada perforata	83	88	74	1.4	1.8	1.92
Sargassum sp.	41	50	-	4.6	4.3	3.7
Ulva spp.	-	-	88	2.8	6.1	7.1
In the PCO plot is possible to identify two groups. Group 1 is formed by all samples from UC sites, and group 2 is composed of samples from NU and UP sites (Fig. 4).
-60	-40	-20	0	20	40	60
PCO1 (33,5% of total variation)
Figure. 4. Principal Coordinates (PCO) plot. O Non Urbanized, ■ Urbanization Process and * Consolidated Urbanization. The vectors correspond to a multiple correlation &gt; 0.6 of macroalgae taxa: Ulv: Ulva spp., Chon: Chondracanthus acicularis, C.rac: Caulerpa recemosa and Sar: Sargassum sp; and Morpho-functional group and feed guilds: SI: Siphonous; FO: Foliose; CA: Canopy; CR: Cnidaria.
4.	Discussion
Reefs classified as UC were located amongst one of the largest metropolitan regions of Brazil (Recife's Metropolitan Region). Despite sewage treatments, only 36% of the sewage is currently collected (SNIS, 2011) leaving a substantial proportion of sewage still running free into the coastal region. UP reefs receive seasonal population booms (activity during summer) and due to their greater distance to larger urban centers, the sewage collecting system is poor. The few places classified as NU were essentially remote locations with little levels of visitation, even during summer.
The studied places supported macroalgal assemblages typical from the tropical phycogeographic region (Horta et al., 2001), although, there were variations on the phyla proportions when places were analyzed for their urbanization degree.
The studied reefs formation presented high abundance values of macroalgae such as Palisada perforata, Gelidiella acerosa, Gracilaria sp. and Caulerpa racemosa, which are dominant algae of the reef plateau from tropical regions (Pereira et al., 2002; Pereira et al., 2008; Villaga et al., 2010; Fonseca et al., 2012).
On the low mesolitoral region reefs, we found species (Sargassum sp., Padina sp. and Hypnea musciformis) that dominate places with great influence from littoral, in other words, places on the reef that are constantly washed by waves, allowing organisms to be wet (Vasconcelos et al., 2013). We also identified another group of macroalgae composed by Ceramiaceae species, Ulva spp. and Gelidium sp., which can't stand great hydrodynamics, or can't compete to colonize the reef edge surroundings, often placing themselves next to plateau and top of the reef, tolerating the desiccation stress.
The abundance of Palisad perforata on reef formations is directly connected to high temperature environments (above 28°C) and air exposure (Tsai et al., 2005), typical of a mesolittoral environment. However, this macroalgae relative abundance responded negatively to the UC urbanization level on the sampled locations. In a reef environment dominated by Gracilaria coronopifolia J. Agardh and P. perforata (previously reported as Laurencia papillosa) (Tsai et al., 2005), the first one takes advantage when there is a eutrophication process in the area, leading to diminish the occurrence of P. perforata, showing that this alga decreases its dominance on impacted environments, based on diverse descriptors (Cabrera et al., 2005).
The dominant taxa P. perforata, Sargassum sp. and Amansia sp. on the beaches with NU and UP urbanization degrees were replaced by Ulva spp., Bryopsis spp. and C. acicularis on the UC beaches. Macroalgae from Ulva and Bryopsis genus have been well documented and classified as opportunistic algae that take advantage in eutrophicated environments (Ortega, 2000; Areces, 2001; Juanes et al., 2008) and that are greatly
related to urbanized environments (Martins et al., 2012; Scherner et al., 2013; Orlandi et al., 2014). Chondracanthus acicularis was classified as opportunistic algae (Orfanidis et al., 2003), with fast growing rate and short life cycles, present in areas with organic contamination, indicating environmental impact. Gracilaria sp. was also present in high urbanization degree environments. Those macroalgae genera are capable to resist changes in salinity, temperature oscillations, high nutrient concentration and even landfilling by suspension particles (Lapointe, 1989; Santelices &amp;amp; Doty, 1989; Peckol &amp;amp; Rivers, 1996; Moreira et al., 2006).
Using a fast and easy data achievement method (Line Point Transect) and a relative abundance descriptor, it was possible to verify changes on macroalgae dominance in the coastal reef environments classified into different urbanization degrees. The present study results also appoint to importance not only of the taxa occurrence, but mostly of the indicator dominant taxa relative abundance. The reef formation leads the community to a natural heterogeneity, but in presence of a gradient of urbanization it tends to shift and simplify the community in the reefs observed. Considering those results, it becomes necessary to find a way to quali-quantitatively evaluate the evolution of those environments due to increasing coast areas urbanization, through environmental quality indexes using key elements from ecosystems.
Acknowledgments
This work was supported by research grants from the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq-Proc. 484647/2012-1). The first author thanks the Fundação de Amparo à Ciência e Tecnologia de Pernambuco (FACEPE) for the PhD Scholarship and the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) for the Science without Frontier Scholarship. MTF thanks CNPq for the Productivity Fellowship (Proc. 303915/2013-7). The authors thank Souza-Filho JS, Neumann-Leitão S, Feitosa FA, Rosa-Filho JS for helpful advice and comments.
References
Airoldi, L. (2003). The effects of sedimentation on rocky coast assemblages. Oceanography and Marine Biology: an annual review, 41, 161 - 236.
Airoldi, L., &amp;amp; Beck, W.M. (2007). Loss, status and trends for coastal marine habitats of Europe. Oceanography and Marine Biology: an annual review, 45, 345-405.
Anderson, M.J., Gorley, R.N., &amp;amp; Clarke, K.R. (2008). PERMANOVA+ for Primer. Plymouth, UK: Primer-E.
Areces A., (2001). La ficoflora intermareal como bioindicadora de calidad ambiental. Estudio de caso: El litoral habanero. In: Alveal K, Antezana T, editors. Sustentabilidad de la biodiversidade. Um problema actual, bases científico-técnicas, teorizaciones y perspectivas. Concepción: Trama Impresores S.A. Chile. pp. 569589.
Balata, D., Piazzi L., &amp;amp; Rindi, F. (2011). Testing a new classification of morphological functional groups of marine macroalgae for the detection of responses to stress. Marine biology, 158(11), 2459-2469.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L. (2001). Variability in abundance of algae and invertebrates at different spatial scales on rocky sea shores. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 215, 79-92.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L., Pannacciulli, F., Bulleri, F., Moschella, P.S., Airoldi, L., Relini G., &amp;amp; Cinelli, F. (2001). Predicting the consequences of anthropogenic disturbance: large-scale effects of loss of canopy algae on rocky shores. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 214, 137-150.
Borowitzka, M.A. (1972). Intertidal algal species diversity and the effects of pollution. Australian Journal of Marrine and Freshwater Research. 25, 73-84.
Branner, J.C. (1904). The stone reefs of Brazil, their geological and geographical relations, with a chapter on the coral reefs. Bull Mus Comp Zool Harv. 54, 1-285.
Cabrera, R., Moreira, A., Primelles, J., &amp;amp; Suárez, A.M. (2005). Variación de la biomasa de Chondrophycus papillosus (C. Agardh) Garbary et Harper (Ceramiales: Rhodophyta) y su epifitismo en la bahía de Nuevitas, Cuba. Rev Invest Mar. 26(1):15-20.
Castro, C.B., &amp;amp; Pires, D.O. (2001). Brazilian Coral Reefs: what we know and what is still missing. B Mar Sci., 69 (2), 357-371.
Clarke, K.R., &amp;amp; Gorley, R.N. (2006). PRIMER v6: user manual/tutorial (Plymouth routines in multivariate ecological research). Plymouth: Primer-E Ltd.
Clarke, K.R., &amp;amp; Warwick, R.M. (2005). Primer-6 computer program. Natural Environment Research Council, Plymouth..
CPRH. (2003) Agência estadual de meio ambiente e recursos hídricos. Diagnóstico Sócioambiental do Litoral Sul de Pernambuco. Avaiable at: http://www.cprh.pe.gov.br.
Connell, S.D., Russell, B.D., Turner, D.J., Shepherd, S.A., Kildea, T., Miller, D., Airoldi, L., &amp;amp; Cheshire, A. (2008). Recovering a lost baseline: missing kelp forests from a metropolitan coast. Marine Ecology Progress Sereries. 360, 63-72.
Davison, I.R. &amp;amp; Pearson, G.A. (1996). Stress tolerance in Intertidal seaweeds. Journal of Phycology, 32, 197-211.
Laborel, J.L. (1969). Madreporaires et hidrocoralliaires recifaux dês cotes brésiliennes. Systematíque, ecologie, repartition verticale et geographic. Ann I Oceanogr Paris. 47, 171-226.
Dominguez, J.M.L., Bittencourt, A.C.S.P., Leão, Z.M.A.N., &amp;amp; Azevedo, A.E.G., (1990). Geologia do quaternário costeiro do Estado de Pernambuco. Rev Brasil Geociênc. 20, 208-215.
Fonseca, A.C., Villaça, R., &amp;amp; Knoppers, B. (2012). Reef flat community structure of Atol das Rocas, northeast Brazil and southwest Atlantic. Journal of Marine Biology, 2012.
Goatley, C.H., &amp;amp; Bellwood, D.R. (2013). Ecological consequences of sediment on high-energy coral reefs. PloS one, 8(10), e77737.
Google Earth®, (2013). Google Inc.
Halpern, B.S., Longo, C., Hardy, D., McLeod, K.L., Samhouri, J.F., Katona, S.K., ... &amp;amp; Rosenberg, A.A. (2012). An index to assess the health and benefits of the global ocean. Nature, 488(7413), 615-620.
IBGE (2010). Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística Censo Demográfico. http://www. censo2010. ibge. gov. br/&gt;. Consultado em, 04/12/2013.
ITEP, (2012). Instituto de Tecnologia de Pernambuco. Relatório de impacto ambiental. Recuperação da orla marítima. Municípios de Jaboatão dos Guararapes, Recife, Olinda e Paulista (Pernambuco). Instituto de Tecnologia de Pernambuco, Recife, 98p
Johnston, E.L., &amp;amp; Roberts, D.A., (2009). Contaminants reduce the richness and evenness of marine communities: A review and meta-analysis. Environ Pollut, 157, 1745-1752.
Juanes, J.A., Guinda, X., Puente, A., &amp;amp; Revilla, J.A., (2008). Macroalgae, a suitable indicator of the ecological status of coastal rocky communities in the NE Atlantic. Ecological Indicators, 8 (4), 351-359.
Koppen, W., (1948). Climatologia: con un estudio de los climas de la tierra. Fondo de Cultura Econômica. México. p.479
Krause-jensen, D., Sagert, S., Schubert, H., &amp;amp; Bostrom, C., (2008). Empirical relationships linking distribution and abundance of marine vegetation to eutrophication. Ecological Indicators, 8(5), 515-529.
Lapointe, B.E. (1989). Macroalgal production and nutrient relations in oligotrophic areas of Florida Bay. Bulletin of Marine Science, 44(1), 312-323.
Manso, V.A.V., Coutinho, P.N., Guerra, N.C., &amp;amp; Soares, C.F.A, (2006). Pernambuco. In: Muehe D, editor. Erosão e Progradação no Litoral Brasileiro. Ministério do Meio Ambiente, Brasília, Brasil. pp. 179-196.
Martins, C.D., Arantes, N., Faveri, C., Batista, M.B., Oliveira, E.C., Pagliosa, P.R., ... &amp;amp; Horta, P.A. (2012). The impact of coastal urbanization on the structure of phytobenthic communities in southern Brazil. Marine pollution bulletin, 64(4), 772-778.
Moreira, A.R., Armenteros, M., Gómez, M., Leon, A.R., Cabrera, R., ... &amp;amp; Suarez, M. (2006). Variation of macroalgae biomass in Cienfuegos bay, Cuba. Revista de investigaciones marinas, 27 (1), 3-12
Orfanidis, S., Panayotidis, P., &amp;amp; Stamatis, N. (2003). An insight to the ecological evaluation index (EEI). Ecological indicators, 3(1), 27-33.
Orlandi, L., Bentivoglio, F., Carlino, P., Calizza, E., Rossi, D., Costantini, M.L., &amp;amp; Rossi, L. (2014). õ 15 N variation in Ulva lactuca as a proxy for anthropogenic nitrogen inputs in coastal areas of Gulf of Gaeta (Mediterranean Sea). Marine pollution bulletin, 84(1), 76-82.
Ortega, J.L.G. (2000). Algas. In: Espino GL, Pulido J, Pérez JLC, editors. Organismos indicadores de la calidad del água y de la contamination (Bioindicadores). Playa y Valdés, México. pp. 109-193.
Paine, R.T. (1980). Food webs: linkage, interaction strength and community infrastructure. Journal of Animal Ecology, 49(3), 667-685.
Peckol, P., &amp;amp; Rivers, J.S. (1996). Contribution by macroalgal mats to primary production of a shallow embayment under high and low nitrogen-loading rates. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 43(3), 311325.
Pereira, S. M. B., Carvalho, M. F. O., Angeiras, J. A., Pedrosa, M. E. B., Oliveira, N. M. B., Torres, J., ... &amp;amp; Cavalcanti, D. R. (2002). Algas marinhas bentônicas do estado de Pernambuco. Diagnóstico da biodiversidade de Pernambuco (M Tabarelli, JMC Silva, orgs.). Secretaria de Ciência, Tecnologia e Meio Ambiente, Editora Massangana, Recife, 1, 97-124.
Pereira, S.M.B., Oliveira-Carvalho, M.F., Burgos, D.C., &amp;amp; Araújo, E.L., (2008). Caracterização estrutural das macroalgas de ambiente recifal da praia de Enseada dos Corais. In: Congresso Brasileiro de Ficologia, XI, Itajaí-SC. Anais de trabalho completos. Rio de Janeiro: Série Livros do Museu Nacional. pp. 231-242.
Projeto Orla, (2002). Projeto Orla: fundamentos para gestão integrada. Brasília: MMA/SQA; Brasília: MP/SPU 78p.
Santelices, B., &amp;amp; Doty. M.S., (1989). A review of Gracilaria farming. Aquaculture. 78, 95-133.
Scherner, F., Horta, P.A., Oliveira, E.C., Simonassi, J.C., Hall-Spencer, J.M., Chow, F., ... &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B. (2013). Coastal urbanization leads to remarkable seaweed species loss and community shifts along the SW Atlantic. Marine pollution bulletin, 76(1), 106-115.
Schiel, D.R. (2006). Rivets or bolts? When single species count in the function of temperate rocky reef communities. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 338(2), 233-252.
Shanmugam, P., Neelamani, S., Ahn, Y. H., Philip, L., &amp;amp; Hong, G. H. (2007). Assessment of the levels of coastal marine pollution of Chennai city, Southern India. Water Resources Management, 21(7), 1187-1206.
SNIS, (2011). Sistema Nacional de Informações sobre Saneamento: Diagnóstico dos serviços de água e esgotos. Brasília: Ministério das cidades SNSA, Brasil. pp. 432
Spalding, M.D., Fox, H.E., Allen, G.R., Davidson, N., Ferdaña, Z.A., Finlayson, M.A.X., ... &amp;amp; Martin, K.D. (2007). Marine ecoregions of the world: a bioregionalization of coastal and shelf areas. BioScience, 57(7), 573-583.
Steneck, R. S., &amp;amp; Dethier, M. N. (1994). A functional group approach to the structure of algal dominated communities. Oikos, 476-498.
Tait, L. W., &amp;amp; Schiel, D. R. (2011). Legacy effects of canopy disturbance on ecosystem functioning in macroalgal assemblages. PLOS one, 6(10), e26986.
Tsai, C., Chang, J., Sheu, F., Shyu, Y., Yu, A., Wong, S., ... &amp;amp; Lee, T. (2005). Seasonal growth dynamics of and from a highly eutrophic reef in southern Taiwan: temperature limitation and nutrient availability. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 315, 49-69.
Turra, A., Croquer, A., Carranza, A., Mansilla, A., Areces, A.J., Werlinger, C., ... &amp;amp; Scarabino, F. (2013). Global environmental changes: setting priorities for Latin American coastal habitats. Global change biology, 19(7), 1965-1969.
Vasconcelos, E.R.T.P.P., Reis, T.N.V., Guimarães-Barros, N.C., Bernardi, J., Areces-Mallea, A.J., Cocentino, A.L.M., &amp;amp; Fujii, M.T. (2013). Padrão espacial da comunidade de macroalgas de mesolitoral em ambiente recifal do nordeste brasileiro. Tropical Oceanography. 41: 84-92.
Villaça, R., Carvalhal Fonseca, A., Jensen, V.K., &amp;amp; Knoppers, B. (2010). Species composition and distribution of macroalgae on Atol das Rocas, Brazil, SW Atlantic. Botanica Marina, 53(2), 113-122.
Worm, B., Lotze, H.K., Bostrom, C., Engkvist, R., Labanauskas, V., &amp;amp; Sommer, U. (1999). Marine diversity shift linked to interactions among grazers, nutrients and propagule banks. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 185, 309-314.
Capítulo II - Caracterização de topos recifais no litoral de Pernambuco, Brasil, a partir de atributos paisagísticos, variáveis geomorfológicas e composição da ficoflora intermareal
A SER SUBMETIDO NA REVISTA REGIONAL STUDIES IN MARINE SCIENCE (ISSN: 23524855).
RESUMO
Dada a importância e necessidade de se conhecer a distribuição de diferentes tipos de habitats marinhos, o presente trabalho tem o objetivo de associar e categorizar em escala local, em uma classificação Top Down-Botton Up, os habitats intermareal baseado nas comunidades fitobentônicas de estruturas recifais do Nordeste do Brasil. Foram considerados seis atributos paisagísticos em mesoescala (Orientação geográfica, Influência dos rios, Tipo de formação, Proteção, Distância da costa e Comprimento total) e seis em microescala (Largura, Inclinação, Altura, orientação em relação ao Norte geográfica, Rugosidade e Cobertura vegetal). Correlações entre variáveis paisagísticas e morfológicas revelam a diferenciação dessas estruturas recifais de acordo com sua origem. Nas formações com presença massiva de algas a rugosidade se relaciona com a distância da costa dos locais de amostragem, bem como com a largura e comprimento total. Já nos recifes areníticos a altura e inclinação são distintivas e a proximidade da costa determina os elementos estruturais da formação. As comunidades de macroalgas responderam a esses atributos formando biotópos característicos. Foram categorizados 3 habitats em maior nível: Recifes de Arenito com 3 biótpos; Recifes Coralíneos-Algáceos com 2 biótpos; e Carneiros (Distinto) com um biótopo. O presente estudo focou as macroalgas, no entanto é imprescindível futuros estudos considerar a presença e abundância dos grupos focais do zoobentos.
1.	Introdução
O habitat constitui o cenário físico e biológico no qual uma espécie ou
comunidade vive. Não representa mais que um espaço onde os elementos bióticos e abióticos associam-se da mesma maneira sem mostrar mudanças aparentes quando se utiliza uma determinada escala. Resulta, portanto, em uma unidade discreta e arbitrária cujos limites dependerão da escala de trabalho empregada (EC, 2003; Airoldi &amp;amp; Beck, 2007; Areces et al., 2015). Em processos de definição tipológica e regionalização da paisagem mediante reagrupamento ou subdivisão de geocomplexos (Lipsky, 2005; Richling, 1989), em geral associados entre si de maneira aninhada, o habitat se sobrepõe na forma de último nível hierárquico.
A degradação, perda e fragmentação de habitats constituem consequências diretas das pressões antrópicas sobre o meio natural (FAO, 2003; Hansson et al., 2007; Murdoch et al., 2007) e por isso, sua identificação resulta em um parâmetro muito útil
A classificação e mapeamento de habitats marinhos baseiam-se em atributos como a zona ou localização referente à posição espacial e a utilização de descritores semiquantitativos ou quantitativos tais como abundância, biomassa ou densidade da vegetação e os grupos faunísticos dominantes referentes à cobertura biológica. Já desde a fase inicial de agrupamento destes atributos, estes são combinados com diversos elementos geomorfológicos para formar classes mutuamente excludentes (Kendal et al., 2001; Madley et al., 2002; Ballesteros et al., 2007). Com este fim se empregam critérios explícitos relativos ao tipo de substrato, nível da costa, presença de bioconstrutores e espécies engenheiras (Fraschetti et al., 2008), geoformas (Holthus &amp;amp; Maragos, 1995; Finkbeiner et al., 2001; Cochram-Marquez, 2005; Alcolado, 2014), composição e abundância relativa de espécies (Bulleri &amp;amp; Benedetti-Cecchi, 2006).
Entretanto, em muitos lugares faltam sistemas de classificação consistentes, apesar da importância sobre a necessidade de se conhecer a distribuição de diferentes tipos de habitats marinhos e o efeito que os impactos antrópicos mais importantes têm sobre eles (Halpern et al., 2008), a fim de monitorar a longo prazo suas mudanças ambientais (Malthus &amp;amp; Mumby, 2003; Godet et al., 2009).
Sobre os recifes costeiros com topos e platôs emersos do nordeste brasileiro, nenhum sistema de classificação, baseado em atributos paisagístico e geoformas, foi elaborado ainda. Uma proporção significativa destes recifes é constituída pelos chamados arenitos de praia, que são formados entre as latitudes 35°N e 35°S (Russell, 1962), principalmente em águas com temperaturas de 25° C ou acima e marés compreendidas entre 2 e 4 m. Os mesmos estão integrados por estruturas rochosas sedimentares de formação recente compostas por areia quartzítica cimentada com carbonato de cálcio e eventualmente sílica ou óxido de ferro (Branner, 1904; Laborel, 1969; Dominguez et al., 1990; Vousdoukas et al., 2007). No litoral nordestino formam cordões paralelos à linha de costa, às vezes com vários kilómetros de extensão. Nesta região, outros recifes são constituídos por conglomerados descontínuos e irregulares com proporção elevada de rochas produzidas por algas calcárias, ou que foram originados pela erosão das escarpas da formação Barreiras (Manso et al., 2006).
O objetivo deste trabalho foi descrever e categorizar em escala local, a partir de um esquema de classificação “Bottom Up-Top Down”, os habitats intermareais de origem recifal existentes no estado de Pernambuco. Desta maneira, a elaboração de indicadores de qualidade adaptados a locais com características ecossistêmicas
2.	Materiais e Métodos
2.1.	ÁREA DE ESTUDO
A costa de Pernambuco possui 187 km de extensão (7°32’52”S, 34°50’27”W e 8°54’57”S, 35°09’76”W) e está localizada na província biogeográfica do Atlântico Sudoeste Tropical e na ecorregião Nordeste do Brasil (Figura 1; Spalding et al., 2007). Considerando a classificação de Koppen (1948), o clima local é classificado como tropical úmido (As’), com temperaturas médias anuais variando entre 25°C (mínimo) e 30°C (máximo) (CPRH, 2003). Existem duas estações bem definidas na região: seca (Setembro a Fevereiro) e chuvosa (Março a Agosto). A região possui regime de marés semidiurnas, com swell predominante de E-SE, e temperatura média superficial do mar entre 27 e 29°C (Manso et al., 2006). A costa de Pernambuco representa apenas 4% do território estadual, entretanto, abriga 46% da população de Pernambuco (IGBE, 2010).
2.2.	Localidades e características da amostragem
No domínio marinho, as macroalgas são conspícuas em substratos consolidados da zona eufótica, por esta razão, em muitos locais a classificação de habitats marinhos rasos concentra-se em critérios fitossociológicos (Fraschetti et al.,
2008). Em vista desse fato, para a tipificação das cristas recifais estudadas, três categorias primárias foram levadas em conta, uma em mesoescala (&gt; 1:100000) e duas em microescala (&gt; 1:1000).
Foram considerados seis atributos paisagísticos em mesoescala: Orientação geográfica, Influência dos rios, Tipo de formação, Proteção, Distância da costa e Comprimento total. Destes, quatro compreenderam variáveis nominais ou ordinais. Em microescala, considerou-se como categoria o substrato em termos de algumas de suas peculiaridades geológicas, sendo elas: Largura, Inclinação, Altura, Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico e Rugosidade. A cobertura vegetal que este apresentava (Composição específica e Abundância relativa) constitui a outra categoria. Com exceção da composição específica, todas as variáveis restantes foram de intervalo ou razão. O
Para classificar a mesoescala dos recifes do litoral pernambucano a partir de seus atributos paisagísticos, 20 formações foram consideradas (Figura 1, Tabela 1). Destas, doze formações foram escolhidas visando avaliar a correspondência e a importância relativa que adquirem entre si, alguns atributos paisagísticos e as cinco variáveis geomorfológicas selecionadas no estudo. A influência destes elementos em condições naturais sobre a cobertura algal foi determinada somente em nove das doze formações selecionadas. Os recifes de Pina, Boa Viagem e Piedade tiveram que ser excluídos em função da significativa deterioração ambiental que apresentam devido ao seu enriquecimento por resíduos urbanos (Passavante &amp;amp; Feitosa, 2005; Souza &amp;amp; Cocentino, 2004; Santos et al., 2006; Dias-Filho et al., 2011; Guimaraens et al., 2012; Scherner et al., 2013)
Embora a coleta de dados tenha sido efetuada para diversos fins na zona intermareal, sempre em baixa-mar e durante suas duas estações climáticas, seca e chuvosa, para esta análise foram selecionados apenas os transectos de amostragem com medições de todas as variáveis. Os 36 transectos selecionados coincidiram com o período de seca e foram amostrados entre novembro de 2013 e fevereiro de 2014. Quanto à incidência que ele poderia ter sobre a cobertura algal, um estudo exploratório prévio já havia demonstrado a não existência de diferenças significativas entre as estações climáticas.
A atribuição dos 36 transectos de amostragem variou entre 4 a 7 transectos por recife e sua distribuição em cada formação recifal foi aleatória. A amostragem da cobertura algal foi feita nos transectos de maneira não destrutiva pelo método de Line Point Transect (Ambrose, 2002), ao longo de uma linha reta de 10 m de extensão, perpendicular à linha de costa. A presença ou não de cobertura algal e sua natureza foi feita pontualmente a cada 10 cm de distância.
As cinco variáveis geomorfológicas foram medidas em cada transecto. Para a medição da altura do recife (H), foi aferida a altura do local amostrado (hLi) em relação ao nível do mar (Nvi) no horário da amostragem (ti), a altura da maré estimada para o horário da amostra (hi) simulada pelo SisBaHiA® v.9b (Fundação COPPETEC, 2007; FEMAR, 2009).
H = hLi +
A inclinação e orientação das amostras nas estruturas recifais foram mensuradas através de giroscópio, acelerômetro e bússola eletrônica do dispositivo Gt-I9300 (smartphone), segundo Liu (2013) esses sensores presentes em smartphones possuem uma acurácia satisfatória, sendo utilizado inclusive na área médica (Mourcou
A rugosidade foi aferida através do método da corrente (chain link method) (Wilson et al., 2007), que consiste em estender uma corrente de comprimento conhecido (2 metros) sobre o substrato, a qual se molda ao relevo, contornando-o. Em seguida é medida a distância linear percorrida pela corrente. A razão entre o comprimento da corrente e a distância linear é o valor do índice de rugosidade do substrato "r".
SS-O'O-W
I
34°30'0"W
I
34n0'0"W
as^o'o-w
CO õ p
Figura 1. Localização das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco, Nordeste do Brasil.
Denominação	Tipo ou cobertura	Coordenadas	
Cupe		34°58'54,26"W	8°27'28,94"S
Muro Alto		34°58'28,77"W	8°25'43,96"S
Guadalupe		35°3'53,09"W	8°40'33,69"S
Porto Galinhas		34°58'54,26"W	8°27'28,94"S
Janga		34°48'49,62"W	7°55'43,08"S
Barra Sirinhaem		35°2'30,69"W	8°36'51,69"S
Toquinho exterior		35°1'51,60"W	8°34'52,59"S
Maria Farinha		34°48'52,49"W	7°52'29,31"S
Pina	Arenítico	34°52'44,12"W	8°5'21,94"S
Boa Viagem	Arenítico	34°53'43,89"W	8°7'27,71"S
Piedade	Arenítico	34°54'58,59"W	8°10'25,85"S
*Enseada dos Corais	Arenítico	34°56'51,81"W	8°19'4,0584"S
*Suape	Arenítico	34°57'9,50"W	8°22'39,70"S
*Toquinho interior	Arenítico	35°1'55,48"W	8°34'14,93"S
*Paiva	1Coralíneo-algáceo	34°56'40,54"W	8°16'29,13"S
*Serrambí	1Coralíneo-algáceo	35°0'20,02"W	8°33'51,01"S
*Campas, Tamandaré	1Coralíneo-algáceo	35°4'45,44"W	8°44'35,37"S
*Mamucabas, Tamandaré	1Coralíneo-algáceo	35°5'50,25"W	8°47'9,39"S
*São José da Coroa Grande	1Coralíneo-algáceo	35°8'25,05"W	8°54'23,04"S
*Carneiros	Misto	35°4'37,21"W	8°42'3,61"S
1Base arenítica e cobertura de corais, algas calcárias, vermetídeos
2.3.	Processamento numérico da informação
Os atributos paisagísticos associados a cada formação recifal foram caracterizados em ambiente SIG através de fotos aéreas de livre acesso obtidas do Google Earth Pro. Para isto, foi utilizada a plataforma de trabalho do programa MapInfo v. 11 e QGIS. A distância da costa foi expressa em metros e o comprimento em kilometros. As variáveis restantes, nominais ou ordinais, foram registradas de acordo com a seguinte escala: Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico (0-10° = 1; &gt; 10-20° = 2; &gt;20-30° = 3; &gt; 30° = 4), Influência do aporte fluvial (distância do rio &gt; 5 km = 1; distância do rio de 3 a 5 km = 2; distância do rio &amp;lt;3 km ou contato direto com um córrego ou fluxo de baixo escoamento = 3; rio com influência potencial somente sobre parte da estrutura recifal = 4; formação recifal em contato direto com o rio = 5), Tipo de formação (Contínua = 1; Fragmentada = 2) e Grau de proteção (sem linhas de recifes na frente que emergem na maré baixa = 0; com linhas de recifes na frente que emergem na maré baixa = 1).
Da mesma forma que os atributos paisagísticos, os dados de abundância algal foram padronizados e depois transformados em raiz quarta antes do processamento
A fim de estabelecer o grau de associação entre os elementos paisagísticos e geomorfológicos, assim como a afinidade entre as formações recifais e a influência que a estrutura física exerce sobre a distribuição da ficoflora, foram empregadas as seguintes análises multivariadas: Análise de Conglomerados (Anderson et al., 2008), Correlação Linear de Pearson (Legendre &amp;amp; Legendre, 1983), Componentes Principais e Análise Discriminante (Kendall, 1972), Correspondências Fatoriais (Benzécri, 1992), Escalonamento Multidimensional não Métrico e Cluster (Clarke &amp;amp; Gorley, 2006). Para tal, foram utilizados os programas XLSTAT 2009.3.02 e PRIMER 6 ver. 6.1.15 + PERMANOVA ver. 1.0.5.
3.	Resultados
3.1. Características paisagísticas e morfológicas
Embora os valores de similaridade, entre todas as formações recifais tenham resultado altos, foi possível observar a formação de dois grupos principais nos quais a influência do aporte fluvial, o tipo de formação, a orientação e em menor escala, a distância da costa e o comprimento parecem constituir os atributos primários que regem esta separação. Ambos os grupos agruparam-se entre si com um valor de similaridade próximo a 85 (Figura 2). Um deles, porém, foi menos homogêneo, pois se separa em outros dois subconjuntos, com um valor de similaridade de quase 90 (Figura 2).
Figura 2. Agrupamento mostrando afinidades entre 20 formações recifais de Pernambuco com topos emersos atendendo a seis atributos paisagísticos. Média entre Grupos e Índice de Similaridade de Bray-Curtis. (PI = Pina; BO = Boa Viagem; EN = Enseada dos Corais; PIE = Piedade; PA = Paiva; MU = Muro Alto; ToI = Toquinho (interior); JA = Janga; CAM = Campas, Tamandaré; MAR = Maria Farinha; GU = Guadalupe; CAR = Carneiros; BA = Barra Sirinhaem; ToE = Toquinho (exterior); MAM = Mamucabas, Tamandaré; SU = Suape; SJ =São José da Coroa Grande; CU = Cupe; PO = Porto Galinhas; SE = Serrambi).
As correlações estatisticamente significativas entre atributos paisagísticos e variáveis geomorfológicas são apresentadas na Tabela 2. A Largura associou-se diretamente com a Orientação, a Rugosidade e a Distância da costa. A Rugosidade associou-se com esta última e com o Comprimento total da formação. A Distância da costa também se correlacionou com o Comprimento total da formação. Somente a Altura e a Inclinação resultaram contrárias à Rugosidade e à Distância da costa (Tabela 2). Esta situação não expressa mais do que a diferenciação estrutural das formações recifais de acordo com a sua origem. Nas formações com presença massiva de algas calcárias, a Rugosidade se relaciona diretamente com a Distância da costa do local de amostragem, e com a Largura e Comprimento total da formação. Tais características parecem indicar que em formações deste tipo a acreção e erosão biótica definem sua morfogênese e dão lugar a estruturas de pouca inclinação com grande número de cavidades ocas e canais, à medida que se incrementa seu desenvolvimento. Por outro lado, em formações do tipo arenítico, a Altura e a Inclinação constituem as variáveis distintivas e a sua proximidade com a costa determina os elementos estruturais da formação ao longo do gradiente mar-terra.
Tabela 2. Correlações significativas e valores de p associados a cada um, entre dois atributos paisagísticos e cinco variáveis geomorfológicas quantificadas em formações recifais da costa de Pernambuco.
Variáveis	Largura	Inclinação	Orientação	Altura	Rugosidade	Dist. costa	Comp. total
Largura	1		0,007		&amp;lt;0,0001	0,022	
Inclinação Orientação	0,370	1	1			0,008	
Altura				1	0,007		
Rugosidade	0,592			-0,370	1	0,011	0,002
Dist. costa	0,317	-0,365			0,350	1	&amp;lt;0,0001
Comp. total					0,418	0,490	1
Dist. costa: Distância da costa.
Comp. total: Comprimento total.
Isto pode ser corroborado quando as formações recifais são separadas espacialmente através de uma análise de Componentes Principais. A Tabela 3 mostra os autovalores e a porcentagem (%) de variabilidade acumulada explicada por cada um dos sete componentes extraidos. Os três primeiros componentes explicam mais de 71% da variabilidade total das amostras. A distribuição no plano cartesiano e o valor dos coeficientes de carga dos dois primeiros vetores são apresentados graficamente na Figura 3. No primeiro eixo, a contribuição das variáveis na carga fatorial é quase igual e, com exceção da Inclinação e da Altura, variam entre 26 e 12%. Entretanto, no segundo eixo, a Inclinação e Altura se distinguem por seus valores de um modo particular do restante dos coeficientes de carga e, embora sejam opostas entre si, sozinhas contribuem com 73,6% do total da carga fatorial.
Tabela 3. Análise de Componentes Principais das estruturas recifaisna costa de Pernambuco.
	F1	F2	F3	F4	F5	F6	F7
Autovalores	2,472	1,358	1,194	0,846	0,553	0,332	0,245
Variabilidade (%)	35,319	19,405	17,057	12,083	7,894	4,738	3,505
% acumulada	35,319	54,724	71,781	83,864	91,758	96,495	100
Figura 3. Distribuição e valores da carga fatorial correspondente aos atributos paisagísticos e às variáveis geomorfológicas nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco nos dois primeiros eigenvectors. INCL = Inclinação; ALT = Altura; RUG = Rugosidade; COMP = Comprimento; LARG = Largura; ORIENT = Orientação; DIST = Distância.
De acordo com a importância relativa que estas características da estrutura física adquirem como elementos de separação, fica evidente que as amostras correspondentes aos recifes de Boa Viagem, Pina, Piedade e quase todos os de Toquinho associam-se entre si de maneira próxima em relação à Altura e Inclinação. O mesmo acontece com os transectos correspondentes a Enseada dos Corais, porém, neste caso, os valores de inclinação não foram equivalentes. Nos transectos amostrados no restante dos recifes, a influência das variáveis remanescentes é maior e em correspondência com os valores que as mesmas alcançaram em cada um deles, formando grupos constituídos por topos e platos recifais com maior afinidade estrutural entre si. Desta forma, Suape-Carneiros e Mamucabas-Paiva-Serrambi aparecem claramente distinguidos. Os transectos de Campas e São José da Coroa Grande, apesar de se associarem ao grupo anterior, também parecem possuir peculiaridades próprias (Figura 4).
A classificação preliminar obtida a partir de variáveis quantitativas, vinculadas à paisagem e a geomorfologia (Figura 4), pode ser delimitada ainda mais quando tomados em conta fatores como a influência fluvial e a orientação da costa em relação ao N geográfico. A diferenciação das formações recifais mediante uma função discriminante, a partir da categorização destes fatores, está apresentada nas Figuras 5 e 6. A Tabela 4 resume as estatísticas descritivas e suas matrizes de confusão derivadas. Quase todos os grupos foram diferentes a partir do ponto de vista estatístico
Observações (eixos F1 e F2: 54,72 %)
• EN4
• EN6
• EN1
TO2CAM1
CAM3
• EN3
• EN2EN7
EN5
TO3
• SE4
• TO1
CAM5
• SE5
o'-.
O
O?
CM
-1
-2
-3
-4
-3
-2
• PI3&gt;
TO4
• MAM2
• .
SE6
MAM1
PA3
• PA1
• MAM3
PFH2
p|e4O45	p|e3
PI1BI05
• BO6
BO2
• PIE1 BO1
• BO4
• SU5
-1
• PA2
• CAR8
• CAR5
SU1CARU2
• SU3 SU4
• SU6
• SJ3
4-----------
• SJ1
• SJ2
3
2
1
0
+
+
0

+
1
+
2
3
4
F1 (35,32 %)
Figura 4. Distribuição no plano cartesiano amostrados em doze formações recifais de Pernambuco. A separação mais significativa entre grupos foi determinada pelas variáveis Altura e Inclinação.
Com relação à Influência fluvial (Figura 5), três agrupamentos foram claramente separados, formados pelos recifes: Toquinho-Enseada dos Corais-Boa Viagem; Paiva-Campas-Piedade e Mamucabas-Serrambi-Suape-Carneiros-São José da Coroa Grande. Pina não foi classificado em seu grupo a priori e seus transectos associaram-se ao grupo 3 constituído por Toquinho-Enseada dos Corais-Boa Viagem (Tabela 6).
De acordo com a orientação, um grupo, integrado somente por Toquinho, parece ter características únicas. Outro conjunto, composto por Suape-Serrambi-Carneiros-São José da Coroa Grande, também não se sobrepões aos grupos restantes. O grupo com maior número de transectos é formado pelos recifes de Piedade-Paiva-
Tabela 4. Estatísticas descritivas e matriz de confusão gerada por uma função discriminante empregada para a estimativa de elementos em cada uma das categorias dos atributos paisagísticos Influência do aporte fluvial (InfluRios) e Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico (Orientação) das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.
Atributos	Categorias	Frequências	de/a				Total	% correta
			1	2	3	5		
	1	12	10	2	0	0	12	83,33
InfluRios	2	4	0	0	4	0	4	0
	3	18	0	2	16	0	18	88,89
	5	18	0	0	0	18	18	100
	Total		10	4	20	18	52	84,62
	1	13	12	1	0	0	13	92,31
Orientação	2	19	3	16	0	0	19	84,21
	3	15	0	0	15	0	15	100
	4	5	1	0	0	4	5	80,00
	Total		16	17	15	4	52	90,38
Tabela 5. Verossimilhança estatística em pares (Distância de Fisher) e global (Prova de Lambda de Wilks com aproximação de Rao) na discriminação das quatro categorias do atributo paisagístico Influência do aporte fluvial das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.____________________________________________________________________________________
Matriz de Distâncias de Fisher e Probabilidades Associadas	Lambda	0,036
Categorias	1	2	3	5	F (val. Obs.)	19,034
1	0/1	0,012	&amp;lt;0,0001	&amp;lt;0,0001	F (val. Crít.)	1,749
2	3,004	0/1	0,536	&amp;lt;0,0001	GDL1	15
3	12,282	0,872	0/1	&amp;lt;0,0001	GDL2	122
5	25,252	18,119	54,367	0/1	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001
					alfa	0,05
Tabela 6. Verossimilhança estatística em pares (Distância de Fisher) e global (Prova de Lambda de Wilks com aproximação de Rao) na discriminação das quatro categorias do atributo paisagístico Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico, das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco._________________________________________________________________________
Matriz de Distâncias de Fisher e Probabilidades Associadas	Lambda	0,043
Categorias	1	2	3	4	F (val. Obs.)	13,936
1	0/1	&amp;lt;0,0001	&amp;lt;0,0001	0,005	F (val. Crít.)	1,689
2	6,601	0/1	&amp;lt;0,0001	&amp;lt;0,0001	GDL1	18
3	24,039	23,518	0/1	&amp;lt;0,0001	GDL2	122
4	3,514	11,578	16,871	0/1	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001
					alfa	0,05
Influência de rios (eixos F1 e F2: 99,42 %)
• 1
• 2
•	3
•	5
O Centroides
Figura 5. Distribuição no plano cartesiano segundo os dois primeiros eigenvectors de uma função discriminante dos grupos formados, atendendo ao fator Influência do aporte fluvial nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.
Orientação (Eixo F1 e F2: 97.48 %)
F1 (68.52 %)
• 1
• 2
•	3
•	4
o Centroides
Figura 6. Distribuição no plano cartesiano segundo os dois primeiros eigenvectors de uma função discriminante dos grupos formados, atendendo ao fator Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.
3.2. Influência da estrutura física sobre a cobertura algal
alcançaram mais de 1% do total de abundâncias.	Destas,	em particular Gelidiella
acerosa, Palisada perforata e os representantes do gênero Sargassum atingiram ou ultrapassaram 14% de abundância, sendo as macroalgas dominantes do substrato		
exposto durante a maré baixa no litoral estudado.		
Tabela 7. Táxons de macroalgas bentônicas identificadas nas formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco.		
Táxon	Siglas	Dominância (&gt;1%) Grupos
Acanthophora spicifera (M. Vahl) B0rgesen	Acan	X
Amansia multifida J. V. Lamouroux Bryothamnion seaforthii (Turner) Kützing	Am	X
Bryothamnion triquetrum (S. G. Gmelin) M. A. Howe		
Digenea simplex (Wulfen) C. Agardh	Dig	X
Laurencia dendroidea J. Agardh	Lau	X
Laurencia translucida M. T. Fujii &amp;amp; Cordeiro-Marino		
Palisada perforata (Bory de Saint-Vincent) K. W. Nam	Pal	X
Palisada furcata (Cordeiro-Marino &amp;amp; M. T. Fujii) Cassano &amp;amp;		
M. T. Fujii		
Wrangelia C. Agardh		
Gracilaria Greville	Gra	X
Chondracanthus acicularis (Roth) Fredericq.		
Hypnea pseudomusciformis Nauer, Cassano &amp;amp; M.C. Oliveira	Hyp	X
Cryptonemia seminervis (C.Agardh) J. Agardh		
Chnoospora minima (Hering) Papenfuss		
Ceratodictyon planicaule (W. R. Taylor) M. J. Wynne		
Gelidiella acerosa (Forsskal) Feldmann &amp;amp; G. Hamel	Gel	X
Gelidium J. V. Lamouroux	Gelum	X
Jania J. V. Lamouroux	Jan	X
Dictyota J. V. Lamouroux	Dictyo	X
Dictyopteris delicatula J. V. Lamouroux	Dicter	X
Padina Adanson	Pad	X
Sargassum C. Agardh	Sar	X
Neomeris J. V. Lamouroux		
Anadyomene J. V. Lamouroux			
Penicillus capitatus Lamarck			
Cladophora Kutzing			
Bryopsis J.V.Lamouroux	Bry	X	
Chaetomorpha antennina (Bory de Saint-Vincent) Kutzing	Chae	X	
Udotea flabellum (J. Ellis &amp;amp; Solander) M. Howe			
Halimeda J.V.Lamouroux	Hal	X	
Caulerpa racemosa (Forsskal) J. Agardh	Crace	X	
Dictyosphaeria Decaisne	Dicphe	X	
Ulva lactuca Linnaeus			
Ulva lingulata A. P. de Candolle			
Ectocarpales C. E. Bessey			X
Corallinaceae J. V. Lamouroux			X
Ceramiaceae Dumortier	Cer	X	X
Turf			X
As amostras se agrupam em respostas às afinidades florísticas geradas por variações da composição e abundância relativa da cobertura algal (Figura 7). Observase a formação de três grupos bem definidos compostos por formações recifais com particularidades comuns. Estas particularidades, definidas pela estrutura física de cada formação recifal, afetam a cobertura algal e determinam uma resposta diferenciada quanto à abundância relativa de seus membros. Desta forma, os efeitos ocasionados pelas cinco variáveis geomorfológicas analisadas sobre a comunidade algal, além de não serem similares, refletem em última instância as diferenças entre recifes formados por conglomerados de algas calcárias, concreções areníticas ou uma mistura entre elas.
	2D Stress: 0.13
TO4	SJ2
TOÍO2 TO5	1	SJ3
EN1 SU6 TO1 EN5 suf^us	PA3	SE6 PA2
EN3	EN2 SU2	
SU5501	* SJ1 MA^
carÓAR5	MA3
CAR8
Figura 7. Representação do escalonamento multidimensional (MDS) da comunidade algal presente em nove topos recifais de Pernambuco, de acordo com suas afinidades florísticas. Dados de frequência relativa transformados em Raiz quarta, Matriz de similaridade com índice de Bray-Curtis.
A Largura, a Inclinação e a Rugosidade, que afetam diretamente a diferenciação estrutural das formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco, tiveram uma influência importante na distribuição destas espécies. Os resultados mostram o peso relativo que as categorias adquirem em cada uma das cinco variáveis geomorfológicas e sua influência sobre a distribuição das 19 macroalgas mais abundantes (Tabela 8).
Tabela 8. Resultados da análise de Correspondência Fatorial para a distribuição das macroalgas das formações recifais estudadas no litoral de Pernambuco, de acordo com 22 condições diferentes de cinco variáveis geomorfológicas. A porcentagem de inércia refere-se ao primeiro vetor no caso da Orientação, e o acumulado dos dois primeiros vetores às variáveis restantes. Em destaque, as categorias mais influentes na distribuição das macroalgas. As espécies que aparecem na última coluna constituem as diferenciadas significativamente pela sua contribuição para a variabilidade total de cada variável.
Variáveis	Independência entre linhas e colunas		Inércia (%)	Inércia (relativa)	Espécies com inércia relativa &gt; 0,100
Rugosidade	À2 (Valor observado)	1406,782	86,916		Gelidiella acerosa
	À2 (Valor crítico)	97,351		0,241	Sargassum sp.
R1: &amp;lt;0,100					
	GDL	76		0,193	
R2: &gt; 0,100 &amp;lt;0,200					
	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001		0,126	
R3: &gt; 0,200 &amp;lt;0,300					
	a	0,05		0,289	
R4: &gt; 0,300 &amp;lt;0,400					
				0,151	
R5: &gt; 0,400					
	À2 (Valor observado)	961,282	86,315		Amansia multifida
Inclinação (graus)					
	À2 (Valor crítico)	97,351		0,188	Dictyota sp.
I1: &amp;lt;0,100					
	GDL	76		0,192	Sargassum sp.
I2: &gt;0,100 &amp;lt;0,200					
	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001		0,098	
I3: &gt;0,200&amp;lt;0,300					
	a	0,05		0,428	
I4: &gt; 0,300 &amp;lt;0,400					
				0,094	
I5: &gt; 0,400					
	À2 (Valor observado)	1558,513	86,722		Caulerpa racemosa
Largura (cm)					
	À2 (Valor crítico)	75,624		0,304	Sargassum sp.
La1: &amp;lt;800					
	GDL	57		0,240	
La2: &gt;800 &amp;lt;1500					
	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001		0,238	
La3: &gt; 1500 &amp;lt;3000					
	A	0,05		0,218	
La4: &gt; 3000					
Orientação (graus)					
O1: &amp;lt;100	À2 (Valor observado)	606,799	80,675	0,170	Caulerpa racemosa
O2: &gt;100 &amp;lt;125					
O3: &gt;125	À2 (Valor crítico)	53,384		0,336	Dictyota sp.
	GDL	38		0,494	Gelidium sp.
	p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001			Sargassum sp.
	a	0,05			
Altura (m)
		À2 (Valor observado)	1139,333	72,601	0,283	Acanthophora spicifera
All:	0,200 S 0,250				
		À2 (Valor crítico)	97,351	0,120	Dictyota sp.
Al2:	&gt; 0,250 S 0,500				
		GDL	76	0,148	Gelidiella acerosa
Al3:	&gt; 0,500 S 1,00				
		p-valor	&amp;lt;0,0001	0,148	Sargassum sp.
Al4:	&gt; 1,000 S 1,500				
		a	0,05	0,302	
Al5: &gt;1,500
Em relação à Rugosidade, existe uma clara distinção entre as espécies que se associam com as duas primeiras categorias e aquelas que o fazem com as três categorias restantes. Os representantes da família Ceramiaceae e dos gêneros Padina, Chaetomorpha e Sargassum estão vinculados diretamente com as áreas de menor rugosidade e Gelidium e Dictyopteris com locais de rugosidade intermediária (R4: &gt;
0,300 &amp;lt;0,400), porém muito significativa (Figura 8, Tabela 8).
1
-1
Gráfico simétrico (eixos F1 e F2: 86.92 %)
(\l
Ll_
-0,5
Dig# • R1 Pad •	Cer Chae Sa* Sa" Lau •	Gel DicPh* R4Gelum Gra	a • • R5 wa Dicter
• Hyp * R2 • Am • Dictyo	Pal	Bry R3 Crace BAcan * Hal
-1,5	-1
-0,5
0
0,5
1	1,5
F1 (72.95 %)
• Colunas • Linhas
Figura 8. Influência da rugosidade sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.
Para a Inclinação, a distinção também aparece entre as primeiras categorias e as restantes (Figura 9). Devido à formação de um gradiente bem definido de zonação algal, quando a inclinação ultrapassa 0,300 (I4 e I5), grupos de espécies associadas à elevada umectação apareceram vinculadas às duas últimas categorias (Sargassum, Padina, Amansia multifida, Digenea simplex, Laurencia dendroidea) (Figura 9).
1
-1
Gráfico simétrico (eixos Fl e F2: 86.32 %)
\O
0s.
oo co
cm,
CM
Dictyo
U Aca^Dlct^ CraceBrv Gra	Lau	Dig lísa^^Pad	Cer&gt; I4
Hal	JlPal Dicphe GeTe * Gelum	I3 “• . * . Hyp	•	Am Chae
-1	-0,5
0	0,5
1	1,5
Fl (59.43 %)
-1,5
• Colunas «Linhas
Figura 9. Influência da inclinação da face externa do recife sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.
A Altura, por outro lado, embora também se relacione com a Inclinação na diferenciação estrutural das formações recifais, interfere igualmente como um elemento explicativo da distribuição algal. Por isso, o gradiente de umectação em relação à Altura somente se diferencia significativamente entre as categorias extremas (Al1: 0,200 &amp;lt;0,250 e Al5: &gt;1,500; Tabela 8), na qual distintas espécies (Gelidiella acerosa e o conjunto formado por Laurencia dendroidea, Sargassum sp. e Amansia multifida) associam-se (Figura. 10)
Gráfico simétrico (eixos F1 e F2: 72.60 %)
0,8
0,4
All
Gel
Pal
Al4. *Acan
Dicte^
+
+
+
F2 (27.99 ó&amp;lt;	Dicphí ••	
	GelumCrace	
	• Hal	, • *Cer Jan
-0,8 -1,2		• Bry
/ Dig Dictyo
•----1—
Chae
Al3 Hyp
Al2
Gra
Al5
Lau
Sar
• -
Pad
Am
\O
0
+
+
-1	-0,8	-0,6	-0,4	-0,2	0	0,2	0,4	0,6	0,8
F1 (44.62 %)
1
• Columnas «Linhas
Figura 10. Influência da altura do recife em relação ao ponto zero da maré sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.
Considerando a Largura, a Figura 11 mostra uma separação em dois grandes grupos, um integrado por perfis com largura &amp;lt;800 cm (La1), próprio de formações areníticas e outro constituído pelas categorias restantes. Ao primeiro grupo se associam todas aquelas espécies presentes nas porções mais próximas ao mar, a partir de um gradiente de zonação (Sargassum sp., Amansia multifida. Padina sp., Laurencia dendroidea, Digenea simplex, Chaetomorpha sp., Hypnea sp., Acanthophora spicifera e Palisada perforata). No segundo grupo estão as demais espécies, sem uma
associação clara com o restante das categorias (Figura 11).
1
-1
Gráfico simétrico (eixos F1 e F2: 86.72 %)
0,5
o'-.
o
0
T—I
OI
Ll_
-0,5
Lau •	Pa Chae Sar.	AcaW	•Hal La5ç,a.e G.ium	-Bry _ a • La4
Am r Cer a Pad • Dig	“*Ge* *Gra	aDVa2e % e Dicter a Dictyo
-1,5	-1
-0,5
0	0,5
1
F1 (71.76 %)
1,5
• Colunas • Linhas
Figura 11. Influência da largura do recife sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.
Finalmente, a Orientação da linha de costa parece não influenciar por si só na distribuição das 19 espécies (Figura 12). Aparentemente, sua correlação direta e positiva com a Largura, e esta com a Distância da costa, evidencia uma melhor associação com o tipo estrutural do recife, e através de sua natureza.
1
-1
Gráfico simétrico (eixos F1 e F2: 100.00 %)
0,5 sõ" o'-.
(\l
Ll_
-0,5
Dictyo	Gfa, ' . ’	Sar °2 . ••		Dicter	Chae D '	•	Am Acan	• 03 Crace	D .Hyp	• •
Cer parr	,• Pad	Pal	• • Hal • Gel	Jan _	• •oi	Gel • Dicphe
-0,5
0
0,5
1
F1 (80.68 %)
-1
• Colunas • Linhas
Figura 12. Influência da Orientação dos transectos sobre a distribuição de macroalgas em nove formações recifais do litoral de Pernambuco.
3.3. OS HABITATS E BIÓTOPOS PRESENTES NOS AMBIENTES RECIFAIS ESTUDADAS DE Pernambuco
Analisando os elementos da sua estrutura física, as analogias entre as formações recifais estudadas são apresentadas na Figura 13. Essas analogias ficam mais claras e corroboradas pela representação gráfica do Cluster da cobertura biótica das localidades estudadas (Figura 14). As espécies que mais contribuem para a formação dos biótopos foram identificadas pela análise de porcentagem de similaridade (Tabela 9).
Figura 13. Afinidades existentes entre formações recifais do litoral pernambucano, em relação a elementos da estrutura física e a composição e abundância relativa da cobertura algal. GEO = Variáveis geomorfológicas; InfRios = Influência de aportes fluviais; Orient. = Orientação em relação ao Norte geográfico; Denominação recifal segundo a Figura 2.
A partir da estrutura física (top-down) e das características de cobertura algal (bottom-up) pode-se, a priori, considerar a seguinte hierarquização de tipologias (habitats e biótopos) para relacionar as formações recifais existentes no litoral de Pernambuco:
1.	Habitat: Recifes de Arenito
Formações: Pina-Boa Viajem-Piedade-Toquinho-Enseada dos Corais-Suape
1.1	Biótopo Sargassum-Palisada-Laurencia
Formações: Toquinho-Enseada
1.2	Biótopo Palisada-Sargassum-Acanthophora
Formação: Suape
1.3	Biótopo Espécies oportunistas
Formações: Piedade-Pina-Boa Viajem
2.	Habitat Recifes Coralíneos-algáceos
Formações: Campas-Serrambi-Mamucabas-Paiva-São José da Coroa Grande.
2.1	Biótopo Caulerpa-Gelidium-Jania
Formação: São José da Coroa Grande
2.2	Biótopo Gelidiella-Palisada-Caulerpa
Formação: Campas-Serrambi-Mamucabas-Paiva
3.	Habitat Carneiros
3.1	Biótopo Dictyota-Padina
Formação: Carneiros
1.1	Av.Abund	Contrib%	Cum.%
Gelidiella acerosa	2,14	22,25	22,25
Palisada perforata	2,14	21,76	44
Caulerpa racemosa	1,87	19,3	63,3
1.2			
Sargassum	2,18	18,56	18,56
Palisada perforata	1,81	14,36	32,92
Hypnea musciformis	1,54	12,54	45,46
Laurencia dendroidea	1,41	10,67	56,13
2.1			
Caulerpa racemosa	2,17	33,03	33,03
Gelidium	1,48	22,03	55,06
Jania	1,19	16,8	71,86
2.2			
Palisada perforata	2,38	21,17	21,17
Sargassum	2,13	18,62	39,79
Acanthophora spicifera	1,56	13,44	53,23
3.1			
Dictyota	2,4	34,87	34,87
Padina	1,79	27,17	62,04
Figura 14. Dissimilaridade entre 9 formações recifais de Pernambuco com topos emersos atendendo a cobertura fitobentônica. Média entre Grupos e Índice de Similaridade de Bray-Curtis. (EN = Enseada dos Corais; PA = Paiva; MU = Muro Alto; TO = Toquinho; CAM = Campas; CAR = Carneiros; MA = Mamucabas, Tamandaré; SU = Suape; SJ =São José da Coroa Grande; SE = Serrambi).
4.	Discussão
A classificação de habitats a partir de variáveis Bottom-Up/Top-Down em meso-escala, através de análise de paisagens, e micro-escala através de amostragem em campo, é difundida por diversos trabalhos há mais de uma década (ex. Frederiksen et al., 2004; Eastwood et al., 2006; Brown &amp;amp; Collier, 2008; Guarinello et al., 2010). Quantificar a biodiversidade utilizando como proxy o habitat e biótopos, tem sido uma boa alternativa frente ao cálculo a partir de inventários genéricos ou específicos, particularmente quando não se pretende realizar um levantamento detalhado e sim um mapeamento em escalas espaciais maiores (Ward et al., 1999; Cushman et al., 2008). No entanto, a diferença de outros níveis de organização biológica, a determinação do habitat sempre resultou em um compromisso entre diferentes opiniões e tem transitado por sistemas classificatórios desde muito vagos a excessivamente detalhados (Fraschetti et al., 2008; Madden et al., 2008; Guarinello et al., 2010).
Os resultados obtidos e as escolhas das variáveis foram suficientes para separar distintos habitats das regiões recifais de Pernambuco. A seleção das váriaves em níveis paisagístico e geomorfológico (top-down) mostraram grande importância na segregação dos habitats e suas consequências nas comunidades de macroalgas. A influência dos rios não está apenas diretamente ligada ao aporte de nutrientes, sedimento e aumento da turbidez na coluna d'água, mas a uma miríade de fatores que afetam diretamente o fitobentos (Longphuirt et al., 2016).
Assim como o aporte fluvial, a posição da estrutura recifal em relação aos ventos dominantes e a pista de vento (fetch), possui papel relevante no tocante ao hidrodinamismo e batimento de onda na estrutura recifal entremarés expostos (Poutinen, 2005; Wallin et al., 2011). Esse é um dos fatores que controlam a distribuição espacial de macroalgas (Rattray et al., 2015) em consequência da abertura de espaço por choque mecânico, afetando tanto as algas como a fauna acompanhante (Thomson et al., 2012). Os dois fatores paisagísticos estão estreitamente associados ao cenário ambiental de cada formação por incidir diretamente tanto em processos de enriquecimento, como é o caso da influência dos rios, ou na dinâmica costeira como ocorre com a direçaõ do recife. Particularmente em regiões costeiras de frente ao oceano aberto, a pista (fetch) e a direção do regime de ventos predominantes em relação a orientação do litoral, determinam a intensidade do batimento de ondas e, portanto, suas características físicas e ecológicas
Dentre as varáveis geomorfológicas testadas e aferidas, a rugosidade obteve destaque ao ter correlações fortes e positivas ao tipo de recife Coralíneo-Algáceo. Segundo (Dominguez, 1990) esses recifes são de base arenítica acrescido de
organismos construtores, como algas calcárias, vermitídeos e corais. O crescimento dessas estruturas a partir de uma acreção biogênica leva a uma maior complexidade de habitat, aumentando assim o número de canais e reentrancias cavadas por herbívoros como ouriços (Guerra &amp;amp; Manso, 2004). Isso explica as correlações negativas com inclinação e altura das formações recifais, uma vez que o grau de inclinação nas estruturas de recifes de arenito está associado a erosão, fratura e quebra das rochas (basculamento) (Guerra &amp;amp; Manso, 2004). Esse tipo de evento ocorre por processos físicos de batimento de onda e acomodação do substrato onde o recife foi formado (Amaral &amp;amp; Bezerra, 2006). Os recifes mais altos são os mais propícios a apresentarem fraturas e formações de rampas mais íngremes em direção ao mar. A acreção biológica nas fendas de fraturas também permite um retardo no basculamento (Amaral &amp;amp; Bezerra, 2006).
A rugosidade dos ambientes coralíneos-algáceos propicia uma alta complexidade de habitat, no entanto os recifes de arenito de regiões não impactadas, possuem grandes populações de Sargassum que garante uma complexidade estrutural ao habitat, devido à conformação e arquitetura do talo dessa alga (Leite &amp;amp; Turra, 2003). As algas associadas aos altos níveis de inclinação, são justamente as algas que colonizam o andar inferior da zona entremarés (Sargassum, Padina, Amansia, Digenia e Laurencia). Nesse tipo de inclinação quando o regime de ondas é moderado ou a borda recifal é exposta, a zona inferior sempre está com um nível de humidade satisfatório.
O grau de Inclinação influencia a riqueza de espécies em experimentos de recrutamento e sucessão, painéis horizontais e verticais apresentaram menores valores de riqueza, do que painéis com inclinações intermediárias (Falace &amp;amp; Bressan, 2002). Por outro lado, o aumento da rugosidade também promove a complexidade do habitat, por fim aumentando seu potencial de diversidade (Martinez et al., 2012)
Em linhas gerais, os gradientes ambientais geram poucas classes, tanto em relação a propriedades geomorfológicas como a fatores paisagísticos associados ao hidrodinamismo costeiros e a eutrofização. A combinação entre estas propriedades geomorfológicas, os fatores paisagísticos (Habitat) e as características da cobertura vegetal (Biótopo) através de um sistema de classificação Top Down-Bottom Up dão lugar a tipologia dos habitats bentônicos existentes nos topos e platôs recifais do litoral de Pernambuco. Os agrupamentos desta proposta tipológica permitem utilizar os intervalos de abundância das macroalgas existentes para diversos fins, inclusive monitoramento e bioindicação.
A classificação detalhada dos habitats associados a fundos rochosos de topos e platôs recifais da zona entremarés, deve levar em conta os limites e a extensão dos
Agradecimentos
Este trabalho teve apoio financeiro do Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq-Proc. 484647/2012-1). O primeiro autor agradece a Fundação de Amparo à Ciência e Tecnologia de Pernambuco (FACEPE) pela Bolsa de Doutorado e à Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) pela Bolsa de Doutorado Sanduíche no Exterior. MTF agradece o CNPq pela Bolsa de Produtividade em Pesquisa (Proc. 303915/2013-7).
Referências
Airoldi, L., &amp;amp; Beck, M. (2007). Loss, status and trends for coastal marine habitats of Europe. Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review, 45, 347-407.
Alcolado, P. M. (2014). Conocimientos básicos para un monitoreo voluntario rápido de alerta temprana en arrecifes coralinos. En: Hernández-Zanuy, A. &amp;amp; Alcolado, P. M. (Eds.). Métodos para el estudio de la biodiversidad en ecosistemas marinos y costeros para la adaptación al cambio climático. Pp. 122-185. Red CYTED BIODIVMAR Instituto de Oceanología, La Habana (ISBN: 978-959-298-031-0).
Amaral, R. F., &amp;amp; Bezerra, F. H. R. (2006). Mapping beachrock fracturing and erosion using small format aerial photography in northeastern Brazil. Journal of Coastal Research, 270-274.
Ambrose RF. (2002). Transects, quadrats, and other sampling units. In: Murray S.N., Ambrose R.F., Dethier M.N., Editors. Methods for performing monitoring, impact, and ecological studies on rocky shores. Coastal Research Center, Marine Science Institute, University of California, Santa Barbara, California, pp. 98-122
Anderson, M., Gorely, R. &amp;amp; Clarke, K. 2008. PERMANOVA+ for PRIMER. Plymouth, 17 UK: Plymouth Marine Laboratory
Areces, A. J., Concentino, A.L.M., Vasconcelos-Reis, T. N., Vasconcelos, E.R., Guimaraes-Barros, N. &amp;amp; Toyota-Fujii, M. 2015. III.2. El hábitat como unidad espacial de comparación. En: Edisa Ferreira y Mutue Toyota Fujii (eds). Las macroalgas como bioindicadoras de calidad ambiental y cambios climáticos. Guía Práctica. Brazilian Journal of Ecology, 17(1) Volume Especial, 31-33
Ballesteros, E., Torras, X., Pinedo, S., Garcia, M., Mangialajo, L., de Torres, M. 2007. A new methodology based on littoral community cartography dominated by macroalgae for the implementation of the European Water Framework Directive. Mar. Poll. Bull., 55: 172-180
Benzécri, J., P. (1992). Correspondence Analysis Handbook, M. Dekker Inc., Nueva York, 665 pp.
Branner, J.C. (1904). The stone reefs of Brazil, their geological and geographical relations, with a chapter on the coral reefs. Bull Mus. Comp. Zool., Harv., 54, 1-285
Brown, C. J., &amp;amp; Collier, J. S. (2008). Mapping benthic habitat in regions of gradational substrata: an automated approach utilising geophysical, geological, and biological relationships. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 78(1), 203-214.
Clarke, K.R., &amp;amp; Gorley, R.N. (2006). PRIMER v6: user manual/tutorial (Plymouth routines in multivariate ecological research). Plymouth: Primer-E Ltd.
Cochram-Marquez, S.A. (2005). Moloka'I benthic habitat mapping: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2005-1070, 18 p. components of mosaics of habitats on shallow rocky reefs. Oecologia 149, 482-492
CPRH. (2003). Agência estadual de meio ambiente e recursos hídricos. Diagnóstico Sócioambiental do Litoral Sul de Pernambuco. Accessed: http://www.cprh.pe.gov.br.
Cushman, S.A., McKelvey, K.S., Flather, C.H. &amp;amp; McGarigal, K. (2008). Do forest community types provide a sufficient basis to evaluate biological diversity? Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment, 6, 13-17
Dias-Filho M.J.O., Araujo M.C.B., Silva-Cavalcanti J.S., Silva A.C.M. (2011). Contaminação da praia de Boa Viagem (Pernambuco-Brasil) por lixo marinho: relação com o uso da praia. Arquivos de Ciências do Mar, 44 (1), 36-39.
Dominguez, J.M.L., Bittencourt, A.C.S.P., Leão, Z.M.A.N. &amp;amp; Azevedo, A.E.G. (1990). Geologia do quaternário costeiro do Estado de Pernambuco. Rev. Brasil. Geociênc., 20: 208-215
Eastwood, P. D., Souissi, S., Rogers, S. I., Coggan, R. A., &amp;amp; Brown, C. J. (2006). Mapping seabed assemblages using comparative top-down and bottom-up classification approaches. Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences, 63(7), 1536-1548.
EC. (2003). Interpretation Manual of European Union Habitats, Version EUR25. EC, DGEnvironment, Brussels. Available Online: http://ec.europa.eu/environment/nature/info/pubs/paper_en.htm.
Falace, A., &amp;amp; Bressan, G. (2002). Evaluation of the influence of inclination of substrate panels on seasonal changes in a macrophytobenthic community. ICES Journal of Marine Science: Journal du Conseil, 59(suppl), 116-121.
FAO. (2003). The Ecosystem Approach to Fisheries. FAO Technical Guidelines for Responsible Fisheries, vol. 4 (Suppl. 2). FAO, Rome.
FEMAR (2009). Fundação Estudos do Mar. Catálogo de Estações Maregráficas Brasileiras. Avaliable in: http://www.fundacaofemar.org.br/biblioteca/emb/indice.html. Retrieve in 06 Agosto. 2015
Finkbeiner, M., Stevenson, B., &amp;amp; Seaman, R. (2001). Guidance for benthic habitat mapping: an aerial photographic approach (p. 75). NOAA Coastal Services Center, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.
Fraschetti, S., Terlizzi, A., &amp;amp; Boero, F. (2008). How many habitats are there in the sea (and where)? Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 366(1), 109-115.
Frederiksen, M., Krause-Jensen, D., Holmer, M., &amp;amp; Laursen, J. S. (2004). Long-term changes in area distribution of eelgrass (Zostera marina) in Danish coastal waters. Aquatic Botany, 78(2), 167-181.
Fundação COPPETEC. (2007). SisBAHIA - Sistema Base de Hidrodinâmica Ambiental. Avaliable in: http://www.sisbahia.coppe.ufrj.br. Retrieve in 06 Agosto. 2015
Godet, L., Fournier, J., Toupoint, N., &amp;amp; Olivier, F. (2009). Mapping and monitoring intertidal benthic habitats: a review of techniques and a proposal for a new visual methodology for the European coasts. Progress in Physical Geography, 33(3), 378-402.
Guarinello, M. L., Shumchenia, E. J., &amp;amp; King, J. W. (2010). Marine habitat classification for ecosystem-based management: a proposed hierarchical framework. Environmental management, 45(4), 793-806.
Guerra, N. C., &amp;amp; Manso, V. A. V. (2004). Beachrocks (Recifes de Arenito). In Oceanografia um cenário tropical eds.E. Eskinazi-Leça, S. Neumann-Leitão, &amp;amp; M. F. Costa. Bagaço. Recife. p. 109-130.
Halpern, B. S., Walbridge, S., Selkoe, K. A., Kappel, C. V., Micheli, F., D'Agrosa, C., ... &amp;amp; Fujita, R. (2008). A global map of human impact on marine ecosystems. Science, 319(5865), 948-952.
Hansson, S., Hjerne, O., Harvey, C., Kitchell, J. F., Cox, S. P., &amp;amp; Essington, T. E. (2007). Managing Baltic Sea fisheries under contrasting production and predation regimes: ecosystem model analyses. AMBIO: A Journal of the Human Environment, 36(2), 265-271.
Holthus, P. F., &amp;amp; Maragos, J. E. (1995). Marine ecosystem classification for the tropical island Pacific. Marine and coastal biodiversity in the tropical island Pacific region, 1, 239-278.
IGBE. 2010. Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística. Demographic census.
Kendall, M. G. (1972). A course in multivariate analysis. Charles Griffin &amp;amp; Co, London, 185 p.
Kendall, M. S., Kruer, C. R., Buja, K. R., Christensen, J. D., Finkbeiner, M., &amp;amp; Monaco, M. E. (2001). Methods used to map the benthic habitats of Puerto Rico and the US Virgin Islands. NOAA NOS NCcOs CCMA Tech. Rpt, 152.
Koppen W. (1948) Climatologia: con un estudio de los climas de la tierra. Fondo de Cultura Económica. México, 479
Laborel, J.L. (1969). Madreporaires et hidrocoralliaires recifaux dês cotes brésiliennes. Systematíque, ecologie, repartition verticale et geographic. Ann. I. Oceanogr., Paris, 47, 171 -226
Legendre, L. &amp;amp; Legendre, P. (1983). 4.2 Correlation matrix. In Numerical Ecology, Elsevier, Amsterdam, 139-145
Leite, F. P. P., &amp;amp; Turra, A. (2003). Temporal variation in Sargassum biomass, Hypnea epiphytism and associated fauna. Brazilian Archives of Biology and Technology, 46(4), 665-671.
Lipsky, Z. (2005). Landscape typology as a basis for sound landscape planning. ALFA SPECTRA, Central European Journal for Architecture and Planning, 9, 8-14
Liu, M. (2013). A study of mobile sensing using smartphones. International Journal of Distributed Sensor Networks, 9 (3), 1-11.
Longphuirt, S. N., O'Boyle, S., Wilkes, R., Dabrowski, T., &amp;amp; Stengel, D. B. (2016). Influence of Hydrological Regime in Determining the Response of Macroalgal Blooms to Nutrient Loading in Two Irish Estuaries. Estuaries and Coasts, 39(2), 478-494.
Madden, C. J., Goodin, K., Allee, R., Bamford, D., &amp;amp; Finkbeiner, M. (2008). Clasificación Ecológica Estandarizada Costera y Marina-Versión III: La clasificación de referencia para hábitats marinos para la Red Temática de Ecosistemas IABIN. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, US Department of Comerse.
Madley, K.A., Sargent, B. &amp;amp; Sargent, F.J. (2002). Development of a system for classification of habitats in estuarine and marine environments (SCHEME) for Florida. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Gulf of Mexico Program (Grant Assistance Agreement MX-97408100), Florida Marine Research Institute, Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission, St. Petersburg, Florida, 43 p.
Malthus, T.J. &amp;amp; Mumby, P.J. (2003). Remote sensing of the coastal zone: an overview and priorities for future research. International Journal of Remote Sensing, 24, 2805-15
Manso V.A.V., Coutinho P.N., Guerra N.C. &amp;amp; Soares C.F.A. (2006). Pernambuco. In: Muehe, D., editor. Erosão e Progradação no Litoral Brasileiro. Ministério do Meio Ambiente, Brasília, Brasil, 179-196
Martinez, A. S., Mendes, L. F., &amp;amp; Leite, T. S. (2012). Spatial distribution of epibenthic molluscs on a sandstone reef in the Northeast of Brazil. Braz'lian Journal of Biology, 72(2), 287-298.
Murdoch, T. J. T., Glasspool, A. F., Outerbridge, M., Ward, J., Manuel, S., Gray, J., ... &amp;amp; Barnes, P. A. (2007). Large-scale decline in offshore seagrass meadows in Bermuda. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 339, 123130.
Passavante, J.Z.O.; Feitosa, F.A.N. (1995). Produção primária do fitoplâncton da plataforma continental de Pernambuco (Brasil): Área de Piedade. Boletim Técnico Científico cEpENE, 3, 7-22.
Puotinen, M. L. (2005). An automated GIS method for modeling relative wave exposure within complex reefisland systems: a case study of the Great Barrier Reef. In A. Zerger &amp;amp; R. Argent (Eds.), Congress of the Modelling and Simulation Society of Australia and New Zealand, 1437-1443.
Rattray, A., lerodiaconou, D., &amp;amp; Womersley, T. (2015). Wave exposure as a predictor of benthic habitat distribution on high energy temperate reefs. Frontiers in Marine Science, 2, 8.
Richling, A. (1989). System of landscape classification in Poland. In: Mazúr, E. (ed.): Landscape classification. Slovak Academy of Sciences, Bratislava, 102-111
Russell, R.J. (1962). Origin of beachrock. Zeitschrift für Geomorphologie. Costal Studies, Louisiania State University, 6, 1-16
Santos, A.A.; Cocentino, A.M.L. &amp;amp; Reis, T.N.V. (2006). Macroalgas como indicadoras da qualidade ambiental da Praia de Boa Viagem - Pernambuco, Brasil. Bol. Téc. Cien. CEPENE, 14 (2), 25-33.
Scherner, F., Horta, P.A., de Oliveira, E.C., Simonassi, J.C., Hall-Spencer, J.M., Chow, F., Nunes, J.M.C. &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B. (2013). Coastal urbanization leads to remarkable seaweed species loss and community shifts along the SW Atlantic. Marine Pollution Bulletin 76, 106-115.
Sousa, G.S. &amp;amp; Cocentino, A.L.M. (2004). Macroalgas como indicadoras da qualidade ambiental. Tropical Oceanography, 32, 1-22
Spalding, M. D., Fox, H. E., Allen, G. R., Davidson, N., Ferdaña, Z. A., Finlayson, M. A. X., ... &amp;amp; Martin, K. D. (2007). Marine ecoregions of the world: a bioregionalization of coastal and shelf areas. BioScience, 57(7), 573-583.
Thomson, D. P., Babcock, R. C., Vanderklift, M. A., Symonds, G., &amp;amp; Gunson, J. R. (2012). Evidence for persistent patch structure on temperate reefs and multiple hypotheses for their creation and maintenance. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 96, 105-113.
Vousdoukas, M., Velegrakis, A. &amp;amp; Plomaritis, T. (2007). Beachrock occurrence, characteristics, formation mechanisms and impacts. Earth-Science Reviews, 85, 23-46
Wallin, A., Qvarfordt, S., Norling, P., &amp;amp; Kautsky, H. (2011). Benthic communities in relation to wave exposure and spatial positions on sublittoral boulders in the Baltic Sea. Aquatic Biology, 12(2), 119-128.
Ward, T. J., Vanderklift, M.A., Nicholls, A. O., &amp;amp; Kenchington, R. A. (1999). Selecting marine reserves using habitats and species assemblages as surrogates for biological diversity. Ecological Applications, 9, 691698
Wilson, S.K., Graham, N.A.J.; Polunin, N.V.C. (2007). Appraisal of visual assessments of habitat complexity and benthic composition on coral reefs. Marine Biology, 151 (3), 1069 -1076
Capítulo III - Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco, Brasil
Publicado na revista Series Oceanológica (ISSN: 2072-800X).
Vasconcelos, E. R. T. P. P.; Bernardi, J.; REIS, T. N. V.; COCENTINO, A. L. M.; Mallea, A. J. A.; FUJII, M.
T. Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco, Brasil. Serie Oceanologica, v. 15, p. 74-88, 2016.
ISSN: 2072-800X
RNPS: 1962
Revista sobre Ciencias del Mar de Cuba y la región en español e inglés.
Se autoriza su
re p ro d u coi ó n s i e m p re que cite la fuente.
Influência da urbanização no padrão de zonação vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés dos recifes de arenito de Pernambuco, Brasil
Influence of urbanization on vertical zonation of benthic communities in sandstone reefs from Pernambuco, Brazil.
RESUMO
O crescente grau de urbanização da costa brasileira, sobretudo na região Nordeste, promove vários impactos nas comunidades marinhas. Esses impactos influenciam diretamente os organismos que habitam a região entremarés dos recifes costeiros. Este estudo descreve as respostas das comunidades bentônicas a diferentes graus urbanização em cinco recifes de arenito da costa nordeste do Brasil. Foram estudadas três zonas verticais: inferior, médio e superior da região entremarés em três níveis de urbanização: Não Urbanizado, Processo de Urbanização e Urbanização Consolidada. Para a análise dos dados foram utilizadas análises univariadas (ANOVA) e multivariadas (PCO e PERMDISP) considerando os descritores riqueza de táxons (S), diversidade (H' - Shannon), dominância (1-À - Simpson), frequência relativa dos táxons (TAX) e os grupos morfofuncionais (GMF). A zona média foi a que apresentou maior diversidade e riqueza, porém, para esses descritores o gradiente de urbanização não teve influência sobre as comunidades. Quando comparada a comunidade como um todo foram notadas diferenças nas comunidades tanto no que se refere a urbanização quanto a zonação vertical, e a interação entre os dois fatores. A alta abundância de Chondracanthus acicularis, Ulva e Bryopsis foram capazes de simplificar a comunidade desfazendo o padrão de zonação nas áreas com urbanização consolidada. Uma vez que a urbanização aumenta os impactos na região costeira, podendo diminuir ou romper padrões como a zonação vertical e suas interações ecológicas, fica clara a importância desse tipo de estudo no monitoramento para manutenção da biodiversidade e dos serviços ecológicos.
Palavras-chave: Biodiversidade, grupos morfofuncionais, impactos antrópicos, macroalgas, distribuição vertical.
1.	Introdução
A região entremarés representa a interface entre o ambiente terrestre e marinho, e apresenta variações de acordo com a estação do ano, características geográficas e oceanográficas locais. Essa região pode ser classificada em quatro distintas zonas, relacionadas ao tempo de exposição ao ar: inferior que fica exposta apenas nas marés baixas de sizígia, média que fica exposta ao ar durante as marés de sizígia e de quadratura, a superior que fica submersa apenas nas marés altas e a zona de spray que só está submersa em eventos de tempestades e ressacas, mas sempre recebe influência marinha (Garrison, 2015).
Os organismos que habitam a região entremarés, como as macroalgas e os demais organismos sésseis, estão adaptados ao dinamismo dos fatores que ali atuam, tais como turbulência, eventos periódicos de emersão e imersão, aporte direto e indireto de águas provenientes da drenagem continental, além de físico-químicos e biológicos (Chapman &amp;amp; Trevarthen, 1953). Tais condições geram um padrão de distribuição diferencial dos organismos na região entremarés. Esse padrão é conhecido como zonação vertical e representa a resposta dos organismos ao gradiente de características bióticas e abióticas, estando os organismos distribuídos em faixas ou zonas preferenciais, limitadas pelas suas capacidades de colonizar ou permanecer em um determinado limite (Lubchenco, 1980; Underwood &amp;amp; Chapman, 1996; Rodil, Lastra &amp;amp; Sánchez-Mata, 2006).
A zonação vertical é um padrão consistente até em escala regional em localidades de mesma zona biogeográfica (Chappuis, Terradas, Cefali, Mariani &amp;amp; Ballesteros, 2014), sendo a estabilidade do habitat ligada diretamente aos organismos que compõem os padrões de zonação (Hurd, Harrison, Bischof &amp;amp; Lobban, 2014). Em um ambiente com impactos de origem antrópica esse padrão de distribuição vertical pode ser alterado (Borowitzka, 1972; Díez, Secilla, Santolaria &amp;amp; Grostiaga, 1999). Os estresses causados às comunidades bentônicas incluem pisoteio, aporte de nutrientes através de esgotos industriais ou domésticos, extrativismo e sedimentação, que são os principais impactos diretos e indiretos de ambientes densamente urbanizados (Eriksson &amp;amp; Johansson, 2005; Machado et al., 2009; Scherner et al., 2013). As consequências desses impactos podem ser o desequilíbrio, a simplificação de habitat ou até mesmo a extinção dos padrões de distribuição (Portugal, Carvalho, Macedo-Carneiro, Rossi &amp;amp; Oliveira-Soares, 2016). Tais variações podem ser detectadas através de distintos descritores e métricas (Hewitt, Trush, Legendre, Cummings &amp;amp; Norkko, 2002), sendo aconselhável o uso de mais de um descritor para melhor compreensão de como está o
O Brasil é considerado um país megadiverso (UNEP, 2011) e a região costeira um hotspot para biodiversidade (Marchese, 2015). A zona econômica exclusiva detém o status de área prioritária de baixo impacto, sendo uma região que representa oportunidades proativas de conservação, antes de estar sujeita ao alto grau de impacto (Selig et al., 2014). No entanto, o aumento da densidade demográfica e do desenvolvimento econômico, principalmente da região nordeste (IBGE, 2010), coloca o Brasil em um quadro de alto crescimento de estressores antropogênicos que ameaçam os ecossistemas e biodiversidades locais (Halpern et al., 2015). Assim, torna-se crucial as ações de políticas públicas, sobretudo a produção e divulgação científica na gestão dos recursos e dinâmica dos ambientes costeiros (Scherer, Costa, Boski Azeiteiro &amp;amp; Dias, 2014).
O objetivo deste trabalho foi descrever a influência do nível de urbanização na modificação da estrutura (composição taxonômica, abundância, riqueza, diversidade, dominância e diversidade morfofuncional) das comunidades bentônicas dominadas por macroalgas na zona entremáres de recifes de arenito da costa de Pernambuco (Basil).
2.	Materiais e Métodos
2.1.	ÁREA DE ESTUDO
As amostras foram coletadas, entre novembro de 2013 a agosto de 2014, nos recifes de arenito do estado de Pernambuco, (7°32’52”S, 34°50’27”O e 8°54’57”S, 35°09’76”O), localizados na província biogeográfica do Atlântico Tropical Sul Ocidental (Spalding et al., 2007), na ecorregião do Nordeste brasileiro. O clima local é tropical úmido com temperaturas médias anuais entre 25°C e 30°C. As marés são classificadas como mesomarés semidiurnas, dominadas por ondas (Amaral et al., 2016). Os recifes são corpos rochosos compostos basicamente de grãos de quartzo cimentados por carbonato de cálcio (Manso, Coutinho, Guerra &amp;amp; Soares, 2006), dispostos paralelamente à linha de costa e quepodem ter alguns quilômetros de comprimento e alguns metros de largura (Kempf, 1969; Pereira et al., 2002).
2.2.	Desenho amostral
O método de amostragem adotado para a quantificação da comunidade de macroalgas e outros organismos sésseis foi o de Line Point Transect (Miller &amp;amp; Ambrose,
2000), que consiste em técnica não destrutiva, onde o observador registra, in situ, o táxon em menor nível taxonómico possível, nos pontos previamente definidos. Foram adotadas transecções de 10 metros perpendiculares à linha de costa na borda oceânica dos recifes, nas zonas inferior, média e superior da região entremarés, os registros realizados a cada 10 cm.
A amostragem se deu em cinco áreas recifais da costa pernambucana (Tabela 1), sendo estabelecidos cinco transectos por área. Cada transecto foi dividido em três zonas: Inferior (de 0,0 a 3 m), Média (de 3,1 a 7 m) e Superior (de 7,1 a 10 m). As coletas ocorreram em duas ocasiões, totalizando 150 amostras.
2.3.	Nível de urbanização
Os locais de amostragem foram classificados de acordo com o grau de urbanização, utilizando variáveis listadas na Tabela 1. As variáveis de população (hab), densidade demográfica (hab/km2) e ocupação das residências, foram obtidas no Atlas Digital do Brasil Censo 2010 e pela ferramenta População e domicílios em grade estatística (IBGE, 2010). Os dados de esgotamento sanitário são provenientes do SNIS (2011). As praias de Pina e Boa Viagem foram classificadas como de Urbanização Consolidada (UC), Enseada dos Corais e Suape em Processo de Urbanização (PU) e Toquinho como Não Urbanizada (NU).
Tabela 1. Grau de urbanização de acordo com variáveis usadas para as localidades próximas aos recifes amostrados. Não urbanizado (NU), Processo de urbanização (PU) e Urbanização Consolidada (UC).
Local	Grau de urbanização	Densidade demográfica (hab.km'2)1	População (hab) 1	Ocupação das residências	Esgoto coletado 2	Coordenadas
Pina	UC	&gt;500	29.176	86.4%	35.5 %	(8.08804 S, 34.87887 W)
Boa Viagem	UC	&gt;500	122.922	86%	35.5 %	(8.12451 S, 34.89583 W)
Enseada dos	PU	250.1 a 500	3.700	29.1%	8.8%	(8.31891 S,
Corais						34.94822 W)
Suape	PU	100.1 a 250	1.631	54.9%	8.8%	(8.37005 S, 34.94938 W)
Toquinho *	NU	100.1 a 250	582	32.8%	-	(8.56885 S, 35.03069 W)
1	Fonte: Atlas do Censo Demográfico de 2010.
2	Fonte: SNIS 2011.
* Dados demográficos da grade estatística IBGE (2010). hab: número de habitantes
2.4.	Análise dos dados
Foram utilizados os descritores diversidade (Shannon H' base e), dominância (1-À, Gini-Simpson), número de espécie (S), abundância relativa dos táxons (TAX, menor nível possível identificado in situ) e grupo morfofuncional (GMF, adaptado de Stennick &amp;amp; Dethier, 1993; Benedetti-Cecchi, 2001; Balata, Piazzi &amp;amp; Rindi, 2015), os invertebrados sésseis foram agrupados de acordo com suas classificação trófica (Paine, 1980) Os fatores testados foram: zona, com três níveis (inferior, média e superior) e urbanização também com três níveis (NU, PU e UC).
Para a comparação dos descritores diversidade, dominância e riqueza foi utilizada ANOVA (two-way), uma vez que os pressupostos foram atingidos (testes de Levenee Kolmogorov-Smirnov). O teste post-hoc utilizado foi o de Tukey (HSD).
Foi utilizada PERMANOVA (ANOVA multivariada permutacional) para comparar a estrutura das comunidades entre zonas (ZON) e níveis de urbanização (URB). Para essa análise calculou-se abundância relativa por táxon (Ai = Ni/T, onde Ai é a abundância relativa do táxon i, Ni o número de vezes que o táxon apareceu na amostra e T o total de organismos na amostra). A matriz de similaridade foi formada com índice de Bray-Curtis e dados transformados em Log (x+1). Uma medida para avaliar a p diversidade é a dispersão multivariada dos grupos (Anderson, Ellingsen &amp;amp; McArdle 2006), e no presente estudo foi utilizada a análise PERMADISP (Anderson, Gorley &amp;amp; Clarke, 2008).
As representações gráficas do plano multivariado foram feitas a partir de gráficos de PCO (Análise de coordenadas principais). Para identificar quais táxons estão mais correlacionados com os fatores testados foi feita a correlação de Pearson (r&gt;0,5) contra os principais eixos da PCO. Para todos os testes estatísticos foi utilizado o nível de significância de 5%. As análises univariadas foram realizados no programa STATISTICA v10 (Statsoft, 2011). Todas as análises multivariadas foram realizadas no programa Primer E v6 Permanova+ (Anderson et al., 2008)
3.	Resultados
Foram registrados 47 táxons, com predominância de macroalgas (Tabela 2). Trinta e seis táxons foram em locais UC, 36 em PU e 28 em NU. Foram registrados 37 táxons na zona inferior, 43 na média e 40 na superior.
Tabela 2. Lista dos organismos e os respectivos grupos morfofuncionais registrados na região entremarés dos recifes de arenito da costa de Pernambuco.			
Táxon		Grupo Morfofuncional	GMF
	Anadyomene J.V.Lamouroux	Folioso	FO
	Bryopsis J.V.Lamouroux	Sifonáceo	SI
Cü H—&amp;lt;&gt;s -C Q_ O O -C O	Caulerpa cupressoides (Vahl) C.Agardh	Sifonáceo	SI
	Caulerpa racemosa (Forsskal) J.Agardh	Sifonáceo	SI
	Caulerpa sertularioides (S.G. Gmelin) M. Howe	Sifonáceo	SI
	Chaetomorpha antennina (Bory de Saint-Vincent) Kützing	Filamentoso	FI
	Cladophora Kützing	Filamentoso	FI
	Dictyosphaeria Decaisne	Corticado	CO
	Ulva lactuca Linnaeus	Folioso	FO
	Ulva lingulata A.P.de Candolle	Filamentoso	FI
	Chnoospora J.Agardh	Canópia	CA
Cü H—&amp;lt;&gt;s -C Q_ O -C O O	Dictyopteris delicatula J.V.Lamouroux	Corticado Folioso	CF
	Dictyota J.V.Lamouroux	Corticado Folioso	CF
	Ectocarpales C.E.Bessey	Filamentoso	FI
	Padina. Adanson	Corticado Folioso	CF
	Sargassum C.Agardh	Canópia	CA
	Acanthophora spicifera (M.Vahl) Borgesen	Corticado	CO
	Amansia J.V.Lamouroux	Corticado	CO
	Bryothamnion seaforthii (Turner) Kützing	Corticado	CO
	Bryothamnion triquetrum (S.G.Gmelin) M.A.Howe	Corticado	CO
	Corallinaceae J.V.Lamouroux	Calcário Articulado	AC
	Centroceras clavulatum (C.Agardh) Montagne	Filamentoso	FI
	Ceramiaceae Dumortier	Filamentoso	FI
	Chondracanthus acicularis (Roth) Fredericq	Corticado	CO
	Corallina Linnaeus	Calcário Articulado	AC
	Cryptonemia seminervis (C.Agardh) J.Agardh	Corticado	CO
Cü H—&amp;lt;&gt;s -C Q_ O ■0 O .C ar	Digenea simplex (Wulfen) C.Agardh	Corticado	CO
	Gelidiella acerosa (Forsskál) Feldmann &amp;amp; G.Hamel	Corticado	CO
	Ceratodictyon planicauli (W.R. Taylor) M.J. Wynne	Corticado	CO
	Gelidium J.V.Lamouroux	Corticado	CO
	Gracilaria Greville	Corticado	CO
	Hypnea musciformis (Wulfen) J.V.Lamouroux	Corticado	CO
	Jania J.V.Lamouroux	Calcário Articulado	AC
	Laurencia dendroidea J.Agardh	Corticado	CO
	Laurencia translucida M.T.Fujii &amp;amp; Cordeiro-Marino	Corticado	CO
	Palisada flagellifera (J.Agardh) K.W.Nam	Corticado	CO
	Palisada furcata (Cordeiro-Marino &amp;amp; M.T.Fujii) Cassano &amp;amp; M.T.Fujii	Corticado	CO
	Palisada perforata (Bory de Saint-Vincent) K.W.Nam	Corticado	CO
	Wrangelia C.Agardh	Filamentoso	FI
	“Turf”	Filamentoso	FI
	Brachidontes sp. Swainson	Filtrador	FL
tn CD cn cn "CD CO CO 'cü E c&amp;lt;	Cirripedia (infra-Class)	Filtrador	FL
	Porifera (Phylum)	Filtrador	FL
	Echinometra lucunter Linneaus	Herbívoro	HE
	Palythoa Lamouroux Polychaeta (Class)	Coral Filtrador	CN FL
	Protopalythoa Verril	Coral	CN
A riqueza variou entre os níveis de urbanização e zonas do entremarés. Diversidade e dominância variaram significativamente apenas entre zonas. A zona MED foi diferente dos outros dois níveis para os três descritores (Tabela 3). Em relação aos níveis de urbanização, a diversidade variou significativamente entre os níveis UC x NU e PU x NU. Por sua vez, a riqueza variou significativamente entre os níveis UC x PU e PU x NU (Tabela 4).
Tabela 3. Resumo da ANOVA considerando os fatores e níveis de urbanização (URB) e zonas entremarés (ZON).
ANOVA (TwoWay)						
			H' (Diversidade)			
Fatores	df		SS	MS	F	p
ZON	2		1,87	0,94	78,82	0,002
URB	2		0,73	0,37	27,98	0,052
ZONxURB	4		22,5	0,56	37,01	0,07
		S (Número de espécies)				
	df		SS	MS	F	p
ZON	2		103,2	51,63	14,03	0,001
URB	2		29,84	14,92	40,56	0,034
ZONxURB	4		19,87	49,68	13,50	0,25
			1-À (Dominância)			
	df		SS	MS	F	p
ZON	2		0,220	0,110	44,47	0,017
URB	2		0,128	641,8	25,85	0,074
ZONxURB	4		0,432	0,108	59,08	0,001
Post-hoc de Tukey						
	H'		S	1-À		
Zonas	t	p	t	p	t	P		
INF x MED	38,99	0,001	41,15	0,001	33,10	0,001		
INF x SUP	0,660	0,496	0,940	0,36	14,07	0,173		
MED x SUP	28,19	0,005	46,831	0,001	14,11	0,14		
Grau de						
Urbanização						
UC x PU	0,231	0,807	20,35	0,046	NS	NS		
UC x NU	20,66	0,041	12,68	0,197	NS	NS		
PU x NU	22,21	0,029	26,85	0,008	NS	NS		
NS - não significativo
Permanova
	TAX Graus de liberdade	Pseudo-F	GMF		P(perm)
			P(perm)	Pseudo-F	
ZON (INF, MED, SUP)	2	13,58	0,001	14,44	0,001
URB (UC, UP, NU)	2	40,45	0,001	60,77	0,001
ZONxURB	4	4,62	0,001	4,39	0,001
Pairwise test
TAX	GMF
ZON	t	P(perm)	t	P(perm)
INFxMED	3,01	0,001	28,82	0,001
INFxSUP	4,96	0,001	50,92	0,001
MEDxSUP	2,71	0,001	30,12	0,001
URB				
UCxPU	8,27	0,001	96,85	0,001
UCxNU	6,22	0,001	83,97	0,001
PUxNU	3,15	0,001	30,48	0,001
Interação de UC em ZON
INFxMED	1,46	0,064	18,58	0,045
INFxSUP	2,95	0,001	34,41	0,001
MEDxSUP	1,77	0,017	19,93	0,019
Interação de PU em ZON				
INFxMED	24,02	0,001	26,63	0,002
INFxSUP	43,16	0,001	37,57	0,001
MEDxSUP	22,50	0,003	18,71	0,016
Interação de NU em ZON
INFxMED		26,35	0,001	23,24	0,017
INFxSUP		34,59	0,001	37,83	0,001
MEDxSUP		18,44	0,006	17,83	0,046
Permadisp (Pairwise)					
	TAX			GMF	
	t	P(perm)	t	P(perm)	
(INF,MED)	0,30	0,80	0,81	0,48	
(INF,SUP)	0,35	0,73	0,61	0,59	
(MED,SUP)	0,31	0,97	0,11	0,92	
(UC,PU)	0,13	0,88	0,46	0,63	
(UC,NU)	4,50	0,001	1,91	0,007	
(PU,NU)	4,50	0,001	3,24	0,006	
Foi possível identificar a formação de grupos de amostras distintos utilizando tanto a abundância relativa dos táxons, como os grupos morfofuncionais. O descritor TAX foi mais preciso em mostrar que os níveis extremos dos fatores Urbanização (UC x NU) e Zonas (INF x SUP) são diferentes tanto em relação à posição quanto às suas dispersões no plano multivariado (Fig 1, A e B) (Tab 4). Para os descritores GMF e TAX
os eixos dos PCO1 explicam cerca de 49 e 32 % da variação das amostras, respectivamente. Esses eixos estão fortemente associados à separação dos níveis de urbanização PU e NU com valores negativos (esquerda) e UC com valores positivos (direita) da Figura 1. Para os descritores GMF e TAX os eixos dos PCO2 explicam cerca de 22 e 18 % da variação das amostras, respectivamente, estando associado à separação dos níveis inferior e superior do fator ZON, quando associado aos níveis de urbanização PU e NU (Fig 1 B), como mostra os resultados de interação da PERMANOVA (Tab 4), porém com uma fraca separação quando comparado com o nível
UC de urbanização.
Figura 1. Representação gráfica do PCO. A) Análise baseada no descritor Grupo morfofuncional (GMF). B) Análise baseada no descritor Frequência dos táxons (TAX). Os diagramas em círculos representam vetores de correlação de Pearson (r&gt;0,04) para as variáveis. Filtrador (FL), Canópia (CA), Corticado folioso (CF), Calcário articulado (AC), Sifonáceo (SI) e Folioso (FO) para os grupos morfofuncionais. Palisada perforata (Pal), Laurencia dendroidea (Lau), Sargassum sp (Sar), Ulva sp. (Ulv), Chondracanthus acicularis (Chon) e Bryopsis sp. (Bry).
Tabela 5. Correlação de (r) Pearson &gt;0,4 dos táxons de algas de Grupo morfofuncional (GMF) e os principais eixos da PCO.
Táxons	PCO1	PCO2
(Bry) Bryopsis	0,46	-0,21
(Chon) Chondracanthus acicularis	0,60	-0,11
(Lau) Laurencia dendroidea	-0,50	-0,27
(Pal) Palisada perforata	-0,28	0,88
(Sar) Sargassum	-0,74	-0,47
(Ulv) Ulva	0,78	0,01
Grupo morfofuncional (GMF)		
FO (Folioso)	0,75	-0,15
AC (Calcário articulado)	0,29	-0,41
SI (Sifonáceo)	0,47	-0,60
CA (Canópia)	-0,73	0,18
CF (Corticado folioso)	-0,34	0,20
FL (Filtrador)	-0,01	-0,59
4. Discussão
Os resultados obtidos evidenciam o padrão de distribuição vertical das comunidades bentônicas da região entremarés recifal e o efeito da urbanização sobre as mesmas. A zona média dos recifes apresentou os maiores valores de diversidade, riqueza e dominância. Isto se deve ao fato da zona média estar localizada entre as zonas inferior e superior e possuir espécies em comum com estas zonas. Recentemente, Rabelo, Soares, Bezerra &amp;amp; Matthews-Cascon (2015) e Portugal et al. (2016) também identificaram claro padrão de zonação em recifes do Nordeste brasileiro. No entanto, estes autores encontraram maior diversidade e número de espécies na zona inferior do entremarés. Ocorre que os recifes estudados por esses autores (costa do Cerá-Brasil) formam grandes platôs, sendo mais extensos e menos íngremes que o os do presente estudo, os quais apresentam maior declividade em direção ao mar (Bezerra et al., 2005; Ferreira-Junior, Araujo, Vieira, Neumann &amp;amp; Gregorio, 2011).
Nas zonas mais elevadas da região entremarés dos recifes, estresses abióticos como dessecação e irradiância são fatores limitantes para os organismos (Raffaelli &amp;amp; Hawkins, 1996), uma vez que ao se afastar da água as condições tornam-se mais hostis
Além disso, outros fatores, como batimento de ondas, podem influenciar a distribuição das comunidades nas distintas zonas (Heaven &amp;amp; Scrosati, 2008). A zona inferior é a que mais sofre com alto grau de hidrodinamismo e o número de espécies que suportam e/ou conseguem se estabelecer ao estresse mecânico das ondas e à pressão de herbivoria/predação de espécies chaves como o ouriço (Wootton, 1995), é limitada, diminuindo a riqueza de espécies e diversidade dessa zona (Lubchenco &amp;amp; Menge, 1978; Archambault &amp;amp; Bourget, 1996).
Foi evidente a variação das comunidades em locais com distintos níveis de urbanização. Assim como a zona média da região entremarés, o nível de urbanização intermediário (PU) apresentou os maiores valores significativos de riqueza e diversidade. A perda da qualidade de um ecossistema pode ser demonstrada por decréscimos nos valores de riqueza de espécie e diversidade, o que seria esperado com o aumento do nível de urbanização (Wells, Wilkinson, Wood &amp;amp; Scanlan, 2007). Porém, ao analisar um gradiente de distúrbio, deve-se levar em conta que o grau de impacto intermediário pode aumentar a diversidade, uma vez que as sucessões secundárias a um distúrbio geram um mosaico de diferentes estágios sucessionais, promovendo a coexistência de um maior número de espécies (Grime, 1974; Connell, 1978; Johst &amp;amp; Huth, 2005).
As análises univariadas não conseguiram detectar mudanças na estrutura destas comunidades em relação ao fator urbanização, sendo os dados multivariados de frequência relativa mais adequados para evidenciar estas mudanças. As inferências ecológicas evidenciadas pelos testes multivariados são de grande importância para elucidação dos efeitos que os fatores e suas interações causam num experimento ou determinada comunidade, uma vez que testam esses efeitos em todas as assembleias de espécies ao mesmo tempo (Anderson, 2001).
As respostas dos grupos morfofuncionais foram identificadas tanto em relação aos níveis de zonação quanto aos níveis de urbanização. Steneck &amp;amp; Dethier (1994) sugerem que poucos atributos das espécies possuem uma importância substancial na estrutura da comunidade de macroalgas e essas características são compartilhadas mesmo com espécies de histórias evolutivas distintas. A assembleia de organismos classificados em sua função ecológica foi sensível a mudanças no nível de urbanização, no entanto não obteve resolução suficiente para contrastar o efeito do gradiente de urbanização nas distintas zonas da região entremarés.
O grupo dos filtradores (FL) e das algas calcárias articuladas (AC) possuem sua distribuição correlacionada principalmente com o gradiente vertical de zonação, sendo FL mais correlacionado com a região superior e AC com a inferior. Tal padrão é persistente em vários estudos que analisam gradiente vertical, tanto em regiões tropicais (Portugal et al., 2016), quanto temperadas (Bustamante, Branch &amp;amp; Eekhout, 1997; Gómez &amp;amp; Houvinen, 2011). Por outro lado, os grupos das algas foliosas (FO) e sifonáceas (SI) tiveram correlação positiva com o gradiente de urbanização, ou seja, preferiram ambientes com maior grau de urbanização e impacto antrópico. Essas algas possuem estratégias comuns, que são o rápido crescimento em ambientes com elevada disponibilidade de nutrientes e em estágios iniciais de sucessão. Experimentos de bioinvasão e recrutamento atestam que essas algas tendem a se estabelecer com a disponibilidade de substrato (Lotze, Schramm, Schories &amp;amp; Worm, 1999; Arrontes, 2002; Arenas, Sánchez, Hawkins &amp;amp; Jenkins 2006).
Na região entremarés, as comunidades de organismos são estruturadas por diferentes processos como distúrbio físico, predação, heterogeneidade espacial, limitação de recrutamento e diferentes histórias evolutivas (Benedetti-Cecchi &amp;amp; Cinelli, 1996; Airoldi, 2000; Menge et al. 2005). Os distúrbios causados pela urbanização (pisoteio, input de nutrientes, extrativismo, contaminação, mudança nos padrões de sedimentação) também são fatores que atuam nessas comunidades. Esses processos que atuam sobre a diversidade nem sempre promovem a complementariedade dos usos do recurso, especialmente onde a diversidade das assembleias bentônicas é mantida por um mosaico de patches em diferentes estágios sucessionais. Desta forma, os distúrbios ou a alteração no padrão nem sempre são notados pelos grupos morfofuncionais.
A hipótese principal do estudo foi aceita apenas ao se comparar as comunidades das distintas zonas no gradiente de urbanização através do descritor de abundância relativa dos táxons. De fato, esse foi o maior nível de detalhe para as comunidades estudadas. A diferença das comunidades se dá no plano multivariado, tanto em relação à distância dos centróides (URB e ZON), quanto na dispersão das amostras (URB). Quando analisada a interação dos fatores, fica evidente a perda do padrão de zonação vertical através da simplificação da zona inferior e média de ambientes de urbanização consolidada. Esse evento não se repete nos níveis PU e NU.
As macroalgas do gênero Sargassum são consideradas perenes e de estágio de sucessão avançada, e estão correlacionadas com a zona inferior das localidades com menor nível de urbanização, bem como Laurencia dendroidea. Palisada perforata tem preferência pelas zonas média e superior de ambientes com pouca urbanização. Uma vasta literatura (Areces, 2001; Orfanidis, Panayotidis &amp;amp; Stamatis, 2003; Lakkis &amp;amp; Novel-
Lakkis, 2007; Martins et al., 2012, Areces et al., 2015) cita espécies de Laurencia, Saragassum e P. perforata (como Laurencia papillosa) como macroalgas que tendem a colonizar lugares pouco impactados por contaminação orgânica. Por outro lado, algas como Ulva, Bryopsis e Chondracanthus acicularis foram constantes e dominantes nos recifes dos locais de urbanização consolidada, e não apresentaram correlações com a zonação vertical. Vários trabalhos no Brasil associam essas macroalgas com os efeitos deletérios da urbanização (Martins et al., 2012; Scherner et al., 2013; Portugal et al., 2016), salientando que o aumento da presença de Ulva em um determinado ambiente é um bom indicador de adição de compostos nitrogenados na água.
Em conclusão, foi demonstrado que um padrão ecológico forte como a zonação vertical dos organismos bentônicos, é um indicativo de saúde ambiental, abrindo novas perspectivas de estudos sobre a perda de diversidade e serviços ecossistêmicos nos ambientes recifais tropicais de áreas impactadas.
Agradecimentos
Os autores agradecem as instituições de financiamento: Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) pela bolsa de Doutorado Sanduíche, ao Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq) pelo financiamento do projeto (Proc. 484647/2012-1) no qual este trabalho se insere e a Fundação de Amparo à Ciência e Tecnologia de Pernambuco (FACEPE) pela bolsa de Doutorado do primeiro autor. MT Fujii agradece ao CNPq pela Bolsa de Produtividade em Pesquisa (Proc. 303915/2013-7).
Referências
Airoldi, L. (2000). Effects of disturbance, life histories, and overgrowth on coexistence of algal crusts and turfs. Ecology, 81(3), 798-814.
Amaral, A. C. Z., Corte, G. N., Filho, J. S. R., Denadai, M. R., Colling, L. A., Borzone, C., &amp;amp; Roberto, J. (2016). Brazilian sandy beaches: characteristics, ecosystem services, impacts, knowledge and priorities. Braz'lian Journal of Oceanography, 64 (2), 5-16.
Anderson, M. J. (2001). A new method for non-parametric multivariate analysis of variance. Austral ecology, 26(1), 32-46.
Anderson, M. J., Crist, T. O., Chase, J. M., Vellend, M., Inouye, B. D., Freestone, A. L., &amp;amp; Harrison, S. P. (2010). Navigating the multiple meanings of p diversity: a roadmap for the practicing ecologist. Ecology letters, 14(1), 19-28.
Anderson, M.J., Gorley R.N &amp;amp; Clarke K.R. (2008). PERMANOVA+ for PRIMER: Guide to software and Statistical Methods. PRIMER-E:Plymouth, UK.
Archambault, P., &amp;amp; Bourget, E. (1996). Scales of coastal heterogeneity and benthic intertidal species richness, diversity and abundance. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 136, 111-121.
Areces A. J., Cocentino, A. L. M., Reis, T. N. V., Vasconcelos, E. R. T. P. P., Guimarães-Barros, N. C. &amp;amp; Fujii, M. T. (2015). Las Macroalgas como Bioindicadoras da Calidad Ambiental y Cambios Climáticos. Guia Prática. Brazilian Journal of Ecology, v. Especial, 1-64.
Areces, A.J. (2001). La ficoflora intermareal como bioindicadora de calidad ambiental. Estudio de caso: el litoral habanero. In: Alveal, K., Antezana, T. (eds.). Sustentabilidad de la biodiversidad, un problema actual. Bases científico-técnicas, Teorizaciones y Proyecciones., (569-589). Univ. de Concepción, Concepción, Chile.
Arenas, F., Sánchez, I., Hawkins, S. J., &amp;amp; Jenkins, S. R. (2006). The invasibility of marine algal assemblages: role of functional diversity and identity. Ecology, 87(11), 2851-2861.
Arrontes, J. 2002. Mechanisms of range expansion in the intertidal brown alga Fucus serratus in northern Spain. Marine Biology 141:1059-1067.
Balata, D., Piazzi, L., &amp;amp; Rindi, F. (2011). Testing a new classification of morphological functional groups of marine macroalgae for the detection of responses to stress. Marine biology, 158(11), 2459-2469.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L. (2001). Variability in abundance of algae and invertebrates at different spatial scales on rocky sea shores. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 215, 79-92.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L., Bertocci, I., Vaselli, S., &amp;amp; Maggi, E. (2006). Temporal variance reverses the impact of high mean intensity of stress in climate change experiments. Ecology, 87(10), 2489-2499.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L., Nuti, S., &amp;amp; Cinelli, F. (1996). Analysis of spatial and temporal variability in interactions among algae, limpets and mussels in low-shore habitats on the west coast of Italy. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 144, 87-96.
Bezerra, F. H. R., Amaral, R. F., Lima-Filho, F. P., Ferreira Junior, A. V., Sena, E., &amp;amp; Diniz, R. F. (2005). Beachrock Fracturing in Brazil. Journal of Coastal Research, 42, 319-332.
Borowitzka, M. A. (1972). Intertidal algal species diversity and the effect of pollution. Marine and Freshwater Research, 23(2), 73-84.
Bustamante, R. H., Branch, G. M., &amp;amp; Eekhout, S. (1997). The influences of physical factors on the distribution and zonation patterns of South African rocky-shore communities. South African Journal of Marine Science, 18(1), 119-136.
Chapman, V. J., &amp;amp; Trevarthen, C. B. (1953). General schemes of classification in relation to marine coastal zonation. Journal of Ecology, 41(1), 198-204.
Chappuis, E., Terradas, M., Cefali, M. E., Mariani, S., &amp;amp; Ballesteros, E. (2014). Vertical zonation is the main distribution pattern of littoral assemblages on rocky shores at a regional scale. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 147, 113-122.
Connell, J.H. (1978). Diversity in tropical rain forests and coral reefs. Science, 199, 1302-1310.
Diez, I., Secilla, A., Santolaria, A., &amp;amp; Gorostiaga, J. M. (1999). Phytobenthic intertidal community structure along an environmental pollution gradient. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 38(6), 463-472.
Eriksson, B. K., &amp;amp; Johansson, G. (2005). Effects of sedimentation on macroalgae: species-specific responses are related to reproductive traits. Oecologia, 143(3), 438-448.
Ferreira Junior, A. V., Araujo, T. C. M., Vieira, M. M., Neumann, V. H. &amp;amp; Gregorio, M. N. (2011). Petrologia dos arenitos de praia (beachrocks) na costa central de Pernambuco. Geociências (UNESP), 30, 545-559.
Garbary, D. J., (2007). The margin of the sea: survival at the top of the tides. In: J. SECKBACH (ed.), Algae and cyanobacteria in extreme environments: (pp. 173-191). Berlin: Springer-Verlag.
Garrison, T. S. (2015). Oceanography: an invitation to marine science. Nelson Education.
Gómez, I., &amp;amp; Huovinen, P. (2011). Morpho-functional patterns and zonation of South Chilean seaweeds: the importance of photosynthetic and bio-optical traits. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 422, 77-91.
Grime, J. (1974). Vegetation classification by reference to strategies. Nature, 250, 26-31.
Halpern, B. S., Frazier, M., Potapenko, J., Casey, K. S., Koenig, K., Longo, C. &amp;amp; Walbridge, S. (2015). Spatial and temporal changes in cumulative human impacts on the world/'s ocean. Nature communications, 6.
Heaven, C. S., &amp;amp; Scrosati, R. A. (2008). Benthic community composition across gradients of intertidal elevation, wave exposure, and ice scour in Atlantic Canada. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 369, 13-23.
Hewitt, J. E., Thrush, S. F., Legendre, P., Cummings, V. J., &amp;amp; Norkko, A. (2002). Integrating heterogeneity across spatial scales: interactions between Atrina zelandica and benthic macrofauna. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 239, 115-128.
Hurd, C. L., Harrison, P. J., Bischof, K., &amp;amp; Lobban, C. S. (2014). Physico-Chemical factors as environmental stressors in seaweed biology. In: Seaweed ecology and physiology. Cambridge University Press. 294-348
IBGE - Institute of Geography and Statistics. (2010). Censo demografico de 2010. Rio de Janeiro
Johst, K., &amp;amp; Huth, A. (2005). Testing the intermediate disturbance hypothesis: when will there be two peaks of diversity? Diversity and Distributions, 11(1), 111-120.
Kempf, M. (1969). A plataforma continental de Pernambuco (Brasil): nota preliminar sobre a natureza do fundo. Trabalhos Oceanográficos, 9, 125-148.
Lakkis, S., &amp;amp; Novel-Lakkis, V. (2007). Diversity and distribution of macrophytes along the coast of Lebanon (Levantine Basin, Eastern Mediterranean). Rapport Commission International pour l'exploration scientifique de la Mer Mediterranee, 38.
Lotze, H. K., Schramm, W., Schories, D., &amp;amp; Worm, B. (1999). Control of macroalgal blooms at early developmental stages: Pilayella littoralis versus Enteromorpha spp. Oecologia, 119(1), 46-54.
Lubchenco, J. (1980). Algal zonation in the New England rocky intertidal community: an experimental analysis. Ecology, 61(2), 333-344.
Lubchenco, J., &amp;amp; Menge, B. A. (1978). Community development and persistence in a low rocky intertidal zone. Ecological Monographs, 48(1), 67-94.
Machado, R. C. A., Gusmão, L. C., Vila-Nova, D. A., Leal, A. F., Oliveira, A. C. A., &amp;amp; Soares, C. L. R. (2009). Percepção sócio-ambiental dos turistas e trabalhadores da praia de Porto de Galinhas (Pernambuco-Brasil) acerca do ecossitema recifal. RGCI-Revista de Gestão Costeira Integrada, 9(3) 71-78.
Manso, V. A. V., Coutinho, P. N., Guerra, N.C., &amp;amp; Soares, C. F. A. (2006). Pernambuco. In: D. Muehe (Ed), Erosão e Progradação no Litoral Brasileiro (pp.179-196), Brasília, Brasil, Ministério do Meio Ambiente.
Marchese, C. (2015). Biodiversity hotspots: A shortcut for a more complicated concept. Global Ecology and Conservation, 3, 297-309.
Martins, C. D., Arantes, N., Faveri, C., Batista, M. B., Oliveira, E. C., Pagliosa, P. R., &amp;amp; Horta, P. A. (2012). The impact of coastal urbanization on the structure of phytobenthic communities in southern Brazil. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 64(4), 772-778.
Menge, B. A., Allison, G. W., Blanchette, C. A., Farrell, T. M., Olson, A. M., Turner, T. A., &amp;amp; van Tamelen, P. (2005). Stasis or kinesis? Hidden dynamics of a rocky intertidal macrophyte mosaic revealed by a spatially explicit approach. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 314(1), 3-39.
Miller, A. W., &amp;amp; Ambrose, R. F. (2000). Sampling patchy distributions: comparison of sampling designs in rocky intertidal habitats. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 196, 1-14.
Orfanidis, S., Panayotidis, P., &amp;amp; Stamatis, N. (2003). An insight to the ecological evaluation index (EEI). Ecological indicators, 3(1), 27-33.
Paine, R. T. (1980). Food webs: linkage, interaction strength and community infrastructure. Journal of Animal Ecology, 49(3), 667-685.
Pereira, S. M. B.; Oliveira-Carvalho, M. F.; Angeiras, J. A. P; Bandeira-Pedrosa, M. E.; Oliveira, N. M. B.; Torres, J, Gestinari, L. M. S.; Cocentino, A. L. M., Santos, M. D, Nascimento, P. R. F. &amp;amp; Cavalcanti D. R. (2002). Algas marinhas bentônicas do Estado de Pernambuco. In: M. Tabarelli &amp;amp; J. M. C. Silva (Ed.). Diagnóstico da Biodiversidade de Pernambuco (pp. 97-124). Recife: Editora Massangana.
Portugal, A. B., Carvalho, F. L., de Macedo Carneiro, P. B., Rossi, S., &amp;amp; de Oliveira Soares, M. (2016). Increased anthropogenic pressure decreases species richness in tropical intertidal reefs. Marine Environmental Research, 120, 44-54.
Quinn GP, Keough MJ (2002) Experimental design and data analysis for biologists. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.
Rabelo, E. F., Soares, M. D. O., Bezerra, L. E. A., &amp;amp; Matthews-Cascon, H. (2015). Distribution pattern of zoanthids (Cnidaria: Zoantharia) on a tropical reef. Marine Biology Research, 11(6), 584-592.
Raffaelli, D. &amp;amp; Hawkins. S. (1996). Intertidal Ecology. Chapman &amp;amp; Hall, London.
Rodil, I. F., Lastra, M., &amp;amp; Sánchez-Mata, A. G. (2006). Community structure and intertidal zonation of the macroinfauna in intermediate sandy beaches in temperate latitudes: North coast of Spain. Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 67(1), 267-279.
Scherer, M., Costa, M. F., Boski, T., Azeiteiro, U., &amp;amp; Dias, J. A. (2014). Integrated coastal management in Latin America: the ever new world. Journal of Integrated Coastal Zone Management, 14, 663-668.
Scherner, F., Horta, P.A., de Oliveira, E.C., Simonassi, J.C., Hall-Spencer, J.M., Chow, F., Nunes, J.M.C. &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B., 2013. Coastal urbanization leads to remarkable seaweed species loss and community shifts along the SW Atlantic. Marine Pollution Bulletin 76, 106e115.
Selig, E. R., Turner, W. R., Troeng, S., Wallace, B. P., Halpern, B. S., Kaschner, K., &amp;amp; Mittermeier, R. A. (2014). Global priorities for marine biodiversity conservation. PLoS One, 9(1), e82898.
SNIS. (2011). SISTEMA NACIONAL DE INFORMAÇÕES SOBRE SANEAMENTO: Diagnóstico dos serviços de água e esgotos 2011. (pp. 432). Brasília BR, Ministério das cidades.
Spalding, M. D., Fox, H. E., Allen, G. R., Davidson, N., Ferdana, Z. A., Finlayson, M. A. X. &amp;amp; Martin, K. D. (2007). Marine ecoregions of the world: a bioregionalization of coastal and shelf areas. BioScience, 57(7), 573-583.
Stachowicz, J. J., Fried, H., Osman, R. W., &amp;amp; Whitlatch, R. B. (2002). Biodiversity, invasion resistance, and marine ecosystem function: reconciling pattern and process. Ecology, 83(9), 2575-2590.
StatSoft, Inc. (2011). STATISTICA (data analysis software system), version 10. www.statsoft.com
Steneck, R. S., &amp;amp; Dethier, M. N. (1994). A functional group approach to the structure of algal dominated communities. Oikos, 476-498.
Underwood, A. J., &amp;amp; Chapman, M. G. (1996). Scales of spatial patterns of distribution of intertidal invertebrates. Oecologia, 107(2), 212-224.
Unep. (2011). Annual Report 2010: A Year in Review. United Nations Environment Programme, Nairobi.
Wells, E., Wilkinson, M., Wood, P., &amp;amp; Scanlan, C. (2007). The use of macroalgal species richness and composition on intertidal rocky seashores in the assessment of ecological quality under the European Water Framework Directive. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 55(1), 151-161.
Wootton, J. T. (1995). Effects of birds on sea urchins and algae: a lower-intertidal trophic cascade. Ecoscience, 2(4), 321-328.
Capítulo IV - Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) baseado na frequência de macroalgas indicadoras de processos antrópicos em regiões entremarés de estruturas recifais: estudo de caso no Nordeste brasileiro
A SER SUBMETIDO NA REVISTA ECOLOGICAL INDICATORS (ISSN: 1470-160X)
Resumo
Apesar da grande importância das comunidades de zonas entremarés de regiões tropicais, por sua contribuição para a biodiversidade costeira, poucos índices para avaliar esses ambientes estão estabelecidos, em comparação a regiões temperadas. O objetivo deste trabalho foi demonstrar a estrutura e relevância do índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA), baseado na frequência relativa de táxons de macroalgas indicadoras. O índice proposto possui métricas baseadas em lista de espécies, frequência relativa teórica e frequência relativa real dos táxons indicadores. O índice foi testado em um estudo realizado na costa de Pernambuco (Nordeste do Brasil) ao longo de gradiente de urbanização, classificado como Não urbanizado (NU), em Processo de urbanização (PU) e Urbanização consolidada (UC) e em dois tipos de estruturas recifais distintas: Recifes de arenito (RA) e Recifes coralíneos-algáceos (CA). As classes de qualidade para estes indicadores são baseadas em dados ecológicos, literatura específica e julgamento de especialista. Uma prévia da aplicação destas métricas foi realizada para locais com status ambientais de urbanização teoricamente bons (NU), intermediários (PU) e ruins (UC). Como resultado, o IDA respondeu de uma forma significativa para o gradiente de pressão testada, provando ser apropriado para o tipo de pressão analisado e obtenção de resultados coerentes na avaliação do estado de conservação. Em conclusão, o IDA pode ser uma ferramenta eficaz para avaliação da qualidade ecológica das comunidades costeiras consolidadas, com base na análise de comunidades de macroalgas.
Palavras-chave: bioindicação, ecossistemas costeiros, macroalgas, qualidade ambiental, status ecológico.
1.	Introdução
A região costeira é uma área fortemente influenciada por impactos antropogênicos, como crescimento populacional e atividades sócio econômicas, as quais incluem: agricultura, pesca, aquicultura, indústria e turismo. Os impactos nos ecossistemas associados a essa região são plurais e acumulativos, tais quais destruição de habitats, sobrepesca, poluição, espécies invasoras e em maiores escalas o aumento do nível do mar e o aquecimento global (UNEP-WCMC, 2011). Nenhuma dessas pressões sobre o ambiente é isolada, e seus efeitos acumulativos impactam os ecossistemas marinhos e sua capacidade de oferecer bens e serviços ecossistêmicos (Worm et al., 2006; Halpern et al., 2008).
Desde o início dos anos 90, com o alerta dos efeitos das mudanças climáticas na conferência ECO-92, acordos internacionais para proteção da biodiversidade foram assinados (United Nations, 1992), e mais atenção foi prestada na avaliação da evolução dos ecossistemas (Barange, 2003). Nesse contexto, houve o desenvolvimento de políticas públicas voltadas para a observação, preservação e recuperação de ambientes naturais (Mann, 2000). Na União Europeia, o Quadro de Diretivas da Água (WFD, 2000/60EC; E.C., 2000) incluiu a pesquisa de comunidades biológicas (fitoplâncton, macroalgas, fanerógamas marinhas, macroinvertebrados e peixes) como bioindicadores para avaliar o estado ecológico de um ecossistema.
No Brasil, o Plano Nacional de Gerenciamento Costeiro - PNGC (MMA, 2015), discorre sobre o zoneamento e os usos e atividades na Zona Costeira, dando prioridade à conservação dos ambientes naturais. Tradicionalmente, no Brasil, a avaliação de impactos ambientais em ecossistemas aquáticos tem sido realizada através da medição de alterações nas concentrações de variáveis físicas e químicas. O Instituto Nacional de Ciência e Tecnologia para Mudanças Climáticas (INCT-MC), fundado em 2008, possui agenda científica voltada para monitoramento e mitigação de problemas decorrentes das mudanças climáticas. Dentro desse panorama, surge a Rede de Monitoramento de Habitats Bentônicos Costeiros (ReBentos), que possui como recomendações estudos sobre a variabilidade e abundância de espécies indicadoras, sensíveis às mudanças nos parâmetros ambientais, através de uma abordagem padronizada (Turra &amp;amp; Denadai, 2015).
As macroalgas são organismos úteis para monitorar a qualidade ambiental e detectar impactos provenientes de atividades antropogênicas (Piazzi et al., 2001; Díez et al., 2009). Por conta de sua condição séssil, esses organismos estão suscetíveis aos efeitos a longo prazo da exposição a nutrientes e outros poluentes, resultando em um
Uma ampla variedade de índices baseado em macroalgas indicadoras (vide Areces et al., 2015) já foram testados em regiões temperadas, com destaque para a constante oferta de índices e métodos relativos às normas do WFD-EU (Quadro de Diretivas da Água da União Europeia) (ex. Blanfuné, 2017). No entanto, são escassos os índices publicados baseados nas macroalgas indicadoras na região tropical (ex. Areces, 2001; Areces et al., 2016).
Desta maneira, o objetivo deste trabalho foi demonstrar a estrutura e relevância do índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA), baseado na frequência relativa de táxons de macroalgas indicadoras. A demonstração foi realizada em um gradiente de urbanização levando em consideração distintos habitats da zona entremarés em uma região do Atlântico sudoeste tropical.
2.	Materiais e Métodos
2.1	Descrição da área
As amostras foram coletadas entre novembro de 2013 e agosto de 2014, nos recifes de arenito do estado de Pernambuco, (7°32’52”S, 34O5Ü’27”O e 8°54’57”S, 35°09’76”O), localizados na província biogeográfica do Atlântico Tropical Sul Ocidental (Spalding et al., 2007), na ecorregião do Nordeste brasileiro. O clima local é tropical úmido com temperaturas médias anuais entre 25°C e 30°C. As marés são classificadas como mesomarés semidiurnas, dominadas por ondas (Amaral et al., 2016). Os recifes são corpos rochosos compostos basicamente de grãos de quartzo cimentados por carbonato de cálcio (Manso et al., 2006), dispostos paralelamente à linha de costa e que podem ter alguns quilômetros de comprimento e alguns metros de largura (Kempf, 1969; Pereira et al., 2002).
2.2	Grau de urbanização
As variáveis usadas para classificar a escala de estrese ambiental nos locais amostrados em graus de urbanização são listadas na Tabela 1 (adaptado de Projeto Orla, 2002). As praias Pina, Boa viagem e Piedade foram classificadas como Urbanização consolidada (UC), devido à sua alta densidade demográfica, com mais de 500 hab.km-2, mais de 85% dos domicílios ocupados e, no caso de Piedade, apenas 6,9% do esgoto coletado. Enseada dos Corais, Suape, Serrambi, Tamandaré (Campas) e São José da Coroa Grande foram classificadas como Em Processo de urbanização
Tabela 1. Grau de urbanização de acordo com variáveis proxy usadas para classificar os locais adjacentes aos recifes em: Não urbanizada (NU), Em Processo de urbanização (PU) e Urbanização consolidada (UC) nos ambientes recifais do Nordeste do Brasil.
Local	Nível de urbanização	Densidade demográfica (hab.km-2)1	População (hab)1	Ocupação das residências	Coleta de esgoto 2	Coordenadas geográficas
Pina	UC	&gt;500	29,176	86,4%	35,5 %	(8.08804 S, 34.87887 W)
Boa Viagem	UC	&gt;500	122,922	86%	35,5 %	(8.12451 S, 34.89583 W)
Piedade	UC	&gt;500	64,503	89,4%	6,9%	(8.17715 S, 34.91479 W)
Paiva	NU	10,1 a 15	421	22,1%	8,8%	(8.27993 S, 34.94484 W)
Enseada dos Corais	UP	250,1 a 500	3,700	29,1%	8,8%	(8.31891 S, 34.94822 W)
Suape	UP	100,1 a 250	1,631	54,9%	8,8%	(8.37005 S, 34.94938 W)
Serrambi *	UP	20,1 a 50	80,637	76,8%	-	(8.56313 S, 35.00510 W)
Toquinho *	NU	100,1 a 250	80,637	76,8%	-	(8.56885 S, 35.03069 W)
Tamandaré	UP	100,1 a 250	20,715	47,4%	3,9%	(8.74357 S,
(Campas) 3 *						35.07965 W)
Tamandaré	NU	5,1 a 10	20,715	47,4%	3,9%	(8.78626 S,
(Mamucabas) 3 *						35.09741 W)
São José da Coroa Grande 3 *	UP	250,1 a 500	18.18	60,8%	-	(8.90432 S, 35.1377 1W)
1	Fonte: Atlas do Censo Demográfico de 2010 (IBGE, 2010).
2	Fonte: Diagnóstico dos serviços de água e esgotos (SNIS, 2011).
3	Áreas de proteção ambiental.
* Dados do setor censitário (IBGE, 2010).
2.3	Desenho amostral
O método de amostragem adotado para a quantificação da comunidade de macroalgas e outros organismos sésseis foi o de Line Point Transect (Miller &amp;amp; Ambrose, 2000), que consiste em uma técnica não destrutiva, onde o observador registra, in situ, o táxon em menor nível taxonómico possível, nos pontos previamente definidos. Foram adotadas transecções de 10 metros perpendiculares à linha de costa na borda oceânica dos recifes, nas zonas inferior, média e superior da região entremarés, e os registros foram realizados a cada 10 cm. A amostragem se deu em onze estruturas recifais da costa pernambucana (Figura 1), sendo estabelecidos cinco transectos por local.
8° 42' S
20
• Praia do Paiva ^Enseada dos Corais
/	5	§
CO	õo
§	§
lO	tT
”	• Pinar0
mwWw
• Boa Viagem
• Piedade
tfátâíw/wfó
w$A,y..^
• Suape
_TÍ-V
SÍSf
^MS«iwnM
Toquinho
: ;
^..Tamandare
-' (Campas)
• /
Tamandaré
(Mamucabas)
.	• São José da Coroa Grande
Figura 1. Locais de amostragem na costa de Pernambuco (Nordeste do Brasil).
2.4	IDA - ÍNDICE DE DISTÚRBIO AMBIENTAl
O índice proposto baseia-se nas frequências de ocorrência de táxons indicadores, escolhidos através de análises estatísticas das localidades e de espécies referenciadas em literatura (Tabela 2). Dessa forma, o índice permite uniformizar os critérios de trabalho e definir de maneira menos arbitrária (evitando tautologias) as espécies indicadoras.
O método estatístico utilizado para seleção dos organismos indicadores é relativamente simples de ser utilizado, conhecido como Valor Indicador Individual (IndVal), desenvolvido por Dufrêne e Legendre (1997). Este método combina o grau de especificidade de uma determinada espécie para um status ecológico, por exemplo, tipo de habitat e sua fidelidade dentro do status, medida através da sua porcentagem de ocorrência (McGeoch et al., 2002). O método de IndVal apresenta algumas vantagens quando comparado com outros métodos de bioindicação (McGeoch &amp;amp; Chown, 1998). Por exemplo, o IndVal é calculado para cada espécie de maneira independente e não há restrição do modo de categorização dos habitats, que podem se agrupar subjetivamente ou quantitativamente, realizando ainda um teste de hipótese, onde é razoável utilizar um intervalo de confiança de até 25% (McGeoch &amp;amp; Chown, 1998).
Macroalgas conspícuas no entremarés recifal do NE do Brasil	Indicadores de impacto
Acanthophora spicifera	+
Amphiroa spp.	+
Anadyomene stellata Bryopsis spp.	+
Caulerpa cupressoides	+
Caulerpa racemosa	+
Caulerpa sertularioides	+
Centroceras clavulatum	+
Ceramium spp. Ceratodictyon planicaule Chaetomorpha spp.	+
Chondracanthus acicularis	+
Cladophora spp.	+
Cladophoropsis	+
Corallina officinalis Cryptonemia spp. Dictyopteris delicatula Dictyosphaeria Dictyota spp. Gelidiella acerosa Gelidium pusillum	+
Gracilaria spp.	+
Halimeda opuntia Herposiphonia Hypnea musciformis Jania spp. Laurencia dendroidea Osmundaria obtusiloba Padina spp. Palisada perforata Sargassum cymosum Sargassum vulgare Ulva spp.	+
O IDA é adimensional e representa a frequência amostrada (Fa) e a frequência teórica (Ff), balanceada pela representatividade dos táxons presentes na amostra. A Fa é a razão da Combinação simples dos pares de amostras e é calculada tanto para os táxons indicadores de impactos (Fai), quanto para os táxons indicadores não impacto (Fab):
Fa(p2) =	(1)
7	(Ni+Nn)
•	Fa - Frequência teórica da amostra;
•	Xi - Número de vezes que o táxon i é encontrado na amostra;
•	Xn - Número de vezes que o táxon n é encontrado na amostra;
•	Ni - Número de organismos presente na amostra i;
•	Nn - Número de organismos presente na amostra n.
o Onde (p2) significa a combinação simples par a par
•	Fr - Frequência relativa dos táxons;
•	Xi - Número de vezes que o táxon i é encontrado na amostra;
•	Ni - Número de organismos presente na amostra.
O índice é balanceado pela razão da combinação simples da proporção de organismos totais na amostra e o número de vezes que as espécies indicadoras
aparecem numa determinada amostra. Assim, mostra independência do esforço amostral e da influência de amostras com poucos organismos indicadores.
Co(p2) =
(Sf+Sn) (Ni+Nn)
(3)
•	Co - Proporção dos táxons indicadores encontrados	na amostra;
•	Si - Número de vezes que os táxons indicadores são	encontrados	na	amostra	i;
•	Sn - Número de vezes que os táxons indicadores são	encontrados	na	amostra	i;
•	Ni - Número de organismos presente na amostra i;
•	Nn - Número de organismos presente na amostra n.
o Onde (p2) significa a combinação simples par a par
O IDA é caracterizado por ser uma equação onde o ponto 0 é a representação de um ambiente ideal, ou seja, com frequências dos táxons indicadores iguais a frequência teórica. Quando a Fa tende a valores negativos, indica que o ambiente está favorecendo espécies indicadoras de locais impactados. No caso do IDA, a literatura cita os táxons escolhidos relacionados à contaminação orgânica, pisoteio e sedimentação, impactos ligados aos estresses de origem antropogênica (Airoldi, 1998, 2003; Connell et al., 2008; Krause-Jensen et al., 2008; Worm et al., 1999). Quando o IDA apresenta valores positivos, significa que a comunidade estudada sofre variações naturais ou estocásticas.
IDA = (1 + [- j*&gt;+^É!]&gt; x (Co/S)	(4)
•	Eb - Número de categorias de espécies dominantes em ambientes de baixo impacto;
•	Ei - Número de categorias de espécies utilizadas como indicadoras de contaminação orgânica;
•	Fai - Frequência amostrada de espécies indicadoras de contaminação orgânica;
•	Fti - Frequência teórica de espécies indicadoras de contaminação orgânica;
•	Fab - Frequência amostrada de espécies indicadoras de baixo impacto;
•	Ftb - Frequência teórica de espécies indicadoras de baixo impacto;
•	Co - Proporção dos pontos amostrados cobertos por algas;
•	S - Proporção de espécies registradas na unidade amostral em relação ao total de espécies utilizadas na análise.
A presença e abundância de várias comunidades recifais respondem a uma variabilidade morfológica natural, não determinada pela qualidade da água ou distúrbios de origem antropogênica (Ballesteros, 2007; Vasconcelos et al., dados não publicados). Assim, o IDA levou em consideração os dois tipos de formações da costa estudada, os recifes de arenito (RA) e os recifes coralíneos-algáceos (CA) (Figura 2).
Figura 2. A. Praia de Enseada dos Corais, em detalhe a formação do tipo Recife de Arenito (RA). B. Praia de Campas (Tamandaré), em detalhe o recife com formação Coralíneo-Algáceo (CA).
Foi utilizada Análise de Variância (ANOVA) para comparar os valores do IDA para as distintas localidades (LO). O índice utilizado na matriz de similaridade foi o de Gower (1971). Para representar os centroides, foi utilizado um Cluster e o escalonamento multidimensional (MDS). As análises foram feitas nos programas STATISTICA v10 (Statsoft, 2011) e Primer E v6 Permanova+ (Anderson et al., 2008).
3.	Resultados
pelo alto grau de urbanização, principalmente algas que estão relacionadas, segundo a literatura, com os impactos de pisoteio, sedimentação e contaminação orgânica (Tabela 3).
Tabela 3. Valores de indicação (IndVal) para os táxons de macroalgas presentes em recifes de Urbanização Consolidada (UC) de Pernambuco. Em negrito, os táxons indicadores de impactos, escolhidos para formação do índice.
Espécies	Urb	IndVal	p	Freq
Chondracanthus acicularis	UC	0,977	0,001	39
Ulva	UC	0,901	0,001	47
Gracilaria	UC	0,696	0,001	75
Bryopsis pennata	UC	0,675	0,001	64
Gelidium	UC	0,337	0,046	61
Caulerpa cupressoides	UC	0,318	0,001	11
Corallina officinalis	UC	0,286	0,001	10
Ceratodictyon planicaule	UC	0,200	0,007	15
Caulerpa sertularioides	UC	0,145	0,006	6
Caulerpa fastigiata	UC	0,129	0,009	4
Caulerpa mexicana	UC	0,096	0,031	3
Para a formação de grupo dos táxons que representam ambientes com poucos impactos provenientes da urbanização, a análise IndVal se baseou nos ambientes com menor grau de urbanização, e levando em consideração o tipo de habitat, a partir da
classificação geomorfológica (Vasconcelos et al., dados não publicados) (Tabela 4).
Tabela 4. Valores de indicação (IndVal) para os táxons de macroalgas presentes em recifes de arenito (RA) e coralíneos-algáceos (CA), existentes em zonas Não Urbanizadas (NU) e em Processo de Urbanização (PU) de Pernambuco. Em negrito, os táxons indicadores de ambientes com baixo impacto escolhidos para formação do índice.
(RA) Recifes de Arenito	Urb	IndVal	p	Freq
Palisada perforata	PU	0,7666025	0.001	30
Osmundaria obtusiloba	NU	0,7306477	0.017	23
Padina	PU	0,6309278	0.011	9
Gelidiella acerosa	PU	0,5603113	0.023	8
Sargassum	NU	0,5534591	0.060	9
Caulerpa racemosa	PU	0,45	0.217	7
Palisada furcata	NU	0,440051	0.223	6
Bryothamnion triquetrum	NU	0,4107981	0.004	17
Digenia simplex	PU	0,4	0.016	14
Dictyosphaeria	PU	0,36	0.011	8
Laurencia translucida	PU	0,3	0.005	6
(CA) Recifes Coralíneos-Algáceos
Gelidiella acerosa	NU	0,5695793	0.072	34
Palisada perforata	NU	0,5580574	0.231	36
Acanthophora spicifera	NU	0,5071681	0.009	12
Jania	PU	0,4243421	0.090	18
Dictyota	NU	0,3227433	0.036	8
Ceramiaceae	PU	0,3125	0.009	5
Chaetomorpha	NU	0,1428571	0.234	3
Sargassum	NU	0,1428571	0.249	3
Coralinaceae	PU	0,125	0.170	2
Para a composição da Ft de ambientes CA foram utilizados os maiores valores médios obtidos das localidades Mamucabas e Paiva. No caso dos recifes tipo RA, foram utilizados os maiores valores médios dos táxons indicadores da localidade Toquinho (Tabela 5).
Tabela 5. Frequência teórica dos táxons de regiões pristinas da costa de Pernambuco. Em A recifes Coralíneos-Algáceos (CA), B recifes de Arenito (RA).
Recifes de Arenito	MÉD	MEDIANA	DESVPAD
Bryopsis spp.	1,0%	0,0%	0,0%
Chondracanthus acicularis	1,0%	0,0%	0,4%
Ulva lactuca	0,6%	0,0%	1,2%
Osmundaria obtusiloba	4,9%	3,3%	4,8%
Palisada perforata	11,8%	12,5%	9,1%
Sargassum sp.	33,1%	30,0%	13,8%
Recifes Coralíneos-Algáceos	MÉD	MEDIANA	DESVPAD
Bryopsis spp.	4,2%	1,3%	6,3%
Chondracanthus acicularis	0,4%	0,0%	0,8%
Ulva lactuca	0,4%	0,0%	1,2%
Gelidiella acerosa	29,0%	28,3%	15,1%
Palisada perforata	26,7%	24,5%	18,2%
Foram escolhidas seis categorias indicativas do estado de conservação a partir dos resultados obtidos, sendo elas:
•	&gt; 1,0 a 0,5: Ambiente com baixo impacto de origem
antrópica, outros tensores naturais;
•	0,4 a -0,4: Ambiente pristino, com impactos de
origem exercendo baixa pressão nas comunidades algais;

-0,5 a -6,0: Ambiente com baixo grau de impactos de origem antrópica;
-6,1 a -11: Ambiente com impactos intermediários; -11,1 a -20: Ambiente impactado;
&amp;lt;-20: Ambiente em alto grau de impacto antrópico, apresentando mudança de fase na estrutura da comunidade.
BAIXO IMPACTO*
PRISTINO
BAIXO IMPACTO
IMPACTO INTERMEDIÁRIO IMPACTADO
MUITO IMPACTADO
A variação média do IDA está apresentada na Figura 3, mostrando as praias do Pina (Muito impactado), Piedade e Boa Viagem (Impactado), com os valores mais baixos, o que indica locais impactados por processos de origem antrópica. Os menores valores encontrados na praia do Pina (-37,7) estão relacionados com emissários de esgoto clandestino que deságuam próximo ao recife amostrado, aumentando a quantidade de nutrientes na água.
A Enseada dos Corais foi classificada como Baixo impacto, e possuiu valor médio de -0,5, enquanto que as praias de Toquinho, Serrambi, São José da Coroa Grande, Campas e Mamucabas apresentaram valores de IDA entre 0,4 e -0,4, representando ambientes pristinos, com impactos de origem antrópica exercendo baixa pressão nas comunidades algais.
O maior valor médio do índice (1,1) foi encontrado no recife de Suape, e foi classificado como Baixo impacto*, uma vez que seu valor é positivo e maior que 0,5, indicando um ambiente com baixa influência de impactos antrópicos, mas com tensores ambientais, como elevado hidrodinamismo e batimento de ondas.
H 0,2	SJ
I 0,5	MAM
0,1	CAM
0,3	SER
-0,3	I	PAI
I	0,4	TOQ
■ 1,1	SUA
-0,5	I	EC
		BV
		PIE PIN
-37,7		
		
1 1 1 45,0	-40,0 -35,0	-30,0	-25,0	-20,0	-15,0	-10,0	-5,0	0,0	5,0
Figura 3. Média do Índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) de onze estruturas recifais no estado de Pernambuco (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).
O índice testado mostrou a diferença entre as localidades estudadas através da análise de variância (Tabela 6). Apenas dois pares de locais (CAM - SJ e EC - PAI) não apresentaram diferenças significativas nos valores do IDA (Tabela 6).
Tabela 6. Resumo das Análises de variância (one way ANOVA), evidenciando as diferenças entre as localidades (LO) estudadas de acordo com o índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA). (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).
ANOVA	df	SS	MS	F	P
LO	9	4,68E+09	52002	554,34	0,001
PAIRWISE					
Groups	t	p	Groups	t	p
BV, PIN	73,064	0,001	PIE, PAI	26,608	0,001
BV, PIE	34,665	0,001	EC, SUA	12,519	0,001
BV, EC	20,441	0,001	EC, TOQ	14,397	0,001
BV, SUA	133,49	0,001	EC, CAM	54,026	0,001
BV, TOQ	64,705	0,001	EC, SJ	52,474	0,001
BV, CAM	46,478	0,001	EC, MAM	15,89	0,001
BV, SJ	32,26	0,001	EC, PAI	14,873	0,147
BV, MAM	67,656	0,001	SUA, TOQ	96,246	0,001
BV, PAI	23,33	0,001	SUA, CAM	12,939	0,001
PIN, PIE	90,125	0,001	SUA, SJ	73,181	0,001
PIN, EC	15,84	0,001	SUA, MAM	81,822	0,001
PIN, SUA	236,07	0,001	SUA, PAI	11,84	0,001
PIN, TOQ	50,036	0,001	TOQ, CAM	52,755	0,001
PIN, CAM	37,942	0,001	TOQ, SJ	2,769	0,009
PIN, SJ	25,272	0,001	TOQ, MAM	22,099	0,023
PIN, MAM	52,234	0,001	TOQ, PAI	11,285	0,001
PIN, PAI	18,133	0,001	CAM, SJ	0,87262	0,396
PIE, EC	23,15	0,001	CAM, MAM	67,748	0,001
PIE, SUA	225,13	0,001	CAM, PAI	40,508	0,001
PIE, TOQ	73,926	0,001	SJ, MAM	39,104	0,001
PIE, CAM	55,13	0,001	SJ, PAI	39,622	0,001
PIE, SJ	37,337	0,001	MAM, PAI	12,668	0,001
PIE, MAM	77,258	0,001			
O Cluster (Figura 4) representa a dissimilaridade entre os locais testados, agrupando as localidades de urbanização consolidada (UC), Pina (PIN), Boa viagem (BV) e Piedade (Pie), e restante das localidades com estatdo ecológico considerado Baixo impacto e Pristino. O MDS representa a localização dos centroides no plano multidimensional (Figura 5) representando graficamente a similaridade de estado ecológico entre Paiva e Enseada dos Corais (Pristino e Baixo impacto,
Figura 4. Dissimilaridade representada no Cluster das localidades testadas com o IDA. (PIN-Pina; PIE-Piedade; BV-Boa Viagem; EC-Enseada dos Corais; SUA-Suape; TOQ-Toquinho; PAI-Paiva; SER-Serrambi; CAM-Campas; MAM-Mamucabas; SJ-São José da Corora Grande).
2D Stress: 0			O RA
	CAr£JT^M □ ° o	SUA 0	□ CA —	UC —	PU —	NU
	EC PAI O □		
Figura 5. Escalonamento multidimensional dos centroides dos fatores Tipo de recife e Nível de Urbanização. RA (Recife de Arenito), CA (Coralíneo-Algáceo), UC (Urbanização Consolidada), PU (Processo de Urbanização) e NU (Não Urbanizado).
4.	Discussão
O índice de distúrbio ambiental (IDA) mostrou clara capacidade de detectar diferenças na resposta das comunidades algais, em um gradiente de impacto antrópico. A metodologia não destrutiva apresenta algumas vantagens, pois não remove espécies estruturadoras como Sargassum spp., que são sensíveis a distúrbios naturais ou de origem antrópica, com um grau de recuperação lenta (Thibaut et al., 2005; Guimaraens et al., 2008). O registro das amostras in situ implica em um menor tempo de bancada no laboratório, o que permite um processo mais rápido e menos oneroso para o processamento dos dados de estudos de monitoramento (Ballesteros et al., 2007). Porém a fase de campo deve possuir um rendimento de trabalho alto em relação ao tempo disponível na região entremarés, ainda mais em ambientes batidos como em locais de mesomarés.
Assim como diversos índices estabelecidos (ICA - Areces, 2001; RSL - Guinda et al., 2008, CFR - Juanes et al., 2008; MarMat - Neto et al., 2012), o IDA utiliza transectos perpendiculares à linha de costa como unidade amostral. Esse tipo de amostragem caracteriza melhor os ambientes de zonas entramarés consolidados, pois contempla grande parte da variação das comunidades (Miller &amp;amp; Ambrose, 2000).
Uma das métricas do índice é a riqueza de táxons, e para isso o índice utilizado trabalha em nível taxonômico de gênero, mas nível específico também é utilizado quando a sua identificação em campo permite. Ainda que os grupos morfofuncionais (Littler &amp;amp; Littler, 1984; Stenneck &amp;amp; Dethier, 1994) sejam bastante difundidos nos
trabalhos de biomonitoramento com macroalgas (Orfanidis et al., 2001; Wells et al., 2007; Sousa-Dias &amp;amp; Melo, 2008), a generalização dentro de um grupo morfofuncional pode levar à falta de precisão na hora de discriminar respostas ecológicas causadas por perturbações naturais ou antropogênicas (Juanes et al., 2008; Oliveira et al., 2008). Para decidir em que nível hierárquico trabalhar (espécie, gênero, família ou grupos morfofuncionais), deve-se levar em conta as limitações da metodologia e os objetivos do trabalho, Bates et al., (2007) compararam a similaridade entre amostras através do nível de gênero e nível de espécie, chegando à conclusão de que as amostras possuem 97% de similaridade, ou seja, não apresentam diferenças significativas entre si, podendo ser facultativo trabalhar em nível de espécies, o que demanda maior conhecimento taxonômico.
O IDA utiliza métricas comuns a vários índices estabelecidos, EEI (Panayotidis, 2004), CFR (Juanes et al., 2008) e CCO (Gall et al., 2016), e é baseado no número e abundância de espécies características por habitat e número e abundância de espécies indicadoras. No entanto, a escolha dessas espécies se dá por uma análise de valor de Indicação (IndVal), diminuindo a arbitrariedade e tautologias para a escolha de espécies indicadoras. Após ser evidenciadas as espécies indicadoras de cada tipo de habitat, ocorre a escolha das espécies indicadoras através de uma lista de espécies locais, que apresentam espécies conspícuas e relacionadas a impactos.
A escolha dos táxons indicadores está fortemente ligado ao seu histórico de vida, características ecológicas e fisiológicas, bem como a observação de padrões de distribuição desses organismos em ambientes naturais e impactados. Muitos autores associaram as proporções de espécies perenes e oportunistas ao status ecológico do ecossistema (ex. Orfanidis et al., 2001; Krause-Jensen et al., 2007; Guinda et al., 2008). Os organismos K-estrategistas, geralmente dominam ambientes com pouca poluição, por outro lado, espécies oportunistas, r-estrategistas, podem indicar um local com baixa qualidade ambiental. Esses organismos que são sensíveis aos impactos de origem antrópica podem ter suas populações diminuídas, ou até mesmo excluídas dependendo do grau de impacto sofrido (Benedetti-Cecchi et al., 2001).
As algas utilizadas no IDA que indicam impactos nas regiões estudadas são: Chondracanthus acicularis, Ulva e Bryopsis. As Chlorophyta dos gêneros Ulva e Bryopsis, já foram bem documentadas e classificadas como algas oportunistas e que levam vantagens em ambientes eutrofizados (ex. Ortega, 2000; Areces, 2001; Orfanidis et al., 2001; Juanes et al., 2008) inclusive em ambientes impactados por urbanização na região nordeste do Brasil (Scherner et al., 2013; Portugal et al., 2016).
Chondracanthus acicularis é classificada por Orfanidis et al., (2003), no grupo das macroalgas oportunistas, com rápido grau de crescimento e curtos ciclos de vida.
No entanto, alguns estudos atestam essa espécie como perene (Guiry et al., 1987). Experimentos feitos por Sousa (1980) relatam que Chondracanthus canaliculatus (Harvey) Guiry (como Gigartina canaliculatus) dominam estágios sucessionais intermediários e tardios em ambientes onde é frequente a remoção natural de cobertura vegetal. Representantes do gênero Chondracanthus estão associados à colonização de lugares com alto grau de sedimentação (Falace &amp;amp; Bressan, 2002; Airoldi, 2003). Carneiro et al. (1987) comentam que espécies do gênero Chondracanthus ocorrem em locais mais poluídos, possuindo altos valores de abundância e cobertura em locais com elevado aporte de matéria orgânica. Essa hipótese vem sendo corroborada por vários trabalhos no âmbito da bioindicação (ex. Orfanidis et al., 2003; Santos et al., 2006; Juanes et al., 2008; Portugal et al., 2016). Com isso, a escolha de C. acicularis para formar o grupo das algas que estão associadas aos impactos de origem antrópica, se baseou na capacidade desse organismo em se estabelecer em ambientes impactados e se manter em estágios sucessionais tardios, indicando uma mudança de fase dominante de uma comunidade.
As macroalgas características de ambientes recifais estáveis ou com baixo grau de impacto antrópico são: Palisada perforata, Sargassum P e Osmundaria obtusiloba para os recifes de arenito (RA) e P. perforata, Gelidiella acerosa (CA). Tsai et al., (2005) afirmam que, em um ambiente recifal dominado por Gracilaria coronopifolia J. Agardh e Palisada perforata (como Laurencia papillosa), G. coronopifolia leva vantagem quando há um quadro de eutrofização da área, levando ao decréscimo da alga P. perforata. Os mesmos autores afirmam que P. perforata está diretamente ligada a ambientes com temperaturas altas (acima de 28°C) e exposição ao ar (entremarés). Juanes et al. (2008), classificaram a alga Laurencia sp., alga da mesma tribo de P. perforata, como natural de ambientes de mesolitoral. Na região Nordeste do Brasil, P. perforata representa uma das macroalgas com os maiores valores de abundância, nos ambientes referência de pouco impacto urbano (Pereira et al., 2002 como Chondrphycus papillosus; Scherner et al 2013; Santos et al., 2015).
Outra alga característica dos ambientes de mesolitoral recifal foi G. acerosa que apresenta alta frequência de ocorrência e abundância em ambientes com pouco impacto urbano (NU e PU). Azevedo et al. (2011) encontraram alta frequência e grande distribuição de G. acerosa ao longo do entremarés de um recife, onde o maior impacto é o turismo de temporada. Freire et al. (2007) discutem o baixo potencial de crescimento da alga G. acerosa em condições de baixa salinidade, penetração de luz e altas concentrações de nutrientes, mostrando a sensibilidade da macroalga aos corpos d'água eutrofizados. Bem como P. perforata é encontrada em grande abundância em
As macroalgas Sargassum e Osmundaria obtusiloba foram utilizadas como indicadoras de ambientes pristinos. Essas macroalgas são conhecidas por dominarem regiões rasas e entremarés inferior exposto de ambientes tropicais (Pereira &amp;amp; Eskinazi-Leça 1970; Norris, 1991; Carvalho et al., 2006, Pereira et al., 2008). Sargassum é utilizado como indicador de estabilidade ambiental em diversos trabalhos, tanto em ambientes tropicais (Széchy &amp;amp; Paula, 2000; Scherner et al., 2013), quanto temperado (Orfanidis et al., 2001; Thibaut et al., 2005). Sua complexidade estrutural, estratégia de vida de crescimento lento (Benedetti-Cecchi et al., 2001) e produção de metabólitos secundários (Appelhans et al., 2010; Nakajima et al., 2016) conferem características de espécie clímax para ambientes recifais com baixo grau de distúrbio.
O IDA classificou os recifes de locais com urbanização consolidada (UC) com o estado de conservação: Impactado (Boa Viagem e Piedade) e Muito Impactado (Pina). Esses recifes estão sob a influência do pisoteio direto de turistas e esgotos clandestinos que deságuam nos efluentes dos rios próximos (Sousa &amp;amp; Cocentino, 2004; Santos et al., 2006; Costa et al., 2008). As localidades com grau de urbanização PU e NU obtiveram valores dentro do intervalo de Baixo Impacto e Pristino. No entanto, as localidades que estão em processo de urbanização podem estar vulneráveis a futuros impactos (Turra et al., 2013) se não forem adotadas políticas de uso e manejo desses ecossistemas em vista às projeções de crescimento populacional para o estado de Pernambuco (mais de 3% nos próximos cinco anos) (IBGE, 2016).
Em conclusão, a abordagem multimétrica aplicada na avaliação do estado de conservação das comunidades recifais, através do IDA, demonstrou que as comunidades de macroalgas são alternativas como indicadoras para detectar os efeitos dos impactos antropogênicos nos ecossistemas recifais. O índice proposto constitui um esforço de uniformizar e categorizar o estado dos ambientes costeiros vegetados, tendo em vista a conservação e manutenção da biodiversidade. A categorização e avaliação do estado desses ambientes dão subsídios a políticas de gestão no sentido de recuperar ou mitigar os impactos de áreas degradadas e proteger áreas em potencial risco.
Agradecimentos
Este trabalho teve apoio financeiro do Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq-Proc. 484647/2012-1). O primeiro autor agradece a Fundação de Amparo à Ciência e Tecnologia de Pernambuco (FACEPE) pela Bolsa de
Referências
Airoldi, L. (1998). Roles of Disturbance, Sediment Stress, and Substratum Retention on Spatial Dominance in Algal Turf. Ecology, 79, (8), 2759-2770.
Airoldi, L. (2003). The effects of sedimentation on rocky coast assemblages. Oceanogr. Mar. Biol. Ann. Rev. 41: 161-236 In: Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review. Aberdeen University Press/Allen &amp;amp; Unwin: London. ISSN 0078-3218
Amaral, A.C.Z., Corte, G.N., Filho, J.S.R., Denadai, M.R., Colling, L.A., Borzone, C., &amp;amp; Roberto, J. (2016). Brazilian sandy beaches: characteristics, ecosystem services, impacts, knowledge and priorities. Brazilian Journal of Oceanography, 64 (2), 5-16.
Anderson, M.J., Gorley R.N &amp;amp; Clarke K.R. (2008). PERMANOVA+ for PRIMER: Guide to software and Statistical Methods. PRIMER-E: Plymouth, UK.
Appelhans, Y. S., Lenz, M., Medeiros, H. E., da Gama, B. A. P., Pereira, R. C., &amp;amp; Wahl, M. (2010). Stressed, but not defenceless: no obvious influence of irradiation levels on antifeeding and antifouling defences of tropical macroalgae. Marine biology, 157 (5), 1151-1159.
Areces A.J., Cocentino, A.L.M., Reis, T.N.V., Vasconcelos, E.R.T.P.P., Guimarães-Barros, N.C. &amp;amp; Fujii, M.T. (2015). Las Macroalgas como Bioindicadoras da Calidad Ambiental y Cambios Climáticos. Guia Prática. Braz'lian Journal of Ecology, v. Especial, 1-64
Areces, A.J., Bacallao, J. &amp;amp; González-Sánchez, P. (2016). El uso de abundancias relativas de macroalgas en la formulación de índices para la evaluación rápida de calidad ambiental. Serie Oceanologica, Cuba, (in press).
Areces, J. A. (2001). La ficoflora intermareal como bioindicadora de calidad ambiental. Estudio de caso: El litoral habanero. En: K. Alveal y T. Antezana (Eds.): Sustentabilidad de la biodiversidade: Un problema actual, bases científico-técnicas, teorizaciones y perspectivas. Universidad de Concepción. Chile. 569-589.
Azevedo, C.A.A.; Carneiro, M.A.A.; Oliveira, S.R. &amp;amp; Marinho-Soriano, E. (2011). Macrolgae as an indicator of the environmental health of the Pirangi reefs, Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil. Revista Brasileira de Farmacognosia, 21 (2), 323-328.
Ballesteros, E., Torras, X., Pinedo, S., Garcia, M., Mangialajo, L., &amp;amp; De Torres, M. (2007). A new methodology based on littoral community cartography dominated by macroalgae for the implementation of the European Water Framework Directive. Marine pollution bulletin, 55(1), 172-180.
Barange, M. (2003). Ecosystem science and the sustainable management of marine resources: from Rio to Johannesburg. Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment, 1(4), 190-196.
Bates, C.R.; Tobin, M. L.; Scott, G. &amp;amp; Thompson, R. 2007. Weighting the cost and benefits of reduced sampling resolution in biomonitoring studies: perspectives from the temperate rocky intertidal. Biological Conservation, 137, 617-625.
Benedetti-Cecchi, L., Pannacciulli, F., Bulleri, F., Moschella, P. S., Airoldi, L., Relini, G., &amp;amp; Cinelli, F. (2001). Predicting the consequences of anthropogenic disturbance: large-scale effects of loss of canopy algae on rocky shores. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 214, 137-150.
Blanfuné, A., Thibaut, T., Boudouresque, C. F., Macic, V., Markovic, L., Palomba, L., &amp;amp; Boissery, P. (2017). The CARLIT method for the assessment of the ecological quality of European Mediterranean waters: Relevance, robustness and possible improvements. Ecological Indicators, 72, 249-259.
Borja, Á., Aguirrezabalaga, F., Martínez, J., Sola, J.C., García-Arberas, L. &amp;amp; Gorostiaga, J.M., (2004). Benthic communities, biogeography and resources management. In: Borja, A., Collins, M. (Eds.). Oceanography and Marine Environment of the Basque Country, Elsevier Oceanography Series, Elsevier, Amsterdam, 70, 455-492
Carvalho, L.R.; Guimarães, S.M.P &amp;amp; Roque, N.F. (2006). Sulfated bromophenols from Osmundaria obtusiloba (C. Agardh) R. E. Norris (Rhodophyta, Ceramiales). Brazilian Journal of Botany, 29(3), 453-459.
Connell, S. D., Russell, B. D., Turner, D. J., Shepherd, S. A., Kildea, T., Miller, D., ... &amp;amp; Cheshire, A. (2008). Recovering a lost baseline: missing kelp forests from a metropolitan coast. Mar Ecol Prog Ser, 360, 63-72.
Costa, M.F.D., Araújo, M.C.B.D., Silva-Cavalcanti, J.S., &amp;amp; Souza, S.D. (2008). Verticalização da Praia da Boa Viagem (Recife, Pernambuco) e suas consequências sócio-ambientais. Revista da Gestão Costeira Integrada,8(2), 233-245.
Díez I., Santolaria A., Secilla A. &amp;amp; Gorostiaga JM. (2009) Recovery stages over long-term monitoring of the intertidal vegetation in the Abra de Bilbao area and on the adjacent coast (N Spain). Eur J Phycol 4:1-14
Dufrêne, M. &amp;amp; Legendre, P. (1997). Species assemblages and indicator species: the need for flexible asymmetrical approach. Ecological Monographs, 67 (3), 345-366
E.C. (2000) European Commision. Council Directive for a legislative frame and actions for the water policy, 2000/60/EC Off. J. E.C. (2000)
Falace, A., &amp;amp; Bressan, G. (2002). Evaluation of the influence of inclination of substrate panels on seasonal changes in a macrophytobenthic community. ICES Journal of Marine Science: Journal du Conseil, 59(suppl), 116-121.
Freire, A.R.S.; Moura, E.A.; Pereira, D.C. &amp;amp; Marinho-Soriano, E. (2007). Efeito dos parâmetros ambientais sobre o crescimento e a biomassa de Gelidella acerosa cultivada em viveiros de camarão. Revista Brasileira de Biociências, 5 (2), 804-806.
Gall, E. A., Le Duff, M., Sauriau, P. G., de Casamajor, M. N., Gevaert, F., Poisson, E., ... &amp;amp; Bréret, M. (2016). Implementation of a new index to assess intertidal seaweed communities as bioindicators for the European Water Framework Directory. Ecological Indicators, 60, 162-173.
Gower, J. (1971). A General Coefficient of Similarity and Some of Its Properties. Biometrics, 27(4), 857-871.
Guimaraens, M. A., Gonçalves, J. E. A., Lourenço, S. O., &amp;amp; Coutinho, R. (2008). Sensitivity analyses of population biomass dynamics for Ulva spp. and Sargassum furcatum at the Cabo Frio upwelling region of Brazil. Journal of Biological Systems, 16(04), 579-596.
Guimaraens, M.A.; Neves, V.C.S.; Aquino, R.E; Almeida, V.C &amp;amp; Ribeiro, T.D.L. (2014). Avaliação da biomassa de macroalgas no platô recifal das praias de Piedade e Porto de galinhas - Pernambuco, Brasil. Rev. Bras. Eng. Pesca, 7(1) 19-31
Guinda, X., Juanes, J. A., Puente, A., &amp;amp; Revilla, J. A. (2008). Comparison of two methods for quality assessment of macroalgae assemblages, under different pollution types. Ecological Indicators, 8(5), 743753.
Guiry, M.D.; Tripodi, G.; &amp;amp; Lfining, K. (1987). Biosystematics, genetics and upper temperature tolerance of Gigartina teedii (Rhodophyta) from the Atlantic and Mediterranean. Helgolander Meeresuntersuchungen, 41 (3), 283-295.
Halpern, B. S., Walbridge, S., Selkoe, K. A., Kappel, C. V., Micheli, F., D'Agrosa, C., ... &amp;amp; Fujita, R. (2008). A global map of human impact on marine ecosystems. Science, 319(5865), 948-952.
IBGE (2010). Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística Censo Demográfico. http://www.censo2010.ibge.gov.br/&gt;. Consultado em, 04/12/2013.
IBGE (2016). Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística - População. Retrieved Setember 5, 2016. from http://www.ibge.gov.br/apps/populacao/projecao/
Juanes, J. A., Guinda, X., Puente, A., &amp;amp; Revilla, J. A. (2008). Macroalgae, a suitable indicator of the ecological status of coastal rocky communities in the NE Atlantic. Ecological indicators, 8(4), 351-359.
Kempf, M. (1969). A plataforma continental de Pernambuco (Brasil): nota preliminar sobre a natureza do fundo. Trabalhos Oceanográficos, 9, 125-148.
Krause-Jensen, D.; Carstensen, J. &amp;amp; Dahl, K., (2007). Total and opportunistic algal cover in relation to environmental variables. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 55, 114-125.
Littler, M. M., &amp;amp; Littler, D. S. (1984). Relationships between macroalgal functional form groups and substrata stability in a subtropical rocky-intertidal system. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 74(1), 13-34.
Mann, K. H. (2009). Ecology of coastal waters: with implications for management. John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons.
Manso, V. A. V., Coutinho, P. N., Guerra, N.C., &amp;amp; Soares, C. F. A. (2006). Pernambuco. In: D. Muehe (Ed), Erosão e Progradação no Litoral Brasileiro (pp.179-196), Brasília, Brasil, Ministério do Meio Ambiente.
McGeoch, M.A. &amp;amp; Chown, S.L. (1998) Scaling up the value of bioindicators. Trends in Ecology Evolution, 13, 46- 47
McGeoch, M.A., Rensburg, B.J.V. &amp;amp; Botes, B. (2002). The verification and application of bioindicators: a case study of dung beetles in a savanna ecosystem. Journal of Applied Ecology, 39 (4), 661-672.
Miller, A. W., &amp;amp; Ambrose, R. F. (2000). Sampling patchy distributions: comparison of sampling designs in rocky intertidal habitats. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 196, 1-14.
MMA (2015). Ministério Do Meio Ambiente (Ed.). Pereira, F. C.; Oliveira, M. R. L. de (Ed.). Plano nacional de gerenciamento costeiro: 25 anos do gerenciamento costeiro no Brasil. Brasília: 181p.
Murray, S. N., &amp;amp; Littler, M. M. (1978). Patterns of algal succession in a perturbated marine intertidal community. Journal of Phycology, 14(4), 506-512.
Nakajima, N., Sugimoto, N., Ohki, K., &amp;amp; Kamiya, M. (2016). Diversity of phlorotannin profiles among sargassasacean species affecting variation and abundance of epiphytes. European Journal of Phycology, 1-10.
Neto, J. M., Gaspar, R., Pereira, L., &amp;amp; Marques, J. C. (2012). Marine Macroalgae Assessment Tool (MarMAT) for intertidal rocky shores. Quality assessment under the scope of the European Water Framework Directive. Ecological Indicators,19, 39-47.
Norris, R. E. (1991). Some unusual marine red algae (Rhodophyta) from South Africa. Phycologia, 30(6), 582-596.
Oliveira, R.B.S.; Castro, C.M. &amp;amp; Baptista, D.F. (2008). Desenvolvimento de índices multimétricos para utilização em programas de monitoramento biológico de integridade de ecossistemas aquáticos. Oecologia brasiliensis, 12 (3), 487-505.
Orfanidis, S., Panayotidis, P., &amp;amp; Stamatis, N. (2001). Ecological evaluation of transitional and coastal waters: a marine benthic macrophytes-based model. Mediterranean Marine Science, 2(2), 45-66.
Ortega, J.L.G. (2000). Algas. In: Espino GL, Pulido J, Pérez JLC, editors. Organismos indicadores de la calidad del água y de la contaminación (Bioindicadores). Playa y Valdés, México. pp. 109-193.
Panayotidis, P., Montesanto, B., &amp;amp; Orfanidis, S. (2004). Use of low-budget monitoring of macroalgae to implement the European Water Framework Directive. Journal of Applied Phycology, 16(1), 49-59.
Pereira, S. M. B.; Oliveira-Carvalho, M. F.; Angeiras, J. A. P; Bandeira-Pedrosa, M. E.; Oliveira, N. M. B.; Torres, J, Gestinari, L. M. S.; Cocentino, A. L. M., Santos, M. D, Nascimento, P. R. F. &amp;amp; Cavalcanti D. R. (2002). Algas marinhas bentônicas do Estado de Pernambuco. In: M. Tabarelli &amp;amp; J. M. C. Silva (Ed.). Diagnóstico da Biodiversidade de Pernambuco (pp. 97-124). Recife: Editora Massangana.
Pereira, S.M.B. &amp;amp; Eskinazi-Lega, E. (1970). Estuarine management in northeast Brazil: Plant biodiversity. WIT Transactions on Ecology and the Environment, 34.
Pereira, S.M.B.; Oliveira-Carvalho, M.D.F.; Burgos, D.C. &amp;amp; Araújo, E.L. 2006. Caracterização estrutural das macroalgas de ambiente recifal da praia de Enseada dos Corais, Pernambuco, Brasil. Congresso Brasileiro de Ficologia, 11 Simpósio Latino-Americano sobre algas nocivas. Itajaí, SC: Museu Nacional Rio de Janeiro. p. 231-242
PNGC (1988). Programa Nacional de Gerenciamento Costeiro. Disponível em: http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/leis/L7661 .htm
Portugal, A. B., Carvalho, F. L., de Macedo Carneiro, P. B., Rossi, S., &amp;amp; de Oliveira Soares, M. (2016). Increased anthropogenic pressure decreases species richness in tropical intertidal reefs. Marine Environmental Research, 120, 44-54.
Projeto, O. (2002). Fundamentos para gestão integrada. Brasília: MMA/SQA. p 78
Santos, A.A.; Cocentino, A.M.L. &amp;amp; Reis, T.N.V. (2006). Macroalgas como indicadoras da qualidade ambiental da Praia de Boa Viagem - Pernambuco, Brasil. Bol. Téc. Cien. CEPENE, 14 (2), 25-33.
Santos, G.S., Burgos, D.C., Lira, S. M., &amp;amp; Schwamborn, R. (2015). The impact of trampling on reef macrobenthos in northeastern Brazil: how effective are current conservation strategies?.Environmental management, 56(4), 847-858.
Scherner, F., Horta, P.A., Oliveira, E.C., Simonassi, J.C., Hall-Spencer, J.M., Chow, F., ... &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B. (2013). Coastal urbanization leads to remarkable seaweed species loss and community shifts along the SW Atlantic. Marine pollution bulletin, 76(1), 106-115.
Simões, I.P.; Guimaraens, M.A.; Oliveira-Carvalho, M.F.; Vadevino, J. &amp;amp; Pereira, S.M.B. (2009). Avaliação florística e sucessão ecológica das macroalgas em recifes na praia de Piedade (PE). Neotropical Biology and Conservation, 4(1), 49-56
SNIS (2011). Sistema Nacional de Informações sobre Saneamento: Diagnóstico dos serviços de água e esgotos. Brasília: Ministério das cidades SNSA, Brasil. 432.
Sousa, G.S. &amp;amp; Cocentino, A.L.M. (2004). Macroalgas como indicadoras da qualidade ambiental. Tropical Oceanography, 32, 1-22
Sousa, W.P. (1980). The responses of a community to disturbance: the importance of successional age and species' life histories. Oecologia, 45(1), 72-81.
Sousa-Dias, A. &amp;amp; Melo, R. 2008. Long-term abundance patterns of macroalgae in relation to environmental variables in the Tagus Estuary (Portugal). Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science, 76 (1), 21-28.
Spalding, M. D., Fox, H. E., Allen, G. R., Davidson, N., Ferdana, Z. A., Finlayson, M. A. X., ... &amp;amp; Martin, K. D. (2007). Marine ecoregions of the world: a bioregionalization of coastal and shelf areas. BioScience, 57(7), 573-583.
StatSoft, Inc. (2011). STATISTICA (data analysis software system), version 10. www.statsoft.com
Steneck, R. S., &amp;amp; Dethier, M. N. (1994). A functional group approach to the structure of algal dominated communities. Oikos, 476-498.
Széchy, M.T.M &amp;amp; Paula, E.J. (2000). Padrões estruturais quantitativos de bancos de Sargassum (Phaeophyta. Fucales) do litoral dos estados do Rio de Janeiro e São Paulo, Brasil. Revista Brasileira de Botânica, 23 (2), 121-132
Thibaut, T., Pinedo, S., Torras, X., &amp;amp; Ballesteros, E. (2005). Long-term decline of the populations of Fucales (Cystoseira spp. and Sargassum spp.) in the Alberes coast (France, North-western Mediterranean). Marine pollution bulletin, 50(12), 1472-1489.
Tsai, C., Chang, J., Sheu, F., Shyu, Y., Yu, A., Wong, S., ... &amp;amp; Lee, T. (2005). Seasonal growth dynamics of and from a highly eutrophic reef in southern Taiwan: temperature limitation and nutrient availability. Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology, 315, 49-69.
Turra, A. &amp;amp; Denadai, M. R. (2015) A rede de monitoramento de habitats bentônicos costeiros (REBENTOS). In: Protocolo para o Monitoramento de Habitats Bentônicos Costeiros - ReBentos. Eds. A. Turra &amp;amp; M. R. Denadai. Instituo Oceanográfiuco da Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo. p.8-16
Turra, A., Croquer, A., Carranza, A., Mansilla, A., Areces, A. J., Werlinger, C., ... &amp;amp; Scarabino, F. (2013). Global environmental changes: setting priorities for Latin American coastal habitats. Global change biology, 19(7), 1965-1969.
UNEP-WCMC (2011) Marine and coastal ecosystem services: Valuation methods and their application. UNEP-WCMC Biodiversity Series, 33, 46 p.
United Nations. (1992). Convention on Biological Diversity, p. 28
Wells, E.; Wilkinson, M.; Wood, P. &amp;amp; Scanlan, C. (2007). The use of macroalgal species richness and composition on intertidal rocky seashores in the assessment of ecological quality under the European Water Framework Directive. Marine Pollution Bulletin, 55,151-161.
Worm, B., Barbier, E. B., Beaumont, N., Duffy, J. E., Folke, C., Halpern, B. S., ... &amp;amp; Sala, E. (2006). Impacts of biodiversity loss on ocean ecosystem services. Science, 314(5800), 787-790.
Worm, B., Lotze, H. K., Bostrom, C., Engkvist, R., Labanauskas, V., &amp;amp; Sommer, U. (1999). Marine diversity shift linked to interactions among grazers, nutrients and propagule banks. Marine Ecology Progress Series, 185, 309-314.
Conclusão Geral
•	A urbanização pode ter um forte efeito na estrutura das assembleias de macroalgas e a grande ocorrência de algas indicadoras como Ulva, Chondracanthus accicularis e Bryopsis (Foliosa e Sifonácia), em detrimento de táxons conspícuos como Sargassum, Palisada e Gelidella (Canópia), podem ser usadas para avaliar o impacto da urbanização nas estruturas recifais do Nordeste do brasileiro.
•	A combinação propriedades geomorfológicas, os fatores paisagísticos (Habitat) e as características da cobertura vegetal (Biótopo) através de um sistema de classificação Top Down-Bottom Up dão lugar a tipologia dos habitats bentônicos existentes nos topos e platôs recifais do litoral de Pernambuco. Os agrupamentos desta proposta tipológica permitem utilizar intervalos de abundância das macroalgas existentes para diversos fins, inclusive monitoramento e bioindicação.
•	O aumento das atividades humanas a regiões altamente urbanizadas elevam os impactos na região costeira, podendo diminuir ou romper padrões como a zonação vertical e suas interações ecológicas, podendo levar a perda da biodiversidade e dos serviços ecológicos.
•	A abordagem multimétrica aplicada na avaliação do estado de conservação das comunidades recifais, através do IDA, demonstrou que as comunidades de macroalgas são alternativas como indicadoras para detectar os efeitos dos impactos antropogênicos nos ecossistemas recifais. O índice proposto constitui um esforço de uniformizar e categorizar o estado dos ambientes costeiros vegetados, tendo em vista a conservação e manutenção da biodiversidade.
Em conclusão, os ambientes recifais de Pernambuco são distintos, tanto em nível morfológico quanto paisagístico e as macroalgas respondem de forma diferente a essa variação, sendo os impactos causados pela urbanização fatores preponderantes na distribuição e estrutura da comunidade desses organismos, que podem ser representados numericamente através de um índice biótico, como o IDA.
ANEXOS
ANEXO I - DADOS
TÁXON	NU	UP	UC
Acanthophora spicifera	4,59%	2,71%	1,48%
Amansia	3,58%	1,61%	0,71%
Anadyomene stellata	0,67%	0,82%	0,00%
Botryocladia	0,00%	0,00%	0,00%
Brachidontes	0,00%	0,00%	0,27%
Bryopsis	3,32%	4,08%	10,28%
Bryothamnion seaforthii	0,54%	0,39%	0,20%
Bryothamnion triquetrum	1,68%	0,16%	0,20%
Caulerpa cupressoides	0,00%	0,16%	2,91%
Caulerpa fastigiata	0,00%	0,00%	0,92%
Caulerpa mexicana	0,00%	0,00%	0,84%
Caulerpa racemosa	5,87%	6,48%	0,57%
Caulerpa sertularioides	0,00%	0,16%	1,08%
Ceramiaceae	2,01%	4,22%	3,21%
Ceratodictyon planicaule	0,64%	0,48%	1,97%
Chaetomorpha	3,54%	1,14%	1,55%
Chnoospora minima	0,25%	1,11%	0,00%
Chondracanthus acicularis	1,15%	0,34%	11,30%
Cladophora	0,21%	0,00%	0,23%
Coral	0,21%	0,00%	0,00%
Coralinaceae	0,00%	0,59%	0,00%
Corallina officinalis	0,22%	0,00%	2,88%
Craca	0,58%	1,96%	0,26%
Cryptonemia	0,72%	0,51%	0,40%
Dictyopteris	2,85%	1,50%	3,17%
Dictyosphaeria	3,35%	4,32%	0,00%
Dictyota	2,04%	1,16%	0,19%
Digenia simplex	0,00%	1,69%	0,00%
Ectocarpales	1,00%	0,41%	0,00%
Esponja	0,00%	0,00%	0,20%
Fenda	1,20%	1,17%	0,45%
Gelidiella acerosa	8,80%	8,40%	6,72%
Gelidium	4,04%	4,16%	6,69%
Gracilaria	4,91%	4,29%	9,92%
Halimeda	1,32%	0,99%	0,00%
Hypnea	5,80%	5,25%	5,67%
Jania	2,15%	2,61%	0,28%
Laurencia dendroidea	4,29%	4,67%	1,63%
Laurencia translucida	0,00%	1,09%	0,00%
Ouriço	0,46%	1,23%	0,40%
Padina	2,00%	4,21%	0,00%
Palisada flagellifera	0,00%	0,19%	0,00%
Palisada furcata	2,53%	1,75%	0,19%
Palisada perforata	9,96%	11,94%	7,79%
Palythoa	1,81%	2,50%	0,80%
Petaloconchus	0,63%	0,00%	0,00%
Poliqueta	0,59%	0,00%	0,00%
Protopalythoa	2,31%	0,00%	1,39%
Sargassum	6,37%	6,71%	0,46%
Turf	0,00%	0,33%	0,00%
Ulva	1,42%	2,33%	12,40%
Wrangelia	0,42%	0,23%	0,40%
Tamanho (Km)
Orientacao				Influência dos Rios					Formação		Proteção	
I = (0-10 N)	II = (&gt;10-20 N)	III = (&gt;10-20 N)	IV = (&gt;30 N)	I = (&gt; 5 Km)	II = (3-5 Km)	III = (&lt;3 Km) ou CD mas pouco caudal	IV = Influência sobre parte da estrutura	V = Pluma do rio grande tocando o recife	Continuo	Fragmentado	Sem linhas de recifes a frente	Com linhas de recifes a frente
Localidade
Distancia da Costa (m)
Cupe Muro Alto	162,9 95,6	0,844 4,083		X	X	X		X		X X			X X	
Suape	570	3,516			X					X	X		X	
Guadalupe	465,5	1,727			X		X					X		X
Porto	154,1	1,523		X				X				X	X	
Paiva	56,7	2,092		X		X					X		X	
Enseada	50	2,934	X					X			X		X	
São José	594,2	5,25			X					X		X	X	
Campas Tam2	264,4	3,981		X		X						X		X
Carneiros	707,1	2,315			X					X		X		X
Barra Sirinhaem	583,8	1,967			X			X			X		X	
Toquinho (ex)	803,2	2,592			X				X		X		X	
Toquinho (in)	94,8	3,351				X		X			X		X	
Serrambi	300,9	4,258			X					X		X	X	
Marinha Farinha	939,7	3,549		X			X					X		x
Mamucabas Tam1	538,6	2,393		X						X		X	x	
Sao José da Coroa Grande	594,2	5,25			X					X		X	X	
Tabela 5. Valores médios para as variáveis morfológicas das estruturas recifais das localidades utilizadas na análise de classificação de habitats.
Localidade	Largura	Inclinação	Orientação	Altura	Rugosidade
Suape	68,18	0,04	115,83	1,75	0,15
Paiva	355,67	0,08	136,67	0,85	0,29
Enseada	42,53	0,31	107,86	0,69	0,08
Serrambi	100,13	0,09	117,67	0,27	0,35
Toquinho In	13,04	0,26	140,60	0,96	0,15
Carneiros	90,40	0,02	119,67	0,79	0,13
Campas	90,87	0,24	85,67	0,54	0,37
Mamucabas	194,63	0,12	136,67	0,22	0,35
São José da Coroa Grande	210,93	0,08	139,00	0,60	0,23
Anexo II - Normas editorias das revistas
MARINE ENVIRONMENTAL RESEARCH
AUTHOR INFORMATION PACK
TABLE OF CONTENTS
•	Description	p.l
•	Audience	P-1
•	Impact Factor	P-l
•	Abstracting and Indexing	p.2
•	Editorial Board	P-2
•	Guide for Authors	p.3
ISSN: 0141-1136
DESCRIPTION
Manne Environmental Research publishes original research papers on chemical, physical, and biological interactions in the oceans and coastal waters. The journal serves as a forum for new information on biology, chemistry, and toxicology and syntheses that advance understanding of marine environmental processes.
Submission of multidisciplinary studies is encouraged. Studies that utilize expen mental appr oaches to clarify the roles of anthropogenic and natural causes of changes in marine ecosystems are especially welcome, as are those studies that represent new developments of a theoretical or conceptual aspect of marine science. All papers published in this journal are reviewed by qualified peers prior to acceptance and publication. Examples of topics considered to be appropriate for the journal include, but are not limited to, the following:
-The extent, persistence, and consequences of change and the recovery from such change in natural maiine systems
-	The biochemical, physiological, and ecological consequences of contaminants to marine organisms and ecosystems
-	The biogeochemistry of naturally occurring and anthropogenic substances
-	Models that describe and predict the above processes
-	Monitoring studies, to the extent that their results provide new information on functional processes
-	Methodological papers describing improved quantitative techniques for the marine sciences.
AUDIENCE
Marine scientists, fisheries research workers, ecologists, biologists.
IMPACT FACTOR
2015: 2.769 © Thomson Reuters Journal Citation Reports 2016
GUIDE FOR AUTHORS
Your Paper Your Way
We now differentiate between the requirements for new and revised submissions. You may choose to submit your manuscript as a single Word or PDF file to be used in the refereeing process. Only when your paper is at the revision stage, will you be requested to put your paper in to a 'correct format' for acceptance and provide the items required for the publication of your article.
To find out more, please visit the Preparation section below.
INTRODUCTION
Marine Environmental Research publishes original research papers on chemical, physical and biological interactions in the oceans and coastal wateis. The journal seives as a forum for new information on biology, chemistry, and toxicology and syntheses that advance understanding of marine environmental processes. Submission of multidisciplinary studies is encouraged. Studies that utilise experimental approaches to clarify the roles of anthropogenic and natural causes of changes marine ecosystems are especially welcome, as are those studies that represent new developments of a theoretical or conceptual aspect of marine science. All papers published in this journal are reviewed by qualified peers poor to acceptance and publication.
Types of paper
Research papeis; Review Articles; Book Reviews; Conference and Meeting Papeis, Short Communications; Letters to the Editors
Contact details for submission
Authois may send queries concerning the submission process, manuscript status, or journal procedures to the Editorial Office.
Submission checklist
You can use this list to cany out a final check of your submission before you send it to the journal for review. Please check the relevant section in this Guide for Authors for more details.
Ensure that the following items are present:
One author has been designated as the corresponding author with contact details:
•	E-mail address
•	Full postal address
All necessary files have been uploaded:
Manuscript:
•	Include keywords
•	All figures (include relevant captions)
•	All tables (including titles, description, footnotes)
•	Ensure all figure and table citations in the text match the files provided
•	Indicate clearly if color should be used for any figures in print
Graphical Abstracts / Highlights files (where applicable)
Supplemental files (where applicable)
Further considerations
•	Manuscript has been 'spell checked' and 'grammar checked'
•	All references mentioned in the Reference List are cited in the text, and vice veisa
•	Permission has been obtained for use of copyrighted material from other sources (including the Internet)
•	Relevant declarations of interest have been made
•	Journal policies detailed in this guide have been reviewed
•	Referee suggestions and contact details provided, based on journal requirements
For further information, visit our Support Center.
BEFORE YOU BEGIN
Ethics in publishing
Please see our information pages on Ethics in publishing and Ethical guidelines for journal publication.
Figures and tables embedded in text
Please ensure the figures and the tables included in the single file are placed next to the relevant text in the manuscript, rather than at the bottom or the top of the file.
REVISED SUBMISSIONS
Use of word processing software
Regardless of the file format of the original submission, at revision you must provide us with an editable file of the entire article. Keep the layout of the text as simple as possible. Most formatting codes will be removed and replaced on processing the article. The electronic text should be prepared in a way very similar to that of conventional manuscripts (see also the Guide to Publishing with Elsevier). See also the section on Electi onic artwork.
To avoid unnecessary errors you are strongly advised to use the 'spell-check' and 'grammar-check' functions of your word processor.
Article structure
Subdivision - numbered sections
Divide your article into dearly defined and numbered sections. Subsections should be numbered
1.1	(then 1.1.1, 1.1.2, ...), 1.2, etc. (the abstract is not included in section numbering). Use this numbering also for internal cross-referencing: do not just refer to 'the text'. Any subsection may be given a brief heading. Each heading should appear on its own separate line.
Introduction
State the objectives of the work and provide an adequate background, avoiding a detailed literature survey or a summary of the results.
Material and methods
Provide sufficient detail to allow the work to be reproduced. Methods already published should be indicated by a reference: only relevant modifications should be described.
Theory/calculation
A Theory section should extend, not repeat, the background to the article already dealt with in the Intr oduction and lay the foundation for further work. In contrast, a Calculation section represents a practical development from a theor etical basis.
Results
Results should be clear and concise.
Discussion
This should explore the significance of the results of the work, not repeat them. A combined Results and Discussion section is often appropriate. Avoid extensive citations and discussion of published literature.
Conclusions
The main conclusions of the study may be presented in a short Conclusions section, which may stand alone or form a subsection of a Discussion or Results and Discussion section.
Appendices
If there is more than one appendix, they should be identified as A, B, etc. Formulae and equations in appendices should be given separate numbering: Eq. (A.l), Eq. (A.2), etc.; in a subsequent appendix, Eq. (B.l) and so on. Similarly for tables and figures: Table A.l; Fig. A.l, etc.
Essential title page information
•	Title. Concise and informative. Titles are often used in information-retrieval systems. Avoid abbreviations and formulae where possible.
•	Author names and affiliations. Please clearly indicate the given name(s) and family name(s) of each author and check that all names are accurately spelled. Present the authors' affiliation addresses (where the actual work was done) below the names. Indicate all affiliations with a lowercase superscript letter immediately after the author's name and in front of the appropriate address. Provide the full postal address of each affiliation, including the country name and, if available, the e-mail address of each author.
•	Corresponding author. Clearly indicate who will handle conespondenoe at all stages of refereeing and publication, also post-publication. Ensure that the e-mail address is given and that contact details are kept up to date by the corresponding author.
Abstract
A condse and factual abstract is requited. The abstract should state briefly the purpose of the research, the principal results and major conclusions. An abstract is often presented separately from the article, so it must be able to stand alone. For this reason, References should be avoided, but if essential, then cite the authorfs) and yearfs). Also, non-standard or uncommon abbreviations should be avoided, but if essential they must be defined at their first mention in the abstract itself. The abstract should be 100-150 words in length.
Graphical abstract
Although a graphical abstract is optional, its use is encouraged as it draws more attention to the online article. The graphical abstract should summarize the contents of the article in a concise, pictorial form designed to capture the attention of a wide leadership. Graphical abstracts should be submitted as a separate file in the online submission system. Image size: Please provide an image with a minimum of 531 x 1328 pixels (h x w) or proportionally more. The image should be readable at a size of 5 x 13 cm using a regular screen resolution of 96 dpi. Preferred file types: TIFF, EPS, PDF or MS Office files. You can view Example Graphical Abstracts on our information site.
Authors can make use of Elsevier's Illustration and Enhancement service to ensure the best presentation of their images and in accordance with all technical requirements: Illustration Service.
Highlights
Highlights are mandatory for this journal. They consist of a short collection of bullet points that convey the core findings of the article and should be submitted in a separate editable file in the online submission system. Please use 'Highlights’ in the file name and include 3 to 5 bullet points (maximum 85 characters, including spaces, per bullet point). You can view example Highlights on our information site.
Keywords
Immediately after the abstract, provide 6-10 keywords which describe the scope of the article. At least 3 of these must be selected from the list of suggested keywords http://cdn.elsevier.com/promis_misc/405865kwd.pdf. Where relevant these should include the main species concerned, the geographical area and the contaminant.
Abbreviations
Define abbreviations that are not standard in this field at their first occurrence in the article: in the abstract but also in the main text after it. Ensure consistency of abbreviations throughout the article.
Acknowledgements
Collate acknowledgements in a separate section at the end of the article before the r eferences and do not, therefore, include them on the title page, as a footnote to the title or otherwise. List here those individuals who provided help during the research (e.g., providing language help, writing assistance or proof reading the article, etc.).
Formatting of funding sources
List funding sources in this standard way to facilitate compliance to funder's requirements:
Funding: This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health [grant numbers xxxx, yyyy); the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Seattle, WA [grant number zzzz); and the United States Institutes of Peace [giant number aaaa].
It is not necessary to include detailed descriptions on the program or type of grants and awards. When funding is from a block grant or other resources available to a university, college, or other research institution, submit the name of the institute or organization that provided the funding.
If no funding has been provided for the research, please include the following sentence:
This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.
Tables
Please submit tables as editable text and not as images. Tables can be placed either next to the relevant text in the article, or on separate page(s) at the end. Number tables consecutively in accordance with their appearance in the text and place any table notes below the table body. Be sparing in the use of tables and ensure that the data presented in them do not duplicate results described elsewhere in the article. Please avoid using vertical rules.
References
Citation in text
Please ensure that every reference cited in the text is also present in the reference list (and vice versa). Any references cited in the abstract must be given in full. Unpublished results and personal communications are not recommended in the reference list, but may be mentioned in the text. If these references are included in the reference list they should follow the standard reference style of the journal and should include a substitution of the publication date with either 'Unpublished results’ or 'Personal communication'. Citation of a reference as 'in press' implies that the item has been accepted for publication.
Reference links
Increased discoverability of research and high quality peer review are ensured by online links to the sources cited. In order to allow us to create links to abstracting and indexing services, such as Scopus, CrossRef and PubMed, please ensure that data provided in the references are correct Please note that incorrect surnames, joumal/book titles, publication year and pagination may prevent link creation. When copying references, please be careful as they may already contain errors. Use of the DOI is encouraged.
A DOI can be used to cite and link to electronic articles where an article is in-press and full citation details are not yet known, but the article is available online. A DOI is guaranteed never to change, so you can use it as a permanent link to any electronic article. An example of a citation using DOI for an article not yet in an issue is: VanDecar J.C., Russo R.M., James D.E., Ambeh W.B., Franke M. (2003). Aseismic continuation of the Lesser Antilles slab beneath northeastern Venezuela. Journal of Geophysical Research, http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2001JB000884i. Please note the format of such citations should be in the same style as all other references in the paper.
Web references
As a minimum, the full URL should be given and the date when the reference was last accessed. Any further information, if known (DOI, author names, dates, reference to a source publication, etc.), should also be given. Web references can be listed separately (e.g., after the reference list) under a different heading if desired, or can be included in the reference list.
References in a special issue
Please ensure that the words 'this issue' are added to any references in the list (and any citations in the text) to other articles in the same Special Issue.
Reference management software
Most Elsevier journals have their reference template available in many of the most popular reference management software products. These include all products that support Citation Style Language styles, such as Mendeley and Zotero, as well as EndNote. Using the woid processor plug-ins from these products, authors only need to select the appropriate journal template when preparing their article, after which citations and bibliographies will be automatically formatted in the journal's style. If no template is yet available for this journal, please follow the format of the sample references and citations as shown in this Guide.
Users of Mendeley Desktop can easily install the reference style for this journal by clicking the following link:
http://open.mendeley.com/use-citation-style/marine-environmental-research
When preparing your manuscript, you will then be able to select this style using the Mendeley plugins for Microsoft Word or LibreOffice.
Reference style
Text: All citations in the text should refer to:
1.	Single author: the author’s name (without initials, unless there is ambiguity) and the year of publication;
2.	Two authors: both authors' names and the year of publication;
3.	Three or more authors: first author's name followed by "et al." and the year of publicabon. Citations may be made directly (or parenthetically). Groups of references should be listed first alphabetically, then chronologically.
Examples: "as demonstrated (Allan, 1996a, 1996b, 1999; Allan and Jones, 1995). Kramer et al. (2000) have recently shown ...."
List: References should be arranged fust alphabetically and then further sorted chronologically if necessary. More than one reference from the same author(s) in the same year must be identified by the letters "a", "b", "c", etc., placed after the year of publication.
Examples:
Reference to a journal publication:
Van der Geer, J., Hanraads, J.A.J., Lupton, R.A., 2000. The art of writing a scientific article. Journal of Scientific Communication 163, 51-59.
Reference to a book:
Strunk Jr., W., White, E.B., 1979. The Elements of Style, third ed. Macmillan, New York.
Reference to a chapter in an edited book:
Mettam, G.R., Adams, L.B., 1999. Howto prepare an electronic version of your article, in: Jones, B.S., Smith , R.Z. (Eds.), Introduction to the Electionic Age. E-Publishing Inc., New York, pp. 281-304.
Video
Elsevier accepts video material and animation sequences to support and enhance your scientific research. Authors who have video or animation files that they wish to submit with their article are strongly encouraged to include links to these within the body of the article. This can be done in the same way as a figure or table by referring to the video or animation content and noting in the body text where it should be placed. All submitted files should be properly labeled so that they directly relate to the video file's content. In order to ensure that your video or animation material is directly usable, please provide the files in one of our recommended file formats with a preferred maximum size of 150 MB. Video and animation files supplied will be published online in the electronic version of your article in Elsevier Web products, including ScienceDirect. Please supply 'stills’ with your files: you can choose any frame from the video or animation or make a separate image. These will be used instead of standard icons and will peisonalize the link to your video data. For more detailed instructions please visit our video instruction pages. Note: since video and animation cannot be embedded in the print version of the journal, please provide text for both the electronic and the print version for the portions of the article that refer to this content.
Supplementary data
Elsevier accepts electronic supplementary material to support and enhance your scientific research. Supplementary files offer the author additional possibilities to publish supporting applications, high-resolution images, background datasets, sound clips and more. Supplementary files supplied will be published online alongside the electronic version of your article in Elsevier Web products, including ScienceDirect: http://www.sciencedirect.com. In order to ensure that your submitted material is directly usable, please provide the data in one of our recommended file formats. Authois should submit the material in electronic format together with the article and supply a concise and descriptive caption for each file. For more detailed instructions please visit our artwork instruction pages at http://www.elsevier.com/artwoiidnstructions.
Database linking
Elsevier encourages authors to connect articles with external databases, giving readers access to relevant databases that help to build a better understanding of the described research. Please refer to relevant database identifiers using the following format in your article: Database: xxxx (e.g., TAIR: AT1G01020; CCDC: 734053; PDB: 1XFN). More information and a full list of supported databases.
REGIONAL STUDIES IN MARINE SCIENCE
ELSEVIER
AUTHOR INFORMATION PACK
TABLE OF CONTENTS
Description	P-l
Editorial Board	P-1
Guide for Authors	p.4
DESCRIPTION
REGIONAL STUDIES IN MARINE SCIENCE will publish scientifically sound papers on regional aspects of maritime and marine resources in estuaries, coastal zones, continental shelf, the seas and oceans.
Papers published may include (but are not limited to):
•	Studies of local interest and importance to the region
•	Studies on regional marine biodiversity and fisheries resources
•	Regional strategies and action plans for conservation of marine biodiversity and sustainable development
•	Marine resources management including sustainable fisheries management and the selection and operation of marine protected areas
•	Studies on chemical contaminants (e.g. pesticides, endocrine disrupting chemicals, and pharmaceutical and personal care chemicals) especially concerning food species
•	Studies on the impacts of eutrophication, hypoxia and chemical contaminants on species important to the region, and their control/mitigation measures
•	Pollution control and management
&gt;• Economic and social impacts of marine pollution and/or coastal development to the region
•	Strategies/impacts of wastewater effluent disposal and contaminated mud disposal
•	Case histories of pollution control and management
•	Environmental damage and compensation
•	Regional experience in habitat restoration and mitigation after environmental perturbation
•	Regional experience and strategies for sustainable development through achieving a balance between coastal development and environmental protection
PREPARATION
Use of word processing software
It is important that the file be saved in the native format of the word processor used. The text should be in single-column format. Keep the layout of the text as simple as possible. Most formatting codes will be removed and replaced on processing the article. In particular, do not use the word processor's options to justify text or to hyphenate words. However, do use bold face, italics, subscripts, superscripts etc. When preparing tables, if you are using a table grid, use only one grid for each individual table and not a grid for each row. If no grid is used, use tabs, not spaces, to align columns. The electronic text should be prepared in a way very similar to that of conventional manuscripts (see also the Guide to Publishing with Elsevier). Note that source files of figures, tables and text graphics will be required whether or not you embed your figur es in the text. See also the section on Electr onic artwork.
To avoid unnecessary errors you are strongly advised to use the 'spell-check' and 'grammar-check' functions of your word processor.
Article structure
Subdivision - numbered sections
Divide your article into clearly defined and numbered sections. Subsections should be numbered 1.1 (then 1.1.1, 1.1.2, ...), 1.2, etc. (the abstract is not included in section numbering). Use this numbering also for internal cross-referencing: do not just refer to 'the text'. Any subsection may be given a brief heading. Each heading should appear on its own separate line.
Introduction
State the objectives of the work and provide an adequate background, avoiding a detailed literature survey or a summaiy of the results.
Material and methods
Provide sufficient detail to allow the work to be reproduced. Methods already published should be indicated by a reference: only relevant modifications should be described.
Theory/calculation
A Theory section should extend, not repeat, the backgr ound to the article already dealt with in the Introduction and lay the foundation for further work. In contrast, a Calculation section represents a practical development from a theoretical basis.
Results
Results should be clear and concise.
Discussion
This should explore the significance of the results of the work, not repeat them. A combined Results and Discussion section is often appropriate. Avoid extensive citations and discussion of published literature.
Conclusions
The main conclusions of the study may be presented in a short Conclusions section, which may stand alone or form a subsection of a Discussion or Results and Discussion section.
Appendices
If there is more than one appendix, they should be identified as A, B, etc. Formulae and equations in appendices should be given separate numbering: Eq. (A.l), Eq. (A.2), etc.; in a subsequent appendix, Eq. (B.l) and so on. Similarly for tables and figures: Table A.l; Fig. A.l, etc.
Essential title page information
• Title. Concise and informative. Titles are often used in information-retrieval systems. Avoid abbreviations and formulae where possible.
•	Author names and affiliations. Please dearty indicate the given name(s) and family name(s) of each author and check that all names a-e accurately spded. P-esent the authors’ aPilation addresses (where the actual work was done) below the names. Indicate all affiliations with a lowercase superscript letter immediately after the author's name and in front of the appropriate address. Provide the full postal address of each aff liatcn, Inducting the country name and, &amp;lt;available, the e-mail address of eadr author.
•	Corresponding author. Clea'ly ndloste who will hand * correspondence at a stages of -efe-eeing and publication, also post-publication. Insure that the e-mail address is given and that contact details are kept up to date by the corresponding author.
•	Present / permanent address. If an author has moved since the work descrbed In the a'tlde was done, or was visiting at the time, a 'P*esent address' (or 'Permanent address') may be ndicated as a footnote to that author's name. The address at which the author actuaiy did the work must be reta "ed as the main, affiliation address Superscript Arabc numerals are used for such footnotes.
Abstract
A concise and factual abstract Is required. The abstract should state briefly the purpose of the research, the principal results and major oondusons. An abst-act Is often presented separatey foorr the arte*, so It must be able to stand alone. For this reason. References should be avoided, but if essenbal, then cite the authors) and year(s). Also, non-standard or uncommon abb-eviat ons should be avoided, but if essential they must be defined at the»- firs* mention in the abstract itself.
Highlights
Highlights are a short collection of bullet points that convey the core findings of the artide. Highlights are optional and should be submitted In a separate ed table file In the online submission system. Please use 'Highlghts' in the file name and include 3 to 5 buiet points (maximum 85 characters, Including spaces, per bullet point). You can view example Highlights on our Information see.
Keywords
Jmmedately after the abstract, pruvlde a maximum of 6 keywortfa, using American spelling and avoid ng genera and plura terms and multiple concepts (avod, for example, 'and', ’or). De sparing with abbreviations: only abbreviations firmly established In the field may be eligible. These keywords will be used for indexing purposes.
Abbreviations
Define abbreviabors that are not standard in ths field In a footnote to be placed on the first page of the artide. Such abbrevtabons that are unavoidable m the abstract must be defined at their first mention there, as well as In the footnote. Ensure consistency of abbreviations throughout the artide.
Admow,fedgemen ts
Collate acknowledgements In a separate section at the end of the artide before the references and do not, therefore. Indude them on the tit* page, as a footnote to the bt* or otherwise. List here those Individuals who provided heip during the research (e.g., providing language help, wrong assistance or proof reading the artide, etc.).
Formatting of funding sources
List funding sources m this standard way to fac Itate com pence tD funder's requirements:
Funding: This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health [grant numbers xxxx, yyyy); the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundabon, Seattle, WA [grant number zzzz); and the United States Institutes of Peace [grant number aaaaj.
It s not necessary to Indude detailed descriptions on the program or type of grants and awards. When funding is from a block grant or other resources available to a unrverslty, college, or other research institution, submit the name of the institute or organ zabon that p-cvided the funding.
If no funding has been p-ovlded for the research, please include the following sentence:
This resea'ch did not 'eceive any specific gmnt from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectm,.
(MH
Follow Intemabonally accepted rules and convenbons: use the International system of urrts (SI). If other units are mentioned, please give their equivalent In St.
References
Citation in text
Please ensure that every reference cited in the text is also present in the reference list (and vice versa). Any references cited in the abstract must be given in full. Unpublished results and personal communications are not recommended in the reference list, but may be mentioned in the text. If these refer ences are included in the reference list they should follow the standard reference style of the journal and should include a substitution of the publication date with either 'Unpublished results' or 'Personal communication'. Citation of a reference as 'in press' implies that the item has been accepted for publication.
Reference links
Increased discoverability of research and high quality peer review are ensured by online links to the sources cited. In order to allow us to create links to abstracting and indexing services, such as Scopus, CrossRef and PubMed, please ensure that data provided in the references are correct Please note that incorrect surnames, joumal/book titles, publication year and pagination may prevent link creation. When copying references, please be careful as they may already contain errors. Use of the DOI is encouraged.
A DOI can be used to cite and link to electronic articles where an article is in-press and full citation details are not yet known, but the article is available online. A DOI is guaranteed never to change, so you can use it as a permanent link to any electronic article. An example of a citation using DOI for an article not yet in an issue is: VanDecar J.C., Russo R.M., James D.E., Ambeh W.B., Franke M. (2003). Aseismic continuation of the Lesser Antilles slab beneath northeastern Venezuela. Journal of Geophysical Research, http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2001JB000884i. Please note the format of such citations should be in the same style as all other references in the paper.
Web references
As a minimum, the full URL should be given and the date when the reference was last accessed. Any further information, if known (DOI, author names, dates, reference to a source publication, etc.), should also be given. Web references can be listed separately (e.g., after the reference list) under a different heading if desired, or can be included in the reference list.
References in a special issue
Please ensure that the words 'this issue' are added to any references in the list (and any citations in the text) to other articles in the same Special Issue.
Reference management software
Most Elsevier journals have their reference template available in many of the most popular reference management software products. These include all products that support Citation Style Language styles, such as Mendeley and Zotero, as well as EndNote. Using the word processor plug-ins from these products, authors only need to select the appropnate journal template when preparing their article, after which citations and bibliographies will be automatically formatted in the journal's style. If no template is yet available for this journal, please follow the format of the sample references and citations as shown in this Guide.
Users of Mendeley Desktop can easily install the reference style for this journal by clicking the following link: http://open.mendeley.com/use-citation-style/regional-studies-in-marine-science
When preparing your manuscript, you will then be able to select this style using the Mendeley plugins for Microsoft Word or LibreOffice.
Reference formatting
There are no strict requirements on reference formatting at submission. References can be in any style or format as long as the style is consistent. Where applicable, author(s) name(s), journal title/book title, chapter title/article title, year of publication, volume number/book chapter and the pagination must be present. Use of DOI is highly encouraged. The reference style used by the journal will be applied to the accepted article by Elsevier at the proof stage. Note that missing data will be highlighted at proof stage for the author to correct. If you do wish to format the references yourself they should be arranged according to the following examples:
Reference style
Text: All citations in the text should refer to:
1.	Single author: the author's name (without initials, unless there is ambiguity) and the year of publication;
2.	Two authors: both authors' names and the year of publication;
3.	Three or more authors: first author's name followed by 'et al.' and the year of publication. Citations may be made directly (or parenthetically). Groups of references should be listed first alphabetically, then chronologically.
Examples: 'as demonstrated (Allan, 2000a, 2000b, 1999; Allan and Jones, 1999). Kramer et al. (2010) have recently shown ....'
List: References should be arranged first alphabetically and then further sorted chronologically if necessary. More than one reference from the same author(s) in the same year must be identified by the letters 'a', 'b', 'c', etc., placed after the year of publication.
Examples:
Reference to a journal publication:
Van dec Geer, J., Hanraads, J.A.J., Lupton, R.A., 2010. The art of writing a scientific article. J. Sci. Commun. 163, 51-59.
Reference to a book:
Strunk Jr., W., White, E.B., 2000. The Elements of Style, fourth ed. Longman, New York.
Reference to a chapter in an edited book:
Mettam, G.R., Adams, L.B., 2009. How to prepare an electronic version of your article, in: Jones, B.S., Smith , R.Z. (Eds.), Introduction to the Electionic Age. E-Publishing Inc., New York, pp. 281-304. Reference to a website:
Cancer Research UK, 1975. Cancer statistics reports for the UK. http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/ aboutcancer/statistics/cancerstatsreport/ (accessed 13.03.03).
Journal abbreviations source
Journal names should be abbreviated according to the List of Tide Word Abbreviations.
ECOLOGICAL INDICATORS
Integrating Sciences for Monitoring, Assessment and Management
ELSEVIER
AUTHOR INFORMATION PACK
TABLE OF CONTENTS

Description
Audience
Impact Factor
Abstracting and Indexing Editorial Board
Guide for Authors
p.l P-2
P-2
p.2
P-2
p.4
ISSN: 1470-160X
DESCRIPTION
The ultimate aim of Ecological Indicators is to integrate the monitoring and assessment of ecological and environmental indicators with management practices. The journal provides a forum for the discussion of the applied scientific development and review of traditional indicator applications as well as for theoretical, modelling and quantitative approaches such as index development. Research into the following areas will be published.
•	All aspects of ecological and environmental indicators and indices.
•	New indicators, and new approaches and methods for indicator development, testing and use.
•	Development and modelling of indices, e.g. application of indicator suites across multiple scales and resources.
•	Analysis and research of resource, system- and scale-spedfic indicators.
•	Methods for integration of social and other valuation metrics for the production of scientifically ngorous and politically-relevant assessments using indicator-based monitoring and assessment programs.
•	Approaches on how research indicators can be transformed into direct application for management purposes.
•	Broader assessment objectivesand methods, e.g. biodiversity, biological integrity, and sustainability, through the use of indicators.
•	Resource-specific indicators such as landscape, agroecosystems, forests ecosystems, aquatic ecosystems, wetlands, etc.
The journal seeks innovative papers which provide new developmental and methodological steps for environmental indication. Submissions of results from simple monitoring programs or single case studies, resulting in descriptive approaches without any exploration from the theory of indication, from the methodology of indication, or from the management points of view are not considered suitable for publication in Ecological Indicators.
The following contributions will be accepted:
Original research papers;
Review articles;
Special themed issues;
Short notes and case studies;
Viewpoints;
Letters to the Editor;
IMPACT FACTOR
Submission checklist
You can use this list to cany out a final check of your submission before you send it to the journal for review. Please check the relevant section in this Guide for Authors for more details.
Ensure that the following items are present:
One author has been designated as the corresponding author with contact details:
•	E-mail address
•	Full postal address
All necessaiy files have been uploaded:
Manuscript:
•	Include keywords
•	All figures (include relevant captions)
•	All tables (including titles, description, footnotes)
•	Ensure all figure and table citations in the text match the files provided
•	Indicate clearly if color should be used for any figures in print
Graphical Abstracts / Highlights files (where applicable)
Supplemental files (where applicable)
Further considerations
•	Manuscript has been 'spell checked’ and 'grammar checked'
•	All references mentioned in the Reference List are cited in the text, and vice versa
•	Permission has been obtained for use of copyrighted material from other sources (including the Internet)
•	Relevant declarations of interest have been made
•	Journal policies detailed in this guide have been reviewed
•	Referee suggestions and contact details provided, based on journal requirements
References
Citation in text
Please ensure that every reference cited in the text is also present in the reference list (and vice versa). Any references cited in the abstract must be given in full. Unpublished results and personal communications are not recommended in the reference list, but may be mentioned in the text. If these references are included in the reference list they should follow the standard r eference style of the journal and should include a substitution of the publication date with either 'Unpublished results’ or 'Personal communication'. Citation of a reference as 'in press’ implies that the item has been accepted for publication.
Reference links
Increased discoverability of research and high quality peer review are ensured by online links to the sources cited. In order to allow us to create links to abstr acting and indexing seivices, such as Scopus, CrossRef and PubMed, please ensure that data provided in the refer ences at e correct. Please note that incoivect surnames, joumal/book titles, publication year and pagination may prevent link creation. When copying references, please be careful as they may already contain errors. Use of the DOI is encouraged.
A DOI can be used to cite and link to electronic articles where an article is in-press and full citation details are not yet known, but the article is available online. A DOI is guaranteed never to change, so you can use it as a permanent link to any electronic article. An example of a citation using DOI for an article not yet in an issue is: VanDecar J.G, Russo R.M., James D.E., Ambeh W.B., Franke M. (2003). Aseismic continuation of the Lesser Antilles slab beneath northeastern Venezuela. Journal of Geophysical Research, http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2001JB000884i. Please note the format of such citations should be in the same style as all other references in the paper.
Web references
As a minimum, the full URL should be given and the date when the reference was last accessed. Any further information, if known (DOI, author names, dates, reference to a source publication, etc.), should also be given. Web references can be listed separately (e.g., after the reference list) under a different heading if desired, or can be included in the reference list.
References in a special issue
Please ensure that the words 'this issue' are added to any references in the list (and any citations in the text) to other articles in the same Special Issue.
Reference management software
Most Elsevier journals have their reference template available in many of the most popular reference management software products. These include all products that support Citation Style Language styles, such as Mendeley and Zotero, as well as EndNote. Using the word processor plug-ins from these products, authors only need to select the appropriate journal template when preparing their article, after which citations and bibliographies will be automatically formatted in the journal's style. If no template is yet available for this journal, please follow the format of the sample references and citations as shown in this Guide.
Users of Mendeley Desktop can easily install the reference style for this journal by clicking the following link:
http://open.mendeley.com/use-citation-style/ecological-indicators
When preparing your manuscript, you will then be able to select this style using the Mendeley plugins for Microsoft Word or LibreOffice.
Reference formatting
There are no strict requirements on reference formatting at submission. References can be in any style or format as long as the style is consistent Where applicable, author(s) name(s), journal title/book title, chapter title/article tide, year of publication, volume number/book chapter and the pagination must be present. Use of DOI is highly encouraged. The reference style used by the journal will be
applied to the accepted article by Elsevier at the proof stage. Note that missing data will be highlighted at proof stage for the author to cotrect. If you do wish to format the references yourself they should be arranged according to the following examples:
Reference style
Text: All citations in the text should refer to:
1.	Single author: the author's name (without initials, unless there is ambiguity) and the year of publication;
2.	Two authors: both authors' names and the year of publication;
3.	Three or more authors: first author’s name followed by 'et al.’ and the year of publication. Citations may be made directly (or parenthetically). Groups of references should be listed first alphabetically, then chronologically.
Examples: 'as demonstrated (Allan, 2000a, 2000b, 1999; Allan and Jones, 1999). Kramer et al. (2010) have recently shown
List: References should be arranged first alphabetically and then further sorted chronologically if necessary. More than one reference from the same author(s) in the same year must be identified by the letter's 'a', 'b', 'c', etc,, placed after the year of publication.
Examples:
Reference to a journal publication:
Van der Geer, J., Hanraads, J.A.J., Lupton, R.A., 2010. The art of writing a scientific article. J. Sci. Commun. 163, 51-59.
Reference to a book:
Strunk Jr., W., White, E.B., 2000. The Elements of Style, fourth ed. Longman, New Yoi1&lt;.
Reference to a chapter in an edited book:
Mettam, G.R., Adams, L.B., 2009. How to prepare an electionic version of your article, in: Jones, B.S., Smith , R.Z. (Eds.), Introduction to the Electronic Age. E-Publishing Inc., New York, pp. 281-304. Reference to a website:
Cancer Resear ch UK, 1975. Cancer statistics reports for the UK. http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/ aboutcancer/statistics/cancerstatsreport/ (accessed 13.03.03).
Journal abbreviations source
Journal names should be abbreviated according to the List of Title Word Abbreviations,</field>
	</doc>
</add>