<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.19614</field>
		<field name="filename">2_000628015.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL 
INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS 

PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOCIÊNCIAS 
 
 
 
 
 
 

ANÁLISE PETROLÓGICA E SÍSMICA DOS 

CONTROLES SOBRE A DEPOSIÇÃO DOS SISTEMAS 

ARENOSOS DE ÁGUAS PROFUNDAS DA BACIA DE 

CAMPOS 
 
 

Marcos Roberto Fetter Lopes 
 
 
 
 
 
ORIENTADORES  

Prof. Dr. Luiz Fernando De Ros – Instituto de Geociências, UFRGS 

Dr. Carlos Henrique Lima Bruhn – Petrobras E&amp;amp;P  

  

 

BANCA EXAMINADORA 

Prof. Dr. Marcus Remus – Instituto de Geociências, UFRGS  

Dr. José Antonio Cupertino – Petrobras E&amp;amp;P 

Dr. Guilherme Pederneiras Raja Gabaglia – Universidade Petrobras 
 

 
 
 

Tese de Doutorado apresentada como 
requisito parcial para a obtenção do 
Título de Doutor em Ciências. 

 
 
 

Porto Alegre – 2007 
 



Dedicatória 

Este trabalho é dedicado para Isabel, Pedro e muito especialmente para Marcella, 

com quem tenho tido o prazer de compartilhar andanças pelas trilhas da Geologia e pela 

vida afora. 



 

Agradecimentos 

De Ros e Bruhn (Orientadores) 

Del Rey, Anderson, Cristiano Sombra e Renato Kowsmann (Revisores) 

Gerson Terra (Universidade Petrobras)  

Cupertino, Helga e Luis Cláudio (Petrobras E&amp;amp;P) 

Luci, Carlos Turbidito Rodrigues e Claudio Lima (Petrobras CENPES) 

Eliane de Freitas Ferreira (Biblioteca da Petrobras) 

André Derraik e Márcio Santi (PUC-RJ/TECGRAF) 

Remus, Claiton, Norberto Dani e Karin (UFRGS) 

François Lafferriére e Mathieu Morris (GOCAD) 

Marcella, Pedro, Isabel, Ruth, Orenita e Eduardo (Niterói) 

Aldo e Marília; Zezinho, Márcia, Alice e Rodrigo (Porto Alegre) 



 

Resumo 

A Bacia de Campos, localizada na margem continental sudeste do Brasil, é a 

principal província petrolífera do país. Sistemas arenosos de águas profundas formados 

entre o Albiano e o Mioceno, durante a fase de margem divergente da bacia, 

genericamente designados como turbiditos, contém a maior parte das reservas de 

hidrocarbonetos. Ao contrário da tendência de aumento de maturidade petrográfica 

esperada para uma margem continental geodinamicamente passiva, os turbiditos da 

Bacia de Campos apresentam uma recorrente imaturidade composicional e textural dada 

por granulometria modal nas frações areia média e grossa e por alta proporção de 

feldspatos. Para o entendimento dos processos que controlaram o suprimento de areia 

para os ambientes de águas profundas da Bacia de Campos foi utilizada uma 

metodologia integrada baseada na petrografia quantitativa dos turbiditos pelo método 

Gazzi-Dickinson de contagem de pontos, na análise estrutural da deformação produzida 

por tectônica de embasamento através de atributos sísmicos, e na restauração de seções 

de estruturas distencionais produzidas por tectônica salífera. 

 A petrografia quantitativa evidenciou as tendências gerais e a organização interna 

dos parâmetros petrográficos dos turbiditos, além de permitir a definição de duas classes 

de sitemas de acordo com sua maturidade textural e composicional. A análise estrutural 

de dados sísmicos indicou quatro fases de reativação transcorrente do embasamento 

durante o estágio de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos. A restauração de seções 

mostrou que a tectônica salífera também tem sido episódica na Bacia de Campos, com 

quatro pulsos de alta taxa de distensão correlacionáveis com os eventos de reativação do 

embasamento, sugerindo que a tectônica salífera rasa tem sido controlada pela tectônica 

de embasamento. 

A integração entre os dados da petrografia quantitativa e da análise tectônica 

possibilitou a definição dos controles que atuaram durante a deposição dos sistemas 

arenosos de águas profundas durante a fase de margem passive da Bacia de Campos. 

Ficou evidente que esta sedimentação foi condicionada pela evolução paleogeográfica 

da margem continental sudeste do Brasil, com a alternância de controle eustático e 

geodinâmico. 

O controle eustático, associado com ciclos de alta frequência relacionados à 

dinâmica interna da bacia e possivelmente a oscilações climáticas, ocorreu em períodos 

de calma tectônica e recuo de escarpa, com relevo costeiro relativamente rebaixado e 

larga plataforma marinha rasa. Os sistemas de águas profundas controlados 



 

eustaticamente são caracterizados por turbiditos relativamente maturos, depositados no 

trato de sistemas de mar baixo. Por sua vez, o condicionamento geodinâmico na 

sedimentação tem predominado durante períodos de rejuvenescimento fisiográfico 

produzido pela atividade geodinâmica ao longo da margem continental, caracterizados 

por relevo costeiro elevado e destruição da plataforma continental. O controle 

geodinâmico é associado com episódios climáticos de precipitação pluvial intensa e 

inundação dos sistemas fluviais montanhosos capazes de carregar sedimentos aluviais 

imaturos diretamente para os ambientes de águas profundas. 

Esta nova abordagem sobre os controles da deposição dos sistemas arenosos de 

águas profundas da Bacia de Campos é muito importante para a definição de modelos 

mais adequados para a exploração de novos reservatórios turbidíticos, bem como para o 

aumento da recuperação de petróleo dos reservatórios já descobertos. Em função da sua 

simplicidade, a metodologia proposta nesta tese pode ser facilmente aplicada para o 

entendimento dos controles da sedimentação de águas profundas em outras bacias de 

margem divergente. 



 

Abstract 

The Campos Basin, located along the southeastern continental margin of Brazil, is 

the major oil province in the country. Deepwater sand-rich systems formed from Albian 

to Miocene during the divergent margin phase of the basin, generically designated as 

turbidites, contain most of the hydrocarbon reserves. Opposite to the trend of increasing 

petrographic maturity expected for a tectonically passive continental margin, the 

turbidite reservoirs in Campos Basin show recurrent immaturity defined by medium to 

coarse sand grain size and high feldspar content. In order to understand the controls on 

the supply of sandy sediments to Campos Basin deepwater settings an integrated 

methodology was used, based on quantitative petrography through the Gazzi-Dickinson 

method of point-counting, on structural analysis of basement-related deformation with 

seismic attributes, and on section restoration of major extensional salt structures. 

 The quantitative petrographic analysis indicated the major average trends and the 

internal organization of the petrographic parameters of the turbidites, and defined two 

classes of systems based on their textural and compositional maturity. The structural 

analysis indicated four episodes of strike-slip reactivation of the basement fabric during 

the passive margin phase of Campos Basin. The section restoration showed that salt 

tectonics in the Campos Basin was also episodic, with four pulses of high extension rate 

that can be well correlated with the basement reactivation events, suggesting that 

basement tectonics have been controlling salt tectonics. 

The integration between data from quantitative petrography and tectonic analysis 

allowed the definition of the controls on the formation of the deepwater sand-rich 

systems during the divergent margin phase in the Campos Basin. It became evident that 

this sedimentation has been constrained by the paleogeographic evolution of the 

southeastern continental margin of Brazil, with alternating eustatic and geodynamic 

control. 

The eustatic control is associated with high-frequency climate cycles related to the 

internal basin dynamics and possibly with climatic oscillations, and occurred during 

periods of tectonic quiescence and escarpment retreat, with relatively low coastal relief 

and well developed continental shelf. The eustatically-controlled deepwater systems are 

characterized by relatively mature turbidites, deposited beyond a wide shelf during sea-

level lowstands. In turn, the geodynamic drive on the sedimentation occurred during 

periods of physiographic rejuvenation produced by geodynamic activity along the 

continental margin, characterized by high coastal relief and degradation of the 



 

continental shelf. The geodynamic control is associated with episodes of intense rainfall 

and flooding of mountainous fluvial systems that transported immature alluvial 

sediments directly to the deepwater settings. 

This new approach to the controls on the formation of the sand-rich deepwater 

systems in Campos Basin will be of key importance to generate realistic models for the 

exploration of new turbidite reservoirs and for the optimized development of producing 

turbidite oilfields in such a world-class hydrocarbon province. As it is very simple, the 

proposed integrated methodology can help to unravel the controls on the deposition of 

deepwater sand-rich reservoirs in other divergent margin settings. 



 

Sobre a Estrutura da Tese 

Esta tese de Doutorado está estruturada em torno de artigos publicados em periódicos 

internacionais. Conseqüentemente, sua organização compreende as seguintes partes 

principais: 

(a) Introdução sobre o tema e descrição do objeto da pesquisa de Doutorado, onde 

são sumarizados os objetivos e a filosofia de pesquisa desenvolvidos e o estado da arte 

sobre o tema de pesquisa, seguidos de uma discussão integradora contendo os principais 

resultados e interpretações deles derivadas; 

(b) Artigos submetidos a periódicos internacionais com corpo editorial permanente e 

revisores independentes, escritos pelo autor durante o desenvolvimento do seu 

Doutorado; 

(c) Anexos, compreendendo a documentação pertinente de natureza numérica 

(tabelas, cálculos), gráfica (figuras, diagramas, mapas, seções) e fotográfica que, por sua 

dimensão e/ou natureza não pode ser incluída nos artigos. 

  

 



SUMÁRIO 

 

Estrutura da Tese ....................................................................................................... 10 

Introdução ................................................................................................................... 11 

Metodologia ................................................................................................................. 14 

Resultados Obtidos ..................................................................................................... 19 

Referências .................................................................................................................. 24 

Artigo I ........................................................................................................................  29 

Artigo II ......................................................................................................................  44 

Artigo III .....................................................................................................................  74 

Anexos ........................................................................................................................ 149 

 

 



 10

Estrutura da Tese 

Esta tese foi organizada na forma de três artigos, presentemente submetidos para 

publicação em periódicos internacionais conceituados, que serão, daqui para frente, 

designados pelos respectivos algarismos romanos: 

I. An active divergent margin: petrographic and seismic evidence on the 

geodinamically-controlled deposition of Campos Basin giant turbidite reservoirs, 

southeastern Brazil. 

Artigo submetido à revista Geology, no qual é discutido o suprimento de areia em 

águas profundas em margens continentais divergentes e é definido o controle 

geodinâmico da deposição dos sistemas siliciclásticos arenosos de águas profundas 

durante o Cretáceo Superior na Bacia de Campos. 

II. The role of basement tectonic reactivation on the structural evolution of 

Campos Basin, offshore Brazil: evidence from 3D seismic analysis and section 

restoration. 

Artigo submetido à revista Marine and Petroleum Geology, no qual é discutida a 

evolução geodinâmica da Bacia de Campos, com ênfase no papel relevante da tectônica 

de embasamento, previamente considerada pouco importante. 

III. Petrographic and seismic evidence for the depositional setting of giant 

turbidite reservoirs and the paleogeographic evolution of Campos Basin, offshore 

Brazil. 

Artigo submetido à revista Earth Science Reviews, no qual são apresentados os 

resultados da petrografia quantitativa dos principais sistemas siliciclásticos arenosos de 

águas profundas da Bacia de Campos, e da análise estrutural de padrões envolvendo 

reativação do embasamento. Com base nestes dados são estabelecidos os controles da 

deposição destes sistemas, através da reconstrução paleogeográfica do sistema fonte-

bacia durante a fase de margem continental divergente, desde o Albiano até o Mioceno. 



 11

Introdução 

O objetivo deste projeto de doutorado foi a definição dos controles que determinaram 

a deposição dos sistemas arenosos de águas profundas formados desde o Albiano até o 

Mioceno, durante a fase de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos, na costa sudeste do 

Brasil (ver Figuras 1 e 2 do Artigo III). Os arenitos de águas profundas, designados 

genericamente como turbiditos, em função de seu processo deposicional a partir de 

correntes de turbidez, apresentam grande relevância econômica por constituírem 

excelentes reservatórios de petróleo. Os turbiditos da Bacia de Campos, 

especificamente, comportam cerca de 80% das reservas e da produção brasileiras de 

hidrocarbonetos (Bruhn et al., 2003) e estão diretamente relacionados com a 

recentemente atingida auto-suficiência de petróleo do Brasil. 

As margens continentais divergentes, contexto geológico geral no qual se insere a 

Bacia de Campos, são ainda encaradas como ambientes tectonicamente passivos, cuja 

evolução geodinâmica do tipo recuo de escarpa se restringe a processos de epirogênese, 

subsidência térmica, erosão, sedimentação e ajustes isostáticos (Ollier, 1985; Weissel e 

Karner, 1989; Gilchrist e Summerfield, 1990; Beaumont et al., 2000). A deformação 

observada nas bacias sedimentares das margens divergentes tem sido em grande parte 

atribuída aos processos gravitacionais da tectônica salífera rasa (Cobbold e Szatmari, 

1991). Com estas condições de contorno o registro estratigráfico destas margens 

passivas seria totalmente controlado pelas variações eustáticas do nível do mar, 

conforme o paradigma clássico da Estratigrafia de Seqüências (Vail et al., 1977), que 

têm sido junto à Sedimentologia (abordagem ES&amp;amp;S) as disciplinas mais utilizadas no 

estudo dos sistemas arenosos de águas profundas em todos os tipos de bacias 

sedimentares (Mutti et al., 2003; Catuneanu, 2006). Mesmo considerando os 

importantes avanços obtidos na compreensão dos ambientes sedimentares de águas 

profundas da Bacia de Campos com base nestas disciplinas (Azambuja Filho, 1990; 

Bruhn, 1993; Peres, 1993; Scarton, 1993; Pereira, 1994; Souza Cruz, 1995; Souza Jr., 

1997), importantes aspectos das condições genéticas desta sedimentação ainda não 

foram adequadamente esclarecidos. A abordagem convencional da estratigrafia de 

seqüências assume que o suprimento de areias para os sistemas de águas profundas 

durante a fase de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos tenha sido essencialmente 

relacionado com períodos de queda acentuada do nível do mar, com retrabalhamento 

sedimentar na plataforma continental, o que parece não ter ocorrido. Além disso, a 

evolução de uma margem continental passiva deveria corresponder a um gradual 



 12

rebaixamento do relevo, e a um aumento progressivo da maturidade composicional e 

textural dos turbiditos, o que também não se verifica, uma vez que expressivos sistemas 

turbidíticos arenosos caracterizados por imaturidade composicional e textural foram 

recorrentemente depositados na Bacia de Campos (Scarton, 1993; Bruhn e Walker, 

1995; Caddah et al., 1998; Artigos I e III).  

Mais recentemente, em trabalhos que seguem uma abordagem geodinâmica, foi 

sugerido que a sedimentação nas bacias da margem continental sudeste do Brasil, 

incluindo a Bacia de Campos, poderia ter sido controlada por reativações tectônicas do 

embasamento (Pereira, 1994; Lima, 1999; Cobbold et al., 2001; Lima, 2003; Artigos I e 

III), e pela passagem da margem sobre uma pluma do manto durante a transição 

Cretáceo-Terciário (Thomaz Filho et al., 2005; Zalán e Oliveira, 2005; Artigo III). 

Paralelamente, o soerguimento da margem continental sudeste do Brasil também vem 

sendo evidenciado por estudos de traços de fissão em apatitas (Gallagher e Brown, 

1999; Saenz et al., 2003). Embora em linhas gerais tanto o rejuvenescimento tectônico 

do relevo quanto a atividade magmática e o soerguimento dinâmico causados pela 

pluma do manto sejam coerentes com a imaturidade dos sistemas arenosos de águas 

profundas, não foram apresentadas ainda evidências científicas sobre o sincronismo do 

tectonismo e da atividade da pluma com a formação dos vários sistemas turbidíticos da 

Bacia de Campos.  

Nesta perspectiva, o presente projeto de pesquisa foi proposto para analisar as 

relações entre os principais eventos geodinâmicos e a deposição dos sistemas arenosos 

de águas profundas da Bacia de Campos. Para isso uma abordagem integrando 

petrografia sedimentar quantitativa e tectônica (PS&amp;amp;T), já utilizada com sucesso em 

bacias de margens convergentes e tectonicamente ativas (Valloni e Zuffa, 1984; Fontana 

et al., 1989; Critelli, 1993; Marchesini et al., 2000; Cibin et al., 2001), foi adaptada para 

a margem divergente da Bacia de Campos. A metodologia proposta corresponde a uma 

abordagem da evolução tectônica e paleogeográfica da Bacia de Campos através da 

integração, até agora não explorada na análise de margens divergentes, de três técnicas 

individualmente já bastante difundidas: (1) a petrografia quantitativa dos arenitos 

turbidíticos (Artigos I e III); (2) a análise estrutural de dados sísmicos, com ênfase na 

deformação produzida pela tectônica de embasamento (Artigos II e III); (3) a 

restauração seqüencial de seções geológicas (Artigo II). Com esta nova abordagem foi 

possível estabelecer um conjunto robusto de evidências que indicam uma alternância de 

controles distintos para o registro estratigráfico de águas profundas da Bacia de 



 13

Campos. Estes controles são estabelecidos pela evolução do peso relativo dos processos 

geodinâmicos, eustáticos e climáticos, cíclicos ou episódicos, durante a fase de margem 

divergente da bacia, desde o Albiano até o Mioceno (Artigo III). 



 14

Metodologia 

Bioestratigrafia 

A primeira demanda metodológica deste projeto foi a definição de um arcabouço 

cronogeológico padrão para todas as análises, uma vez que o tema central da pesquisa 

envolve a investigação da hipótese de sincronismo do processo de sedimentação em 

águas profundas com os processos geodinâmicos e eustáticos na Bacia de Campos. Este 

arcabouço se faz necessário não apenas para garantir a uniformidade das correlações 

entre eventos, mas também para verificar se a resolução temporal está adequada para as 

correlações estabelecidas. 

Todas as datações citadas no presente trabalho estão baseadas no zoneamento de 

nanofósseis calcários estabelecido para as bacias da margem continental do Brasil por 

Antunes et al. (2004), com equivalência cronométrica absoluta baseada na Carta 

Estratigráfica Internacional da Comissão Internacional em Estratigrafia – ICS 

(http://www.stratigraphy.org/cheu.pdf; Gradstein et al., 2004). Para a fase de margem 

divergente da Bacia de Campos, o referido zoneamento bioestratigráfico corresponde a 

18 biozonas no Período Cretáceo, entre as Idades Albiano e Maastrichtiano, com uma 

resolução em torno de 2,6 Ma, e a 35 biozonas na Era Cenozóica, entre os Períodos 

Paleogeno e Quaternário, o que equivale a uma resolução aproximada de 1,8 Ma. Cabe 

ressaltar que o nível de resolução temporal do arcabouço cronogeológico adotado 

mostrou-se adequado tanto para a datação da formação dos sistemas turbidíticos 

arenosos analisados na petrografia quantitativa (Artigos I e III), quanto para a 

interpretação dos eventos tectônicos indicados pela análise estrutural (Artigos II e III). 

Petrografia Quantitativa 

A contagem de pontos em lâminas delgadas foi a técnica utilizada no presente 

projeto para a análise petrográfica quantitativa dos arenitos de águas profundas da Bacia 

de Campos. A contagem foi feita através do método Gazzi-Dickinson (Gazzi, 1966; 

Dickinson, 1970; Ingersoll et al., 1984), conforme adaptações sugeridas por Zuffa 

(Zuffa, 1980; Zuffa, 1985; Zuffa, 1991). Esta metodologia foi escolhida pela sua 

praticidade e robustez de resultados já amplamente comprovados (Dickinson e Suczec, 

1979; Dickinson et al., 1983; Dickinson, 1985; Zuffa, 1987; Dickinson, 1988; Zuffa et 

al., 1995; Zuffa et al., 2000). 

A petrografia quantitativa foi aplicada a onze sistemas turbidíticos da fase de 

margem divergente da Bacia de Campos, com idades entre o Albiano e o Mioceno (ver 



 15

Figura 4 do Artigo III). Foram contados 300 pontos por lâmina em 117 lâminas 

delgadas correspondentes a 990 m de testemunhos dos sistemas turbidíticos estudados 

(ver Tabela 1 do Artigo III).  

Os parâmetros petrográficos composicionais e texturais e os resultados brutos da 

contagem de pontos estão registrados nas planilhas em anexo (ver CD em anexo). 

Também estão discriminadas nas planilhas as totalizações composicionais para os 

principais diagramas ternários convencionalmente utilizados neste tipo de análise 

petrográfica (Figuras 5, 6 e 7 do Artigo III). Mesmo não sendo adequadas para análise 

quantitativa, foram descritas qualitativamente 4 lâminas delgadas de conglomerados do 

sistema turbidítico do Eoceno Médio (ver CD em anexo), por apresentarem um 

significado paleogeográfico importante (Artigo III). 

Análise Estrutural de Dados Sísmicos 

A utilização do método sísmico na análise de bacias sedimentares tem experimentado 

um grande crescimento nas últimas décadas em função dos progressos tecnológicos e da 

redução dos custos de aquisição e processamento dos dados sísmicos. Atualmente a 

maior parte das grandes províncias de hidrocarbonetos do mundo, como a Bacia de 

Campos, está coberta com sísmica 3D de boa qualidade, de modo que os dados sísmicos 

já são apontados como um novo marco tecnológico na evolução das Ciências da Terra 

(Cartwright e Huuse, 2005). Este potencial têm se evidenciado bastante nas áreas de 

Geologia Estrutural e Tectônica, uma vez que a visualização tridimensional e detalhada 

das feições estruturais em volumes sísmicos possibilita um entendimento dos sistemas 

esforço-deformação muitas vezes até melhor do que o que pode ser obtido pelos 

métodos tradicionais de análise estrutural através de estudo de afloramentos, 

mapeamento de superfície e sensoreamento remoto. No caso das bacias submersas nas 

margens continentais, o método sísmico constitui a única ferramenta disponível para o 

desenvolvimento de análises estruturais de detalhe. 

Mais recentemente esta vantagem tecnológica tem sido ampliada pelo estudo de 

atributos sísmicos voltados especificamente para a interpretação estrutural. Trata-se dos 

chamados atributos sísmicos geométricos entre os quais se destacam a coerência, 

inverso da variância (Bahorich e Farmer, 1995), e os atributos obtidos pela aplicação da 

geometria diferencial aos volumes sísmicos, tais como o gradiente e a curvatura, 

respectivamente a primeira e a segunda derivadas da estrutura em um referencial 

tridimensional cartesiano (Chopra e Marfurt, 2006 e 2007). 



 16

A análise estrutural de dados sísmicos segue o mesmo fluxo de trabalho da análise 

estrutural convencional, com a classificação espacial e temporal da deformação quanto 

ao estilo estrutural, ao padrão cinemático e ao condicionamento dinâmico das estruturas 

(Davis e Reynolds, 1996). Neste trabalho foi desenvolvida uma análise estrutural de 

quatro volumes sísmicos regionais da Bacia de Campos. Foram identificadas nestes 

volumes seis áreas correspondentes aos principais sistemas esforço-deformação 

produzidos pela tectônica de embasamento. Nestas áreas a análise estrutural de detalhe 

foi sustentada pela consistência espacial de atributos sísmicos geométricos (Artigos II e 

III). Todos os volumes sísmicos utilizados, originalmente adquiridos com a coordenada 

vertical em tempo de trânsito, foram convertidos para profundidade com um único 

modelo regional de velocidades sísmicas calibradas com um conjunto de tabelas tempo-

profundidade medidas em poços. Adicionalmente todos os horizontes sísmicos que 

fundamentaram o estudo da deformação foram ajustados a marcadores 

bioestratigráficos.  

Através da análise estrutural foi possível caracterizar os principais eventos de 

deformação relacionados com a tectônica de embasamento durante a fase de margem 

continental divergente da Bacia de Campos (Artigos II e III). Previamente todos os 

trabalhos de análise estrutural da fase de margem divergente da bacia haviam sido 

voltados para o estudo da deformação associada à tectônica salífera (Cobbold e 

Szatmari, 1991; Demercian et al., 1993). Neste sentido os resultados do presente projeto 

constituem uma contribuição inédita sobre a Geologia Estrutural e a Tectônica da Bacia 

de Campos. 

Restauração de Seções 

A técnica de restauração ou balanceamento de seções geológicas vem sendo utilizada 

pelo menos desde o início do século passado nos estudos de Geologia Estrutural 

(Chamberlin, 1910). O princípio básico do método é a restauração de todas as unidades 

geológicas de uma seção deformada à sua geometria original, com preservação de 

comprimentos, áreas e volumes, de acordo com a hipótese de um estado plano de 

deformação. Deste modo, se a restauração não for possível, a estrutura expressa na 

seção não é viável, ou porque a interpretação não está correta, ou porque houve 

deformação significativa fora do plano da seção (Dahlstrom, 1969). 

Durante muito tempo a restauração foi utilizada apenas para o estudo da deformação 

compressiva em faixas de cavalgamento, em seções definidas através de mapeamento de 

superfície (Chamberlin, 1910; Dahlstrom, 1969; Hossack, 1979). Com o uso crescente 



 17

do método sísmico, particularmente nas bacias de margem divergente, a restauração de 

seções passou a ser usada também para o estudo da tectônica distensional de 

embasamento e da tectônica salífera (Gibbs, 1983; Schultz-Ela, 1991; Rowan, 1993).  

Uma importante característica do balanceamento de seções é o fato de que se a 

restauração é possível, além da definição de interpretações estruturais viáveis, também 

podem ser feitas inferências e estimativas sobre o processo de deformação (Chamberlin, 

1910; Dahlstrom, 1969; Hossack, 1979; Gibbs, 1983; Nunns, 1991; Schultz-Ela, 1992). 

Particularmente, se as unidades restauradas estiverem ajustadas a um arcabouço 

geocronológico, podem ser computadas, além das medidas absolutas, as taxas temporais 

de deformação. 

No presente projeto foram restauradas cinco seções extraídas de volumes sísmicos no 

domínio proximal-distensional da área deformada por tectônica salífera na Bacia de 

Campos (Artigo II). Todas as seções foram convertidas de tempo para profundidade 

com o mesmo modelo regional de velocidades citado anteriormente e são transversais a 

falhas normais lístricas de grande rejeito, que representam adequadamente o processo de 

tectônica salífera distencional que tem atuado durante a fase de margem divergente da 

Bacia de Campos. O objetivo deste trabalho foi estudar as taxas de deformação 

associadas ao processo de deslizamento gravitacional sobre o descolamento definido 

pelo sal Aptiano, para verificar o possível sincronismo entre a tectônica salífera e as 

reativações de embasamento (Artigo II). 

A restauração de seções foi realizada com o aplicativo RECON desenvolvido pelo 

Grupo TecGraf da PUC-RJ (http://www.tecgraf.puc-rio.br) em convênio com a 

Petrobras. Foi adotado o procedimento padrão para restauração seqüencial de seções em 

zonas de tectônica salífera distencional, com ajuste isostático e descompactação 

(Schultz-Ela, 1991 e 1992; Rowan, 1993). Em todas as seções os falhamentos normais 

foram restaurados através do algoritmo de movimento sobre falha, com cisalhamento 

antitético no bloco baixo. Foi assumido o descolamento totalmente desacoplado no sal 

Aptiano, de modo que as sucessões pré-Aptianas da fase distencional não foram 

restauradas. Esta hipótese foi assumida para garantir o valor lógico de uma eventual 

correlação entre pulsos de tectônica salífera e reativações de embasamento (Artigo II). 

Foram restaurados em cada seção nove horizontes da fase de margem divergente da 

Bacia de Campos, ajustados a marcadores bioestratigráficos com idades entre o Albiano 

e o Recente (Fundo do Mar). Os resultados geometricamente compatíveis em todas as 

etapas da restauração das cinco seções indicaram que, em linhas gerais, a hipótese de 



 18

descolamento constitui uma aproximação razoável para o processo de deformação do 

domínio distencional da tectônica salífera na Bacia de Campos (Artigo II). 



 19

Resultados Obtidos 

A petrografia quantitativa pelo método Gazzi-Dickinson evidenciou a existência de 

duas classes de turbiditos durante a fase de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos, em 

função da maturidade petrográfica. Estas duas classes ficaram bem discriminadas no 

gráfico dos parâmetros médios tamanho de grão versus razão quartzo-feldspato – Q/F 

(Figura 1). Os turbiditos relativamente maturos apresentam granulometria areia fina e 

igual proporção de quartzo e feldspato (Q/F = 1). Os turbiditos imaturos são definidos 

pela granulometria areia média e pela maior proporção de feldspatos do que de quartzo 

(Q/F = 0.75).  

Estas duas classes de turbiditos são caracterizadas também por padrões distintos de 

variação interna dos principais parâmetros petrográficos. Nos sistemas turbidíticos 

relativamente maturos os parâmetros petrográficos apresentam ou uma organização 

interna cíclica (Figuras 9 e 20 do Artigo III), ou uma tendência bem definida (Figura 22 

do Artigo III). Por sua vez os sistemas imaturos, caracterizados por uma ausência de 

organização interna dos parâmetros petrográficos, mostram uma correlação direta entre 

a proporção de quartzo (Q/F) e o tamanho de grão (Figura 12 do Artigo III). 

Outro resultado importante da petrografia quantitativa foi a definição das principais 

tendências dos parâmetros petrográficos médios dos sistemas turbidíticos da fase de 

margem divergente da Bacia de Campos: (1) a progressiva redução no conteúdo de 

micas foi interpretada como resultado do final da exumação da Faixa Orogênica 

Ribeira, do Proterozóico Superior, que aflora na margem da Bacia de Campos (Figura 

30 do Artigo III); (2) o aumento significativo da contribuição de fragmentos vulcânicos 

na transição Cretáceo-Paleógeno foi interpretada como efeito da passagem da margem 

continental sobre a pluma do manto de Trindade (Figuras 26 e 39 do Artigo III); (3) a 

redução da proporção de quartzo (Q/F), e o aumento da granulometria foram 

interpretados como conseqüências do rejuvenescimento do relevo nas margens da bacia, 

associado com reativações tectônicas de embasamento e com o soerguimento dinâmico 

causado pela pluma do manto; (4) o aumento da contribuição de intraclastos foi 

interpretado como efeito conjunto do aumento da energia das correntes de fundo e de 

reconfigurações da fisiografia do talude continental; (5) o aumento da contribuição de 

glauconita implica na existência de uma plataforma continental bem desenvolvida e 

adicionalmente em mudanças nas trajetórias das correntes de fundo através desta 

plataforma; (6) a contribuição de carbonato intrabacial (CI) também está diretamente 

relacionada com a existência de uma plataforma rasa na bacia, neste sentido a 



 20

significativa redução do parâmetro CI durante o Cretáceo Superior evidencia muito bem 

a destruição da plataforma Albiana na Bacia de Campos (Figura 27 do Artigo III). 

 
Figura 1 – Classificação dos turbiditos da fase de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos segundo 
os parâmetros petrográficos médios de maturidade composicional (Q/F – razão quartzo-feldspato) 
e textural (tamanho de grão).  

A análise estrutural de dados sísmicos permitiu a definição de quatro fases principais 

de reativação tectônica do embasamento durante o estágio de margem divergente da 

Bacia de Campos: duas fases no Cretáceo, uma no Paleogeno e uma no Neogeno 

(Tabela 1 do Artigo II e Tabela 3 do Artigo III). A deformação tem estilo estrutural e 

padrão cinemático transcorrentes e está concentrada junto aos altos estruturais do 

embasamento, configurando um contexto geodinâmico de tectônica de blocos, com 

reativação seletiva de estruturas, típicos do ambiente intraplaca (Ziegler et al., 1995; 

Sibson, 1995; Storti et al., 2003). Cabe ressaltar que os principais altos internos do 

embasamento da Bacia de Campos controlam, além da deformação transcorrente 

localizada, feições regionais expressivas, tais como os domínios da tectônica salífera e a 

frente de progradação do Neogeno (Artigo II). 



 21

Através da restauração de seções foi possível definir a natureza episódica da 

tectônica salífera distencional durante a fase de margem divergente da Bacia de Campos 

(Figuras 14 e 15 do Artigo II). Adicionalmente observou-se uma boa correlação entre os 

pulsos da tectônica salífera computados com base na restauração de seções e os eventos 

de reativação do embasamento definidos com base na análise estrutural de atributos 

sísmicos (Artigo II). Esta correlação sugere que, na Bacia de Campos, a tectônica 

salífera tem sido controlada pela tectônica de embasamento. 

A integração dos resultados obtidos permitiu o estabelecimento de uma associação 

entre a evolução geodinâmica, as tendências dos parâmetros petrográficos médios e as 

duas classes de maturidade dos turbiditos da Bacia de Campos (Figura 2). A evolução 

da fase de margem passiva da bacia corresponde a uma interação de três processos 

geodinâmicos (Artigo III): (1) recuo de escarpa em regime tectonicamente passivo; (2) 

reativações tectônicas de embasamento; (3) soerguimento dinâmico e magmatismo 

relacionados com pluma de Trindade.  

Durante os períodos de recuo de escarpa, no Albiano-Cenomaniano e posteriormente 

a partir do Oligoceno, foram depositados sistemas turbidíticos relativamente maturos 

(Figuras 1 e 2). Estes sistemas são caracterizados por proporção mais alta de quartzo 

(Q/F) e granulometria mais fina (Artigo III). O sistema Cenomaniano tem uma 

expressiva contribuição de intraclastos e é mais imaturo que o sistema Albiano, já 

evidenciando algum controle tectônico na sedimentação. O sistema do Mioceno 

apresenta uma baixa proporção de quartzo (Q/F) e uma contribuição significativa de 

glauconita em função do rejuvescimento fisiográfico da costa e da plataforma causado 

pelo evento tectônico do Neogeno.  

Por outro lado, durante as fases de reativação tectônica e de soerguimento dinâmico, 

do Santoniano até o Eoceno, foram depositados sistemas arenosos imaturos nas águas 

profundas da Bacia de Campos (Figuras 1 e 2). Estes sistemas caracterizam-se por baixa 

proporção de quartzo, granulometria mais grossa e contribuição significativa de 

intraclastos (Artigo III). A partir do Paleogeno, com a reconstrução da plataforma 

continental, também se observa um conteúdo maior de glauconita. Os turbiditos do 

Maastrichtiano apresentam uma contribuição vulcânica expressiva em função do intenso 

magmatismo na borda da bacia que estava posicionada exatamente sobre a pluma do 

manto ao final do Cretáceo. 



 22

 
Figura 2 – Correlação entre os processos geodinâmicos atuantes e os valores médios dos parâmetros 
petrográficos dos sistemas arenosos de águas profundas depositados durante a fase de margem 
divergente da Bacia de Campos. Q/F - razão quartzo-feldspato. VRF – fragmentos de rocha 
vulcânica. 

A metodologia integrada utilizada permitiu estabelecer um quadro evolutivo do 

controle da sedimentação em águas profundas durante a fase de margem divergente da 

Bacia de Campos (Tabela 1). Este quadro está associado à proposição de um modelo 

coerente de evolução geodinâmica e paleogeográfica para a margem continental sudeste 

do Brasil. Em linhas gerais a sedimentação de águas profundas na Bacia de Campos 

evidencia uma alternância entre controle eustático e controle geodinâmico. O controle 

eustático, associado com ciclicidade climática de alta freqüência, ocorre durante as fases 

de calma tectônica e recuo de escarpa com deposição de sedimentos maturos no trato de 

mar baixo através de uma plataforma continental bem desenvolvida. Por sua vez, o 

controle geodinâmico é associado com episódios climáticos de precipitação pluvial 

intensa e inundação fluvial capazes de carrear sedimentos aluviais imaturos diretamente 

para águas profundas durante as fases de rejuvenescimento do relevo causado por 

reativação tectônica ou por efeito da pluma do manto (Artigo III). 

 

 



 23

Sistema 
turbidítico 

Análise 
petrograf. 

Padrão 
interno 

Processo 
geodinâmico 

Controle 
estratigráfico 

Relevo da 
margem 

Plataforma 
continental 

Mioceno Relativam.Maturo Tendência 
Reativação 
Tectônica 

Variação do 
Nível do Mar Moderado Ampla 

Oligoceno 
Superior 

Relativam.
Maturo 

Cíclico/ 
Tendência 

Recuo de 
Escarpa 

Variação do 
Nível do Mar Baixo Ampla 

Oligoceno 
Inferior 

Relativam.
Maturo Episódico  

Recuo de 
Escarpa 

Variação do 
Nível do Mar Moderado Estreita 

Eoceno 
Superior Imaturo Episódico 

Reativação 
Tectônica 

Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto Estreita 

Eoceno 
Médio Imaturo Episódico 

Reativação 
Tectônica 

Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto Estreita 

Paleoceno Imaturo Episódico Reativação Tectônica 
Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto Estreita 

Maastricht. Imaturo Episódico Soerguimento Dinâmico 
Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto 

Muito 
Estreita 

Campaniano Imaturo Episódico Soerguimento Dinâmico 
Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto 

Muito 
Estreita 

Santoniano Imaturo Episódico Reativação Tectônica 
Relevo/ 
Regime Pluvial Alto 

Muito 
Estreita 

Cenoman. Relativam.Maturo Episódico 
Recuo de 
Escarpa 

Variação do 
Nível do Mar Moderado Estreita 

Albiano Relativam.Maturo 
Cíclico/ 
Tendência 

Recuo de 
Escarpa 

Variação do 
Nível do Mar Baixo Ampla 

Tabela 1 – Maturidade, padrão petrográfico interno, processos geodinâmicos, controle 
estratigráfico e paleogeografia dos sistemas arenosos de águas profundas da fase de margem 
divergente da Bacia de Campos. 



 24

Referências 

Antunes, R.L., Shimabukuro, S., Oliveira, L.C.V., Rosa, A.L.Z., Costa, S.O., Cunha, 
A.A.S. e Lima, F.H.O. 2004. Origem e evolução estrutural do Sistema de Riftes 
Cenozóicos do Sudeste do Brazil. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras, 12:421-427. 

Azambuja Filho, N.C. 1990. The Oligo-Miocene turbidites and associated facies of 
Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. London. 456 p. Tese (PhD) Imperial College. 

Bahorich, M. e Farmer, S. 1995. 3D Seismic discontinuity for faults and stratigraphic 
features: The coherence cube. The Leading Edge, 14:1053-1058. 

Beaumont, C., Kooi, H. e Willett, S. 2000. Coupled tectonic-surface process models 
with applications to rifted margins and collisional orogens. In: M. Summerfield (ed.), 
Geomorphology and Global Tectonics. New York, John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons, p. 29-55. 

Bruhn, C.H.L. e Walker, R.G. 1995. High-resolution stratigraphy and sedimentary 
evolution of coarse-grained canyon-filling turbidites from the Upper-Cretaceous 
transgressive megasequence, Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. J. Sed. Res., 65:426-442. 

Bruhn, C.H.L. 1993. High-resolution stratigraphy, reservoir geometry, and facies 
characterization of Cretaceous and Tertiary turbidites from Brazilian passive margin 
basins. Hamilton, Canadá. 433 p. Tese (PhD) McMaster University. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., Gomes, J.A.T., Del Luchese, C., e Johann, P.R.S. 2003. Campos Basin: 
reservoir characterization and management – historical overview and future challenges. 
In: OTC-Houston, paper OTC 15220, p. 1-14. 

Caddah, L.F.G., Alves, D.B. e Mizusaki, A.M.P. 1998. Turbidites associated with 
bentonites in the Upper-Cretaceous of the Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. Sed. Geol., 
115:175-184. 

Cartwright, J. e Huuse, M. 2005. 3D seismic technology: the geological ‘Hubble’. Basin 
Res., 17:1-20. 

Catuneanu, O. 2006. Principles of Sequence Stratigraphy. Amsterdam, Elsevier, 375 p. 

Chamberlin, R.T. 1910. The Appalachian folds of Central Pennsylvania. J. Geol., 
18:225-251. 

Chopra, S. e Marfurt, K.J. 2006. Seismic Attribute Mapping of Structure and 
Stratigraphy. Tulsa, Soc. Explor. Geoph., 226 p. (SEG/EAGE Distinguished Instructor 
Series, 9). 

Chopra, S. e Marfurt, K.J. 2007. Curvature attribute applications to 3D surface seismic 
data. The Leading Edge, 26:404-414.  

Cibin, U., Spadafora, E., Zuffa, G.G. e Castellarin, A. 2001. Continental collision 
history from arenites of episutural basins in the Northern Apennines, Italy. GSA Bull., 
113:04-19. 

Cobbold, P.R., e Szatmari, P. 1991. Radial gravitational gliding on divergent margins. 
Tectonophys., 188:249-289. 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E. e Mount, S.V. 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely-rifted 
margin - Campos and Santos basins, SE Brazil. AAPG Bull., 85:1925-1944. 

Critelli, S. 1993. Sandstone detrital modes in the Paleogen Liguride Complex, 
accretionary wedge of the Southern Apennines (Italy). J. Sed. Petrol., 63:464-476. 

Dahlstrom, C.D.A. 1969. Balanced cross sections. Can. J. Earth Sci., 6:743-757.  



 25

Davis, G.H. e Reynolds S.J. 1996. Structural Geology of Rocks and Regions. New 
York, John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons, 776 p. 

Demercian, S., Szatmari, P., e Cobbold, P.R. 1993. Style and pattern of salt diapirs due 
to thin-skinned gravitational gliding, Campos and Santos basins, offshore Brazil. 
Tectonophys., 228:393-433. 

Dickinson, W.R. e Suczec, C.A. 1979. Plate tectonics and sandsdtone compositions. 
AAPG Bull., 63:2164-2182. 

Dickinson, W.R. 1970. Interpreting detrital modes of greywacke and arkose. J. Sed. 
Petrol., 40:695-707. 

Dickinson, W.R. 1985. Interpreting provenance relations from detrital modes of 
sandstones. In: G.G. Zuffa (ed.) Provenance of Arenites. Dordrecht, D. Reidel Publ. 
Co., p. 333-361. (NATO ASI Series, Math. Phys. Sci., 148). 

Dickinson, W.R. 1988. Provenance and sediment dispersal in relation to paleotectonics 
and paleogeography of sedimentary basins. In: K.L. Kleinspehn e C. Paola (eds.) New 
Perspectives in Basin Analysis. New York, Springer-Verlag, p. 03-25. 

Dickinson, W.R., Beard, L.S., Brakenridge, G.R., Erjavec, J.L., Ferguson, R.C., Inman, 
K.F., Kneep, R.A., Lindberg, F.A. e Ryberg, P.T. 1983. Provenance of North American 
Phanerozoic sandstones in relation to tectonic setting. GSA Bull., 94:222-235. 

Fontana, D., Zuffa, G.G. e Garzanti, E. 1989. The interaction of eustacy and tectonism 
from provenance studies of the Eocene Hecho Group turbidite complex (South-Central 
Pyrenees, Spain). Basin Res., 2:223-237. 

Gallagher, K. e Brown, R. 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic 
margins of southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore 
sedimentation. In: N.R. Cameron, R.H. Bate, e V.S. Clure, (eds.) The Oil and Gas 
Habitats of the South Atlantic. London, The Geological Society, p. 41-53. (Geol. Soc. 
London, Spec. Publ., 153). 

Gazzi, P. 1966. Le arenaire del flysch sopracretaceo de´ll Appennino modenese, 
correlazioni con il flysch di Monghidoro. Mineral. et Petrogr. Acta, 12:69-97. 

Gradstein, F.M., Ogg, J.G., Smith, A.G., Bleeker, W. e Lourens, L.J. 2004. A new 
Geologic Time Scale with special reference to Precambrian and Neogene. Episodes, 
27:83-100. 

Gibbs, A.D. 1983. Balanced cross-section construction from seismic sections in areas of 
extensional tectonics. J. Struct. Geol., 5:153-160. 

Gilchrist, A.R. e Summerfield, M.A. 1990. Differential denudation and flexural isostasy 
in the formation of rifted-margin upwarps. Nature, 346:739-742. 

Hossack, J.R. 1979. The use of balaced cross-sections in the calculation of orogenic 
contraction: a review. J. Geol. Soc. London, 136:705-711. 

Ingersoll, R.V., Bullard, T.F., Ford, R.L., Grimm, J.P., Pickle, J.D. e Sares, S.W. 1984. 
The effect of grain size on detrital modes: a test of the Gazzi-Dickinson point-counting 
method. J. Sed. Petrol., 54:103-116. 

Lima, C.C. 1999. Expressions topographiques et structurales de l´etat de compression 
généralisée au sein de la plaque Sud-Américaine. Rennes, France. 353 p. Tese (PhD) 
Université Rennes 1. 



 26

Lima, C.C. 2003. Ongoing compression across South American plate: observations, 
numerical modelling and some implications for petroleum geology. In: M. Ameen (ed.) 
Fracture and In-Situ Stress Characterization of Hydrocarbon Reservoirs. London, The 
Geological Society, p. 87-100. (Geol. Soc. London, Spec. Publ., 209). 

Marchesini, L., Amorosi, A., Cibin, U., Zuffa, G.G., Spadafora, E. e Preti, D. 2000. 
Sand composition and sedimentary evolution of a Late Quaternary depositional 
sequence, Northwestern Adriatic Coast, Italy. J. Sed. Res., 70:829-838. 

Mutti, E., Tinterri, R., Benevelli, G., di Biase, Davide, e Cavanna, G. 2003. Deltaic, 
mixed and turbidite sedimentation of ancient foreland basins. Mar. Petrol. Geol., 
20:733-755. 

Nunns, A.G. 1991. Structural restoration of seismic and geologic sections in extensional 
regimes. AAPG Bul.., 75:278-297. 

Ollier, C.D. 1985. Morphotectonics of continental margins with great escarpments. In: 
M. Morisawa e J.T. Hack (eds.) Tectonic Geomorphology. Boston, Allen &amp;amp; Unwin, p. 
3-25. 

Pereira, M.J. 1994. Seqüências deposicionais de 2a. e 3a. ordens (50 a 2 Ma) e tectono-
estratigrafia no Cretáceo de cinco bacias marginais do Brasil - comparações com outras 
áreas do globo e implicações geodinâmicas. Porto Alegre. 430 p. Tese de Doutorado em 
Geociências, Instituto de Geociências, Curso de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, 
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 

Peres, W.E. 1993. Shelf-fed turbidite system model and its application to the Oligocene 
deposits of the Campos Basin, Brazil. AAPG Bull., 77:81-101. 

Rowan, M.G. 1993. A systematic technique for the sequential restoration of salt 
structures. Tectonophys., 228:331-348. 

Saenz, C.A.T., Hackspacker, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, 
L.F.B., e Paulo, S.R. 2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene tectonic 
reactivation through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambriam areas of southeast 
Brazil - association with the opening of the south Atlantic ocean. J. South Am. Earth 
Sci., 15:765-774. 

Scarton, J.C. 1993. Análise estratigráfica do Terciário Inferior da Bacia de Campos – 
Uma visão moderna (com ênfase na região dos campos petrolíferos de Corvina e 
Malhado). Porto Alegre. 403 p. Tese de Doutorado em Geociências, Instituto de 
Geociências, Curso de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio 
Grande do Sul. 

Schultz-Ela, D.D. 1991. Practical restoration of extensional cross-sections. Geobyte, 
6:14-23. 

Schultz-Ela, D.D. 1992. Restoration of cross-sections to constrain deformation 
processes of extensional terranes. Mar. Pet. Geol., 9:372-388. 

Sibson, R.H. 1995. Selective fault reactivation during basin inversion - potential for 
fluid redistribution through fault-valve action. In: J.G. Buchanan e P.G. Buchanan (eds.) 
Basin Inversion. London, The Geological Society, p. 3-19. (Geol. Soc. London, Spec. 
Publ., 88). 

Souza Cruz, C.E. 1995. Estratigrafia e sedimentação de águas profundas do Neogeno da 
Bacia de Campos, Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil. Porto Alegre. 186 p. Tese de 
Doutorado em Geociências, Instituto de Geociências, Curso de Pós-Graduação em 
Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 



 27

Souza Jr., O.G. 1997. Stratigraphie séquentielle et modélisation probabiliste d´un cône 
sous-marine profond, champ de Namorado. Paris. 231 p. Tese (PhD) Université Paris 
VI. 

Storti, F., Holdsworth, R.E., e Salvini F. 2003. Intraplate strike-slip deformation belts. 
In: F. Storti, R.E. Holdsworth, e F. Salvini (eds.) Intraplate Strike-slip Deformation 
Belts. London, The Geological Society, p. 3-19. (Geol. Soc. London, Spec. Publ., 210) 

Thomaz Filho, A., de Cesaro, P., Mizusaki, A.M.P. e Leão, J.G. 2005. Hot spot volcanic 
tracks and their implications for South American plate motion, Campos Basin (Rio de 
Janeiro state), Brazil. J. South Am. Earth Sci., 18:383-389. 

Vail, P.D., Mitchum Jr., R.M., and Thompson III, S. 1977. Seismic stratigraphy and 
global changes of sea level, Part 4: Global cycles of relative changes of sea level. In: 
C.E. Payton (ed.) Seismic Stratigraphy – Applications to hydrocarbon exploration. 
Tulsa, AAPG, p. 83-97. (AAPG Memoir, 26). 

Valloni, R. e Zuffa, G.G. 1984. Provenance changes for arenaceous formations of the 
Northern Apennines, Italy. GSA Bull., 95:1035-1039. 

Weissel, J.K. e Karner, G.D. 1989. Flexural uplift of rift flancs due to mechanical 
unloading of the lithosphere during extension. J. Geophys. Res., 94:13919-13950. 

Zalán, P.V. e Oliveira, J.A.B. 2005. Origem e evolução estrutural do Sistema de Riftes 
Cenozóicos do Sudeste do Brazil. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras, 13:269-300. 

Ziegler, P.A., Cloetingh, S., e van Wees, J.D. 1995. Dynamics of intra-plate 
compressional deformation: the Alpine foreland and other examples. Tectonophys., 
252:7-59. 

Zuffa, G.G. 1980. Hybrid arenites: their composition and classification. J. Sed. Petrol., 
50:21-29. 

Zuffa, G.G. 1991. On the use of turbidite arenites in provenance studies: critical 
remarks. In A.C. Morton, S.P. Todd e P.D.W. Haughton, (eds.) Developments in 
Sedimentary Provenance Studies. London, The Geological Society, p. 23-29. (Geol. 
Soc. London, Spec. Publ., 57). 

Zuffa, G.G. 1985. Optical analysis of arenites: influence of methodology on 
composition. In: G.G. Zuffa (ed.) Provenance of Arenites. Dordrecht, D. Reidel Publ. 
Co., p. 165-189. (NATO ASI Series, Math. Phys. Sci., 148). 

Zuffa, G.G. 1987. Unravelling hinterland and offshore paleogeography from deep-water 
arenites. In: J.K. Leggett e G.G. Zuffa, (eds.) Marine Clastic Sedimentology. London, 
Graham &amp;amp; Trotman, p. 39-61. 

Zuffa, G.G., Cibin, U. e Di Giulio, A. 1995. Arenite petrography in sequence 
stratigraphy. The J. of Geol., 103:451-459. 

Zuffa, G.G., Normark W.R., Serra, F., e Brunner, C.A. 2000. Turbidite megabeds in an 
ocean rift valley recording jökulhlaups of the Late Pleistocene lakes in the western 
United States. The J. of Geol., 108:253-274. 



 28

Artigos Publicados 



 29

Artigo I. An active divergent margin: petrographic and seismic evidence on the 

geodinamically-controlled deposition of Campos Basin giant turbidite reservoirs, 

southeastern Brazil (Submitted to Geology). 



 30

An active passive margin: petrographic and seismic evidence for the 
geodynamically-controlled deposition of giant sand-rich turbidite reservoirs 

in the Campos Basin, offshore Brazil 
 

Marcos Fettera*, Carlos H. L. Bruhna and Luiz F. De Ros b#
 

aPetrobras E&amp;amp;P, Av. Chile, 65/1702, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 20035-900;  
bUFRGS, Institute of Geosciences, Av. Bento Gonçalves, 9500, Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil, 21501-970;  

e-mail: *fetter@petrobras.com.br; #lfderos@inf.ufrgs.br 
 

Abstract 
Thick turbidite reservoirs composed of feldspathic, coarse-grained and poorly-sorted sandstones were 

deposited during the Late Cretaceous in the Campos Basin, southeastern Brazilian margin. Conversely to 
what would be expected for the evolution of a passive divergent margin under transgression, the 
sandstones became more feldspathic and coarser-grained from the Albian-Cenomanian to the Santonian 
and the Campanian-Maastrichtian. Simultaneously tectonic reactivation of the basement fabric generated 
strike-slip systems bordering structural highs associated with steep rift phase fault zones, causing en-
echelon folding of Albian to Turonian successions. Additionally, it was observed a significant increase in 
the contribution of volcanic rock fragments in the uppermost Cretaceous because of the magmatic activity 
associated with the passage of the Campos Basin border above the Trindade mantle plume. The 
abundance and distribution of such sandy turbidites and the structural features indicate that the evolution 
of Campos Basin deviated substantially from a typical passive margin, being affected by intense and 
increasing tectonism, magmatism and uplift along the coastal chain source terrains during the Late 
Cretaceous. The deposition of geodymamically-controlled, thick, sand-rich turbidites during a major 
transgression indicates that, even at passive margins, the classic eustatic lowstand model of deepwater fan 
deposition is too simplistic and restrictive to be used for the exploration for turbidite reservoirs in frontier 
deepwater areas. An integrated approach is proposed for the understanding of sand-rich deepwater 
systems in divergent margins, based on quantitative petrography, and on the analysis of the geodynamic 
evolution. 

 
Keywords: Deepwater sediment supply, paleogeographic interpretation, passive margin geodynamics, 
sand-rich turbidites, basement uplift 
 

Introduction 

The association of deepwater fans with eustatic sea level lowstands is a classic 

paradigm of sequence stratigraphy (Shanmugan and Moiola, 1982). Nevertheless, some 

deepwater systems are in disagreement with this model (Piper and Normark, 1983; 

Kolla and Perlmutter, 1993; Mutti et al., 1996; Normark et al., 2006). Most of the 

objections to the classic eustatic lowstand model for deepwater fans were based on data 

from active margin systems. For passive margin basins, the association between eustatic 

sea level lowstands and deepwater fans remains accepted as a general rule (Shanmugan 

et al., 1985; Milliman and Syvitski, 1992; Covault et al., 2007). The development of 

deepwater fans is fundamentally related to sediment supply itself, which can be 

controlled by eustatic sea level, but also by the geodynamic evolution of source-terrains 

and basins, by coastal and shelf physiography, by deltaic progradation rates, and by 



 31

climatic cycles (Ricci-Luchi, 1985; Mutti, 1985; Weltje and De Boer, 1993; Burges and 

Hovius, 1998; Piper and Normark, 2001).  

More recently, the critical role of sediment supply in the development of thick, sand-

rich deepwater fans in both ancient and recent active margins has been discussed on the 

basis of high-resolution stratigraphy (Carvajal and Steel, 2006), and piston cores and 

high-resolution seismic data (Covault et al., 2007). In the present work we develop 

further that discussion, taking it both to a wider, geodynamic scale, and to a detailed, 

petrographic view. It is interesting to observe that we reach similar conclusions to that 

of Carvajal and Steel (2006) and Covault et al. (2007) in a very different geologic 

setting, as we have studied turbidite petrography, structural geology, tectonics and 

magmatism in a South Atlantic divergent margin basin, during the Upper Cretaceous 

second-order eustatic sea-level highstand (Haq et al., 1987).  

Geological Setting 

Thick, sand-rich turbidite systems were deposited from the Late Albian to the 

Maastrichtian in the Campos Basin (Fig. 1), the most prolific oil province in Brazil, 

which was originated during the Early-Cretaceous break-up of the Gondwana and 

opening of South Atlantic Ocean. The basin follows the classic rift-drift model for 

passive margin basins (Falvey, 1974; Le Pichon and Sibuet, 1981). The Early-

Cretaceous was characterized by intense magmatic activity, contemporaneous with the 

massive extrusion of tholeiithic lavas in the Paraná Basin (Mizusaki et al., 1992). 

Taphrogenic successions thicker than 3.5 km were deposited on a basal volcanogenic 

sequence from the Valaginian to the Barremian (Fig. 1). During the Aptian, a 

transitional siliciclastic and evaporitic succession was deposited over the breakup 

unconformity, at thermal subsidence conditions. The divergent margin stage began 

during Albian, and is still going on (Chang et al., 1992). Thermal subsidence and 

sediment loading allowed the deposition of an up to 7 km thick transgressive-regressive 

marine succession. The basin is presently bordered by an up to 2 km high coastal ridge 

(Fig. 1). 

During the Late Cretaceous, in agreement with eustatic sea level curves (e.g. Haq et 

al., 1987), a second-order transgressive succession was deposited in the Campos Basin, 

following the drowning of a shallow carbonate ramp formed during the Albian (Fig. 1). 

Upper Cretaceous continental and shallow marine deposits are poorly-preserved in 

Campos Basin. However, thick (up to 300 m) sand-rich systems were deposited 



 32

throughout the transgression, particularly during the Late Albian (Bruhn et al., 1998), 

the Late Cenomanian (Souza Jr., 1997), the Santonian (Bruhn and Walker, 1995), and 

the Campanian-Maastrichtian (Santos et al., 1999). 

Turbidite petrography 

Petrographic analysis was performed on 61 thin sections sampled along 456 m of 

cores from 5 wells, selected in order to represent the above cited turbidite systems: 

Upper Albian (17 samples), Upper Cenomanian (14 samples), Santonian (10 samples), 

and Campanian-Maastrichtian (20 samples). Three hundred points were counted per 

thin section, using the Gazzi-Dickinson point-counting method (Ingersoll et al., 1984; 

Zuffa, 1987; 1991). 

All samples are of feldspathic sandstones, and most plot into the Basement Uplift 

field of the Dickinson QtFL diagram (Dickinson, 1985; Fig. 2). Campanian-

Maastrichtian and Santonian samples are very immature, displaying poorer sorting, 

higher feldspar content, and coarser grain size than Cenomanian and Albian samples 

(Fig. 2). Such increase in compositional immaturity is expressed in the Dickinson QtFL 

plot by an Albian to Maastrichtian trend towards the feldspar pole (Fig. 2, dashed 

arrow). 

Some Campanian-Maastrichtian samples show also a departure towards a litho-

feldspathic trend (Fig. 2, dotted arrow) caused by an increase in the contribution of 

volcanic rock fragments (Fig. 3b). Cenomanian and Albian samples show significant 

contribution of intrabasinal carbonate grains from the contemporaneous shallow 

carbonate ramp (Figs. 3f, 3h). 

The variation in the maturity of the analyzed sandstones is further indicated by 

plotting the ratio of detrital quartz to feldspar content (Q/F) against the modal grain size 

(Fig. 4).  It is clearly perceived that Albian and Cenomanian turbidite systems were 

supplied by finer-grained and more quartzose sands than Santonian and Campanian-

Maastrichtian systems (Fig. 4). This trend is opposite to that expected for a passive 

margin under transgression. 

Structural evolution, tectonics, and magmatism 

The detached structural style in the Campos Basin is characterized by basement 

horsts and grabbens limited by steep normal faults active during the extensional rift 

phase in the Early Cretaceous (Fig. 2; Chang et al., 1992), and by thin-skinned salt 

tectonics with extensional-proximal and compressional-distal domains active during 



 33

divergent margin phase since the Early Albian (Fig. 2; Cobbold and Szatmari, 1991). 

However it is possible to observe departures from this general style, caused by episodic 

reactivation of the basement fabric that occurred during the divergent margin phase 

(Cobbold et al., 2001; Fetter et al., 2002). The tectonic reactivation in the Campos Basin 

during the Late Cretaceous is represented by strike-slip fault systems that caused en-

echelon folding of Albian to Turonian successions (Fig. 5). The deformation had been 

concentrated at basement highs associated with steep shear zone systems previously 

activated during the rift phase. The folds are symmetric with 1 km wavelength, 100 m 

amplitude, and up to 6 km long sinuous fold axes (Fig. 5). 

During the Late Cretaceous Campos Basin was the site of alkaline magmatism with 

compositional affinity to ocean-island basalts (OIB), associated to its dislocation above 

the Trindade mantle plume (Misuzaki et al., 1992; Almeida et al., 1996; Thompson et 

al., 1998; Thomaz Filho et al., 2005).  This coincides with the occurrence of volcanic 

ash layers intercalated with Santonian turbidites (Caddah et al., 1998), and with the 

significant contribution of volcanic rock fragments in the Campanian-Maastrichtian 

turbidites (Figs. 2 and 3).  

Geodynamic and paleogeographic interpretation of the deepwater sand supply  

The evolution of divergent margins is currently described by a few geodynamic 

processes: (i) continuous escarpment retreat of rift shoulders with flexural isostatic 

adjust to the unloading caused by denudation (Ollier, 1985; Gilchrist and Summerfield, 

1990; Kooi and Beaumont, 1994), (ii) episodic intraplate tectonic reactivations related 

to plate border orogenies (Ziegler et al., 1995; Lima, 2003), and (iii) magmatic 

underplating related to episodic mantle plume activity (Brodie and White, 1995); (iv) 

reactivation of secondary (edge-driven) convection cells in the upper mantle (Praeg et 

al., 2005). 

As previously discussed, there is compelling evidence of Late Cretaceous basement 

tectonic reactivation and magmatic activity in the Campos Basin. Besides, the 

compositional and textural immaturity of deepwater sandstones indicates that the 

geodynamic and paleogeographic evolution of the basin border cannot be explained by a 

continuous escarpment retreat during the Late Cretaceous, which would be better 

expressed by a petrographic trend of increasing maturity. The role of tectonism and 

magmatism as major controls on the evolution of the Campos Basin physiography 

during the Late Cretaceous was previously suggested (Pereira, 1994; Bruhn and Walker, 



 34

1995; Caddah et al., 1998). Nevertheless, the aspect that the deposition of the giant 

turbidite reservoirs cannot be related to the classic eustatic lowstand model for 

deepwater fans remains poorly explored and explained. 

The increase in quartz to feldspar ratio and grain size of the turbidites from the 

Albian to the Maastrichtian agrees with the seismic evidence of Upper Cretaceous 

tectonic reactivation represented by strike-slip fault systems and by en-echelon folding. 

The petrographic and seismic evidence are also in agreement with the fission-track 

indication of uplift of the coastal source terrains (Lima, 2003), and with the distribution 

of magmatism in the basin, associated to its dislocation above the Trindade mantle 

plume (Thompson et al., 1998; Thomaz Filho et al., 2005).  The whole set of evidence 

indicates that: (a) Campos Basin and adjacent sectors of the southeastern Brazilian 

margin behaved as a tectonically active, rather than as a passive margin during the Late 

Cretaceous; (b) the deposition of large turbidite reservoirs was controlled by the 

geodynamic evolution, and supplied by the recurrently uplifted basement terrains along 

the border of the Campos Basin, during a major transgressive period; and (c) the classic 

eustatic lowstand model of deepwater fan deposition is too simplistic and restrictive to 

be used for the prediction of turbidite reservoirs in deepwater frontier areas at divergent 

margin settings. 

Conclusions  

The deepwater sand-supply in divergent continental margins is not exclusively 

controlled by eustatic sea level changes and fluvial-deltaic progradation, as stated by the 

current paradigm of sequence-stratigraphy. It was shown that the sand budget in 

deepwater during the evolution of a typical passive margin basin can be constrained by 

episodic tectonism and magmatism, just as in active margin settings. Thick sandy 

turbidites can be deposited along divergent margins even during major eustatic 

transgressive periods, as emphatically illustrated by Campos Basin giant turbidite 

reservoirs. 

The composition and texture of turbidite sandstones can be used to unravel the 

paleogeographic and geodynamic evolution of passive margin systems in the same way 

as they are used in active margins. The combination of petrographic and structural 

analyses allows the understanding of the tectonic versus eustatic controls on the 

turbidite deposition. The proposed approach can positively impact the prediction of 

reservoirs in deepwater frontier areas at divergent margins, as it envisages a broader 



 35

spectrum of physiographic possibilities for the development of thick sand-rich turbidite 

systems. 

Acknowledgements 

This work is part of a doctorate research developed by M. Fetter at Rio Grande do 
Sul Federal University (UFRGS – Porto Alegre, Brazil) sponsored by Petrobras. We 
acknowledge the discussions with Cláudio Lima and Luci Arienti from Petrobras 
Research Center, and Carlos Rodrigues from Petrobras E&amp;amp;P International. We wish to 
thank also Eliane de Freitas Ferreira from Petrobras Documentation Center. 

 

References 

Almeida, F.F.M., Carneiro, C.D.R., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1996. Correlação do 
magmatismo das bacias da margem continental brasileira com o das áreas emersas 
adjacentes. Rev. Bras. Geoc. 26, 125-138. 

Brodie, J. and White, N., 1995. The link between sedimentary basin inversion and 
igneous underplating. In: J.G. Buchanan and P.G. Buchanan (Editors) Basin 
Inversion. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 88, 21-38. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., and Walker, R.G., 1995. High-resolution stratigraphy and sedimentary 
evolution of coarse-grained canyon-filling turbidites from the Upper-Cretaceous 
transgressive megasequence, Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. J. Sed. Res. 65, 426-
442. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., Barroso, A.S., Fetter, M., Sarzenski, D.J., Abreu, C.J., and Silva, 
C.M.A., 1998. High-resolution stratigraphy and reservoir heterogeneities of Upper 
Albian turbidite reservoirs of Albacora field, Campos Basin,  offshore Brazil. 1998 
AAPG Annual Conv., Salt Lake City, Ext. Abstr., AAPG Bull. 82. 

Caddah, L.F.G., Alves, D.B., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1998. Turbidites associated with 
bentonites in the Upper-Cretaceous of the Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. Sed. Geol. 
115, 175-184. 

Carvajal, C.R., and Steel, R.J., 2006. Thick turbidite succesions from supply-dominated 
shelves during sea level highstand. Geology 34, 665-668. 

Chang, H.K., Kowsmann, R.O., Figueiredo, A.M.F., and Bender, A.A., 1992. Tectonics 
and stratigraphy of the East Brazil Rift system: an overview. Tectonophys. 213, 97-
138. 

Cobbold, P.R., and Szatmari, P., 1991. Radial gravitational gliding on passive margins. 
Tectonophys. 188, 249-289. 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E., and Mount, S.V., 2001, Reactivation of an obliquely-
rifted margin - Campos and Santos basins, SE Brazil: AAPG Bull., v. 85, p. 1925-
1944. 

Covault, J.A., Normark, W.R., Romans, B.W., and Graham, S.A., 2007. Highstand fans. 
In the California borderland: The overlooked deep-water depositional systems. 
Geology 35, 783-786. 

Falvey, D.A., 1974. The development of continental margins in plate tectonics theory. 
Australian Petr. Expl. Ass. Journal, 14, 95-106. 

Fetter, M., Lima, C.C., Silva, A.T., Machado, D., Castro, D.D., and Adams, T., 2002. 
Interaction between salt related extension and basement strike-slip reactivation in 
northern Campos Basin, deepwater Brazil. SEG 72nd Ann. Meet., Salt Lake, Exp. 
Abstr., 2413-2416. 



 36

Gilchrist, A.R. and Summerfield, M.A., 1990. Differential denudation and flexural 
isostasy in the formation of rifted-margin upwarps. Nature, 346, 739-742. 

Haq, B.U., Hardenbol, J., and Vail, P.R., 1987. Chronology of fluctuating sea levels 
since the Triassic. Science 235, 1156-1167. 

Ingersoll R.V., Bullard T.F., Ford R.L., Grimm J.P., Pickle J.D., and Sares S.W., 1984. 
The effect of grain size on detrital modes: a test of the Gazzi-Dickinson point-
counting method. J. Sedim. Petrol., 54, 103-116. 

Kolla, V., and Pelmutter, M.A., 1993. Timing of turbidite sedimentation on the 
Mississipi Fan. AAPG Bull. 77, 1129-1141. 

Kooi, H. and Beaumont, C., 1994. Escarpment retreat on high-elevation rifted 
continental margins: Insights derived from a surface-process model that combines 
diffusion, reaction and advection. J. Geophys. Res., 99, 12191-12209. 

Le Pichon, X., and Sibuet, J.C., 1981. Passive margins: A model of formation. J. 
Geophys. Res. 86, 3708-3720. 

Lima, C.C., 2003. Ongoing compression across South American plate: observations, 
numerical modelling and some implications for petroleum geology. In: M. Ameen 
(Editor) Fracture and In-Situ Stress Characterization of Hydrocarbon Reservoirs. 
Geol. Soc. London, Spec. Publ. 209, 87-100. 

Milliman, J.D. and Syvitski, J.P.M., 1992. Geomorphic/tectonic control of sediment 
discharge to the ocean: the importance of small mountainous rivers. J. Geol. 100, 
525-544. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Petrini, R., Bellieni, G., Comin-Chiaramonti, P., Dias, J., De Min, 
A., and Piccirillo, E.M., 1992. Basalt magmatism along the passive continental 
margin of SE Brazil (Campos Basin). Contrib. Min. Petrol. 111, 143-160. 

Mutti, E., 1985. Turbidite systems and their relations to depositional sequences. In G.G. 
Zuffa (Editor) Provenance of Arenites. D. Reidel Publ. Co., NATO ASI Series, 
Math. Phys. Sci. 148, 65-93. 

Mutti, E., Davoli, G., Tinterri, R., and Zavala, C., 1996. The importance of fluvio-
deltaic systems dominated by catastophic flooding in tectonically active basins. 
Mem. Sci. Geol. Padova, 48, 233-291. 

Normark, W.R., 1978. Fan valleys, channels and depositional lobes on modern 
submarine fans: characters for recognition of sandy turbidite enviroments. AAPG 
Bull. 62, 912-931. 

Normark, W.R., Piper, D.J.W., and Sliter, R., 2006. Sea level and tectonic control of 
middle to late Pleistocene turbidite systems in Santa Monica Basin, offshore 
California. Sedimentology 53, 867-897. 

Ollier, C.D., 1985. Morphotectonics of continental margins with great escarpments. In: 
M. Morisawa and J.T. Hack (Editors) Tectonic Geomorphology. Allen &amp;amp; Unwin, 3-
25. 

Pereira, M.J., 1994. Seqüências deposicionais de 2a. e 3a. ordens (50 a 2 Ma) e tectono-
estratigrafia no Cretáceo de cinco bacias marginais do Brasil: Comparações com 
outras áreas do globo e implicações geodinâmicas. PhD Thesis. UFRGS, Porto 
Alegre, Brazil. 

Piper, D.J.W., and Normark, W.R., 1983. Turbidite depositional patterns and flow 
characteristics, Navy submarine fan, California borderland. Sedimentology 30, 681-
691. 

Piper, D.J.W. and Normark, W.R., 2001. Sandy fans – from Amazon to Hueneme and 
beyond. AAPG Bull. 85, 1407-1438. 

Praeg, D., Stoker, M.S., Shannon, P.M., Ceramicola, S., Hjelstuen, B., Laberg, J.S., and 
Mathisen, A., 2005. Episodic Cenozoic tectonism and the development of the NW 
European ‘passive’ continental margin. Mar. Petr. Geol. 22, 1007-1030. 



 37

Ricci-Lucchi, F., 1985. Influence of transport processes and basin geometry on sand 
composition. In G.G. Zuffa (Editor) Provenance of Arenites. D. Reidel Publ. Co., 
NATO ASI Series, Math. Phys. Sci. 148, 19-45. 

Santos, P. R. S., Rangel, H. D., Quintaes, C. M. S. P., and Caixeta, J. M., 1999. 
Turbidite reservoir distribution in Roncador field, Campos Basin, Brazil. 1999 
AAPG International Conference and Exhibition, Birmingham, England. Extended 
Abstracts, 530–531. 

Shanmugan, G., and Moiola, R.J., 1982. Eustatic control of turbidites and winnowed 
turbidites. Geology 10, 231-235. 

Shanmugam, G., Moiola, R.J., and Damuth, J.E., 1985. Eustatic control of submarine 
fan development. In: A.H. Bouma et al. (Editors) Submarine fans and related 
turbidite systems. Springer-Verlag, 23-28. 

Souza Jr., O.G., 1997. Stratigraphie séquentielle et modélisation probabiliste d´un cône 
sous-marine profond, champ de Namorado. PhD Thesis. Université Paris VI, Paris, 
France. 

Thomaz Filho, A., de Cesero, P., Mizusaki, A.M., and Leão, J.G., 2005. Hot spot tracks 
and their implications for South American Plate motion, Campos Basin (Rio de 
Janeiro state), Brazil. J. South Am. Earth Sci. 18, 383-389. 

Thompson, R.N., Gibson, S.A., Mitchell, J.G., Dickin, A.P., Leonardos, O.H., Brod, 
J.A., and Greenwood, J.C., 1998. Migrating Cretaceous-Eocene magmatism in the 
Serra do Mar alkaline province, SE Brazil: melts from the deflected Trindade mantle 
plume. J. Petrol. 39, 1493-1526. 

Weltje, G., and de Boer, P.L., 1993. Astronomically induced paleoclimatic oscillations 
reflected in Pliocene turbidite deposits on Corfu (Greece): implications for the 
interpretation of higher order cyclicity in ancient turbidite systems. Geology 21, 307-
310. 

Ziegler, P.A., Cloetingh, S., and van Wees, J.D., 1995. Dynamics of intra-plate 
compressional deformation: the Alpine foreland and other examples. Tectonophys. 
252, 7-59. 

Zuffa, G.G., 1987. Unravelling hinterland and offshore paleogeography from deep-
water arenites. In J.K. Leggett and G.G. Zuffa (Editors) Marine Clastic 
Sedimentology. Graham &amp;amp; Trotman, 39-61. 

Zuffa, G.G., 1991. On the use of turbidite arenites in provenance studies: critical 
remarks. In A.C. Morton, et al. (Editors). Developments in Sedimentary Provenance 
Studies. Geol. Soc. Spec. Publ., 57, 23-29. 

 
List of Figures 
 
Figure 1 - Structural section through central Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. The inserts 
show basin location and the position of the section in the basin. The grayscale map 
indicates the basement structure with darker gray tones in deeper portions, and the 
digital topographic model of the coastal mountains in white and lighter gray tones. 
 
Figure 2 - QtFL Dickinson ternary diagram for Campos Basin Cretaceous turbidites. 
Most samples plot along the continental block quartz-feldspathic trend. Dashed arrow 
shows an increase in feldspar content from Upper Albian to Maastrichtian turbidites. 
Dotted arrow indicates a departure from quartz-feldspathic trend caused by an increase 
in the contribution of volcanic rock fragments in the Campanian-Maastrichtian 
turbidites. 
 



 38

Figure 3 - Photomicrographs taken with crossed polarizers from thin sections of typical 
Campos Basin turbidites: (a) Very poorly-sorted arkose; coarse, angular microcline 
grains indicate very limited or no reworking by fluvial or shelf systems. (b) Medium-
grained, lithic arkose with volcanic rock fragment. (c) Coarse-grained arkose. (d) 
Medium- to coarse-grained, poorly selected arkose. (e) Fine- to medium-grained, 
poorly-sorted arkose. (f) Fine- to medium-grained arkose with carbonate bioclast. (g) 
Fine-grained, well-sorted arkose. (h) Fine-grained hybrid arenite with carbonate ooids. 
 
Figure 4 - Change in deepwater supply patterns in the Campos Basin from finer-grained 
and more quartzose sand during the Albian and Cenomanian to coarser and more 
feldspathic sand during the Santonian and Campanian-Maastrichtian. 
 
Figure 5 – Basement tectonics during the Late Cretaceous in Campos Basin. (a) Dip 
map of Albian horizon. Observe sinuous pattern of en-echelon fold axes in Albian 
strata. The structure can be interpreted as a strike-slip reactivation of NNW-SSE 
basement fabric. (b) 3D perspective with seismic section and attribute map of Albian 
horizon. Observe that low dip defines very well the fold axes in Albian successions of 
the early divergent margin phase. (c) Depth-converted seismic section (see the regional 
position of section B in the insert). Observe thrust-faulted and folded strata ranging in 
age from Barremian to Turonian. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 39

 
Figure 1 



 40

 

Figure 2 
 



 41

 
Figure 3 

 
  



 42

 
Figure 4 

 
 

  

 

 



 43

 
Figure 5 

 
 

 

 



 44

Artigo II. The role of basement tectonic reactivation on the structural evolution of 

Campos Basin, offshore Brazil: evidence from 3D seismic analysis and section 

restoration (Submitted to Marine and Petroleum Geology). 



 45

The role of basement tectonic reactivation on the structural evolution of 
Campos Basin, offshore Brazil: evidence from 3D seismic analysis and 

section restoration 
 

Marcos Fettera* 
 

aPetrobras E&amp;amp;P, Av. Chile, 65/1702, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, ZIP 20035-900 
*e-mail address: fetter@petrobras.com.br 

 
Abstract 

The structural analysis of regional 3D seismic data based on geometric seismic attributes, associated 
with restored balanced cross-sections show evidence of important basement tectonic reactivations during 
the divergent margin phase of Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. Such tectonic activity is episodic and 
controls salt tectonic pulses. Additionally, major basin features like the Neogene progradation front and 
the salt tectonic domains are constrained by the main basement trends. As the basement involved 
structures observed in Campos Basin can be attributed to general geodynamic processes, it is suggested 
that basement tectonic reactivations can be as relevant as isostatic adjustments and detached tectonics on 
the evolution of divergent margin settings.  

Keywords: Divergent margin tectonics; salt tectonics; section restoration; geometric seismic attributes; 
structural analysis; seismic interpretation. 

Introduction 

The structural analysis of divergent margin basins has been improved during the past 

decades as a function of seismic coverage acquired by oil industry. The extensional 

structural style of the rift-drift divergent margin model was initially observed in 2D 

seismic surveys (Falvey, 1974), and was soon after associated with the geodynamic 

model of mechanical-thermal subsidence caused by lithospheric stretching (McKenzie, 

1978; Le Pichon and Sibuet, 1981). The improvement in the quality of 2D seismic data 

allowed important advances in the field of detachment tectonics related to shale and salt 

(Doust and Omatsola, 1989; Jackson, 1995), and in the technology of section restoration 

of extensional structures (Gibbs, 1983; Rowan and Kligfield, 1989; Nunns, 1991). 

Subsequently there was a continuous progress in detailed structural analysis with local 

3D surveys (Hesthammer and Fossen, 1997; Cartwright and Huuse, 2005), particularly 

with the use of geometric seismic attributes (Chopra and Marfurt, 2006). 

With recent increasing oil prices and lowering acquisition and processing costs many 

divergent margin basins are now also covered with extensive 3D seismic surveys. The 

interpretation of this kind of detailed and extensive dataset has rendered possible a 

substantial advance in the structural analysis of divergent margin basins. In the Campos 

Basin, the most prolific oil province of Brazil, one of the main improvements obtained 

with the structural analysis of recent regional 3D seismic surveys was the definition of 

the structural style produced by the interaction between dominant detachment salt 

tectonics and strike-slip reactivations of the basement fabric (Fetter et al., 2002). In the 



 46

present work it is shown that this interaction can be well defined by the analysis of 

geometric seismic attributes, with the aid of balanced cross-sections based on seismic 

horizons tied to biostratigraphic markers. A remarkable observation is that even being 

apparently subdued, basement tectonics appears to control salt tectonics pulses. If this 

reactive model of salt tectonics triggered by basement tectonic pulses is accepted, as it 

is indicated by evidence from Campos Basin, the current model, purely epeirogenic and 

related to escarpment retreat and mantle plume activity, assumed for the geodynamic 

evolution of the southeastern continental margin of Brazil should be revised. 

Geological Setting 

Campos Basin is located at the South Atlantic continental margin along the 

southeastern coast of Brazil (Fig. 1). The basin formation was initiated during the Late 

Jurassic/Early Cretaceous break-up of the Gondwana supercontinent. Early mechanical 

subsidence was accomplished by episodic events that reactivated main Proterozoic 

basement fabric along regional E-W extension (Ponte and Asmus, 1976; Rabinowitz 

and LaBrecque, 1979; Mohriak and Dewey, 1987; Dias et al., 1990; Chang et al., 1992). 

The lowermost Cretaceous was characterized by intense magmatic activity, 

contemporaneous to the Paraná Basin continental basalt floods (Hawkesworth et al., 

1992; Mizusaki et al., 1992; Wilson, 1992). Up to 3.5 km thick fault-controlled 

taphrogenic successions were deposited from uppermost Valaginian to Barremian with 

volcanogenic contribution at the base. During the Aptian a widespread transitional 

siliciclastic and evaporitic succession was deposited over the break-up unconformity at 

already thermal subsidence conditions. From this, it has been suggested that the 

extensional tectonic phase in the Campos Basin ended by Aptian times (Chang et al., 

1992). The divergent margin stage began at Albian and is still going on. Thermal 

subsidence and sediment loading allowed the deposition of up to 7 km-thick, 

transgressive-regressive marine successions (Fig. 2).   

The overall structural style in Campos Basin is detached (Fig. 1). The main structural 

features in the basement are horsts and grabbens limited by steep normal faults active 

during the rift phase in the Early Cretaceous (Dias et al., 1990; Chang et al., 1992). The 

thin-skinned salt tectonics with extensional-proximal and compressional-distal domains 

have been active during divergent margin phase since the Albian, and is characterized 

by listric fault-rollover systems, turtle-back structures, raft tectonics, downbuilding 

diapirs, salt walls, and compressional salt tongues (Cobbold and Szatmari, 1991; 



 47

Demercian et al., 1993). The salt tectonic domains are controlled by the basement 

structure, with extensional structures to the West, and diapirs, salt walls, and 

compressional structures to the East of the main trend of internal basement highs (Fig. 

1). 

A regional basement map of Campos Basin (Fig. 2) was obtained by the integration 

of regional 3D seismic datasets, with complementary 2D seismic surveys to fill 3D 

acquisition gaps, and with the digital topographic model of the continental margin. This 

map was converted from time to depth with a single basin scale velocity model, which 

is another product of regional seismic data integration. The integrated basement map 

suggests that the Proterozoic fabric, defined in the basin by NE-SW and NNW-SSE 

basement highs, controls the main depocenters of rift phase, as it is commonly observed 

in many rift systems (Michon and Sokoutis, 2005). It is important to observe that the 

basement trends have been controlling also the progradation of the divergent margin 

phase, as it is suggested by the perfect fitting between the internal basement highs and 

the limits of present continental rise (Figs. 1 and 2).  

Structural Analysis of Seismic Data 

Most of the previous work published about the structural geology of Campos Basin 

was based on 2D seismic data, and on magnetic and gravimetric data (Mohriak and 

Dewey, 1987; Dias et al., 1990; Cobbold and Szatmari, 1991; Chang et al., 1992; 

Demercian et al., 1993). With the available data it was indicated the general detached 

structure of the basin. It was also possible to define the main basement highs and 

depocenters of the rift phase, and to get a good picture of the dominant salt tectonic 

structural style of the divergent margin phase. More recently, with mapping of 3D 

seismic surveys, it was suggested that the Campos Basin structure is not completely 

detached (Fetter et al., 2002). It was observed that basement fabric appears to have been 

subjected to episodic strike-slip reactivations during the divergent margin phase, and 

that the coupling between basement reactivations and salt tectonics can be observed at 

structural highs.  

In the following examples it is shown that further evidence of basement strike-slip 

reactivation can be obtained from regional 3D seismic surveys, with the analysis of 

geometric seismic attributes. Geometric attributes are robust images computed from 3D 

seismic data that define the morphology and lateral variability of seismic reflectors, so 

that they are very useful for structural analysis (Chopra and Marfurt, 2006). In the 



 48

present work were used three types of geometric attributes: (i) dip - first derivative of 

structure; (ii) curvature - second derivative of structure, and (iii) semblance - inverse of 

amplitude variance.  

Lower Cretaceous Transpression  

The basement reactivation in the Early Creataceous was observed at the southern 

portion of Campos Basin in a 500 km2 area of folding with rhombohedral shape (Fig. 3). 

The structural trend NE-SW is sub-parallel to the Proterozoic basement fabric. Up to 

1800 m thick taphrogenic and transitional strata, ranging in age from Barremian to 

Aptian were folded by flexural slip under NNW-SSE shortening. The fold pattern, well 

defined by the maximum curvature map, is quite regular and sinuous (Figs 3a and 3b), 

with 1 km wavelength and 100 m amplitude (Fig. 3c). Fold axes are slightly rotated 

counter-clockwise in relation to the main NE-SW structural trend (Fig. 3a). The 

rhombohedral folded area is interpreted as a transpressive structure related to left-lateral 

strike-slip reactivation of steep basement shear zones trending NE-SW (insert of Fig. 

3a). As post-Aptian strata are not deformed, it is possible to place deformation in the 

Early Cretaceous, still under the regional stress field of the rift phase with N-S 

maximum horizontal stress (SHmax). This deformation phase is related to the end of 

extension, but there was not yet a rotation of the regional stress field. It is also 

interesting to observe the alkaline magmatic activity during the Paleogene in southern 

Campos Basin, represented by the volcanic structure in Figures 3b and 3c. 

Lower Cretaceous and Upper Cretaceous Transpression 

The second example of tectonic reactivation during the Cretaceous was observed in a 

90 km2 area faulted and folded in northeastern Campos Basin (Fig. 4). The deformation 

of pre-Aptian successions (up to 1200 m thick) is given by quite complex thrust-faulting 

and folding (Fig. 4c). The strata ranging in age from Albian to Turonian (up to 1000 m 

thick) were subjected to more regular folding with 1km wavelength and 100 m 

amplitude. Fold axes trending NE-SW show interference between Z and S sinuous 

patterns disposed en-echelon (Fig. 4a). The observed geometry is interpreted as a result 

of transpression caused by strike-slip reactivation of NNW-SSE basement fabric with 

right-lateral followed by left-lateral kinematics. The right-lateral Lower Cretaceous 

transpression represents the end of regional E-W extension still related to a regional 

loading with N-S SHmax, as in the example in Figure 3. The left-lateral Upper 

Cretaceous kinematics is related to the rotation of the regional SHmax to E-W caused 

by the ridge-push stress associated with the development of the South Atlantic mid-



 49

oceanic spreading center. The structure was probably amplified by salt movement 

across the section and by a buttress effect of the basement high (Fig. 4c). 

Paleogene Transpression 

Next example is contiguous to the previous one in northeastern Campos Basin, and is 

characterized by a huge fold with 3 km half-wavelength and 300 m amplitude affecting 

up to 2700 m of Upper-Cretaceous to Paleogene strata (Fig. 5). The structure is 

interpreted as a fault-propagation fold (Suppe, 1985), and is clearly episodic with well 

constrained pre-kinematics, sin-kinematics and post-kinematics phases (Fig. 5c). The 

main deformation phase in the Eocene is indicated by onlap pattern and section growth 

(Fig. 5c). The fold was probably related to transpression associated with left-lateral 

reactivation of the NNW-SSE basement fabric during the Paleogene still under E-W 

maximum horizontal stress. It appears that transpression caused the inversion of Lower 

Albian normal faults (Fig. 5c). 

Paleogene Transtension and Salt Tectonics 

In central Campos Basin, 100 km to the south of previous example of transpression, 

the Paleogene reactivation event is characterized by normal faulting and section growth 

(Fig. 6). Most of the faults are restricted to Paleogene and older strata, and are 

concentrated above a basement high (Fig. 6b). The faults are planar and discontinuous, 

and the fault system is characterized by a dispersed distribution of orientations around 

NNE-SSW (Fig. 6a and 6c). The structure is interpreted as a negative flower caused by 

transtension (Woodcock and Schubert, 1994). The observed dispersion of fault 

orientation distribution was probably caused by the strong coupling between stress 

fields related to both basement reactivation and detached gravitational gliding above the 

basement high.  

In a contiguous area just to the west of the flower structure is observed a detached 

listric fault-rollover system related to extensional salt tectonics (Fig.7). There is no 

strong coupling with basement reactivation because the area is sufficiently far from the 

influence of the basement high to the East (Fig. 7c). The fault orientation distribution is 

concentrated around NNW-SSE (Fig. 7d). The fault system was active from Albian to 

Recent time, but the imprint of Paleogene basement reactivation is indicated by extra 

section growth at the antithetic fault of the rollover system (Fig. 7b). Farther south, 

Paleogene magmatism was indicated by the volcanic structure showed above (Fig. 3c). 

Tectonic and magmatic reactivation along the Paleogene southeastern continental 

margin of Brazil was already well documented (Mizusaki and Mohriak, 1992; Chang et 



 50

al., 1992; Scarton, 1993; Almeida et al., 1996; Thompson et al., 1998; Thomaz Filho et 

al., 2005).   

Neogene Transpression 

Just to the west of the rollover system, still in central Campos Basin, the Neogene 

deformation is characterized by folding (Fig. 8). Observe that the anticline trending NE-

SW is positioned exactly above the basement high (Fig. 8b). The structure is interpreted 

as an inversion fold that can be properly defined according to both the clay models of 

Eisenstad and Withjack (1995), and the conceptual model of Sibson (1995). The 

inversion of listric normal faults related to gravitational gliding extension active from 

Cretaceous to Paleogene was probably caused by transpression at the basement high 

during Neogene (Figs. 8c and 8d). The Neogene folding is quite synchronous with the 

extra displacement of Lower Miocene horizon at the main fault of the rollover system 

just to the West (Fig. 7b). As the fold plane lie at high angle to the main rollover fault, 

the folding and the extra extension can be associated with the same reactivation event.  

Overview of structural analysis 

The structural analysis of regional 3D seismic data indicates four periods of 

basement reactivation during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin (Table 1). 

The timing of the Neogene and Paleogene deformation events is very well constrained. 

The kinematical interpretation and the involved strata indicate two phases of 

deformation during the Cretaceous, but the timing of the basement reactivation has a 

certain degree of uncertainty. The deformation is subtle and sparse, with open folds and 

moderate fault inversion observed mainly at regional and local basement highs. The 

reactivation has an overall strike-slip kinematical pattern.  

Section Restoration 

Section restoration is another relevant improvement of structural analysis in 

divergent margin basins because balanced cross-sections can generate quantitative 

chronological information about the kinematics of structural models (Nunns, 1991). In 

present work five sections of the extensional salt tectonic domain in Campos Basin were 

restored (sections HH’, II’, JJ’, KK’ and LL’ in Fig. 2). The objective was to get a 

quantitative approach to the kinematical pattern of salt tectonics during the divergent 

margin phase in order to investigate if the synchronicity between basement and salt 

tectonic pulses suggested in central Campos Basin (Figs. 6, 7 and 8) is a general rule. 



 51

A very uniform restoration methodology was adopted because the objective was to 

get a general pattern. The five sections, defined in 3D seismic datasets, cut 

perpendicular to major detached extensional fault systems, and range from 18 km to 23 

km in length (Figs. 9 to 13). It was assumed that the basement and the rift phase 

successions were not involved in the extensional deformation, and that the Aptian salt 

layer is a regional detachment surface. Eleven horizons were interpreted in each section 

ranging in age from Aptian to Recent (Table 2). The horizons were interpreted within a 

sequence-stratigraphy framework, and were tied to biostratigraphic markers that 

correspond to time intervals between 9 Ma and 19 Ma, except for the 1 Ma interval 

between the Sea Bottom and the Pleistocene at the top of the sections. The sections 

were restored in 9 steps, from Sea Bottom (0 Ma) to Albian (99 Ma). This time span 

corresponds to the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin. So that, the rift phase 

deformation was not restored in present work.  

Restoration was performed with the RECON package (PETROBRAS/TECGRAF-

PUCRJ - Brazil). It was used a standard sequential restoration procedure recommended 

for detached extensional sections, with isostatic adjustment and decompaction (Schultz-

Ela, 1991; Schultz-Ela, 1992; Rowan, 1993). Isostatic adjustment was local, with a fine 

discrete mesh. Decompaction was computed by a power-law porosity function: 

0
cze? ? ?= , 

where ?  is the compacted porosity, 0?  is the initial decompacted porosity, c is the 

porosity decay parameter, and z is depth. The appropriated parameters for decompaction 

of shale, sandstone and carbonate in Campos Basin were defined by fitting the power-

law function to a typical sonic porosity log (Table 3). For all sections, fault restoration 

was computed by an algorithm of movement along fault trace with antithetic shear 

strain in the moving block. 

With the uniform procedure described above it was possible to restore quite well all 

the five sections with the assumption of detached deformation (Figs. 9 to 13). During 

the divergent margin phase in the restored sections from Campos Basin, since the 

Albian (99 Ma), total extension ranges from 2.78 km to 5.07 km, with rates between 28 

m/Ma and 51 m/Ma (Table 4). Section JJ’, positioned far from the basement highs has 

the lower extension rate (Table 4).  

Taking a closer look to the extension measured in the sections since the Pleistocene 

(Table 5), it is possible to interpret the average total extension rate around 40 m/Ma 

(Table 4) as a background because the extensional process can reach up to 570 m/Ma 



 52

episodic peak rates (Section KK’, Fig. 12). If this episodic behavior is extended for the 

divergent margin phase as a whole, and assuming that the deformation has been 

concentrated in time intervals around 1 Ma, it is possible to infer even higher peaks of 

extension rates (Fig. 14). The choice of the 1 Ma interval was based on the rates 

measured for the restored Pleistocene horizon, but is important to observe that the 

episodic nature of extension measured in the restored sections is independent of the time 

interval used to compute the extension rates. It also is important to observe that the 

deformation peaks are quite synchronous in the five restored sections, particularly the 

Paleogene and Neogene peaks. The same episodic and synchronous pattern is indicated 

by the conventional engineering strain curves of the five restored sections (Fig. 15). So 

that, section restoration indicates that the detached extension related to gravitational 

gliding above the Aptian salt in Campos Basin is characterized by an episodic and 

synchronous pattern. Four deformation peaks were observed during the divergent 

margin phase: Neogene, Paleogene, Upper Cretaceous, and Lower Cretaceous (Figs. 14 

and 15). The detached extensional peaks can be well correlated with the basement 

reactivation events interpreted in 3D seismic surveys (Table 1).   

Discussion 

Campos Basin has been interpreted with the classic rift-drift detached model, 

characterized by shallow gravitational gliding above a quiet passive basement (Cobbold 

and Szatmari, 1991; Chang et al., 1992). The high elevations at the basin margin (Figs. 

1 and 2) have been attributed to isostatic models related to rift shoulder rebound, 

escarpment retreat, mantle plume activity, and magmatic underplating (Weissel and 

Karner, 1989; Gallagher et al., 1995; Thompson et al., 1998; Thomaz Filho et al., 2005; 

Zalán and Oliveira, 2005). Conversely, there are already some reported suggestions of 

basement reactivations in the southeastern continental margin of Brazil (Assumpção, 

1998; Gallagher and Brrown, 1999; Lima, 1999; Cobbold et al., 2001; Fetter et al., 

2002; Saenz et al., 2003), as well as in other divergent margins (Stein et al., 1989; 

Withjack et al., 1995; Bezerra and Vita-Finzi, 2000; Cramez and Jackson, 2000; Hudec 

and Jackson, 2004). No matter the proposed model, previous work was all based in 

regional information, magnetic and gravimetric data, apatite fission-track analysis, 

sparse 2D seismic lines and local 3D seismic data. In present work, even considering 

the relevance of salt tectonics and isostatic processes, it is sustained, with three lines of 

evidence depicted from regional 3D seismic surveys and section restoration, that the 



 53

structural style of the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin may fit better a 

geodynamic model that encompass episodic tectonic reactivations. 

The first line of evidence indicating basement reactivation came from Campos Basin 

regional sections and maps (Figs. 1 and 2). Regional data show that the present 

progradation front is controlled by the main structural highs of the basin. If the 

basement has been completely passive it hardly could control the present major 

sedimentation trend, which would be controlled by salt tectonic structures. In fact, the 

salt tectonics major domains are also controlled by the basement structure. Besides, 

there are depocenters beyond the structural highs during the Cretaceous and the 

Paleogene (Fig. 1), suggesting that the stronger sedimentation constraint was 

established in the Neogene. 

The second group of evidence of basement tectonic activity came from the structural 

analysis of 3D seismic surveys. In section AA’ it is observed that up to 1800 m of 

sediments were folded in a 500 km2 area, probably during the Lower Cretaceous, at the 

beginning of the divergent margin phase (Fig. 3c). The kinematical interpretation can be 

questioned, but the folding of Lower Cretaceous taphrogenic and transitional 

successions can not be attributed to salt tectonics. Therefore, it is a concrete evidence of 

basement reactivation. 

In section BB’ it is possible to observe the regular folding of up to 1000 m of early 

divergent margin phase sediments (Fig. 4). The proposed kinematical model can be 

questioned, but the structure can hardly be attributed to salt tectonics, instead it can be 

better interpreted as a result of transpression caused by basement reactivation because 

the fold axes are sinuous and disposed en echelon (Woodcock and Schubert, 1994). The 

section CC’, in the same area, shows a huge fault-propagation fold active during the 

Paleogene (Fig. 5). The episodic character and the timing of the structure are quite 

evident. As section CC’ is contiguous to section BB’ (Figs. 2, 4 and 5), it is reasonable 

to interpret both folding events as results of successive reactivations of the same 

basement structure. It seems unlikely that both structures (sections BB’ and CC’) had 

been generated by one single Paleogene event because affected strata and structural 

style are very different.  

Sections DD’, FF’ and GG’ show a transition from extension during the Paleogene to 

compression during the Neogene above a basement high (Figs. 2, 6 and 8). Both 

structures can hardly be attributed to salt tectonics. They can be better interpreted as a 

result of stress field rotation, with basement transtension followed by transpression. In 



 54

the same area, but sufficiently far from the basement high it is possible to observe a 

listric fault-rollover system in section EE’ (Figs. 2 and 7). The rollover is a typical salt 

tectonic structure that was active since the Albian. Nevertheless it shows the effects of 

both Paleogene and Neogene basement reactivations (Fig. 7). 

The third group of evidence about the relevance of basement tectonics came from 

balanced cross-sections. Section restoration of five major detached structures indicates 

that the extensional process have been episodic and synchronous during the divergent 

margin phase in Campos Basin. Four main extension events were defined: Neogene, 

Paleogene, Upper Cretaceous, and Lower Cretaceous. These events can be well 

correlated with the basement reactivation events interpreted in regional 3D seismic 

datasets (Table 1). This correlation suggests that salt tectonics have been controlled by 

basement tectonics during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin. Additionally, 

the general correlation pattern is reinforced by a few local details:  

(i) The less deformed detached system (Section JJ’) is positioned relatively far 

from the main basement highs (Figs. 2, 11, and 14; Tables 4 and 5).  

(ii) In southern Campos Basin, Section HH’ show no extension during Lower 

Cretaceous, at the same time of the folding event observed in section AA’ 

(Figs. 2, 3, 9, and 14). As both structures trend NE-SW (Figs. 3 and 9), the 

detached extension was inhibited by the compressive event.  

(iii) In central Campos Basin, the Neogene extension rate is relatively low in 

section II’, during the inversion event interpreted in sections FF’ and GG’ 

(Figs. 2, 8, 10, and 14). Again, as both structures trend NE-SW (Figs. 8 and 

10), the detached extension was subdued by the compressive inversion. 

Considering the presented field evidence of basement reactivation in Campos Basin, 

it is important to discuss about an adequate geodynamic model for the evolution of 

divergent margins. According to the Wilson Cycle model, continental rift systems 

eventually evolve to mid-ocean spreading centers at a new plate border, leaving behind 

passive continental margins at intraplate position. The evolution of the basement in 

divergent margin basins is characterized by cooling (Sleep, 1971; Mckenzie, 1978), and 

by a transition from extension to compression (Le Pichon and Sibuet, 1981; Withjack et 

al., 1998). Possible sources of compression are related to ridge push (Bott, 1992), to 

spreading stresses (Stein et al., 1989), to flexural compressive stresses associated with 

sediment loading (Stein et al., 1989), and to the remote effect of active margin processes 

(Ziegler et al., 1995). Additionally, the crust is thin, weak and prone of basement shear 



 55

zones bellow divergent margin basins (Mckenzie, 1978; Le Pichon and Barbier, 1987; 

Lister et al., 1991). So that, the tectonic reactivation in divergent margin basins is not 

only possible, actually it seems to be expected, as it has been suggested in other 

intraplate settings (Storti et al., 2003). 

Conclusions 

Campos Basin was subjected to episodic tectonic reactivations during the divergent 

margin phase, from Albian to Recent time. The structural style indicates a strike-slip 

kinematical pattern for the reactivations. Deformation has been concentrated above 

main structural highs and probably reflects the coupling between divergent margin 

sediments and active basement shear zones. 

The interference between basement tectonics and detached gravitational gliding 

inferred from the interpretation of 3D seismic data was confirmed by quantitative 

information obtained from section restoration of detached extensional structures. The 

detached extension, previously attributed exclusively to salt tectonics, is also episodic 

and synchronous in Campos Basin, and the extensional events can be well correlated 

with basement tectonic pulses interpreted in regional 3D seismic datasets: Neogene, 

Paleogene, Upper Cretaceous, and Lower Cretaceous.  

The basement highs control also major basin features like the present front of 

Neogene progradation and the salt tectonic domains. So that it is possible to conclude 

that basement tectonics has been exerting an important control on the structural and 

stratigraphic evolution of the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin. Additionally, it 

is suggested that basement tectonic reactivations can be as relevant as isostatic 

adjustments and detached tectonics on the evolution of divergent margin settings, 

because the basement involved structures observed in Campos Basin can be attributed 

to general geodynamic processes. 

Acknowledgements 

Present work was developed as part of a doctorate research project at Geosciences 
Graduate Program of Rio Grande do Sul Federal University (UFRGS – Porto Alegre, 
Brazil) sponsored by Petrobras. I acknowledge the supervision by Luiz Fernando De 
Ros, Carlos Bruhn, and Cláudio Lima. I wish to thank also Anderson Moraes, Maria 
José Oliveira, and Mario Neto de Araujo from Petrobras Research Center, Eliane de 
Freitas Ferreira from Petrobras Documentation Center, Marcio Santi and André Derraik 
from Tecgraf/PUCRJ, and François Lafferriére and Mathieu Moriss from Paradigm-
Gocad. A very special thank to my kids Pedro and Isabel, and to my wife Marcella, with 
love. 



 56

References 

Almeida, F.F.M., Carneiro, C.D.R., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1996. Correlação do 
magmatismo das bacias da margem continental brasileira com o das áreas emersas 
adjacentes. Rev. Bras. Geoc., 26, 125-138. 

Assumpção, M., 1998. Seismicity and stresses in the Brazilian divergent margin. Bull. 
Seismol. Soc. Am., 88, 160-169. 

Bezerra, F.H.R. and Vita-Finzi, C., 2000. How active is a divergent margin? 
Paleoseismicity in northeastern Brazil. Geology, 28, 591-594. 

Bott, M.H., 1992. The stress state regime associated with continental break-up, in: B.C. 
Storey, T. Alabaster, and R.J. Pankhurst (Eds.), Magmatism and the Causes of 
Continental Break-up. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ., 68, pp. 125-136. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., and Walker, R.G., 1995. High-resolution stratigraphy and sedimentary 
evolution of coarse-grained canyon-filling turbidites from the Upper-Cretaceous 
transgressive megasequence, Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. J. Sed. Res., 65, 426-
442. 

Caddah, L.F.G., Alves, D.B., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1998. Turbidites associated with 
bentonites in the Upper-Cretaceous of the Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. Sed. Geol., 
115, 175-184. 

Cartwright, J. and Huuse, M., 2005. 3D seismic technology: the geological ‘Hubble’. 
Basin Res., 17, 1-20. 

Chang, H.K., Kowsmann, R.O., Figueiredo, A.M.F., and Bender, A.A., 1992. Tectonics 
and stratigraphy of the East Brazil Rift system: an overview. Tectonophys., 213, 97-
138. 

Chopra, S., and Marfurt, K.J., 2006. Seismic Attribute Mapping of Structure and 
Stratigraphy. SEG/EAGE Distinguished Instructor Series, 9. 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E., and Mount, S.V., 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely-
rifted margin: Campos and Santos basins, SE Brazil. AAPG Bull., 85, 1925-1944. 

Cobbold, P.R., and Szatmari, P., 1991. Radial gravitational gliding on divergent 
margins. Tectonophys., 188, 249-289. 

Cramez, C., and Jackson, M.P.A., 2000. Supperposed deformation straddling the 
continental-oceanic transition in deep-water Angola. Mar. Petr. Geol., 17, 1095-1109. 

Demercian, S., Szatmari, P., and Cobbold, P.R., 1993. Style and pattern of salt diapirs 
due to thin-skinned gravitational gliding, Campos and Santos basins, offshore Brazil. 
Tectonophys., 228, 393-433. 

Dias, J.L., Scarton, J.C., Guardado, L.R., Esteves, F.R., and Carminatti, M., 1990. 
Aspectos da evolução tectono-sedimentar e da ocorrência de hidrocarbonetos na Bacia 
de Campos, in: G.P. Raja-Gabaglia and E.J. Milani (Eds.), Origem e Evolução de 
Bacias Sedimentares. Petrobras, Rio de Janeiro, pp. 333-360. 

Doust, H., and Omatsola, E., 1989. Niger Delta, in: J.D. Edwards and P.A. Santogrossi 
(Eds.),  Divergent Margin Basins. AAPG Memoir, 48, pp. 201-238. 

Eisenstad, G., and Withjack, M.O., 1995. Estimating inversion: results from clay 
models, in: J.G. Buchanan and P.G. Buchanan (Eds.), Basin Inversion. Geol. Soc. 
London Spec. Publ., 88, pp. 119-136. 

Falvey, D.A., 1974. The development of continental margins in plate tectonics theory. 
Australian Petr. Expl. Ass. Journal, 14, 95-106. 

Fetter, M., Lima, C.C., Silva, A.T., Machado, D., Castro, D.D., and Adams, T., 2002. 
Interaction between salt related extension and basement strike-slip reactivation in 
northern Campos Basin, deepwater Brazil. SEG 72nd Ann. Meet., Salt Lake City, Exp. 
Abstr., pp. 2413-2416. 



 57

Gallagher, K., and Brown, R., 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic 
margins of southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore 
sedimentation, in: N.R. Cameron, R.H. Bate, and V.S. Clure (Eds.), The Oil and Gas 
Habitats of the South Atlantic. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ., 153, pp. 41-53. 

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., and Mantovani, M.S.M., 1995. Denudation, fission 
track analysis and the long-term evolution of divergent margin topography: application 
to southeast Brazilian margin. J. South. Am. Earth Sci., 8, 65-77. 

Gibbs, A.D., 1983. Balanced cross-section construction from seismic sections in areas 
of extensional tectonics. J. Struct. Geol., 5, 153-160. 

Hawkesworth, C.J., Gallagher, K., Kelley, S., Mantovani, M., Peate, D.W., Regelous, 
M., and Rogers, N.W., 1992. Paraná magmatism and the opening of the South 
Atlantic, in: B.C. Storey, T. Alabaster, and R.J. Pankhurst (Eds.), Magmatism and the 
Causes of Continental Break-up. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ., 68, pp. 221-240. 

Hesthammer, J. and Fossen, H., 1997. Seismic attribute analysis in structural 
interpretation of the Gulfalks Field, northern North Sea. Petrol. Geosc., 3, 13-26. 

Hudec, M.R. and Jackson, M.P.A., 2004. Regional restoration across the Kwanza Basin, 
Angola: Salt tectonics triggered by repeated uplift of a metastable divergent margin. 
AAPG Bull., 88, 971-990. 

Jackson, M.P.A., 1995. Retrospective salt tectonics, in: M.P.A. Jackson, D. G. Roberts 
and S. Snelson (Eds.), Salt Tectonics: A Global Perspective. AAPG Memoir, 65, pp. 
201-238. 

Le Pichon, X., and Barbier, F., 1987. Divergent margin formation by low-angle faulting 
within the uuper crust. Tectonics, 6, 133-150. 

Le Pichon, X., and Sibuet, J.C., 1981. Divergent margins: A model of formation. J. 
Geophys. Res., 86, 3708-3720. 

Lister, G.S., Etheridge, M.A., and Symonds, P.A., 1991. Detachment models for the 
formation of passive continental margins. Tectonics, 10, 1038-1064. 

Lima, C.C., 1999. Expressions topographiques et structurales de l´etat de compression 
généralisée au sein de la plaque Sud-Américaine. PhD Thesis. Univ. Rennes 1, France. 

McKenzie, D., 1978. Some remarks on the development of sedimentary basins. Earth 
Planet. Sci. Lett., 40, 25-32. 

Michon, L., and Sokoutis, D., 2005. Interaction between structural inheritance and 
extension direction during graben and depocenter formation: an experimental 
approach. Tectonophys., 409, 125-146. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., and Mohriak, W.W., 1992. Sequências vulcano-sedimentares na 
região da plataforma continental de Cabo Frio (RJ). Anais 37o. Congr. Soc. Bras. 
Geol., pp. 52-56. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Petrini, R., Bellieni, G., Comin-Chiaramonti, P., Dias, J., De Min, 
A., and Piccirillo, E.M., 1992. Basalt magmatism along the passive continental margin 
of SE Brazil (Campos Basin). Contrib. Min. Petrol., 111, 143-160. 

Mohriak, W.U., and Dewey, J.F., 1987. Deep seismic reflectors in the Campos Basin, 
offshore Brazil. Geophys. J. R. Astron. Soc., 89, 133-140. 

Nunns, A.G., 1991. Structural restoration of seismic and geologic sections in 
extensional regimes. AAPG Bull., 75, 278-297. 

Ponte, F.C., and Asmus, H.E., 1976. Brazilian marginal basins: Current state of 
knowledge. Anais Acad. Bras. Ciências, 48, 215-239. 

Rabinowitz, P.D., and LaBrecque, J., 1979. The Mesozoic South Atlantic Ocean and 
evolution of its continental margins. J. Geophys. Res., 84, 5973-6002. 

Rowan, M.G., and Kligfield, R., 1989. Cross section restoration and balancing as an aid 
to seismic interpretation in extensional terranes. AAPG Bull., 73, 955-966. 



 58

Rowan, M.G., 1993. A systematic technique for the sequential restoration of salt 
structures. Tectonophys., 228, 331-348. 

Saenz, C.A.T., Hackspacker, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, 
L.F.B., and Paulo, S.R., 2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene 
tectonic reactivation through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambriam areas of 
southeast Brazil: association with the opening of the south Atlantic ocean. J. South. 
Am. Earth Sci., 15, 765-774. 

Scarton, J.C., 1993. Análise estratigráfica do Terciário Inferior da Bacia de Campos – 
Uma visão moderna (com ênfase na região dos campos petrolíferos de Corvina e 
Malhado). PhD Thesis. UFRGS, Porto Alegre, Brazil. 

Schultz-Ela, D.D., 1991. Pratical restoration of extensional cross-sections. Geobyte, 6, 
14-23. 

Schultz-Ela, D.D., 1992. Restoration of cross-sections to constrain deformation 
processes of extensional terranes. Mar. Petrol. Geol., 9, 372-388. 

Sibson, R.H., 1995. Selective fault reactivation during basin inversion: potential for 
fluid redistribution through fault-valve action, in: J.G. Buchanan and P.G. Buchanan 
(Eds.), Basin Inversion. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ., 88, pp. 3-19. 

Sleep, N.H., 1971. Thermal effects of the formation of Atlantic continental margins by 
continental break up. Geophys. J. R. Astron. Soc., 24, 325-350. 

Stein, S., Cloetingh, S., Sleep, N.H., and Wortel, R., 1989. Divergent margin 
earthquakes, stresses, and rheology, in: S. Gregersen and PW Basham (Eds.), 
Earthquakes at North-Atlantic Divergent margins: Neotectonics and Post Glacial 
Rebound. Kluwer Academic, pp. 231-259. 

Storti, F., Holdsworth, R.E., and Salvini F., 2003. Intraplate strike-slip deformation 
belts, in: F. Storti, R.E. Holdsworth, and F. Salvini (Eds.), Intraplate Strike-slip 
Deformation Belts. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ., 210, pp. 1-14. 

Thomaz Filho, A., de Cesaro, P., Mizusaki, A.M.P., and Leão, J.G., 2005. Hot spot 
volcanic tracks and their implications for South American plate motion, Campos Basin 
(Rio de Janeiro state), Brazil. J. South Am. Earth Sci., 18, 383-389. 

Thompson, R.N., Gibson, S.A., Mitchell, J.G., Dickin, A.P., Leonardos, O.H., Brod, 
J.A., and Greenwood, J.C., 1998. Migrating Cretaceous-Eocene magmatism in the 
Serra do Mar alkaline province, SE Brazil: melts from the deflected Trindade mantle 
plume. J. Petrol., 39, 1493-1526. 

Weissel, J.K., and Karner, G.D., 1989. Flexural uplift of rift flancs due to mechanical 
unloading of the lithosphere during extension. J. Geophys. Res., 94, 13919-13950. 

White, R. and McKenzie, D., 1989. Magmatism at rift zones: The generation of 
volcanic continental margins and flood basalts. J. Geophys. Res., 94, 7685-7729. 

Withjack, M.O., and Olsen, P.E., Schlische, R.W., 1995. Tectonic evolution of the 
Fundy rift basin, Canada: Evidence of extension and shortening during divergent 
margin development. Tectonics, 14, 390-405. 

Withjack, M.O., Schlische, R.W., and Olsen, P.E.,1998. Diachronous rifting, drifting, 
and inversion on the divergent margin of central eastern North America: An analogue 
for other divergent margins. AAPG Bull., 82, 817-835. 

Woodcock, N.H., and Schubert, C., 1994. Continental strike-slip tectonics, in: P. 
Hancock (Ed.), Continental Deformation. Oxford Pergamon Press, pp. 251-263. 

Zalán, P.V., and Oliveira, J.A.B., 2005. Origem e evolução estrutural do Sistema de 
Riftes Cenozóicos do Sudeste do Brazil. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras, 13, 269-300. 

Ziegler, P.A., Cloetingh, S., and van Wees, J.D., 1995. Dynamics of intra-plate 
compressional deformation: the Alpine foreland and other examples. Tectonophys., 
252, 7-59. 



 59

List of Tables 

Table 1 - Basement reactivation events indicated by structural analysis of regional 3D 
seismic data during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin. 

Table 2 - Horizons mapped in restored sections. 

Table 3 - Decompaction parameters used for the power-law porosity function in 
Campos Basin. 

Table 4 - Total extension and extension rates measured in restored sections from 
Campos Basin. The total restored time span (around 100 Ma) corresponds to the 
divergent margin phase, from the Albian to Recent time. 

Table 5 - Extension rates measured in the sections restored to the Pleistocene horizon, 
during a time interval around 1 Ma. 

List of Figures 

Figure 1 - Structural section through central Campos Basin at the southeastern coast of 
Brazil. Observe the dominant detached structural style. Observe also that the limit 
between salt tectonic domains, as well as the continental rise, are constrained by a 
basement high (black dashed line indicated by vertical black arrow). The inserts show 
the localization of the basin, and the position of the section in the basin. 

Figure 2 – Campos Basin map showing the basement elevation in grayscale and the 
present sea-bottom in white contours (500 m interval). Observe the structural highs 
constrained by NE-SW and NNW-SSE Proterozoic fabric (black dashed lines). Observe 
also that the basement highs control both the rift phase depocenter (black dotted 
contour) and the present progradation front of the divergent margin phase (white 
contours). The insert shows the position of seismic sections presented in the following 
figures. 

Figure 3 – (a) Seismic attribute map of Barremian horizon and insert with kinematical 
interpretation. (b) 3D perspective with seismic section and attribute map of Barremian 
horizon. (c) Depth-converted seismic section and insert with localization of the area in 
southern Campos Basin (see the regional position of section AA’ in Fig. 2). Observe 
Lower-Cretaceous strata folded at Albian times. Fold axes are indicated by darker high 
maximum curvature trends. The structure is interpreted as a result of transpression 
related to left-lateral strike-slip reactivation of NE-SW basement fabric. SHmax is the 
maximum horizontal stress. 

Figure 4 - (a) Dip map of Albian horizon and insert with kinematic interpretation. 
Observe mixed S and Z sinuous pattern of en-echelon fold axes at Albian strata. The 
structure can be interpreted as a change from right-lateral to left-lateral reactivation of 
NW-SE basement fabric associated with rotation of regional loading stresses. (b) 3D 
perspective with seismic section and attribute map of Albian horizon. Observe that low 
Dip values define very well the fold axes at Albian successions of the early divergent 
margin phase. (c) Depth-converted seismic section and insert with localization of the 
area in northeastern Campos Basin (see the regional position of section BB’ in Fig. 2). 
Observe that pre-Aptian strata of the rift phase are also faulted and folded. Observe 
possible buttress effect of the basement high. SHmax is the maximum horizontal stress. 

 

 



 60

Figure 5 – (a) Structural map of Santonian horizon showing an anticline trending NE-
SW and plunging to NE. (b) 3D perspective of the anticline. (c) Depth-converted 
seismic section showing a huge fold (3 km half-wavelength; around 300 m amplitude); 
insert show section position (see the regional position of section CC’ in Fig. 2). Up to 
2700 m of Upper Cretaceous and Paleogene strata where folded during the Eocene. The 
main deformation phase is indicated by onlap and section growth in the Eocene. The 
structure is interpreted as a fault propagation fold associated with inversion of Albian 
listric normal faults. Inversion was probably caused by transpression along NW-SE 
basement fabric at northeastern Campos Basin. The structure is contiguous to the 
folding area of Figure 4. 

Figure 6 – (a) Semblance map of Maastrichtian horizon showing a NNE-SSW fault 
system. (b) Depth-converted seismic section of the fault system and insert with section 
position (see the regional position of section DD’ in Fig. 2). Observe fault activity and 
section growth during the Paleogene indicated by black bars. (c) Stereonet contour plot 
of the faults mapped in the area showing a quite dispersed distribution (188 fault poles). 
Faulting is interpreted as a negative flower structure associated with transtension caused 
by reactivation of NNE-SSW basement fabric. 

Figure 7 – (a) Semblance map of Lower Miocene horizon showing a NNW-SSE fault 
system. (b) Depth-converted seismic section showing the listric fault-rollover system 
and insert with section position (see the regional position of section EE’ in Fig. 2). 
Observe that the system have been active from Albian to Recent time, but there are 
extra section growth during Paleogene (black bar along antithetic fault), and Neogene 
(black bar along main rollover fault). (c) 3D perspective showing the fault system above 
a basement low. (d) Stereonet contour plot of the faults mapped in the area showing a 
concentrated distribution (106 fault poles). The structure can be interpreted as a listric 
fault-rollover system related to extensional salt tectonics. 

Figure 8 – (a) Structural map of Lower Miocene horizon showing an anticline trending 
NE-SW. (b) 3D perspective of the structure and insert with position of the area in 
central Campos Basin (see the regional position of sections FF’ and GG’ in Fig. 2). (c) 
Depth-converted seismic sections showing an inversion fold. Observe that Paleogene 
depocenters (indicated by black bars) were inverted during Neogene. Fold axial plane is 
vertical and oriented at N40E. Folding was probably caused by transpression related to 
reactivation of basement fabric at structural highs. 

Figure 9 – Restoration steps of Section HH’. Local position of the section is indicated 
in the semblance map. Regional position of the section is indicated in Figure 2.  

Figure 10 - Restoration steps of Section II’. Local position of the section is indicated in 
the semblance map. Regional position of the section is indicated in Figure 2. 

Figure 11 - Restoration steps of Section JJ’. Local position of the section is indicated in 
the semblance map. Regional position of the section is indicated in Figure 2. 

Figure 12 - Restoration steps of Section KK’. Local position of the section is indicated 
in the semblance map. Regional position of the section is indicated in Figure 2. 

Figure 13 - Restoration steps of Section LL’. Local position of the section is indicated 
in the semblance map. Regional position of the section is indicated in Figure 2. 

 

 



 61

Figure 14 – Curves of extension rate vs time for the five sections restored in Campos 
Basin. Extension rates were computed for a constant 1 Ma deformation interval. 
Observe the episodic character of the extensional process defined by the synchronous 
peaks of extension rates. The extension peaks can be well correlated with the basement 
reactivation events interpreted in 3D seismic surveys. Observe also that the choice of a 
larger deformation interval can change the extension rate values, but not the episodic 
nature of the curves. 

Figure 15 - Curves of conventional engineering strain vs time for the five sections 
restored in Campos Basin. 



 62

 
Age Structural Style Kinematics Position in the basin 

Neogene Inversion fold Transpression or 
compression 

Center 

Paleogene Fault-propagation 
fold; negative flower 

Transpression; 
transtension 

Northeastern; Center 

Upper Cretaceous Regular folds with 
sinuous axes 

Transpression Northeastern 

Lower Cretaceous Regular folds with 
sinuous axes 

Transpression South; Northeastern 

Table 1 
 
 

Horizon Age (Ma) 

Sea Bottom 0 

Pleistocene 1 

Middle Miocene 12 

Lower Miocene 21 

Lower Oligocene 30 

Eocene 47 

Maastrichtian 65 

Santonian 84 

Albian 99 

Salt Top 112 

Salt Base 120 

Table 2 
 
 

Lithology 0?  c 

shale 0.60 0.38 

sandstone 0.56 0.27 

carbonate 0.46 0.33 

Table 3 
 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 63

 
 

Section Original Length (km) Total Extension (km) Extension Rate (m/Ma) 
HH’ 18.93 5.07 51 
II’ 14.62 3.38 34 
JJ’ 19.22 2.78 28 
KK’ 18.93 4.07 41 
LL’ 13.87 4.13 42 

Average 17.11 3.89 39 
StdDev - 0.77 7.8 

Table 4 
 

Section Pleistocene Extension Rate (m/Ma) 
HH’ 230 
II’ 270 
JJ’ 50 
KK’ 570 
LL’ 170 

Average 258 
StdDev 172.8 

Table 5 
 



 64

 
Figure 1 

 

 

Figure 2 
 

 



 65

 
Figure 3 

 

 



 66

 
Figure 4 



 67

 
Figure 5 

 



 68

 
Figure 6 

 

 
Figure 7 



 69

 
Figure 8 

 
Figure 9 

 



 70

 
Figure 10 

 

 
Figure 11 

 



 71

 
Figure 12 

 
Figure 13 

 
 



 72

 
Figure 14 

 



 73

 
Figure 15 

 
 
 

 



 74

Artigo III. Petrographic and seismic evidence for the depositional setting of giant 

turbidite reservoirs and the paleogeographic evolution of Campos Basin, offshore 

Brazil (Submitted to Earth and Science Reviews). 



 75

Petrographic and seismic evidence for the depositional setting of giant 
turbidite reservoirs and the paleogeographic evolution of Campos Basin, 

offshore Brazil 
 

Marcos Fettera*, Luiz F. De Ros b#, and Carlos H. L. Bruhna
 

aPetrobras E&amp;amp;P, Av. Chile, 65/1702, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 20035-900;  
bFederal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Institute of Geosciences, Av. Bento Gonçalves, 9500, Porto 

Alegre, RS, Brazil, 21501-970l;  
e-mail adress: *fetter@petrobras.com.br; #lfderos@inf.ufrgs.br 

 
 

 
Abstract 

The paleogeographic evolution of Campos Basin, major oil-province of Brazil, during the deposition 
of its giant turbidite reservoirs was reinterpreted based on the integration of quantitative sandstone 
petrography and structural analysis of regional 3D seismics. The major detrital compositional trends 
indicate that the geodynamic evolution of the continental margin, rather than global eustatic sea level 
fluctuations, has exerted the main control on sand supply to the deepwater systems. This control was 
imposed by the interaction of three geodynamic processes: (i) escarpment retreat of the coastal mountain 
chains, (ii) mantle plume-related dynamic uplift and magmatic activity, and (iii) tectonic reactivation of 
major basement fault-zones. The pattern of distribution of compositional and textural parameters within 
the turbidite sequences indicated that the sand supply to deepwater was also constrained by high-
frequency stratigraphic processes of the climate Milankovitch band. This new approach to the controls on 
the formation of the sand-rich deepwater systems in Campos Basin will be of key importance to generate 
realistic models for the exploration of new turbidite reservoirs and for the optimized development of 
producing turbidite oilfields in such a world-class hydrocarbon province. As it is very simple, the 
proposed integrated methodology can help to unravel the controls on the deposition of deepwater sand-
rich reservoirs in other divergent margin settings.  

   

Keywords: Turbidite reservoirs, quantitative petrography, structural analysis, divergent margins, mantle 
plumes, intraplate tectonics, paleogeography, sequence stratigraphy. 
 

1. Introduction 

Campos Basin (Fig. 1) is by far the most prolific oil province in Brazil. Up to 93% of 

the 8.5 billion bbl proven hydrocarbon reserves in Campos Basin are contained in sand-

rich turbidite reservoirs deposited in deepwater settings during the divergent margin 

phase from the Albian to the Miocene (Bruhn et al., 2003). As many other divergent 

margin settings, the structural and stratigraphic evolution of Campos Basin and the 

adjacent basins along eastern Brazilian continental margin have been studied with 

classic approaches such as lithospheric stretching, escarpment retreat, sequence 

stratigraphy, and detached salt tectonics (Dias et al., 1990; Cobbold and Szatmari, 1991; 

Chang et al., 1992; Peres, 1993; Gallagher et al., 1995; Souza Cruz, 1995). However, 

this conventional conceptual background was not able to define the controls for the 

development of the large deepwater hydrocarbon reservoirs of Campos Basin. This 

question remains open probably because the methods and data used for the analysis of 



 76

Campos Basin are inadequate for unraveling the conditions for the deposition of 

deepwater sand-rich systems in such a complex tectonic-stratigraphic setting. 

Campos Basin turbidites show strong compositional and textural immaturity, 

conversely to the pattern typical of passive divergent margins (Scarton, 1993; Bruhn 

and Walker, 1995; Caddah et al., 1998). Large volumes of gravel and sand were 

deposited in deepwater during the Upper Cretaceous transgression, when the sea-level 

was, in average, 200 m higher than the present (Bruhn and Walker, 1995; Caddah et al., 

1998; Santos et al., 1999). Additionally, the Upper Cretaceous and Paleogene 

stratigraphic record of Campos Basin cannot be correlated with the global 3rd order sea-

level cycles defined according to the conventional sequence stratigraphic concepts 

(Scarton, 1993; Pereira, 1994; Bruhn and Walker, 1995).  

In the present work, an integrated approach combining quantitative petrography and 

structural analysis is proposed to improve the understanding of the deepwater sand-rich 

systems in Campos Basin. Quantitative petrography of deepwater sandstones is a 

powerful source of information on the paleogeographic evolution of source-basin 

systems (Zuffa, 1987; 1991; Zuffa et al., 1995; 2000). The structural analysis of 

regional 3D seismic datasets was focused on the evidence of basement tectonic 

reactivations observed during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin (Cobbold et 

al., 2001; Fetter et al., 2002). 

2. Geological Setting 

The development of Campos Basin was initiated during the Late-Jurassic/Early-

Cretaceous break-up of Gondwana supercontinent, followed by the opening of the 

South Atlantic Ocean. Early mechanical subsidence was accomplished by episodic 

events that reactivated the Proterozoic basement fabric under regional E-W extension 

(Ponte and Asmus, 1976; Rabinowitz and LaBrecque, 1979; Mohriak and Dewey, 1987; 

Dias et al., 1990; Chang et al., 1992; Karner, 2000). Thermal subsidence started during 

the Aptian, which was characterized by evaporitic-rich sedimentation, and has 

proceeded during the oceanic phase from the Albian to the Recent. 

Most of the Campos Basin border corresponds to the Neo-Proterozoic Ribeira Belt 

(Figs. 2 and 3), which is the northernmost expression of a NE-SW trending orogenic 

system mostly controlled by steep strike-slip shear belts (Campos Neto, 2000). From 

Neo-Proterozoic to Middle Cambrian NE-SW oriented shearing accommodated the 

amalgamation of several terrains and crustal shortening along the Ribeira Belt. The 



 77

northern limit of the Ribeira Belt is defined by the Vitória-Colatina shear zone (Chang 

et al., 1992), a major long-lived Proterozoic structure trending NNW-SSE (Fig. 3). 

2.1. Mantle plumes and magmatism 

Intense magmatic activity took place in Campos Basin during the lowermost 

Cretaceous, which may have been associated with the Tristão da Cunha mantle plume. 

This magmatism resulted in the extrusion of basalts, geochemically similar to the 

continental flood basalts of the Paraná Basin magmatic province (Fig. 1) – CFB affinity 

(Hawkesworth et al., 1992; Mizusaki et al., 1992; Wilson, 1992).  

A new pulse of magmatic activity, associated with the Trindade mantle plume (Fig. 

1), is observed in the Upper Cretaceous and the Paleogene. The basic-alkaline rocks 

generated by this magmatism show a compositional correlation with ocean island 

basalts – OIB affinity (Thompson et al., 1998). 

2.2. Stratigraphy 

The stratigraphic record of Campos Basin can be subdivided in two major 2nd-order 

sequences. During the extensional phase (Valaginian to Barremian), an up to 3.5 km 

thick, 2nd-order sequence formed by fault-controlled taphrogenic successions was 

deposited, with volcanogenic contribution at the base (Fig. 2). The second, up to 7 km-

thick, 2nd-order sequence started to accumulate during the Aptian, with a transitional 

siliciclastic, carbonatic, and evaporitic succession, which was followed by an early 

Albian shallow carbonate platform, and a late Albian to Recent marine transgressive to 

regressive succession (Fig. 2).  

Thermal subsidence and sediment loading allowed the deposition of the 

transgressive-regressive marine succession, which contains several turbidite systems 

ranging in age from late Albian to Miocene. The thermal subsidence and the global sea-

level rise allowed a transgressive setting for entire Upper Cretaceous, with the 

maximum transgression achieved in the early Paleocene.  

During the Paleogene, there was intense sea-level variation, with the development of 

many 3rd-order sequences, but the overall stratigraphic pattern is slightly progradational 

(Fig. 2). The mainly regressive sedimentation started in the Neogene, and is presently 

going on; it has been characterized by an expressive progradation that has been building 

a wide continental shelf in the Campos Basin (Figs. 2 and 3). 

 

 



 78

2.3. Structural geology and tectonics 

The overall structural style in Campos Basin is detached (Fig. 2). The main structural 

features in the basement are horsts and grabbens limited by steep normal faults active 

during the Early Cretaceous rift phase (Dias et al., 1990; Chang et al., 1992). The 

basement structural fabric is dominated by two main directions: (i) NE-SW, associated 

with the Ribeira Orogenic Belt, and (ii) NNW-SSE, associated with the Vitória-Colatina 

shear zone (Fig. 3). 

The thin-skinned salt tectonics with extensional-proximal and compressional-distal 

domains have been active during divergent margin phase since the Early Albian, and is 

characterized by listric fault-rollover systems, turtle-back structures, raft tectonics, 

downbuilding diapirs, salt walls, and compressional salt tongues (Cobbold and 

Szatmari, 1991; Demercian et al., 1993). More recently it was observed that the overall 

detached structural style has been disturbed by episodic strike-slip reactivations of the 

basement structures during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin (Cobbold et 

al., 2001; Fetter et al., 2002). 

From a geodynamic point of view it is important to mention the presence of tall 

mountains of the Serra do Mar (Sea Ridge), constituted of uplifted terrains of the 

Ribeira Orogenic Belt, along the basin border (Figs 2 and 3). The persistence of up to 

2700 m high elevations at around 75 km from the rift border 130 Ma after the main 

extensional rift phase suggests that the continental margin adjacent to Campos Basin 

has not been exactly a tectonically passive setting.  

3. Petrography 

In the present work we performed quantitative petrographic analysis of the main 

turbidite systems deposited in Campos Basin during the divergent margin phase. The 

petrographic analysis was developed on 121 thin sections sampled along 990 m of cores 

from 10 wells representative of 11 turbidite systems ranging in age from the Albian to 

the Miocene (Fig. 4; Table 1). The Gazzi-Dickinson point-counting method (Gazzi, 

1966; Dickinson, 1970; Dickinson and Suczec, 1979; Ingersoll et al., 1984; Zuffa, 1985) 

was used, with 300 points counted per thin section. 

Most of the analyzed samples correspond to arkoses (sensu Folk, 1968), and just a 

few samples of the Maastrichtian samples are classified as lithic arkoses (Fig. 5). 

According to the high-hierarchy grain origin classification of Zuffa (1980), most of the 

samples show a siliciclastic, non-carbonate extrabasinal composition (NCE), with 



 79

departures towards a carbonate intrabasinal (CI) contribution during the Albian and the 

Late Eocene, and towards a non-carbonate intrabasinal (NCI) contribution during the 

Santonian and the Paleocene (Fig. 6). The Cenomanian and the Miocene reservoirs 

show a mixed contribution from CI and NCI, and a departure towards the field of hybrid 

arenites (sensu Zuffa, 1980; Fig. 6). 

The extrabasinal composition of most Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems 

corresponds to the uplifted basement block field in the tectonic provenance diagram of 

Dickinson and Suczec (1979) and Dickinson (1985), which is typical of rift basins and 

immature divergent margins (Fig. 7). The Upper Oligocene samples show a consistent 

departure towards the field of transitional continent field, typical of mature divergent 

margins (Fig. 7). The Maastrichtian reservoir shows a not expected compositional trend 

towards the volcanic arc field (Fig. 7). 

The overall results of turbidite petrography, and the integrated analysis of the 

classification diagrams (Figs. 5, 6 and 7), indicate the most significant petrographic 

parameters for the study of the paleogeographic evolution of Campos Basin divergent 

margin phase (Table 2). The main parameters are the quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) and 

the grain size. The content of volcanic rock fragments (VRF), the carbonate intrabasinal 

contribution (CI), and the content of non-carbonate intrabasinal grains (NCI, mainly 

mud intraclasts and glaucony) also seem to be very diagnostic of the type of connection 

between the sediment source areas and the deepwater depositional sites. The content of 

micaceous grains is related to the long term evolution of the continental margin. 

3.1. Albian 

The petrographic analysis of the Albian turbidite reservoir (Well 01; Fig. 4; Tables 1 

and 2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with quartz to feldspar ratio Q/F = 

1.02, and fine sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, with 

moderate to good sorting (Fig. 8). 

There is a well-defined pattern for the internal variation of composition and texture 

(Fig. 9). Although the fine sand grain size is quite constant along the core, the Q/F ratio 

shows high-frequency cyclicity, with a growing upwards trend. 

The contribution of carbonate intrabasinal grains (CI) is very high (Figs. 8b, 8e, 8f, 

and 9), and their distribution follows that of Q/F ratio, with a high-frequency cyclicity 

superimposed to a growing upwards trend (Fig. 9). Calcite cementation is widespread 

(Fig. 8), probably due to the source and nuclei provided by carbonate intraclasts, 

bioclasts and ooids, as well as by the proximity to Albian carbonate successions. The 



 80

content of mica grains is also high (Fig. 8c), and a few foliated, low-grade metamorphic 

rock fragments where observed (Fig. 8a). The contents of volcanic rock fragments, mud 

intraclasts, and glaucony are low. 

3.2. Cenomanian 

The petrography of the Cenomanian turbidite reservoir (Well 02; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 

2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with quartz to feldspar ratio Q/F = 1.00, 

and fine sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, with moderate 

sorting (Fig. 10). Plutonic rock fragments up to cobble-size where observed in poorly-

sorted conglomeratic sandstone samples (Fig. 10e). There is no recognizable cyclic 

pattern of compositional and textural internal variation as for the Albian deepwater 

system. 

The carbonate intrabasinal contribution (Fig. 10a) is smaller than in the Albian 

reservoir, but is still fairly high. Calcite cementation is widespread (Fig. 10), probably 

for the same reasons invoked for the Albian. On the other hand, there is a significant 

increment in the intraclast content (Fig. 10f). The content of micaceous grains is quite 

significant (Fig. 10d). The volcanic contribution and the glaucony content are low. 

 

3.3. Santonian 

The petrographic analysis of the Santonian deepwater sand-rich system (Well 03; 

Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with low quartz to 

feldspar ratio (Q/F = 0.88), and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-

angular to sub-rounded, with poor to moderate sorting (Fig. 11). Up to cobble-size 

feldspar grains where observed in very poorly-sorted conglomeratic sandstone samples 

(Fig. 11e). The internal compositional and textural variation shows a direct correlation 

between the grain size and the quartz to feldspar ratio (Fig. 12). 

The content of mud intraclasts is very high. The intraclasts are compacted into 

pseudo-matrix, and commonly replaced by opaline silica or by calcite (Figs. 11a, 11b, 

and 11c). There is a significant drop in the contents of carbonate intrabasinal grains and 

of micaceous grains relative to the Albian and Cenomanian. The glaucony content and 

the volcanic contribution are still low. 

3.4. Campanian 

The Campanian turbidite reservoir (Well 04; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) corresponds in 

average, to an arkose composition with very low quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F = 0.69), 



 81

and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, with poor 

to moderate sorting (Fig. 13). The internal variation pattern of composition and texture 

is not well-defined. 

The content of mud intraclasts is high (Fig. 13b), as well as the contribution of 

volcanic rock fragments (Figs. 13d and 13e). The content of micaceous grains is very 

significant. The contents of intrabasinal carbonate and glaucony grains are very low. 

3.5. Maastrichtian 

The Maastrichtian turbidite reservoir (Well 05; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) represents to a 

major deepwater sand-rich system in Campos Basin with huge sand volumes in 

northeastern, northern and southern portions of the basin. The petrographic analysis 

indicates, in average, a lithic arkose composition with very low quartz to feldspar ratio 

(Q/F = 0.65), and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-

rounded, with poor sorting (Fig. 14). There is no recognizable trend of internal variation 

of composition and texture. 

The contribution of volcanic rock fragments is very high (Figs. 14a and 14f). The 

intraclast content is lower than in the Santonian and Campanian reservoirs, but is still 

significant, as well as the content of micaceous grains (Figs. 14d and 14e). There is also 

a significant contribution of carbonaceous fragments with features indicative of charcoal 

(burned wood; Figs. 14d and 14e). The carbonate intrabasinal (CI) and the glaucony 

contents remain very low. 

3.6. Paleocene 

The petrographic analysis of the Paleocene deepwater sand-rich system (Well 06; 

Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with low quartz to 

feldspar ratio (Q/F = 0.75), and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-

angular to sub-rounded, with moderate to poor sorting (Fig. 15).There is a good 

correlation between grain size and quartz to feldspar ratio (Fig. 12). 

The amounts of volcanic rock fragments (Figs. 15b, 15c, and 15e) and of intraclasts 

(Figs. 15d and 15f) are very high. The contribution of carbonate intrabasinal grains is 

also important (Figs. 15d and 15e). There is a significant contribution of glaucony 

peloids and intraclasts (Figs. 15d and 15f), and a significant drop in the content of 

micaceous grains. 

 

 



 82

3.7. Middle Eocene 

The Middle Eocene turbidite reservoir (Well 06; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) corresponds 

to thick deepwater sand-rich systems that fill fault controlled troughs in Campos Basin. 

The petrographic analysis indicates, in average, an arkose composition with low quartz 

to feldspar ratio (Q/F = 0.77), and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-

angular to sub-rounded, with moderate to poor sorting (Fig. 16). The internal variation 

of composition and texture shows a fairly good correlation between the grain size and 

the quartz to feldspar ratio (Fig. 12). 

The content of mud intraclasts is very high (Fig. 16f). The glaucony content is lower 

than in the Paleocene, but still significant (Fig. 16a). There is a drop in the contribution 

of volcanic rock fragments, carbonate intrabasinal grains (CI), and micaceous grains. It 

is important to mention the presence of large mud fragments with internal textures 

typical of soils (Fig. 16d) and of laminated microbialite fragments (Fig. 16e) in the 

conglomeratic turbidites. 

3.8. Upper Eocene 

The petrography of the Upper Eocene turbidite reservoir (Well 06; Fig. 4; Tables 1 

and 2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with very low quartz to feldspar 

ratio (Q/F = 0.71), and medium sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-

rounded, with moderate to poor sorting (Fig. 17). As in other analyzed deepwater 

systems, there is a direct correlation between grain size and quartz to feldspar ratio (Fig. 

12). 

The contents of intrabasinal carbonate and glaucony grains are very high (Figs. 17a, 

17c, 17e, and 17f). as the contribution of mud intraclasts. The content of micaceous 

grains is quite significant (Fig. 17b). The contribution of volcanic rock fragments is 

even lower than in the Middle Eocene turbidite system. 

3.9. Lower Oligocene 

The Lower Oligocene turbidite reservoir (Well 07; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) 

corresponds in average, to an arkose composition with low quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F 

= 0.82), and fine sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, with 

moderate sorting (Fig. 18). There is no recognizable pattern of internal variation of 

composition and texture. 

The content of mud intraclasts is very high (Fig. 18c). The contribution of carbonate 

intrabasinal grains is also significant (Figs. 18a and 18e). The contents of volcanic rock 



 83

fragments and glaucony grains are very low. There is also a significant drop in the 

content of micaceous grains. 

3.10. Upper Oligocene 

The Upper Oligocene reservoir (Wells 08 and 09; Fig. 4; Tables 1 and 2) corresponds 

to another major deepwater system with huge sand volumes in central, northeastern, and 

northern Campos Basin. The petrography of this reservoir indicates, in average, an 

arkose composition with high quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F = 1.40), and fine sand grain 

size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, with poor to moderate sorting 

(Fig. 19).  

As in the Abian reservoir, the internal variation of composition and texture is well 

organized (Fig. 20). The fine sand grain size is dominant, with levels of medium size. 

The quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) shows a growing-upwards trend superimposed by a 

high-frequency cyclicity. There is also a well-defined step with higher quartz content in 

the upper-half of the cored section.  

The content of carbonate intrabasinal grains (Figs. 19b and 19d), of mud intraclasts 

(Fig. 19e), and of volcanic rock fragments are significant, but lower than in the 

previously-described turbidite systems. The contents of glaucony and micaceous grains 

are very low. 

3.11. Miocene 

The petrographic analysis of the Miocene turbidite reservoir (Well 10; Fig. 4; Tables 

1 and 2) indicates, in average, an arkose composition with low quartz to feldspar ratio 

(Q/F = 0.91), and fine sand grain size. The sand grains are sub-angular to sub-rounded, 

with moderate to good sorting (Fig. 21). Up to very coarse sand feldspar grains where 

observed in poorly-sorted sandstone samples (Fig. 21f). There is a fining-upwards trend 

from medium sand to very fine sand grain size, as well as a growing-upwards trend of 

the quartz to feldspar ratio (Fig. 22). 

The contents of glaucony (Figs. 21d and 21e) and carbonate intrabasinal grains (Figs. 

21a, 21b, 21c and 21f) are significant. The content of mud intraclasts is low. The 

contribution of volcanic rock fragments and micaceous grains are very low. 

4. Average petrographic trends 

It was observed in the previous section that the Albian, Upper Oligocene, and 

Miocene turbidite systems show well-defined variation of the compositional and 

textural parameters, with internal trends and cyclicity (Figs. 9, 20, and 22). Another 



 84

internal petrographic trend was observed in the Santonian and Paleogene deepwater 

sandstones, which show a fairly good correlation between grain size and quartz to 

feldspar ratio (Fig. 12). Below we compare the average petrographic parameters of the 

analyzed deepwater sand-rich systems, which also show defined trends during the 

divergent margin phase of Campos Basin (Table 2). 

4.1. Quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) and grain size 

The average quartz to feldspar ratio - Q/F (Fig. 23) starts with a value around 1.00 in 

the Albian and the Cenomanian, and drops almost linearly to 0.65 in the Maastrichtian. 

Then the ratio grows a little to 0.75 in the Paleocene and Middle Eocene, and drops 

again to 0.70 during the Upper Eocene. There is an exponential increase in Q/F from the 

average 0.75 during the Paleogene to 1.4 in the Upper Oligocene, and an equally strong 

drop to 0.90 in the Miocene. 

The trend of average grain size (Fig. 24) starts with fine sand during the Albian and 

the Cenomanian and changes to medium sand from Santonian to Upper Eocene. There 

are shifts towards coarse sand limit during the Maastrichtian and during the Upper 

Eocene. The average grain size returns to fine sand from Lower Eocene to Miocene. 

The cross-plot of the parameters grain size and quartz to feldspar ratio allows the 

definition of two types of deepwater sand-rich systems (Fig. 25). The first type is 

represented by the Albian, Cenomanian, Lower Oligocene, Upper Oligocene, and 

Miocene turbidite systems. This group has a relatively higher compositional and 

textural maturity, as it is characterized by a close to 1:1 quartz to feldspar proportion 

(Q/F = 1.00) and by fine sand grain size. The Upper Oligocene reservoir has the highest 

quartz to feldspar ratio of this group (Q/F = 1.40). 

The second type is formed by the Santonian, the Campanian, the Maastrichtian, the 

Paleocene, the Middle Eocene, and the Upper Eocene reservoir systems (Fig. 25). This 

group is more immature compositional and texturally, as characterized by an around to 

3:4 quartz to feldspar proportion (Q/F=0.75) and average medium grain size. In this 

group, the Maastrichtian reservoir has the lowest quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F = 0.65). 

4.2. Volcanic rock fragments 

The background amount of volcanic rock fragments in Campos Basin turbidite 

reservoirs is around 1% (Fig. 26). There is an episodic pulse of volcanic contribution 

that reaches almost 9.00% during the Maastrichtian (Fig 26), up to 3.10% during the 

Campanian, and up to 4.50% during the Paleocene. 



 85

 

 

4.3. Intrabasinal carbonate grains 

The contribution of carbonate intrabasinal grains (CI) to turbidite systems encompass 

mainly bioclasts and ooids generated at shallow-water settings in carbonate platforms 

and ramps. It may also comprise planktonic bioclasts and intraclasts from slope settings. 

Average CI content was initially high in Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems in 

the Albian (up to 13%), and later dropped progressively to zero in the Maastrichtian 

(Fig. 27). There was a strong oscillation of CI content during the Lower Paleogene that 

culminated with a peak around 18% in the Upper Eocene (Fig. 27). Then the average CI 

drops again to around 5% during the Oligocene, and grows again to 7.5% in the 

Miocene (Fig. 27). 

4.4. Mud intraclasts  

The contribution of mud intraclasts to the Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich 

systems was very low in the Albian (around 1%), and reaches a step above 10% from 

the Cenomanian to the Lower Oligocene (Fig. 28). During this period of high intraclast 

content there were a drop to around 8% in the Maastrichtian, and two peaks above 12% 

in the Santonian, and in the Lower Paleogene. The average content of mud intraclasts 

drops to around 5% during the Upper Oligocene and the Miocene (Fig. 28). 

4.5. Glaucony 

The background of glaucony content in Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs is less 

than 0.5% (Fig. 29). There are two peaks of glaucony content around 2% in the 

Paleocene and Miocene, and another peak of almost 5% in the Upper Eocene (Fig. 29). 

4.6. Micaceous grains 

The content of micaceous grains in Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems 

shows a pattern of oscillation between 1% and 3% (Fig. 30). This pattern is 

superimposed to a trend of decreasing micaceous content from 3.5% in the Albian to 

0.5% in the Miocene (dashed arrow in Fig. 30). 

5. Structural analysis of basin deformation through basement faults reactivation 

In convergent margin basins, the quantitative petrographic analysis of deepwater 

sand-rich systems has shown that the physiographic evolution of source-basin systems 

and the compositional-textural character of turbidites are essentially controlled by the 



 86

tectonic activity (Fontana et al., 1989; Cibin et al., 2001). It is also already known that 

divergent margins are subjected to intraplate tectonic activity (Stein et al., 1989; 

Withjack et al., 1995; Bezerra and Vita-Finzi, 2000). Although the geodynamic energy 

involved in the tectonic processes in divergent margins is lower than in convergent 

margins, the amount of tectonic energy needed to change the physiography of the 

source-basin system and consequently the petrography of deepwater sediments is 

largely unknown. In order to investigate the possible effects of tectonic activity on the 

petrography of Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich reservoirs, it was performed a 

detailed analysis of basement structures involved with already documented strike-slip 

reactivations of the Proterozoic fabric (Cobbold et al., 2001; Fetter et al., 2002).  

The structural analysis was developed with seismic attribute maps and sections 

selected from regional 3D seismic datasets recently acquired in Campos Basin (Fig. 31). 

All the seismic data was subjected to pre-stack time migration in order to improve the 

structural imaging. The depth-conversion was done with a basin-scale velocity model 

sufficiently smooth to avoid artifacts caused by local velocity bias. The velocity model 

was calibrated with an evenly distributed set of time-depth tables computed from check-

shot data. 

5.1. Albian-Cenomanian Transpression 

The first example of basement reactivation was observed at the southern portion of 

Campos Basin in a 500 km2 area of folding with rhombohedral shape (Fig. 32). The 

structural trend NE-SW is sub-parallel to Proterozoic basement fabric. Up to 1800 m 

thick taphrogenic and transitional strata, ranging in age from Barremian to Aptian were 

folded by flexural slip under NNW-SSE shortening. The fold pattern well-defined by 

the maximum curvature map is quite regular and sinuous (Figs 32a and 32b), with 1 km 

wavelength and 100 m amplitude (Fig. 32c). Fold axes are slightly rotated counter-

clockwise in relation to the main NE-SW structural trend (Fig. 32a). The rhombohedral 

folded area is interpreted as a transpressive structure related to left-lateral strike-slip 

reactivation of steep basement shear zones trending NE-SW (insert of Fig. 32a). As 

post-Aptian strata are not deformed, it is possible to place deformation at the Albian-

Cenomanian transition, still under the regional stress field of the rift phase with N-S 

maximum horizontal stress (SHmax). This deformation phase is related to the end of 

extension, but there was not yet a rotation of the regional stress field. 

 



 87

5.2. Albian-Cenomanian and Santonian Transpression 

The second example of basement reactivation was observed in a 90 km2 area faulted 

and folded in northeastern Campos Basin (Fig. 33). Deformation of pre-Aptian 

successions (up to 1200 m thick) is given by quite complex thrust-faulting and folding 

(Fig. 33c). Strata ranging in age from Albian to Turonian (up to 1000 m thick) were 

subjected to more regular folding with 1km wavelength and 100 m amplitude. Fold axes 

trending NE-SW show interference between Z and S sinuous patterns disposed en-

echelon (Fig. 33a). Such geometry is interpreted as a result of transpression caused by 

strike-slip reactivation of NNW-SSE basement fabric with right-lateral followed by left-

lateral kinematics. The right-lateral Albian-Cenomanian transpression represents the 

end of regional E-W extension still related to a regional loading with N-S SHmax, as in 

the example in Figure 31. The left-lateral Santonian kinematics is related to the rotation 

of the regional SHmax to E-W caused by the development of the South Atlantic mid-

oceanic spreading center. The structure was probably amplified by salt movement 

across the section and by a buttress effect of the basement high (Fig. 33c). 

Another example of transpression was observed in northwestern Campos Basin (Fig. 

34). In this case, strata ranging in age from Albian to Santonian were subjected to en-

echelon folding. The folds with axes oriented N-S can be interpreted as a result of right-

lateral strike-slip reactivation of the NE-SW basement fabric related to the already 

mentioned rotation of the regional SHmax to E-W. As the Maastrichtian strata are not 

folded is possible to place this deformation phase at the Santonian. 

5.3. Paleogene Transpression and Transtension 

The Paleogene example of basement reactivation (section D, Fig. 35) is contiguous 

to the folding area in section B at northeastern Campos Basin (Fig. 31). A large fold 

with 3 km half-wavelength and 300 m amplitude affects up to 2700 m of Upper-

Cretaceous to Paleogene strata (Fig. 35). The structure is interpreted as a fault 

propagation fold (Suppe, 1985). The deformation is clearly episodic with well-

constrained pre-kinematic, sin-kinematic and post-kinematic phases (Fig. 35c). The 

main deformation phase in the Eocene is indicated by onlap pattern and section growth 

(Fig. 35c). The fold was related to transpression associated with left-lateral reactivation 

of NW-SE basement fabric during the Paleogene under E-W maximum horizontal 

stress. The shortening associated with transpression caused the inversion of Lower 

Albian listric normal faults (Fig. 35c). 



 88

In central Campos Basin, 80 km to the south of previous example of transpression, 

the Paleogene reactivation event is characterized by normal faulting and section growth 

(Fig. 36). Most of the faults are restricted to Paleogene and older strata, and are 

concentrated above a basement high (Fig. 36b). The faults are planar and discontinuous. 

The fault system is characterized by a dispersed distribution of orientations around 

NNE-SSW (Fig. 36a and 36c). The structure is interpreted as a negative flower caused 

by transtension (Woodcock and Schubert, 1994). The observed dispersion of fault 

orientations was probably caused by the coupling between stress fields related to both 

basement reactivation and gravitational gliding above the Aptian salt detachment. 

The tectonic and magmatic reactivation along the southeastern continental margin of 

Brazil during the Paleogene was already well documented (Chang et al., 1992; Scarton, 

1993; Almeida et al., 1996; Thompson et al., 1998; Cobbold et al., 2001; Thomaz Filho 

et al., 2005; Zalán and Oliveira, 2005). The Paleogene magmatic activity was 

particularly intense in southern Campos Basin, where many volcanic structures have 

been described (Mizusaki and Mohriak, 1992; Figs. 32b and 32c). 

5.4. Neogene Transpression 

Just to the north of the previous Paleogene negative flower structure, still in central 

Campos Basin, the Neogene deformation is characterized by folding (Fig. 37). Observe 

that the anticline trending NE-SW is positioned exactly above the basement high (Fig. 

37b). The structure is interpreted as an inversion fold that can be properly defined 

according to both the clay models of Eisenstad and Withjack (1995), and the conceptual 

model of Sibson (1995). The inversion of listric normal faults related to gravitational 

gliding extension active from Cretaceous to Paleogene was caused by transpression at 

the basement high during Neogene (Figs. 37c and 37d). 

Another structure that indicates Neogene transpression was observed in northeastern 

Campos Basin, 50 km to the north of the previous inversion fold (section H, Fig. 31). 

The structure is interpreted as an inverted grabben (Fig. 38). The grabben was formed 

by normal faulting during the Upper Cretaceous. The Cretaceous depocenter was 

inverted in the Neogene with the shortening caused by transpression related to the 

reactivation of the basement fabric (Fig. 38c). 

5.5. Overview of the structural analysis 

The structural analysis of regional 3D seismic data indicates four periods of 

basement reactivation during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin (Table 3). 

The timing of the Neogene and Paleogene deformation events is very well-constrained. 



 89

The kinematic interpretation and the involved strata indicate two phases of deformation 

during the Cretaceous, but the timing of the basement reactivation has a certain degree 

of uncertainty.  

Except by the Paleogene tectonic event, which has a more widespread manifestation 

in Campos Basin, and along the southeastern coast of Brazil (Chang et al., 1992; Zalán 

and Oliveira, 2005), the tectonic reactivation is selective and sparse, with open folds and 

moderate fault inversion observed mainly above basement structural highs. The 

structural style of the tectonic reactivation indicates an overall strike-slip kinematic 

pattern. This overall picture of the reactivation of basement structures in Campos Basin 

interpreted in the present work agrees with previously published observations (Scarton, 

1993; Pereira, 1994; Bruhn and Walker, 1995; Lima, 1999; Cobbold et al., 2001; Fetter 

et al., 2002; Zalán and Oliveira, 2005), as well as with the events indicated by apatite 

fission track analysis along the southeastern continental margin of Brazil (Gallagher and 

Brown, 1999; Saenz et al., 2003). Nevertheless, the structural analysis developed in the 

present study allowed the definition of an accurate timetable for the tectonic events 

involving basement faults reactivation, with the indication of two deformation phases 

during the Cretaceous, and of a further tectonic event in the Neogene (Table 3).    

6. Major controls on deepwater sedimentation within Campos Basin 

The quantitative petrographic analysis indicates that the sandstones deposited in 

Campos Basin deepwater during the divergent margin phase do not follow the 

increasing maturity trend expected for tectonically passive margin basins. Actually, 

most of the petrographic parameters of Campos Basin turbidites show a quite complex 

evolution pattern (Figs. 23 to 30). Particularly, the variation of the parameters grain size 

and quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) indicates an alternated deposition of two main types of 

deepwater sandstones in Campos Basin (Fig. 25): (i) relatively mature turbidites with 

fine sand grain size and Q/F = 1.00, deposited in the Albian, Cenomanian, Oligocene 

and Miocene, internally characterized by well developed trend patterns (Figs. 9, 20, and 

22); (ii) immature turbidites with medium sand grain size and Q/F = 0.75, deposited in 

the Santonian, Campanian, Maastrichtian, Paleocene and Eocene. 

Therefore it is clear that the evolution of the physiography of source terrains and 

basin, and the formation of the deepwater sand-rich systems during the thermal 

subsidence phase in Campos Basin was not exclusively controlled by the processes 

conventionally postulated for the evolution of divergent continental margins, namely the 



 90

eustatic sea-level changes (Posamentier et al., 1988; Galloway, 1989), and the passive 

escarpment retreat associated with the flexural unloading caused by the erosion of the 

rift-shoulder relief (Ollier, 1985; Gilchrist and Summerfield, 1990). This indicates that 

an integrated model of geodynamic and stratigraphic evolution must be developed in 

order to understand the controls on the deepwater sedimentation in Campos Basin. This 

model must encompass all the petrographic trends previously described. 

6.1. The exhumation of the Ribeira Orogenic Belt 

The long-term evolution of the source-areas of Campos Basin can be envisaged by 

the trend of decrease, of about one order of magnitude, in the contribution of micaceous 

grains to the deepwater sandstones (dashed arrow in Fig. 30). This trend represents the 

increasing exhumation of the Ribeira Belt. The average mica content has progressively 

dropped as the mica-bearing medium grade metamorphic rocks of the orogenic belt 

were removed by uplift and erosion, exposing the mica-poor rocks of high metamorphic 

grade. 

This long-term signal is related to the escarpment retreat geodynamic model, defined 

by progressive erosion, unloading and flexural uplift along the basin margin. It is 

important to observe that most of the other petrographic parameters would have 

followed the same simple long-term trend if other geodynamic processes have not been 

active during Campos Basin divergent margin phase. 

6.2. The mantle plume control 

The Campos Basin was positioned along the trajectory of the rotational drift of the 

South-American plate above the Trindade mantle plume (Fig. 39). The influence of the 

passage of the basin above the plume on the texture and composition of the deepwater 

systems is indicated by the nearly symmetric distribution of average grain size, Q/F and 

volcanic rock fragments of the turbidites around the Maastrichtian, when the plume was 

below the Campos Basin border (Figs. 25 and 39). 

The major control of the dynamic uplift caused by the thermal anomaly of the plume 

on the compositional and textural character of the deepwater sandstones is indicated by 

the dominant medium average grain size and low quartz to feldspar ratio from the 

Santonian to the Eocene (Figs. 23, 24 and 39). However it is important to observe that 

the high content of volcanic rock fragments (VRF), which represents the magmatic 

activity of the plume at the Campos Basin border, is manifested in a shorter time period, 

from the Campanian to the Paleocene (Figs. 26 and 39). 



 91

6.3. The episodic tectonic control 

Detailed structural analysis of regional seismic 3D datasets indicated four major 

deformation events of tectonic reactivation of Campos Basin basement fabric. 

Quantitative petrographic analysis of major sand-rich turbidite systems from Albian to 

Miocene confirmed that these tectonic events have indeed changed the physiographic 

character of the source-basin system during the divergent margin phase in Campos 

Basin (Table 3; Fig. 40).  

The beginning of the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin during the Albian was 

characterized by the construction of a wide carbonate ramp, associated with tectonic 

stability and escarpment retreat of the rift-shoulder relief. Therefore, the Albian 

turbidite system is relatively mature with higher quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F), and fine 

sand grain size (Figs. 23, 24, 25, and 40). With poorly developed slopes of essentially 

carbonatic composition, the contribution of glaucony and mud intraclasts to the 

deepwater systems were low (Figs. 28, 29, and 40).  

The first evidence of paleogeographic reorganization, related to the tectonic 

reactivation at the Albian-Cenomanian transition (Fig. 40), can be recognized by 

slightly lower Q/F ratio and larger average grain size (close to the limit of medium 

sand) of the Cenomanian deepwater sandstones (Figs. 23, 24, 25, and 40). Additionally, 

a significant increase in mud intraclasts content is observed (Figs.28 and 40). These 

petrographic differences are well illustrated by the photomicrographs of the two 

deepwater systems (Figs. 8 and 10). This increasing immaturity is interpreted in terms 

of a rejuvenation of the coastal relief, associated with partial degradation of the shelf, 

and with changes in the sedimentary pathways from the coast to deepwater. 

A more expressive paleogeographic change was caused by the Santonian tectonic 

event. Comparing with the previous systems, the Santonian deepwater sandstones are 

characterized by a significant decrease in the Q/F ratio, and a considerable increase in 

the grain size and in the content of mud intraclasts (Figs. 23, 24, 25, 28, and 40). The 

photomicrographs in Figure 11 illustrate the textural and compositional immaturity of 

the Santonian turbidites. Again the increasing immaturity is interpreted as consequence 

of the tectonic rejuvenation of the source-basin system. The glaucony contribution 

remained very low because of the further degradation of the shelf (Figs. 29 and 40).  

 Despite the relative tectonic quiescence from the Campanian to the Maastrichtian, 

the Trindade mantle plume was sufficiently close to Campos Basin to cause volcanic 

activity and dynamic uplift along the coast. Consequently, the deepwater systems 



 92

deposited during this period were also very immature, and particularly rich in volcanic 

rock fragments (Figs. 13, 14, 23, 24, 25, 26, and 40). There is a progressive decrease in 

the average content of mud intraclasts from Santonian to Maastrichtian (Figs. 28 and 

40). This drop in the average content of intraclasts may be interpreted as a result of 

stable sedimentary supply routes to deep water through canyons deeply incised by 

recurrent currents in the slope that were kept constant because of the tectonic 

quiescence during this period. Due to the absence of a stable shelf, there is virtually no 

glaucony contribution to deepwater (Figs. 29 and 40). The increase in the contribution 

of volcanic fragments and the decrease in the content of mud intraclasts in Campos 

Basin turbidites during Upper Cretaceous illustrate well two different types of 

geodynamic impact along the continental margin (Fig. 40): (i) tectonic reactivation - 

coastal elevation plus reorganization of the source-basin system in the Santonian, and 

(ii) effects of the mantle plume - coastal elevation by dynamic uplift and volcanism 

without major physiographic reorganization in the Maastrichtian. 

Campos Basin paleogeography was substantially changed again during the Paleocene 

owing to the beginning of the Paleogene basement reactivation. Additionally, with the 

end of the 2nd order transgression, a new shelf was built. The tectonic activity caused a 

rejuvenation of the coastal relief and a further reorganization of the source-basin 

system, still under the influence of the Trindade mantle plume. Consequently, the 

Paleocene deepwater sandstones remained very immature, with a significant 

contribution of volcanic rock fragments (Figs. 15, 23, 24, 25, 26, and 40). A significant 

increase in the mud intraclasts content was observed (Figs. 28 and 40), probably due to 

the redefinition of the bottom current pathways caused by the physiographic 

reorganization. This interpretation is further supported by the increase in the glaucony 

content (Figs. 29 and 40). 

 During Eocene the tectonic activity strengthened, and Campos Basin depocenters 

moved above Trindade mantle plume. Therefore, Eocene turbidite systems are very 

immature, with high mud intraclasts and glaucony contents (Fig. 40), as a consequence 

of coastal relief rejuvenation, and of the ongoing physiographic changes into the basin. 

On the other hand, a considerable drop in the contribution of volcanic rock fragments is 

observed, because the volcanic activity ceased along the coastal areas, being transferred 

to within the basin (Figs. 32b, 32c, and 40). 

During Lower Oligocene, with the end of the Paleogene tectonic reactivation and 

without the effects of Trindade plume, then already relatively far from Campos Basin, a 



 93

significant increase in the maturity of the deepwater sandstones is observed (Figs. 25 

and 40). The higher Q/F ratio and the fine sand grain size indicate a lowering of the 

relief and a widening of the shelf. The small contribution of glaucony (Fig. 40) indicates 

that the physiography and the sediment pathways along the shelf had been keeping 

stable. On the other hand, the relatively high content of mud intraclasts (Fig. 40) 

suggests a situation of active physiographic changes on the slope, which were probably 

related to the ongoing progradation and to salt tectonic activity.  

As the mantle plume was very far, the Upper Oligocene tectonic quiescence allowed 

erosion and escarpment retreat along Campos Basin coast. In turn, the progradation 

related to the high sediment supply built a very wide shelf. This set of conditions caused 

a further increase in the maturity of the deepwater sandstones (Figs. 25 and 40). The 

grain size remained fine, and there was an expressive growth in the Q/F ratio (Fig. 40). 

The physiographic stability of the source-basin system is confirmed by the low 

contribution of glaucony and mud intraclasts (Fig. 40). As a consequence of the 

constant sediments pathways through the shelf and the slope to the deepwater settings, 

only minor contents of glaucony and intraclasts were taken by bottom currents to the 

Upper Oligocene deepwater sand-rich systems. 

With the onset of the Neogene basement reactivation in the Miocene, the associated 

physiographic reorganization caused a relative decrease in the maturity of the Miocene 

turbidites. The average grain size remained fine, but there was a significant drop in Q/F 

ratio (Figs. 23, 24, and 40). There was an increase in the content of glaucony (Figs. 29 

and 40), indicating shifting bottom currents trajectories along the shelf as a consequence 

of physiographic rejuvenation. On the other hand the content of mud intraclasts was 

relatively low (Figs. 28 and 40), suggesting that the sediment pathways in the shelf-edge 

and the slope were almost the same of the Upper Oligocene. 

6.4. The downstream and the upstream control on the stratigraphic record 

Sequence stratigraphy is undoubtedly the most powerful concept for the study of the 

patterns of sedimentary basins filling, particularly aiming at the prediction of reservoirs 

distribution. Nevertheless, the approach of sequence stratigraphy is strictly valid only 

for a well-defined set of boundary conditions.  

The ideal set of conditions for the application of the classic sequence stratigraphy 

model, recently defined as the downstream control on the stratigraphic record by 

Catuneanu (2006), is related to wide shelves in stable tectonic settings, without 

significant changes in the topographic gradients and in the sediment supply. Under these 



 94

boundary conditions, relative sea-level changes will fully control the stratigraphic 

record, and systems tracts delimited by key stratigraphic surfaces will function as a 

predictive model for the pattern of basin filling. 

Conversely, the boundary conditions may involve narrow shelves in active tectonic 

settings with pronounced changes in topographic gradients and sediment supply caused 

by tectonic pulses, ice melting, anomalous rainfall cycles, and mantle plume effects. 

Under these conditions, an upstream control on the stratigraphic record is established, 

and relative sea-level changes will not work so well as a predictive tool for basin filling 

pattern (Catuneanu, 2006). 

Following this conceptual reasoning, it can be stated that the development of 

significant deepwater sand-rich systems is constrained by the type of stratigraphic 

control. Under downstream control, sand supply to deepwater is enhanced in the late 

stage of relative sea-level fall, and large turbidite systems may be deposited in the distal 

domain of the late forced-regression systems tract (Catuneanu, 2006). On the other 

hand, under upstream stratigraphic control, sand supply to deepwater can be enhanced 

by tectonic uplift or by river flooding caused by either ice melting, or episodic rainfall 

peaks. In this case important deepwater sand-rich systems may develop in any stage of 

relative sea-level, depending on the paleogeography of the source-basin system (Kolla 

and Perlmutter, 1993; Burgess and Hovious, 1998; Zuffa et al., 2000; Carvajal and 

Steel, 2006). Therefore, the definition of the balance between downstream and upstream 

stratigraphic control is a fundamental requisite for reservoir prediction in basin analysis. 

The evidence supplied by the petrographic analysis of the turbidite reservoirs and the 

structural analysis of seismic data indicate that the deposition of sand-rich deep-water 

systems occurred in Campos Basin under alternating downstream control and upstream 

control, associated with tectonic reactivations of basement structures and with the 

effects of the Trindade mantle plume. The dominant type of control can be directly 

related to the two petrographic categories of deepwater sandstones defined in present 

work (Fig. 25): the relatively mature systems (Albian, Cenomanian, Oligocene and 

Miocene) were deposited under prevailing downstream control, while the immature 

systems (Santonian, Campanian, Maastrichtian, Paleocene, and Eocene) were formed 

under prevailing upstream control. 

6.5. The high-order stratigraphic control 

The biostratigraphic data in Campos Basin indicates that most of the deepwater 

systems were deposited within short time spans of one single biozone that corresponds 



 95

to intervals between 1 and 2 Ma (Antunes et al., 2004). Detailed cyclostratigraphic 

studies indicate that the Upper Oligocene turbidite system was deposited during an even 

shorter time interval into the respective biozone (Perlmutter and Azambuja, 2005). 

Additionally, it was previously observed that these deepwater sandstone successions 

were formed by amalgamation of multiple events (Bruhn and Walker, 1995; Bruhn et 

al., 1998; Barroso et al., 2000; Perlmutter and Azambuja, 2005). The evidence of 

multiple depositional events during time intervals around 1 Ma suggests that the sand 

supply to deepwater settings in Campos Basin has been also controlled by high-order 

stratigraphic processes, possibly of climate nature.   

The internal organization of petrographic parameters observed in some Campos 

Basin deepwater systems confirms their amalgamated architecture. The Q/F ratio shows 

an internal high-frequency oscillation with constant grain size in the relatively mature 

Albian and Upper Oligocene turbidite systems (Figs. 9 and 20). In the Albian system 

the content of intrabasinal carbonate grains (CI) shows internal cyclicity parallel to the 

Q/F ratio (Fig. 9). These internal compositional oscillations are interpreted as a result of 

supply alternation between predominant reworked shelf sediments (higher Q/F and CI), 

during periods of normal rainfall, and first-cycle sediments from the upstream alluvial 

systems (lower Q/F and CI), during episodic torrential rainfall events. 

7. Paleogeographic reconstruction 

Campos Basin was not subjected to major climate changes related to plate drift 

during the divergent margin phase. The latitudes in Campos Basin have been restricted 

to a range between S20o and 30o, around the temperate-tropical climate boundary, from 

the Albian to the present time (Ford and Golonka, 2003). 

During the Albian, at the onset of the divergent margin phase, a wide and shallow 

carbonate ramp was developed in Campos Basin (Spadini et al., 1988). The relatively 

mature Upper Albian deepwater sand-rich system, characterized by high carbonate 

intrabasinal content (CI), was deposited beyond this ramp under stratigraphic 

downstream control, probably during relative a 3rd order lowstand subjected to high-

frequency climate oscillations. 

The Albian ramp was destructed in the Upper Cretaceous by drowning and by 

gravitational gliding above the salt detachment triggered by the ongoing basement 

tectonic reactivation. The Upper Cenomanian turbidites were deposited still under 

downstream control, but are slightly more immature than the Albian turbidites, probably 



 96

because of the initial degradation of the Albian ramp, and of some coastal uplift 

associated with the tectonic reactivation phase at the Albian-Cenomanian transition. The 

deepwater system was probably formed during a punctuated 3rd order lowstand during 

the ongoing 2nd order transgression. With the proceeding transgression, and without 

further tectonic uplift of the source-areas, the formation of deepwater sand-rich systems 

was subdued during Turonian and Coniacian. 

The immature Santonian deepwater sand-rich system was formed under fully 

upstream stratigraphic control. At this time, Campos Basin was bordered by a very 

narrow shelf. The coastal relief was actively uplifted by the Santonian tectonic 

reactivation phase, and the deepwater systems were fed by fan deltas or by short 

mountain rivers, similar to the equivalent environments already described in convergent 

margin basins (Mutti et al., 1996). The Santonian turbidites can be defined as sin-

tectonic, as the deformation was in course during their deposition (Bruhn and Walker, 

1995). The deposition of volcanic ash layers and the presence of significant amounts of 

burned palynomorfs in the Santonian fine-grained turbidites are related to the proximity 

of the Trindade mantle plume to Campos Basin (Caddah et al., 1998; Arai et al., 2005). 

The formation of a new shelf was inhibited during Upper Cretaceous because of the 

overall transgression. Therefore, the Campanian and the Maastrichtian immature 

deepwater sand-rich systems were deposited also under upstream stratigraphic control, 

with a narrow shelf and high coastal relief. The significant contribution of volcanic rock 

fragments and the presence of burned wood fragments in the Maastrichtian coarse-

grained turbidites indicate the arrival of the Trindade mantle plume to basin margin 

(Figs. 14 and 39). The coastal relief was probably very high, uplifted both by the 

tectonic Santonian reactivation phase and by the dynamic uplift of the mantle plume. 

Consequently, the deepwater systems were fed by short mountain-rivers and fan deltas.  

After the end of the 2nd order transgression in the Lower Paleocene, a new shelf 

begins to form in Campos Basin, but still sufficiently narrow to allow an overall 

upstream control on the deposition of the immature Paleocene and the Eocene 

deepwater sand-rich systems. The coastal relief was kept high by the Paleogene tectonic 

reactivation, and the deepwater systems were still fed by mountain-rivers and fan deltas.  

As the shelf was still narrow, the limited contribution of intrabasinal grains in the 

very immature Middle Eocene turbidites, including soil and microbialite fragments 

(Figs. 16, 27, and 40), can be interpreted as the contribution from offshore highs located 

very close to the deepwater depocenters, because these fragments would not resist long 



 97

transportation distances. These offshore islands were formed along the elevated footwall 

blocks of major fault systems activated during the Paleogene tectonic phase, under the 

influence of the dynamic uplift caused by the Trindade mantle plume that was then 

beneath Campos Basin depocenter (Fig. 39). The Paleogene uplift of the Campos Basin 

depocenter was previously documented by Scarton (1993). With the widening of the 

shelf during Upper Eocene, the intrabasinal contribution to deepwater systems was 

increased significantly (Figs. 17 and 27).  

As the regression proceeded with the progradation driven by high sediment supply 

from the mountains formed during the Paleogene tectonic phase, a relatively wide shelf 

was built in Campos Basin by the Lower Oligocene. The Lower Oligocene deepwater 

sand-rich system was deposited during a 3rd order lowstand, beyond a renewed shelf, 

and under downstream stratigraphic control (Souza Cruz, 1995). It is characterized by 

increasing compositional and textural maturity, as compared with the Upper Cretaceous 

and Paleogene turbidites, owing to the feeding of deepwater systems by longer fluvial 

systems and by sediment reworked on the widening shelf. 

With further progradation during the Oligocene, Campos Basin shelf continued to 

widen. The large Upper Oligocene deepwater system, which is the most mature 

turbidite system within Campos Basin, was also deposited during a 3rd order lowstand, 

under downstream stratigraphic control (Souza Cruz, 1995). As for the Lower 

Oligocene, the maturity of Upper Oligocene deepwater sandstones was probably related 

to both long transportation along an extensive fluvial system and sediment reworking on 

the shelf. 

The costal physiography was rebuilt by the new tectonic pulse occurred during the 

Neogene. The high sediment supply associated with the renewed relief produced a rapid 

progradation front and a very wide shelf in Campos Basin (Figs. 2 and 3). The Lower 

Miocene turbidite system was also deposited during a 3rd order lowstand, under fully 

downstream stratigraphic control (Souza Cruz, 1995), but with significantly higher 

feldspar and glaucony content than the Upper Oligocene deepwater system, what is 

attributed to the rejuvenation of the relief caused by the Neogene tectonic reactivation. 

However the low content in mud intraclasts suggests that the sand supply to deepwater 

during the Miocene used the same pathways incised into shelf edge and slope that were 

previously used during Upper Oligocene. 

 



 98

8. Discussion 

The energy necessary to promote the process of turbiditic mass transportation may be 

derived from two types of systems (Normark and Piper, 1991; Mutti et al., 2003): (i) 

potential energy of coastal relief or shelf gradient plus kinetic energy of river flooding; 

and (ii) potential energy of delta-front gradient plus kinetic energy of delta-front failure. 

The potential energy supplied by coastal relief is a product of geodynamic processes, 

while the potential energy of shelf and delta-front gradients is fundamentally related to 

stratigraphic processes. In turn, the kinetic energy of river flooding is a product of 

climatic processes, either ice melt or rainfall flooding, while the kinetic energy of delta-

front failure can be released by tectonic activity and/or by slope instability. Therefore, 

the recently proposed concept of downstream versus upstream control on the 

stratigraphic record (Catuneanu, 2006) can be applied to turbidite systems. Following 

this concept, geodynamic driven relief, climate flooding events and tectonic activity are 

upstream controls, while shelf gradients, delta progradation rates, and delta-front 

instabilities are downstream controls. 

A process-response relation was observed between the type of energy system and the 

compositional and textural parameters of Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems 

(Table 4). The trends of average petrographic parameters and the overall 

paleogeographic evolution are well constrained by the major geodynamic and 

stratigraphic controls that were operating during the divergent margin phase of Campos 

Basin (Fig. 40; Table 4). 

The geodynamic control is interpreted as a consequence of the interplay of three 

processes: (i) the passive escarpment retreat of the coastal relief, (ii) the dynamic uplift 

and the magmatic activity promoted by the Trindade mantle plume, and (iii) the 

episodic tectonic reactivations of major basement structures (Fig. 40; Table 4). None of 

these specific geodynamic controls alone can explain all the observed petrographic 

trends. A purely tectonic drive fails to explain the formation of the large Maastrichtian 

turbidite system with massive contribution of volcanic rock fragments, which was 

undoubtedly related to the passage of the southeastern continental margin of Brazil 

above the Trindade mantle plume (Fig. 39). However, it is important to observe that 

only large plumes, generated at the core-mantle boundary with CFB magmatic affinity, 

reach the base of the crust generating dynamic uplift in areas around 2000 km2, with up 

to 1000 m elevations (Griffiths and Campbell, 1990). Small plumes with OIB magmatic 

affinity, as in the case of the Trindade plume, are generated into the mantle and tend to 



 99

arrive fast to the base of the crust, producing dynamic uplift in smaller areas, around 

300 km2, with lesser elevations (Griffiths and Campbell, 1990). In any case, the time 

span of the dynamic uplift caused by the passage above a mantle plume is even shorter 

than the exponential isostatic adjustment of the oceanic crust generated at mid-ocean 

ridges (Condie, 2001). Therefore, it is not reasonable to credit all the evolution of the 

coastal relief along Campos Basin border, indicated by turbidite petrography and 

structural analysis, to the Trindade plume. Actually, the observed relief rejuvenations 

and paleogeographic reorganizations are episodic, and have been occurring during at 

least 80 Ma (Figs. 39 and 40). It is suggested that episodic and repeated uplift of the 

coastal mountain chain along southeastern  Brazilian margin (Serra do Mar) can be 

better explained by episodic tectonic reactivations of the major basement fabrics, 

probably enhanced by the thermal anomaly related to the plume during the Cretaceous-

Paleogene transition (Cobbold et al., 2001). During the periods of tectonic quiescence, 

and without the plume effects, escarpment retreat has been the dominant geodynamic 

process acting along the Campos Basin border (Fig. 40, Table 4). 

The above discussed geodynamic processes have been exerting a strong control on 

the stratigraphic record during the divergent margin phase in Campos Basin. The 

periods of passive escarpment retreat of the continental margin have been characterized 

by downstream stratigraphic control, largely constrained by base level changes. 

Therefore it is supposed that the respective relatively mature deepwater systems have 

been formed during 3rd order lowstands. As it was formed beyond a carbonate ramp, 

even the Albian turbidite system fits this interpretation, because the stratigraphic 

response to base level changes of carbonate ramps and siliciclastic platforms is similar 

(Catuneanu, 2006) . On the other hand, during the periods of tectonic reactivation 

and/or mantle plume activity, the upstream stratigraphic control has been dominant. In 

this case the immature deepwater systems could have been formed in any stage of the 

eustatic sea level.   

The internal organization of the petrographic parameters, particularly Q/F ratio, grain 

size and CI content, indicates that the relatively mature Campos Basin deepwater 

sandstones were formed by the amalgamation of multiple depositional events. The well-

defined petrographic oscillations observed in the mature turbidites formed beyond a 

wide platform, with moderate coastal relief, under downstream stratigraphic control, 

suggest that the sand supply to deepwater settings has been controlled by high-

frequency climate changes of the Milankovitch band during 3rd order lowstands (Figs. 9, 



 100

20, and 22; Table 4). Following this interpretation, the internal growing-upwards trends 

of Q/F ratio and CI with constant or fining-upwards grain size (Albian – Fig. 9; Upper 

Oligocene – Fig. 20; Miocene – Fig. 22) are attributed to the rise of the base level at the 

end of 3rd order lowstands, with progressive restriction of the contribution of first-cycle 

sediments to deepwater settings.  

In the case of immature deepwater sandstones formed under upstream stratigraphic 

control, the triggering of the turbidity currents was probably related to the association 

between the potential energy of the high coastal relief and by the kinetic energy of 

episodic events of enhanced rainfall flooding of coastal alluvial systems (Table 4). In 

the absence of a well developed shelf, immature, first-cycle alluvial and fluvial 

sediments were taken directly to deepwater settings during flooding events.  

9. Conclusions 

Two classes of deepwater sand-rich systems were defined in Campos Basin based on 

quantitative petrographic analysis (Fig. 25): (i) relatively mature turbidites, with 

alternating shelf-reworked and first-cycle contributions, and (ii) immature turbidites, 

with predominant first-cycle contribution. The geodynamic evolution of the continental 

margin has exerted the major control on the deposition of these deepwater systems. This 

control is determined by the interaction of three geodynamic processes (Fig. 40; Table 

4): (i) escarpment retreat of the coastal relief, (ii) dynamic uplift and magmatic activity 

of the Trindade mantle plume, and (iii) tectonic reactivations of the major basement 

structures 

The relatively mature deepwater sandstones were deposited beyond wide shelves or 

shallow ramps, during periods of escarpment retreat, with low to moderate coastal 

relief. Under such boundary conditions, the stratigraphic record was controlled by 

downstream factors, namely the 3rd order eustatic variations in the sea level and climate 

cyclicity of the Milankovitch band. However, it is important to notice that, in presence 

of a wide shelf, the downstream control can prevail even during phases of active 

tectonism (e.g. Cenomanian and Miocene systems; Fig. 40, Table 4).  

The immature turbidite systems were formed during periods of high coastal relief 

and shelf degradation, caused by tectonic activity and by dynamic uplift. In such 

periods, the upstream stratigraphic control has prevailed and the deepwater 

sedimentation had been triggered exclusively by episodic rainfall flooding (Fig. 40, 

Table 4).  



 101

The two largest turbidite reservoir systems in Campos Basin are the Maastrichtian 

and the Upper Oligocene (black stars in Fig. 40). These systems were formed during 

periods of tectonic quiescence, just before the onset of the subsequent tectonic 

reactivation. This observation indicates that giant deepwater sand-rich systems can be 

formed in divergent margins as a consequence of tectonic rejuvenation followed by 

stable configuration of the source-basin system, independently of the type of 

stratigraphic control. In this situation, huge sand volumes can accumulate until the 

system happen to be aborted by a new tectonic pulse. Conversely, relatively more 

dispersed deepwater systems were formed when the physiography was unstable because 

of ongoing tectonic activity. 

From a methodological point of view, the quantitative petrography of deepwater 

sandstones was revealed to be a powerful tool in the paleogeographic reconstruction of 

divergent margin settings, as it was emphatically confirmed for convergent margins. 

Particularly, the grain size and the quartz to feldspar ratio are very sensitive to the 

rejuvenation of the coastal relief, while the contents of intrabasinal carbonate grains, 

glaucony, and mud intraclasts are indicative of the evolution of the shelf-slope 

physiography. As the methodology is very simple, it can be easily applied in other 

divergent margin basins. 

 The integrated paleogeographic reconstruction presented in this work represents a 

significant change in the interpretation of the geodynamic and stratigraphic evolution of 

Campos Basin divergent margin phase. Particularly, the main controls on the formation 

of the Campos Basin giant turbidite reservoir systems were redefined as a complex 

interplay of tectonic, magmatic, eustatic and climatic aspects, contrasting with the 

conventional, sequence-stratigraphic models previously interpreted for these systems. 

This new approach will be of key importance to generate realistic models for the 

exploration of new turbidite reservoirs and for the optimized development of producing 

turbidite oilfields in such a world-class hydrocarbon province. 

Acknowledgements 

The present work was developed as part of a doctorate research project at the 
Graduate Program in Geosciences of Rio Grande do Sul Federal University (UFRGS – 
Porto Alegre, Brazil), sponsored by Petrobras. We acknowledge the discussions and the 
support of Cláudio Lima and Luci Arienti from Petrobras Research Center, and Carlos 
Rodrigues from Petrobras International. We also wish to thank Eliane de Freitas 
Ferreira from Petrobras Documentation Center. LFDR acknowledges the support by the 
National Council of Research - CNPq. 



 102

References 

Almeida, F.F.M., Carneiro, C.D.R., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1996. Correlação do 
magmatismo das bacias da margem continental brasileira com o das áreas emersas 
adjacentes: Rev. Bras. Geoc. 26: 125-138. 

Antunes, R.L., Shimabukuro, S., Oliveira, L.C.V., Rosa, A.L.Z., Costa, S.O., Cunha, 
A.A.S., and Lima, F.H.O., 2004. Towards a high resolution biostratigraphy: the 
Petrobras calcareous nannofossil zonation performance. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras 14: 125-
131. 

Arai, M., Lana, C.C., Araújo, C.V., and Menezes, T.R., 2005. The great Santonian fire - 
implications for the regional geology and petroleum exploration. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras 
14: 125-131. 

Assumpção, M., 1998. Seismicity and stresses in the Brazilian divergent margin: Bull. 
Seismol. Soc. Am. 88: 160-169. 

Barroso, A.S., Mihaguti, M.K., Castro, D.D., Stank, C.V., Sarzenski, D.J., Adams, T., 
2000. Roncador giant oil field: exploration and production from a heterogeneous 
Maastrichtian turbidite reservoir in ultra deep water Campos Basin, Brazil. AAPG 
Ann. Met., New Orleans, Louisiana, Abstr., AAPG Bull. 84:13. 

Bezerra, F.H.R., and Vita-Finzi, C., 2000. How active is a divergent margin? 
Paleoseismicity in northeastern Brazil. Geology 28: 591-594. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., Gomes, J.A.T., Del Luchese, C., and Johann, P.R.S., 2003. Campos 
Basin: reservoir characterization and management – historical overview and future 
challenges. OTC-Houston, paper OTC 15220, pp. 1-14. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., Barroso, A.S., Lopes, M.R.F., Sarzenski, D.J., Abreu, C.J., Silva, 
C.M.A., 1998. High-resolution stratigraphy and reservoir heterogeneities of Upper 
Albian turbidite reservoirs of Albacora Field, Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. 1998 
AAPG Ann. Conv., Salt Lake City, Utah, Ext. Abstr. 1:A95. 

Bruhn, C.H.L., and Walker, R.G., 1995. High-resolution stratigraphy and sedimentary 
evolution of coarse-grained canyon-filling turbidites from the Upper-Cretaceous 
transgressive megasequence, Campos Basin, offshore Brazil. J. Sed. Res. 65: 426-442. 

Burgess, P.M., and Hovius, N., 1998. Rates of delta progradation during highstands: 
consequences foe timing of deposition in deep-marine systems. J. Geol. Soc. London 
155: 217-222. 

Caddah, L.F.G., Alves, D.B., and Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1998, Turbidites associated with 
bentonites in the Upper-Cretaceous of the Campos Basin, offshore Brazil: Sed. Geol., 
v. 115, 175-184. 

Campos Neto, M.C., 2000, Orogenic systems from southwestern Gondwana. In: U.G. 
Cordani, E.J. Milani, A. Thomaz Filho and D.A. Campos (Editors), Tectonic 
Evolution of South America. 31st Int. Geol. Congress, Rio de Janeiro, pp. 335-365. 

Carvajal, C.R., and Steel, R.J., 2006. Thick turbidite succesions from supply-dominated 
shelves during sea-level highstand. Geology 34: 665-668. 

Catuneanu, O., 2006. Principles of Sequence Stratigraphy. Elsevier, Amsterdam, 375 
pp. 

Chang, H.K., Kowsmann, R.O., Figueiredo, A.M.F., and Bender, A.A., 1992. Tectonics 
and stratigraphy of the East Brazil Rift system: an overview. Tectonophys. 213: 97-
138. 

Cibin, U., Spadafora, E., Zuffa, G.G., and Castellarin, A., 2001. Continental collision 
history from arenites of episutural basins in the Northern Apennines, Italy. GSA Bull. 
113: 04-19. 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E., and Mount, S.V., 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely-
rifted margin: Campos and Santos basins, SE Brazil. AAPG Bull. 85: 1925-1944. 



 103

Cobbold, P.R., and Szatmari, P., 1991. Radial gravitational gliding on divergent 
margins. Tectonophys. 188: 249-289. 

Condie, K.C., 2001. Mantle Plumes and Their Record in Earth History. Cambridge 
University Press, Cambridge, 306 p. 

Demercian, S., Szatmari, P., and Cobbold, P.R., 1993. Style and pattern of salt diapirs 
due to thin-skinned gravitational gliding, Campos and Santos basins, offshore Brazil. 
Tectonophys. 228: 393-433. 

Dias, J.L., Scarton, J.C., Guardado, L.R., Esteves, F.R., and Carminatti, M., 1990. 
Aspectos da evolução tectono-sedimentar e da ocorrência de hidrocarbonetos na Bacia 
de Campos. In: G.P. Raja-Gabaglia, and E.J. Milani (Editors), Origem e Evolução de 
Bacias Sedimentares. Petrobras, Rio de Janeiro, pp. 333-360. 

Dickinson, W.R., 1970. Interpreting detrital modes of greywacke and arkose. J. Sedim. 
Petrol. 40: 695-707. 

Dickinson, W.R. and Suczec, C.A., 1979. Plate tectonics and sandsdtone compositions: 
AAPG Bull. 63: 2164-2182. 

Dickinson, W.R., 1985. Interpreting provenance relations from detrital modes of 
sandstones. In: G.G. Zuffa (Editor), Provenance of arenites. D. Reidel Publ. Co.; 
NATO ASI Series, Math. Phys. Sci. 148, pp. 333-361. 

Eisenstad, G., and Withjack, M.O., 1995. Estimating inversion: results from clay 
models. In: J.G. Buchanan and P.G. Buchanan (Editors), Basin Inversion. Geol. Soc. 
London Spec. Publ. 88, pp. 119-136. 

Fetter, M., Lima, C.C., Silva, A.T., Machado, D., Castro, D.D., and Adams, T., 2002. 
Interaction between salt related extension and basement strike-slip reactivation in 
northern Campos Basin, deepwater Brazil. SEG 72nd Ann. Meet., Salt Lake City, Exp. 
Abstr., pp. 2413-2416. 

Folk, R.L., 1968. Petrology of Sedimentary Rocks. Hemphill’s Bookstore, Austin, 170 
p. 

Fontana, D., Zuffa, G.G., and Garzanti, E., 1989. The interaction of eustacy and 
tectonism from provenance studies of the Eocene Hecho Group turbidite complex 
(South-Central Pyrenees, Spain). Basin Res. 2: 223-237. 

Ford, D., and Golonka, J., 2003. Phanerozoic paleogeography, paleoenviroment and 
lthofacies of the circum-Atlantic margins. Mar. Petrol. Geol. 20: 249-285. 

Gallagher, K., and Brown, R., 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic 
margins of southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore 
sedimentation. In N.R. Cameron, R.H. Bate, and V.S. Clure (Editors), The Oil and Gas 
Habitats of the South Atlantic. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 153, pp. 41-53. 

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., and Mantovani, M.S.M., 1995. Denudation, fission 
track analysis and the long-term evolution of divergent margin topography: application 
to southeast Brazilian margin. J. South Am. Earth Sci. 8: 65-77. 

Galloway, W.E., 1989. Genetic stratigraphic sequences in basin analysis I: architecture 
and genesis of flooding-surface bounded depositional units. AAPG Bull. 73: 125-142. 

Gazzi, P., 1966. Sulla determinazione microscopica della compozicione mineralogica e 
granulometrica delle rocce, in particolare delle arenarie e delle sabbie. Mineral. et 
Petrogr. Acta. 12: 61-68. 

Gilchrist, A.R., and Summerfield, M.A., 1990. Differential denudation and flexural 
isostasy in the formation of rifted-margin upwarps. Nature 346: 739-742. 

Griffiths, R.W., and Campbell, I.H., 1990. Stirring and structure in mantle starting 
plumes. Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 99: 66-78. 

Hawkesworth, C.J., Gallagher, K., Kelley, S., Mantovani, M., Peate, D.W., Regelous, 
M., and Rogers, N.W., 1992. Paraná magmatism and the opening of the South 



 104

Atlantic. In: B.C. Storey, T. Alabaster, and R.J. Pankhurst (Editors), Magmatism and 
the Causes of Continental Break-up. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 68, pp. 221-240. 

Ingersoll R.V., Bullard T.F., Ford R.L., Grimm J.P., Pickle J.D., and Sares S.W., 1984. 
The effect of grain size on detrital modes: a test of the Gazzi-Dickinson point-counting 
method: J. Sedim. Petrol. 54: 103-116. 

Karner, G.D., 2000. Rifts of the Campos and Santos Basins, southeastern Brazil: 
distribution and timing. In: M.R. Melo, and B.J. Katz (Editors), Petroleum Systems of 
South Atlantic Margins. AAPG Memoir 73, pp. 301-315. 

Kolla, V., and Pelmutter, M.A., 1993. Timing of turbidite sedimentation on the 
Mississipi Fan: AAPG Bull. 77: 1129-1141. 

Lima, C.C., 1999. Expressions topographiques et structurales de l´etat de compression 
généralisée au sein de la plaque Sud-Américaine. PhD Thesis, Univ. Rennes 1, France. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., and Mohriak, W.W., 1992. Sequências vulcano-sedimentares na 
região da plataforma continental de Cabo Frio (RJ). Anais 37o. Congr. Soc. Bras. 
Geol., pp. 52-56. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Petrini, R., Bellieni, G., Comin-Chiaramonti, P., Dias, J., De Min, 
A., and Piccirillo, E.M., 1992. Basalt magmatism along the passive continental margin 
of SE Brazil (Campos Basin). Contrib. Min. Petrol. 111: 143-160. 

Mohriak, W.U., and Dewey, J.F., 1987. Deep seismic reflectors in the Campos Basin, 
offshore Brazil. Geophys. J. R. Astron. Soc. 89: 133-140. 

Mutti, E., Davoli, G., Tinterri, R., and Zavala, C., 1996. The importance of fluvio-
deltaic systems dominated by catastophic flooding in tectonically active basins. Mem. 
Sci. Geol. Padova 48: 233-291. 

Mutti, E., Tinterri, R., Benevelli, G., di Biase, Davide, and Cavanna, G., 2003. Deltaic, 
mixed and turbidite sedimentation of ancient foreland basins. Mar. Petrol. Geol. 20: 
733-755. 

Normark, W.R., and Piper, D.J.W., 1991. Initiation processes and flow evolution of 
turbidity currents: implications for the depositional record. In: R.H. Osborne (Editor), 
From Shoreline to Abyss: Contributions in Marine Geology in Honor of Francis 
Parker Shepard. SEPM Spec. Publ. 46, pp. 207-230. 

Ollier, C.D., 1985. Morphotectonics of continental margins with great escarpments. In: 
M. Morisawa and J.T. Hack (Editors), Tectonic Geomorphology. Allen &amp;amp; Unwin, 
Boston, pp. 3-25. 

Perlmutter, M.A., and Azambuja, N.C., 2005. Cyclostratigraphy. In: E.A.M. 
Koutsoukos (Editor), Applied Stratigraphy. Springer Topics in Geobiology 23, pp. 
301-338. 

Pereira, M.J., 1994. Seqüências deposicionais de 2a. e 3a. ordens (50 a 2 Ma) e tectono-
estratigrafia no Cretáceo de cinco bacias marginais do Brasil: comparações com outras 
áreas do globo e implicações geodinâmicas. PhD Thesis, Universidade Federal do Rio 
Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil. 

Peres, W.E., 1993. Shelf-fed turbidite system model and its application to the Oligocene 
deposits of the Campos Basin, Brazil. AAPG Bull. 77: 81-101. 

Ponte, F.C., and Asmus, H.E., 1976. Brazilian marginal basins: current state of 
knowledge. Anais Acad. Bras. Ciênc. 48: 215-239. 

Posamentier, H.W., Jervey, M.T., and Vail P.R., 1988. Eustatic controls on clastic 
deposition I: conceptual framework. In: C.K.. Wilgus, B.S. Hastings, C.G. st. C. 
Kendal, H.W. Posamentier, C.A. Ross, and J.C. Van Wagoner (Editors), Sea Level 
Changes: An Integrated Approach. SEPM Spec. Publ. 42, pp. 110-124. 

Rabinowitz, P.D., and LaBrecque, J., 1979. The Mesozoic South Atlantic Ocean and 
evolution of its continental margins. J. Geophys. Res. 84: 5973-6002. 



 105

Saenz, C.A.T., Hackspacker, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, 
L.F.B., and Paulo, S.R., 2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene 
tectonic reactivation through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambriam areas of 
southeast Brazil: association with the opening of the south Atlantic ocean. J. South 
Am. Earth Sci. 15: 765-774. 

Santos, P. R. S., Rangel, H. D., Quintaes, C. M. S. P., and Caixeta, J. M., 1999. 
Turbidite reservoir distribution in Roncador field, Campos Basin, Brazil. AAPG Int. 
Conf. Exhib., Birmingham, England, Ext. Abstr., pp. 530–531. 

Scarton, J.C., 1993. Análise estratigráfica do Terciário Inferior da Bacia de Campos: 
Uma visão moderna (com ênfase na região dos campos petrolíferos de Corvina e 
Malhado). PhD Thesis, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, 
Brazil. 

Sibson, R.H., 1995. Selective fault reactivation during basin inversion - potential for 
fluid redistribution through fault-valve action. In: J.G. Buchanan and P.G. Buchanan 
(Editors), Basin Inversion. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 88, pp. 3-19. 

Souza Cruz, C.E., 1995. Estratigrafia e sedimentação de águas profundas do Neogeno 
da Bacia de Campos, Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil. PhD Thesis, Universidade 
Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, PortoAlegre, Brazil. 

Spadini, A.R., Esteves, F.R., Dias-Brito, D., Azevedo, R.L.M., and Rodrigues, R., 1988. 
The Macaé Formation, Campos Basin, Brazil: its evolution in the context of the initial 
history of the South Atlantic. Rev. Bras. Geoc. 18: 261-272. 

Stein, S., Cloetingh, S., Sleep, N.H., and Wortel, R., 1989. Divergent margin 
earthquakes, stresses, and rheology. In: S. Gregersen and P.W. Basham (Editors), 
Earthquakes at North-Atlantic Divergent Margins: Neotectonics and Post Glacial 
Rebound. Kluwer Academic, Dodrecht, pp. 231-259. 

Thomaz Filho, A., de Cesaro, P., Mizusaki, A.M.P., and Leão, J.G., 2005. Hot spot 
volcanic tracks and their implications for South American plate motion, Campos Basin 
(Rio de Janeiro state), Brazil. J. South Am. Earth Sci. 18: 383-389. 

Thompson, R.N., Gibson, S.A., Mitchell, J.G., Dickin, A.P., Leonardos, O.H., Brod, 
J.A., and Greenwood, J.C., 1998. Migrating Cretaceous-Eocene magmatism in the 
Serra do Mar alkaline province, SE Brazil: melts from the deflected Trindade mantle 
plume. J. Petrol. 39: 1493-1526. 

Wilson, M., 1992. Magmatism and continental rifting during the opening of the South 
Atlantic Ocean: a consequence of Lower Cretaceous super-plume activity? In: B.C. 
Storey, T. Alabaster, and R.J. Pankhurst (Editors), Magmatism and the Causes of 
Continental Break-up. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 68, pp. 241-255. 

Withjack, M.O., and Olsen, P.E., Schlische, R.W., 1995. Tectonic evolution of the 
Fundy rift basin, Canada: evidence of extension and shortening during divergent 
margin development. Tectonics 14: 390-405. 

Woodcock, N.H., and Schubert, C., 1994. Continental strike-slip tectonics. In: P. 
Hancock (Editor), Continental Deformation. Oxford Pergamon Press, New York, pp. 
251-263. 

Zalán, P.V., and Oliveira, J.A.B., 2005. Origin and structural evolution of the Cenozoic 
Rift System of southeastern Brazil. Bol. Geoc. Petrobras 13: 269-300. 

Ziegler, P.A., Cloetingh, S., and van Wees, J.D., 1995. Dynamics of intra-plate 
compressional deformation: the Alpine foreland and other examples. Tectonophys. 
252: 7-59. 

Zuffa, G.G., 1980. Hybrid arenites: their composition and classification. J. Sed. Petrol. 
50: 21-29. 



 106

Zuffa, G.G., 1985. Optical analysis of arenites: influence of methodology on 
compositional results. In: G.G. Zuffa (Editor), Provenace of Arenites. D. Reidel Publ. 
Co, Dodrecht, pp. 165-189. 

Zuffa, G.G., 1987. Unravelling hinterland and offshore paleogeography from deep-
water arenites. In: J.K. Leggett and G.G. Zuffa (Editors), Marine Clastic 
Sedimentology. Graham &amp;amp; Trotman, London,  pp. 39-61 

Zuffa, G.G., 1991. On the use of turbidite arenites in provenance studies: critical 
remarks. In: A.C. Morton, S.P. Todd, and P.D.W. Haughton (Editors), Developments 
in Sedimentary Provenance Studies. Geol. Soc. London Spec. Publ. 57, pp. 23-29. 

Zuffa, G.G., Cibin, U., and Di Giuglio, A., 1995. Arenite petrography in sequence 
stratigraphy. The J. of Geol. 103: 451-459. 

Zuffa, G.G., Normark W.R., Serra, F., and Brunner, C.A., 2000. Turbidite megabeds in 
an ocean rift valley recording jökulhlaups of the Late Pleistocene lakes in the western 
United States. The J. of Geol. 108: 253-274. 

Table Captions 

Table 1 - Dataset used for the petrographic analysis of Campos Basin turbidite 
reservoirs, wells location is indicated in Figure 4. The average sample interval was 
around 8 m. 

Table 2 - Average results of the quantitative petrographic analysis of the Campos Basin 
turbidite reservoirs. Q/F – quartz to feldspar ratio; VRF – volcanic rock fragment 
content; CI – carbonate intrabasinal content; Intracl – mud intraclasts content; Glauc – 
glaucony content; Mica –content of micaceous grains. 

Table 3 - Basement reactivation events indicated by structural analysis of regional 3D 
seismic data during the divergent margin phase in Campos basin. 

Table 4 - Maturity, internal petrographic pattern, main geodynamic and stratigraphic 
controls, and paleogeography of the deepwater sand-rich systems formed during the 
divergent margin phase of Campos Basin. 

Figure Captions 

Figure 1 - Location of Campos Basin in southeastern Brazilian coast. Observe the 
mantle plumes related to Campos Basin evolution. CFB – continental flood basalts of 
the Paraná Basin. 

Figure 2 - Structural section through central Campos Basin. Observe the thick rift 
successions deposited during Lower Cretaceous, and the transgressive-regressive 
successions deposited from the Albian to the Neogene. Observe also the up to 2700 m 
high Serra do Mar mountains close to the basin border, the wide Neogene shelf, and the 
dominant detached structural style. The inserts show the location of the basin, and the 
position of the section in the basin. 

Figure 3 - Integrated map of Campos Basin with the basement structure (to the right of 
the coast line) and the digital topographic model of the continental margin. The 
bathymetry is indicated in white contours (500 m interval). Observe the wide shelf 
formed by progradation during the Neogene (closed black dashed line), and the high 
mountains along the basin border. Observe also the main orientations of the Proterozoic 
basement fabrics (white dashed lines): Ribeira (NE-SW) and Vitória-Colatina (NNW-
SSE). 



 107

Figure 4 - Location of the well cores used for quantitative petrographic analysis of the 
Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs (see Table 1 for details). The integrated map was 
composed with the basement elevation and the digital topographic model along the 
basin border. 

Figure 5 - Compositional classification of the main Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs 
according to the classic compositional diagram for sandstones of Folk (1968). Observe 
that most of the samples plot in the arkose field, with a few samples in the lithic arkose 
field. 

Figure 6 - High-hierarchy compositional classification of the Campos Basin turbidite 
reservoirs according to the major classes of grains (modified from Zuffa, 1980). 
Observe that most of the samples plot in the field of siliciclastic non-carbonate 
extrabasinal grains (NCE). The Albian turbidites show a departure towards the 
carbonate intrabasinal origin (CI). The Santonian and the Paleocene reservoirs show a 
departure towards the non-carbonate intrabasinal contribution (NCI). The Cenomanian, 
Upper Eocene and Miocene turbidites show a mixed departure to intrabasinal 
contribution (CI and NCI). The Upper Eocene includes one sample classified as a 
calcarenite. 

Figure 7 - Compositional classification of the Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs 
according to the tectonic setting of the sediment-source area (Dickinson and Suczec, 
1979; Dickinson, 1985). Observe that most of the samples plot in the field of uplifted 
basement blocks (rift basin and immature divergent margin). The Upper Oligocene 
reservoir shows a departure towards the transitional continent field (mature divergent 
margin), as well as a few Albian, Cenomanian and Miocene samples. The Maastrichtian 
reservoir shows a departure towards the field of volcanic contribution. 

Figure 8 - Photomicrographs of the Albian reservoir (Well 01): Observe the widespread 
calcite cementation. (a) Well-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone arkose; 
observe the foliated metamorphic rock fragment. (b) Well-sorted, subr-ounded, fine-
grained sandstone arkose; observe the intrabasinal carbonate grains (oncoid, bioclasts). 
(c) Well-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone arkose; observe the significant 
content of micaceous grains. (d) Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone 
arkose; observe the coarse microcline and plagioclase grains. (e) Moderately-sorted, 
sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone arkose to hybrid arenite; observe the large 
carbonate bioclasts (mostly mollusks). (f) Well-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained 
sandstone arkose to hybrid arenite; observe the carbonate ooids. 

Figure 9 - Petrographic parameters grain size, quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F), and 
carbonate intrabasinal content (CI) of the Albian reservoir (Well 01). Observe constant 
fine grain size. Observe also that Q/F and CI show co-variant, high-frequency cyclicity, 
and growing upwards trend (dashed arrows). 

Figure 10 - Photomicrographs of the Cenomanian reservoir (Well 02): Observe the 
widespread calcite cementation. (a) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained 
sandstone arkose; observe the carbonate bioclast. (b) Well-sorted, sub-angular, medium-
grained sandstone arkose. (c) Moderately-sorted, sub-rounded, medium-grained 
sandstone arkose; observe the coarse plagioclase grain. (d) Moderately-sorted, sub-
angular, fine-grained sandstone arkose; observe the high content of micaceous grains. 
(e) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone arkose; observe the pebble-size 
plutonic rock fragment. (f) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone arkose; 
observe the coarse microcline grain and the large mud intraclast. 

 



 108

Figure 11 - Photomicrographs of the Santonian reservoir (Well 03): (a) Moderately-
sorted, sub-rounded, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the pseudo-matrix 
(derived from compacted mud intraclasts) replaced by calcite (cc) and opaline silica 
(sc). (b) Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the 
pseudo-matrix (from compacted mud intraclasts) replaced by opaline silica (sc), 
containing bioclasts of nannofossils and planktonic foraminifera. (c) Poorly-sorted, sub-
angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the large compacted mud 
intraclast. (d) Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, coarse-grained sandstone, arkose. (e) Very 
poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the pebble-
sized microcline grain. (f) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, 
arkose; observe the coarse quartz and feldspar grains. 

Figure 12 - Cross plot showing the internal correlation between grain size and quartz to 
feldspar ratio (Q/F) observed in the Santonian and in the Paleogene deepwater sand-rich 
systems of Campos Basin. 

Figure 13 - Photomicrographs of the Campanian reservoir (Well 04): (a) Poorly-sorted, 
sub-angular, very coarse-grained sandstone arkose. (b) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-
grained sandstone, arkose; observe the large mud intraclast with planktonic bioclasts. 
(c) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, coarse-grained sandstone arkose. (d) Moderately-sorted, 
sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone arkose; observe the volcanic rock fragment with 
trachytic texture. (e) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone arkose; 
observe the compacted volcanic rock fragment. (f) Moderately-sorted, sub-rounded, 
coarse-grained sandstone arkose. Observe the overall very low quartz to feldspar ratio. 

Figure 14 - Photomicrographs of the Maastrichtian reservoir (Well 05): (a) Poorly-
sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, lithic arkose; observe the volcanic rock 
fragments. (b) Very poorly-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; 
observe the pebble-sized feldspar grains. (c) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, coarse-grained 
sandstone, arkose; observe the pebble-size feldspar grains. (d) Moderately-sorted, sub-
angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the high content of micaceous grains 
and of black carbonaceous fragments of burned wood. (e) Detail of the compacted 
carbonaceous fragments and micas. (f) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained 
sandstone, lithic arkose; observe the volcanic rock fragment. 

Figure 15 - Photomicrographs of the Paleocene reservoir (Well 06): (a) Poorly-sorted, 
sub-rounded, coarse-grained sandstone, arkose. (b) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, 
medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the volcanic rock fragments. (c) 
Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, medium sand arkose; observe the volcanic rock 
fragment. (d) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe 
the mollusk bioclast (lower-left), the compacted mud intraclast (upper-right), and the 
glaucony grain (G). (e) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; 
observe the planktonic foraminifer bioclasts, and the volcanic rock fragment.  (f) 
Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, coarse sand arkose; observe the large glauconitic intraclast 
(G). 

 

 

 

 

 



 109

Figure 16 - Photomicrographs of the Middle Eocene reservoir (Well 06): (a) 
Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the compacted 
glaucony grain (G). (b) Moderately-sorted, sub-rounded, medium-grained sandstone, 
arkose; observe the high feldspar content. (c) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, coarse-grained 
sandstone, arkose. (d) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; 
observe the large argillaceous fragment with “silky” texture characteristic of soils (SF). 
(e) Large, laminated microbialite fragment.  (f) Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained 
sandstone, arkose; observe the large intraclast (lower left), and the very coarse plutonic 
rock fragment and microcline grains. 

Figure 17 - Photomicrographs of the Upper Eocene reservoir (Well 06): (a) Poorly-
sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the large red algae 
bioclast (RA). (b) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; 
observe the moderately compacted mica grain. (c) Poorly-sorted, medium-grained 
calcarenite; observe the glaucony grains (G), the macroforaminifer bioclast (FF), and 
the intense calcite cementation. (d) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, coarse-grained 
sandstone, arkose. (e) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained hybrid arenite; 
observe the foraminifer bioclasts. (f) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, medium-grained 
sandstone, arkose; observe the carbonate bioclasts, and the glaucony grains (G). 

Figure 18 - Photomicrographs of the Lower Oligocene reservoir (Well 07): (a) Well-
sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the carbonate bioclasts; 
“coatings” around the grains are effect of defective impregnation. (b) Poorly-sorted, 
sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the very coarse sand grains. (c) 
Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the large, 
compacted mud intraclast with planktonic bioclasts. (d) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, 
medium-grained sandstone, arkose. (e) Poorly-sorted, subangular fine-grained 
sandstone, arkose; observe the large bryozoan bioclast.  (f) Well-sorted, sub-angular, 
fine-grained sandstone, arkose. 

Figure 19 - Photomicrographs of the Upper Oligocene reservoir (Wells 08/09): (a) 
Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the coarse feldspar 
grains. (b) Poorly-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the large 
bryozoan bioclast. (c) Poorly-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone, arkose. (d) 
Moderately-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the 
foraminifer bioclast. (e) Well-sorted, sub-rounded fine-grained sandstone, arkose; 
observe the planktonic foraminifer bioclasts, and the large mud intraclast (lower right) 
with carbonaceous fragments (black).  (f) Well-sorted, sub-angular, fine–grained 
sandstone, arkose. 

Figure 20 - Petrographic parameters of the Upper Oligocene reservoir (Wells 08/09): 
grain size and quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F). Observe the almost constant fine grain size. 
Observe also that the Q/F ratio shows a growing-upwards trend (dashed arrow), a well-
defined step with higher quartz content in the upper-half of the cored section, and a 
superimposed high-frequency cyclicity. 

Figure 21 - Photomicrographs of the Miocene reservoir (Well 10): (a) Well-sorted, sub-
angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the foraminifer bioclast. (b) Well-
sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the foraminifer bioclasts. 
(c) Well-sorted, sub-rounded, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the carbonate 
bioclasts. (d) Moderately-sorted, sub-angular, fine-grained sandstone, arkose; observe 
the carbonate bioclasts, and the glaucony grains (G). (e) Well-sorted, sub-rounded fine-
grained sandstone, arkose; observe the glaucony grain (G).  (f) Poorly-sorted, sub-
angular, medium-grained sandstone, arkose; observe the very coarse microcline grain. 



 110

Figure 22 - Petrographic parameters grain size and quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) of the 
Miocene reservoir (Well 10): Observe the fining-upwards trend from medium to very 
fine sand grain size. Observe also that the Q/F ratio shows a well-defined growing-
upwards trend (dashed arrow). 

Figure 23 - Average quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) of the main Campos Basin deepwater 
sand-rich systems. The Q/F trend shows a linear drop from 1.00 in the Albian and the 
Cenomanian to 0.75 in the Upper Cretaceous and the Paleogene; then there is an 
exponential increase to 1.40 in the Upper Oligocene, and an equally strong drop to 0.90 
in the Miocene. 

Figure 24 - Grain size trend of the main Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems. 
The average grain size changed from fine sand during the Albian and Cenomanian, to 
medium sand from Santonian to Upper Eocene, and returned to fine sand from Lower 
Oligocene to Miocene. 

Figure 25 - Cross-plot between the petrographic parameters grain size and quartz to 
feldspar ratio (Q/F) of the main Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs. Observe that two 
types of deepwater sand-rich systems can be defined by the compositional-textural 
character: (i) mature, fine sand systems (average Q/F = 1.00), and (ii) immature, 
medium sand systems (average Q/F = 0.75). 

Figure 26 - Average amounts of volcanic rock fragments (VRF) in the main Campos 
Basin deepwater sand-rich systems. VRF content shows a background around 1%, and a 
peak close to 9% in the Maastrichtian, with amounts above 3% in the Campanian and in 
the Paleocene. 

Figure 27 - Average contribution of carbonate intrabasinal grains (CI) in the main 
Campos Basin deepwater sand-rich systems. The CI content shows strong oscillations, 
with peaks in the Albian and Upper Eocene, and troughs around zero at the end of the 
Cretaceous and during the Middle Eocene. CI contribution is around 5% in the 
Cenomanian, the Paleocene, and the Oligocene turbidite systems; it grows slightly in 
the Miocene (7.5%). 

Figure 28 - Average content of mud intraclasts in the main Campos Basin deepwater 
sand-rich systems. Mud intraclast contribution was very low during the Albian. There is 
a step of average intraclast content around 10% from Cenomanian to Lower Oligocene. 
During the Upper Oligocene and the Miocene the intraclast contribution dropped to 
around 5%. 

Figure 29 - Average content of glaucony in the main Campos Basin turbidite reservoirs. 
The background glaucony content is very low (below 0.5%), but there are significant 
peaks in the Paleocene, Upper Eocene and Miocene (above 2%). 

Figure 30 - Average content of micaceous grains in the main Campos Basin deepwater 
sand-rich systems. Observe the oscillation in the amount of micaceous grains between 
1% and 3%, and the overall trend of decrease (dashed arrow) from 3.5% in the Albian to 
0.5% in the Miocene. 

Figure 31 - Location of the seismic sections used in the structural analysis of basement 
reactivations (sections A, B, C, D, E, F, G, and H). The map was composed with the 
basement structure, in the offshore portion to the right of the coast line, and the digital 
topographic model of the continental margin, to the left of the coast line. 

 



 111

Figure 32 - (a) Seismic attribute map of Barremian horizon and insert with kinematical 
interpretation. (b) 3D perspective with seismic section and attribute map of Barremian 
horizon. (c) Depth-converted seismic section (see the regional position of section A in 
Fig. 31). Observe Lower-Cretaceous strata folded at Albian-Cenomanian transition. 
Fold axes are indicated by darker high maximum curvature trends. The structure is 
interpreted as a result of transpression related to left-lateral strike-slip reactivation of 
NE-SW basement fabric. SHmax is the maximum horizontal stress. Observe also the 
Paleogene volcanic structure. 

Figure 33 - (a) Dip map of Albian horizon and insert with kinematic interpretation. 
Observe mixed S and Z sinuous pattern of en-echelon fold axes at Albian strata. The 
structure can be interpreted as a change from right-lateral to left-lateral reactivation of 
NNW-SSE basement fabric associated with rotation of regional loading stresses. (b) 3D 
perspective with seismic section and attribute map of Albian horizon. Observe that low 
Dip values define very well the fold axes at Albian successions of the early divergent 
margin phase. (c) Depth-converted seismic section (see the regional position of section 
B in Fig. 31). Observe that pre-Aptian strata of the rift phase are also faulted and folded. 
Observe possible buttress effect of the basement high. SHmax is the maximum 
horizontal stress. 

Figure 34 - (a) Structural map of Albian horizon and insert with kinematic 
interpretation. Observe the pattern of en-echelon fold axes at Albian strata. The 
structure can be interpreted as a right-lateral reactivation of NE-SW basement fabric. (b) 
3D perspective with seismic section and structural map of Albian horizon. Observe 
folding of Albian and Upper Cretaceous strata. (c) Depth-converted seismic section (see 
the regional position of section C in Fig. 31). Observe that only pre-Maastrichtian strata 
are folded. SHmax is the maximum horizontal stress. 

Figure 35 - (a) Structural map of Santonian horizon showing an anticline trending NE-
SW and plunging to NE. (b) 3D perspective of the anticline. (c) Depth-converted 
seismic section showing a large fold with 3 km half-wavelength, and around 300 m 
amplitude (see the regional position of section D in Fig. 31). Up to 2700 m of Upper 
Cretaceous and Paleogene strata were folded during the Eocene. The main deformation 
phase is indicated by onlap and section growth in the Eocene. The structure is 
interpreted as a fault propagation fold associated with inversion of Albian listric normal 
faults. Inversion was caused by transpression along NW-SE basement fabric at 
northeastern Campos Basin. The structure is contiguous to the folded area of Figure 32. 

Figure 36 - (a) Semblance map of Maastrichtian horizon showing a NNE-SSW fault 
system. (b) Depth-converted seismic section of the fault system (see the regional 
position of section E in Fig. 31). Observe fault activity and section growth during the 
Paleogene indicated by black bars. (c) Stereonet contour plot of the faults mapped in the 
area showing a quite dispersed distribution (188 fault poles). Faulting is interpreted as a 
negative flower structure associated with transtension caused by reactivation of NE-SW 
basement fabric. 

Figure 37 - (a) Structural map of Lower Miocene horizon showing an anticline trending 
NE-SW. (b) 3D perspective of the structure. (c) Depth-converted seismic sections 
showing an inversion fold (see the regional position of sections F and G in Fig. 31). 
Observe that Paleogene depocenters (indicated by black bars) were inverted during 
Neogene. Fold axial plane is vertical and oriented at N40E. Folding was probably 
caused by transpression related to reactivation of basement fabric at the observed 
structural high. 



 112

Figure 38 - (a) Structural map of Oligocene horizon showing an anticline trending N-S, 
and plunging to the north. (b) 3D perspective of the structure. (c) Depth-converted 
seismic section showing an inverted grabben (see the regional position of section H in 
Fig. 31). Observe the constant isopach of the Paleogene, between Oligocene and 
Maastrichtian (pre-kinematic). The inversion of the Cretaceous depocenter in the 
Neogene is indicated by the sin-kinematic onlap pattern (dashed circle). The inversion 
was probably caused by transpression related to reactivation of the basement highs. 

Figure 39 - Correlation between the drift of the South-American plate above the 
Trindade mantle plume and the evolution of the petrographic parameters of the 
deepwater sandstones in Campos Basin. Observe that the passage of the Campos Basin 
above the plume is associated with a consistent trend of increasing compositional and 
textural immaturity with average lower quartz to feldspar ratio (Q/F) and coarser grain 
size from the Santonian to the Eocene. Observe also that the average high contribution 
of volcanic rock fragments (VRF) corresponds to a shorter time interval from the 
Campanian to the Paleocene, when the plume was at the basin margin. 

Figure 40 - Correlation between the main petrographic parameters of the deepwater 
sandstones and the geodynamic processes during the divergent margin phase in Campos 
Basin. Plume effects include dynamic uplift and magmatism. Observe that the two 
major deepwater sand-rich systems in Campos Basin (Bruhn et al., 2003), indicated 
with black stars, were formed at the end of periods of tectonic quiescence. 



 113

 
Well Age Age (Ma BP) Core (m) Thin Sections 

Well 10 Miocene 16.5 110 10 
Well 08/Well 09 Upper Oligocene 23.5 190 18 

Well 07 Lower Oligocene 31 100 8 
Well 06 Upper Eocene 41 20 6 
Well 06 Middle Eocene 47 30 10 
Well 06 Paleocene 58 50 8 
Well 05 Maastrichtian 65 80 10 
Well 04 Campanian 72 30 10 
Well 03 Santonian 84 100 10 
Well 02 Cenomanian 94 140 14 
Well 01 Albian 98 140 17 

  Total 990 121 

Table 1 

 

 

 

 
Reservoir Q/F Grain Size  VRF (%) CI (%) Intracl (%) Glauc (%) Mica (%) 
Miocene 0.91 Fine sand 0.40 7.85 5.03 2.02 0.33 

Upper Oligocene 1.40 Fine sand 1.29 3.87 4.66 0.17 0.35 
Lower Oligocene 0.82    Fine sand 0.08 5.65 11.10 0.06 1.21 
Upper Eocene 0.71 Medium sand 0.72 18.15 9.74 4.80 2.94 
Middle Eocene 0.77 Medium sand 1.39 0.54 12.75 0.54 1.00 

Paleocene 0.75 Medium sand 4.54 5.76 13.44 2.41 1.75 
Maastrichtian 0.65 Medium sand 8.67 0.00 7.90 0.04 3.47 
Campanian 0.69 Medium sand 3.10 0.30 11.46 0.00 3.23 
Santonian 0.88 Medium sand 0.03 1.52 13.75 0.31 1.00 

Cenomanian 1.00 Fine sand 0.62 5.43 11.10 0.30 2.95 
Albian 1.02 Fine sand 0.78 13.42 0.82 0.12 3.53 

Table 2 

 
 
 
 

Age Structural Style Kinematics Position in the basin 

Neogene Inversion fold; inverted grabben 
Transpression or 

compression Center; Northeastern 

Paleogene Fault-propagation fold; negative flower 
Transpression; 

transtension Northeastern; Center 

Santonian Regular folds with sinuous axes Transpression Northeastern 

Albian-Cenomanian Regular folds with sinuous axes Transpression South; Northeastern 

Table 3 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 114

Deepwater 
system Petrography 

Internal 
pattern 

Geodynamic 
Control 

Stratigraphic 
Control Relief Shelf 

Miocene Relativ. Mature Trend 
Tectonic 

reactivation Downstream Moderate Wide 

Upper 
Oligocene 

Relativ. 
Mature Cyclic/Trend 

Escarpment 
retreat Downstream Low Wide 

Lower 
Oligocene 

Relativ. 
Mature Episodic 

Escarpment 
retreat Downstream Moderate Short 

Upper Eocene Immature Episodic Tectonic reactivation Upstream High Short 

Middle 
Eocene Immature Episodic 

Tectonic 
reactivation Upstream High Short 

Paleocene Immature Episodic Tectonic reactivation Upstream High Short 

Maastrichtian Immature Episodic Dynamic uplift Upstream High Null 

Campanian Immature Episodic Dynamic uplift Upstream High Null 

Santonian Immature Episodic Tectonic reactivation Upstream High Null 

Cenomanian Relativ. Mature Episodic 
Escarpment 

retreat Downstream Moderate Short 

Albian Relativ. Mature Cyclic/Trend 
Escarpment 

retreat Downstream Low Wide 

Table 4 



 115

 
Figure 1 

  

 
Figure 2  



 116

 
Figure 3 



 117

 
Figure 4 

 

 
Figure 5  



 118

 
Figure 6  

 
Figure 7  



 119

 
Figure 8  



 120

 
Figure 9  



 121

 
Figure 10  

   

 

 



 122

 
Figure 11  



 123

 

Figure 12  



 124

 
Figure 13  

 
 
 



 125

 
Figure 14  

 
 
 

 



 126

 
Figure 15  

 
 
 

 



 127

 
Figure 16  

 
 
 



 128

 
Figure 17  

 
 
 



 129

 
Figure 18  

 
 
 



 130

 
Figure 19  



 131

 

Figure 20  

 



 132

 
Figure 21  



 133

 
Figure 22  



 134

 

Figure 23  



 135

 
Figure 24  

 



 136

 
Figure 25  



 137

 
Figure 26  

 
 
 



 138

 
Figure 27  



 139

 

Figure 28  



 140

 

Figure 29  



 141

 
Figure 30  

 

 
Figure 31  

 



 142

 
Figure 32  



 143

 
Figure 33  



 144

 

Figure 34  



 145

 

Figure 35  



 146

 
Figure 36  

 
Figure 37  



 147

 
Figure 38  



 148

 
Figure 39  

 
Figure 40  

 

 



 149

Anexos 



 150

Anexo A 

Comprovantes de Recebimento dos Artigos Submetidos 



 151

Anexo B 

CD com Planilhas de Descrição Petrográfica 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 


	Abstract 
	 
	Section
	 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>