<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.18530</field>
		<field name="filename">25523_S1678-77572005000200021.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
S

D

ABSTRACT

RESUMO

www.fob.usp.br/revista or www.scielo.br/jaos

EVALUATION OF THE BLEACHED HUMAN ENAMEL
BY SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY

AVALIAÇÃO DO ESMALTE DENTAL HUMANO SUBMETIDO AO TRATAMENTO
CLAREADOR POR MEIO DE MICROSCOPIA ELETRÔNICA DE VARREDURA

Carolina Baptista MIRANDA1, Clovis PAGANI2, Ana Raquel BENETTI1, Fábio da Silva MATUDA3

1- DDS, MSc, Graduate student (Master degree), Department of Restorative Dentistry, São José dos Campos School of Dentistry  - UNESP.
2- DDS, MSc, PhD, Associate Professor, Department of Restorative Dentistry, São José dos Campos School of Dentistry - UNESP.
3- DDS, MSc, PhD, Graduate student (Doctor degree), Department of Restorative Dentistry, São José dos Campos School of Dentistry - UNESP.

Corresponding address: Carolina Baptista Miranda - Rua Guillard Muniz, 75 apto. 1301 - Pituba - Salvador / BA Cep.: 41810-110
Fone: (071) 3451-7992 ou 8114-5536 - carolinabmiranda@superig.com.br

Received: March 15, 2004 - Modification: May 12, 2004 - Accepted: September 28, 2004

 ince bleaching has become a popular procedure, the effect of peroxides on dental hard tissues is of great interest in research. Purpose: The aim
of this in vitro study was to perform a qualitative analysis of the human enamel after the application of in-office bleaching agents, using Scanning
Electron Microscopy (SEM). Materials and Methods: Twenty intact human third molars extracted for orthodontic reasons were randomly divided
into four groups (n=5) treated as follows: G1- storage in artificial saliva (control group); G2- four 30-minute applications of 35% carbamide
peroxide (total exposure: 2h); G3- four 2-hour exposures to 35% carbamide peroxide (total exposure: 8h); G4- two applications of 35% hydrogen
peroxide, which was light-activated with halogen lamp at 700mW/cm2 during 7min and remained in contact with enamel for 20min (total
exposure: 40min). All bleaching treatments adopted in this study followed the application protocols advised by manufacturers. Evaluation of
groups submitted to 35% carbamide peroxide was carried out after two time intervals (30 minutes and 2 hours per session), following the extreme
situations recommended by the manufacturer. Specimens were prepared for SEM analysis performing gold sputter coating under vacuum and were
examined using 15kV at 500x and 2000x magnification. Results: Morphological alterations on the enamel surface were similarly detected after
bleaching with either 35% carbamide peroxide or 35% hydrogen peroxide. Surface porosities were characteristic of an erosive process that took
place on human enamel. Depression areas, including the formation of craters, and exposure of enamel rods could also be detected. Conclusion:
Bleaching effects on enamel morphology were randomly distributed throughout enamel surface and various degrees of enamel damage could be
noticed. Clinical significance: In-office bleaching materials may adversely affect enamel morphology and therefore should be used with caution.
Uniterms: Hydrogen peroxide; Carbamide peroxide; Tooth bleaching.

  esde o aumento da popularidade de tratamentos clareadores, o interesse em se pesquisar os efeitos dos peróxidos nos tecidos dentais duros é
crescente. Proposta: O objetivo deste trabalho foi conduzir uma análise qualitativa in vitro do esmalte dental humano após clareamento com
agentes para consultório, por meio de Microscopia Eletrônica de Varredura (MEV). Material e métodos: Foram utilizados 20 terceiros molares
humanos hígidos, extraídos por motivos ortodônticos, sendo aleatoriamente divididos em 4 grupos (n=5) e tratados da seguinte forma: G1-
armazenamento em saliva artificial (grupo controle); G2- 4 aplicações de peróxido de carbamida a 35% por 30 min (tempo total de aplicação: 2h);
G3- 4 aplicações de peróxido de carbamida a 35% por 2 h (tempo total de aplicação: 8h); G4- 2 aplicações de peróxido de hidrogênio a 35%, que
foi foto-ativado com lâmpada halógena a 700mW/cm2 por 7 min e mantido em contato com o dente durante 20 min (tempo total de aplicação:
40min). A avaliação dos grupos submetidos ao clareamento com peróxido de carbamida a 35% após 2 tempos de aplicação (30 minutos e 2 horas
por sessão) para testar as situações extremas recomendadas pelo fabricante. As amostras foram recobertas com ouro para análise em MEV e foram
examinadas utilizando 15kV e aumentos de 500x e 2000x. Resultados: Foram detectadas alterações morfológicas similares na superfície do esmalte
após o clareamento com peróxido de carbamida a 35% e peróxido de hidrogênio a 35%. Porosidades e irregularidades caracterizando um processo
erosivo foram observadas no esmalte humano. Áreas de depressão, incluindo a formação de crateras e exposição dos prismas de esmalte também
foram observadas. Conclusão: Os efeitos do clareamento na morfologia do esmalte encontraram-se distribuídos aleatoriamente por toda a
superfície do esmalte e danos em diferentes intensidades puderam ser evidenciados. Significância clínica: Agentes concentrados para clareamento
em consultório podem comprometer a morfologia do esmalte e, portanto, devem ser utilizados com cautela.
Unitermos: Peróxido de hidrogênio; Peróxido de carbamida; Clareamento de dente.

204

J Appl Oral Sci 2005; 13(2): 204-11



INTRODUCTION

Esthetics has strongly influenced patient’s perceptions
and appealed to the development and expansion of the
cosmetic industry. Inevitably, the request of whiter teeth
has become a major concern in dental practice since
discoloration of a single tooth or a group of teeth negatively
interferes with the harmony of smile. Although tooth color
is only one of the aspects involved in facial harmony, it
represents the most important isolated factor because it is
immediately noticed1.

Esthetic dentistry has introduced various corrective
measures to treat discolored teeth, such as laminate veneers,
direct resin restorations, crowns or fixed prostheses. Dental
bleaching represents a conservative treatment option or may
become an auxiliary therapy when restorative procedures
are required to eliminate color abnormalities2.

Bleaching agents are provided for in-office or at-home
therapies. In-office bleaching requires less patient’s
cooperation, but longer sessions are necessary in the dental
office, which increases the treatment costs. Otherwise, at-
home bleaching is less expensive, but patient’s collaboration
is essential to obtain successful treatment results3.

Hydrogen peroxide is the main active ingredient of
bleaching agents and the whitening effect it produces is
due to its low molecular weight and its ability to penetrate
through enamel and dentin1,4. The basic process involves
oxidation and reduction reactions that convert organic
pigments into carbon dioxide and water1,5. Carbamide
peroxide decomposes into urea and hydrogen peroxide5.
Therefore, products containing the same concentration but
different active ingredients are expected to behave
differently on dental hard tissues. Such behavior might
become even more evident when considering regular or
light-activated gels or distinct exposure periods.

Although dental hard tissues are highly mineralized, their
organic content can play an important role in the bleaching
process. It is speculated that the reaction between peroxide
and organic materials on the surface or in the subsurface of
enamel can result in morphological alterations6.

Despite the advantages offered by the bleaching
treatment, the effect of bleaching agents on dental hard
tissues is rather controversial. Some studies have
demonstrated no significant effects of bleaching agents on
human enamel 4,7. Contrary results have shown
morphological alterations on bleached enamel, thus
suggesting an erosive process8, 9, 10, 11.

Since bleaching has been widely advocated by dental
professionals, the effect of bleaching agents on dental hard
tissues is of great interest in research. Therefore, the purpose
of this in vitro study was to investigate the influence of in-
office bleaching agents on human enamel morphology,
comparing 35% carbamide peroxide or 35% light-activated
hydrogen peroxide.

MATERIALS AND METHODS

This study was developed in accordance with the Code
of Ethics in Research (nº063/2001 PH/CEP). Twenty intact
human third molars extracted for orthodontic reasons were
selected for this study. Immediately after extraction,
periodontal tissue was removed and teeth were stored in
saline solution at -20°C for a maximum period of 28 days12.
Prior to group division, teeth were examined at a
stereomicroscope Stemi 2000 (Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany) at
20x magnification to select teeth without cracks or structural
defects that could compromise the results of the study.

All teeth were submitted to mesio-distal crosscut
sections to separate buccal and lingual fragments. Horizontal
sections were performed at the cementoenamel junction,
separating coronary and root pieces. Buccal sections were
selected for the SEM analysis and randomly divided into
four groups of five specimens each, treated as follows:

· Group 1: no bleaching treatment was performed. All
buccal sections were kept in artificial saliva at 37ºC until
SEM analysis was performed.

· Group 2: buccal sections were placed in contact with
35% carbamide peroxide (Opalescence Quick, batch #479B,
Ultradent, South Jordan, Utah, United States), facing a Petri
dish containing the gel. Product was heated in warm water
prior to use, following the manufacturer’s recommendation.
Specimens were kept in contact with the bleaching agent
for 30 minutes. Next, specimens were rinsed with distilled
water and stored in artificial saliva at 37°C. This procedure
was repeated weekly in four applications (total exposure:
2h).

· Group 3: bleaching protocol followed steps determined
for group 3, but adopting a longer exposure period. Two-
hour applications of 35% carbamide peroxide (Opalescence
Quick, batch #479B, Ultradent, South Jordan, Utah, United
States) were performed weekly for four weeks (total exposure:
8h). Variation in the exposure period was determined since
the manufacturer suggested a minimum of 30-minute and
maximum of 2-hour exposure. Therefore, minimum time
exposure was investigated in group 2 while maximum
exposure period was evaluated in group 3.

· Group 4: two 20-minute applications of 35% hydrogen
peroxide (Opalescence X-tra, batch #532B, Ultradent, South
Jordan, Utah, United States) were performed in accordance
to manufacturer’s recommendation. Gel was applied on
enamel specimens and light-activation was performed
initially for 5 minutes. The light source used was Curing
Light XL3000 (3M ESPE) at 700mW/cm2. Four extra 30-
second light-activations were carried out every 3.5min during
the 15-minute period that the gel remained in contact with
enamel. Therefore, total light activation was performed for 7
minutes during gel contact of 20 minutes. Teeth were rinsed
with distilled water to remove the gel and bleaching protocol
was repeated (total exposure: 40 minutes).

After carrying out bleaching protocols, teeth were rinsed
and stored in artificial saliva at 37ºC for 24 hours. The artificial
saliva contained calcium chloride (0.16g), sodium benzoate
(1g), carboxymethyl cellulose (10g), magnesium chloride

205

EVALUATION OF THE BLEACHED HUMAN ENAMEL BY SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY



(0.05g), potassium chloride (0.62g), sodium chloride (0.82g),
sodium fluoride (4.29g), sorbitol (42.74g), potassium
phosphate (1.12g), and distilled water up to 100ml. Teeth
were rinsed thoroughly prior to SEM investigation.

Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM)
investigation

Twenty-four hours after bleaching, specimens were
dehydrated in ascending grades of ethanol. Twenty-minute
immersion in each solution was performed at concentrations
of 50%, 60%, 70%, 80%, and 90% ethanol. Sixty-minute
immersion in 100% ethanol was carried out. Specimens dried
at room temperature during 12 hours. Crowns were fixed in
aluminum stubs and then sputter-coated with gold-
palladium (Desk II, Denton Vacuum, Moorestown, NJ, United
States) during 2 minutes.

Enamel surface was examined at 500x and 2000x
magnification with scanning electron microscope (JMS 5310,
JEOL, Tokyo, Japan), using 15kV. A scanning of the entire
buccal surface was performed and most critical areas were
selected for scanning electron microscope
photomicrographs.

RESULTS

Figure 1 depicts unbleached enamel. Although the
surface is not completely smooth, uniformity of the aprismatic
surface layer can be observed. Pores and superficial
irregularities were also present.

Effects of bleaching were randomly distributed on enamel
surface after the application of in-office products (Figures
2, 3, 4, and 5). In fact, different types of defects and distinct
severity of such events could be observed throughout the
enamel surface. Modification of enamel morphology was

detected either after 35% carbamide peroxide (Figures 2 and
3) or 35% hydrogen peroxide applications (Figures 4 and 5).
In general, it seems that bleaching evidenced original
irregularities present on enamel surface. Morphologic
surface alterations became much more pronounced after
bleaching, including partial removal of the aprismatic layer,
increased depth of enamel grooves, and exposure of the
enamel prisms (Figures 2B, 4A, 4B and 5B). An increased
number of porosities on enamel surface could be noticed
(Figures 2A and 5A), when compared to the control group
(Figure 1). Intermittent depressions of various depths were
present (Figures 3A, 3B, 4A and 5B); craters (Figure 2B),
and shallow erosions (Figures 2A and 5A) could also be
observed.

Similar observations were detected on enamel
morphology of teeth treated with either conventional
carbamide peroxide gel or light-activated hydrogen peroxide.
It must be emphasized, however, that the irregularities found
on enamel surface  were more frequently distributed in the
experimental groups, but were also detected on the
unbleached enamel.

DISCUSSION

Effects of bleaching agents on enamel surface have been
discussed recently. When considering in-office bleaching
agents, controversial results have been reported. Thirty-
five percent hydrogen peroxide applications did not produce
morphological alterations on enamel in research conducted
by Ernst, el al.7. Likewise, Gultz, et al.13, who adopted the
same methods of this study and tested the same bleaching
agents (Opalescence Quick and Opalescence X-tra), did not
report significant alterations on the enamel surface. However,
exposure periods determined in their study were shorter
(total exposures of 2 hours for 35% carbamide peroxide and

FIGURE 1- Photomicrographs of unbleached enamel (control group) at 500x (A) and 2000x magnifications (B)

206

MIRANDA C B, PAGANI C, BENETTI A R, MATUDA F da S



8 to 10 minutes for 35% light-activated hydrogen peroxide)
than those stipulated for this investigation (total exposures
of 2 or 8 hours for 35% carbamide peroxide and 40 minutes
for 35% light-activated hydrogen peroxide).

In this study, defects could be randomly detected on the
enamel surface with distinct severity after bleaching. Similar
behavior has been reported in previous studies, even after
10% carbamide peroxide bleaching, which releases lower
amounts of hydrogen peroxide when compared to in-office
bleaching agents. Surface erosion9, depressions14, porosity,
and increased depth of enamel grooves6 were some of the
alterations mentioned.

More severe alterations could be expected on enamel
surface after in-office bleaching. Increased porosity14,15 and
precipitate deposition16 characterized enamel erosion9,17,18.

Depressions6, 19 with crater formation, removal of the
aprismatic layer and exposure of the enamel prisms15,17 could
also be detected. Hegedüs, et al.6 detected a pronounced
increase in the depth of enamel grooves after 30% hydrogen
peroxide bleaching. McGuckin, et al. 1 9 reported
morphological alterations on enamel surface, describing
enamel patterns similar to type II acid etching, after 30%
hydrogen peroxide applications.

Although 35% hydrogen peroxide presents higher
concentration of free hydrogen peroxide when compared to
35% carbamide peroxide gel, no visual difference was
detected between groups treated with such products. Similar
results were probably observed due to the shorter exposure
periods and fewer sessions determined for the light-activated
gel.

FIGURE 2- Photomicrographs of bleached enamel after 35% carbamide peroxide applications at 500x (A and B) and 2000x
magnifications (C and D): removal of the aprismatic layer, craters, pores, and erosion

207

EVALUATION OF THE BLEACHED HUMAN ENAMEL BY SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY



Authors believe that enamel alterations are probably
due to an initial process of demineralization. McCracken
and Haywood20 and Rotstein, et al.21 have proven loss of
calcium in teeth exposed to peroxide. Rotstein, et al.22
observed lower resistance and higher solubility of dental
hard tissues after bleaching procedures, possibly due to
modification of the organic and inorganic ratio of the tissues.
Oltu and Gürgan23 observed changes in the inorganic
composition of the bleached enamel after 35% carbamide
peroxide exposure. Indeed, most bleaching agents are acidic,
which is not favorable to enamel, dentin, and cement. The
pH of bleaching agents investigated in this study was 6.4
and 3.8 for 35% carbamide peroxide (Opalescence Quick)
and 35% hydrogen peroxide (Opalescence X-tra),
respectively.

Although artificial saliva was used in this study to
simulate oral conditions, its remineralization potential is not
equivalent to natural saliva in vivo. Fewer alterations are
expected in vivo, due to the buffer capacity of saliva.
Rodrigues, et al.24 reminded that saliva and fluoride ions
present in oral care substances are essential to equilibrate
the demineralization and remineralization processes.
According to Lopes, et al.25, pH values as low as 6.4 may
remove minerals from teeth in in vitro situations; thus,
artificial saliva might not be able to guarantee remineralization.

In vivo or in vitro bleaching, various concentrations
and exposure periods to bleaching agents, use of different
substances prior to treatment, sample size, and evaluation
criteria are distinct among different research studies. Thus,
a comparison between studies becomes rather difficult.

FIGURE 3- Photomicrographs of bleached enamel after 35% carbamide peroxide applications at 500x (A and B) and 2000x
magnifications (C and D): depressions and increased depth of enamel irregularities

208

MIRANDA C B, PAGANI C, BENETTI A R, MATUDA F da S



However, most papers are in agreement with findings
reported in this study, which detected significant changes
on the enamel surface after bleaching with concentrated
hydrogen or carbamide peroxide. Therefore, caution is
required when performing in-office bleaching.

Significant changes in the enamel morphology and
microstructure produced by bleaching agents are
suggestive of alterations in physical and mechanical
properties of dental hard tissues10, 25, 26, 27. Indeed, further
studies are necessary to completely understand the effects
of bleaching agents on dental tissues.

CONCLUSION

SEM qualitative investigation demonstrated that in-
office bleaching agents affected human enamel morphology,
producing porosities, depressions, craters, increased depth
of enamel grooves, and partial removal of enamel prisms.
These defects were randomly distributed and affected the
enamel surface at various degrees.

Clinical implications

In-office bleaching materials may adversely affect enamel
morphology and therefore should be used with caution.

FIGURE 4- Photomicrographs of bleached enamel after 35% hydrogen peroxide applications at 500x (A and B) and 2000x
magnifications (C and D): depressions, removal of the aprismatic layer, and increased depth of enamel irregularities

209

EVALUATION OF THE BLEACHED HUMAN ENAMEL BY SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY



FIGURE 5- Photomicrographs of bleached enamel after 35% hydrogen peroxide applications at 500x (A and B) and 2000x
magnifications (C and D): partial removal of the aprismatic layer, pores, depressions and erosions

REFERENCES

1- Baratieri LN. Clareamento dental. 3rd ed. São Paulo: Quintessence
Books; 1993. 176p.

2- Miranda CB, Benetti AR, Pagani C. Inovação no clareamento
dental caseiro – Crest Whitestrips: combinação de gel em fitas. J Bras
Clin Estet Odontol. 2002;6: 291-4.

3- Papathanasiou A, Bardwell D, Kugel G. A clinical study evaluating
a new chairside and take-home whitening system. Compend Contin
Educ Dent. 2001;22:289-97.

4- Haywood VB, Leech T, Heymann HO, Crumpler D, Bruggers K.
Nightguard vital bleaching: effects on enamel surface texture and
diffusion. Quintessence Int. 1990;21:801-4.

5- Haywood VB, Houck V, Heymann HO. Nightguard vital bleaching:
effects of various solutions on enamel surface texture and color.
Quintessence Int. 1991;22:775-82.

6- Hegedüs C, Bistey T, Flora-Nagy E, Keszthelyi G, Jenei A. An
atomic force microscopy study on the effect of bleaching agents on
enamel surface. J Dent. 1999;27:509-15.

7- Ernst CP, Marroquin BB, Willershausen-Zönnchen B. Effects of
hydrogen peroxide-containing bleaching agents on the morphology
of human enamel. Quintessence Int. 1996;27:53-6.

8- Ledoux WR, Malloy RB, Hurst RV, McInnes-Ledoux P, Weinberg
R. Structural effects of bleaching on tetracycline-stained vital rat
teeth. J Prosthet Dent. 1985;54:55-9.

210

MIRANDA C B, PAGANI C, BENETTI A R, MATUDA F da S



9- Covington JS, Friend GN, Lamoreaux WJ, Perry T. Carbamide
peroxide tooth bleaching: effects on enamel composition and
topography [abstract 530]. J Dent Res. 1990;69(Spec Issue):175.

10- Bitter NC. Scanning electron microscopy study of the effect of
bleaching agents on enamel: a preliminary report. J Prosthet Dent.
1992;67:852-5.

11- Shannon H, Spencer P, Gross K, Tira D. Characterization of
enamel exposed to 10% carbamide peroxide bleaching agents.
Quintessence Int. 1993;24:39-44.

12- Tonami K, Takahashi H, Nishimura F. Effect of frozen storage
and boiling on tensile strength of bovine dentin. Dent Mater J.
1996;15:205-11.

13- Gultz J, Kaim J, Scherer W, Gupta H. Two in-office bleaching
systems: a scanning electron microscope study. Compend Contin
Educ Dent. 1999;20:965-9.

14- Josey AL, Meyers IA, Romaniuk K, Symons AL. The effect of a
vital bleaching technique on enamel surface morphology and the
bonding of composite resin to enamel. J Oral Reahabil. 1996;23:244-
5 0 .

15- Bitter NC. A scanning electron microscope study of the long-
term effect of bleaching agents on the enamel surface in vivo. Gen
Dent. 1998;46:84-8.

16- Titley K, Torneck CD, Smith D. The effect of concentrated
hydrogen peroxide solutions on the surface morphology of human
tooth enamel. J Endod. 1988;14:69-74.

17- Bitter NC, Sanders JL. The effect of four bleaching agents on the
enamel surface: a scanning electron microscopic study. Quintessence
Int. 1993;24:817-24.

18- Junqueira JC, Colombo CED, Martins CAP, Tavares PG, Araújo
MAM, Valera, MC. Efeito da técnica de clareamento, utilizando
peróxido de carbamida a 35%, sobre o esmalte dental: avaliação por
microscópio de luz polarizada e microscópio eletrônico de varredura.
J Bras Clin Estet Odontol. 2000;4:61-5.

19- McGuckin RS, Babin JF, Meyer BJ. Alterations in human enamel
surface morphology following vital bleaching. J Prosthet Dent.
1992;68:754-60.

20- McCracken MS, Haywood VB. Demineralization effects of 10
percent carbamide peroxide. J Dent. 1996;24:395-8.

21- Rotstein I, Dankner E, Goldman A, Heling I, Stabholtz A, Zalkind
M. Histochemical analysis of dental hard tissues following bleaching.
J Endod. 1996;22:23-5.

22- Rotstein I, Lehr Z, Gedalia I. Effect of bleaching agents on
inorganic components of human dentin and cementum. J Endod.
1992;18:290-3.

23- Oltu Ü, Gürgan S. Effects of three concentrations of carbamide
peroxide on the structure of enamel. J Oral Rehabil. 2000;27:332-
4 0 .

24- Rodrigues JA, Basting RT, Serra MC, Rodrigues Junior AL. Effects
of 10% carbamide peroxide bleaching materials on enamel
microhardness. Am J Dent. 2001;14:67-71.

25- Lopes GC, Bonissoni L, Baratieri LN, Vieira LC, Monteiro Junior
S. Effect of bleaching agents on the hardness and morphology of
enamel. J Esthet Restor Dent. 2002;14:24-30.

26- Seghi RR, Denry I. Effects of external bleaching on indentation
and abrasion characteristics of human enamel in vitro. J Dent Res.
1992;71:1340-4.

27- Miranda CB. Avaliação da microdureza e tenacidade do esmalte
dental humano submetido ao tratamento clareador; São José dos
Campos; 2003. 132f. [Dissertação de Mestrado - Faculdade de
Odontologia de São José dos Campos, Universidade Estadual Paulista].

211

EVALUATION OF THE BLEACHED HUMAN ENAMEL BY SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY


</field>
	</doc>
</add>