<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.21274</field>
		<field name="filename">4991_327913.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE SANTA CATARINA
DEPARTAMENTO DE ENGENHARIA MECA?NICA

Julian Esteban Barrera Torres

USO DOS CICLOS RANKINE ORGA?NICOS PARA O
APROVEITAMENTO DO CALOR RESIDUAL EM

INSTALAC?O?ES DE PRODUC?A?O DE PETRO?LEO E GA?S

Floriano?polis

2014





Julian Esteban Barrera Torres

USO DOS CICLOS RANKINE ORGA?NICOS PARA O
APROVEITAMENTO DO CALOR RESIDUAL EM

INSTALAC?O?ES DE PRODUC?A?O DE PETRO?LEO E GA?S

Dissertac?a?o submetida ao Programa
de Po?s-Graduac?a?o em Engenharia Meca?nica
para a obtenc?a?o do Grau de Mestre
em Engenharia Meca?nica.
Orientador: Edson Bazzo, Dr.Eng.

Floriano?polis

2014



Catalogac?a?o na fonte elaborada pela biblioteca da
Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina



Julian Esteban Barrera Torres

USO DOS CICLOS RANKINE ORGA?NICOS PARA O
APROVEITAMENTO DO CALOR RESIDUAL EM

INSTALAC?O?ES DE PRODUC?A?O DE PETRO?LEO E GA?S

Esta Dissertac?a?o foi julgada aprovada para a obtenc?a?o do T??tulo
de “Mestre em Engenharia Meca?nica”, e aprovada em sua forma final
pelo Programa de Po?s-Graduac?a?o em Engenharia Meca?nica.

Floriano?polis, 01 de Abril 2014.

Armando Albertazzi Gonc?alves Jr, Dr.Eng.
Coordenador do Curso

Edson Bazzo, Dr.Eng.
Orientador

Banca Examinadora:

Edson Bazzo, Dr.Eng.
Presidente

Silvio de Oliveira Junior, Dr.Eng

Ricardo Antonio Machado, Dr.Eng.

Alexandre Kupka da Silva, Ph.D.





For anyone who reads this dissertation
with a purpose.





ACKNOWLEDGMENTS

I would like to express my very great appreciation to Professor
Edson Bazzo for his valuable and constructive suggestions during the
planning and development of this research work. His willingness to give
his time so generously has been very much appreciated.

I would also like to express my deep gratitude to Professor Silvio
Oliveira, Professor Ricardo Machado and Professor Alexandre Kupka,
my research examining board, for their enthusiastic encouragement and
useful critiques of this research work.

Special thanks should be given to Eduardo Kami, for his profes-
sional guidance and constructive recommendations on this project.

Finally, I wish to thank my parents for their support and encou-
ragement throughout my study.





Our intelligence and our technology have
given us the power to affect the climate.
How will we use this power? Are we wil-
ling to tolerate ignorance and complacency
in matters that affect the entire human
family? Do we value short-term advan-
tages above the welfare of the Earth? Or
will we think on longer time scales, with
concern for our children and our grand-
children, to understand and protect the
complex life-support systems of our pla-
net? The Earth is a tiny and fragile world.
It needs to be cherished.

Carl Sagan, Cosmos (1980)





RESUMO

A presente dissertac?a?o contempla o melhoramento do desempenho de
uma plataforma de processamento de o?leo e ga?s por meio da incor-
porac?a?o hipote?tica de um ciclo Rankine orga?nico (ORC). Esse ciclo
termodina?mico recuperaria parte do calor residual associado aos gases
de exausta?o das turbinas na planta, para gerac?a?o de pote?ncia adicio-
nal, permitindo um decre?scimo na carga das mesmas e, portanto no
consumo de combust??vel. O modelamento do processo foi desenvolvido
com o propo?sito de caracterizar a operac?a?o normal da plataforma e
assim estabelecer as condic?o?es de refere?ncia para comparar o desempe-
nho energe?tico da mesma. A partir da informac?a?o obtida do modelo,
uma ana?lise exerge?tica permitiu identificar as operac?o?es com maior ir-
reversibilidade e tambe?m com potencial para recuperac?a?o da exergia
perdida. Ale?m disso demonstrou diferenc?as significativas na ordem de
grandeza entre os fluxos de exergia associados a?s correntes de o?leo e
ga?s produzidos e as demais correntes relacionadas com o seu proces-
samento. Considerando isto, foram considerados tre?s indicadores de
eficie?ncia, dois relacionados com os fluxos de exergia e um relacionado
com o gasto energe?tico. De outro lado, o sistema ORC foi definido
tendo em conta os resultados de estudos recentes focados na selec?a?o
do fluido de trabalho e na configurac?a?o do ciclo, visando as melhores
condic?o?es de operac?a?o do ciclo enquadrado dentro das restric?o?es impos-
tas pelo processo. Considerando a grande variabilidade dos para?metros
de produc?a?o deste tipo de instalac?a?o, a comparac?a?o dos resultados do
modelo incluindo o ORC integrado com o processo foi feita ao longo de
um perfil de produc?a?o que contempla a variac?a?o de cinco para?metros
de maneira independente: (i) vaza?o de o?leo, (ii) vaza?o de a?gua de
produc?a?o, (iii) pressa?o de poc?o, (iv) vaza?o de ga?s injetado e (v) vaza?o de
a?gua injetada. Os resultados mostraram que a implementac?a?o do ciclo
traz um melhoramento dos indicadores de eficie?ncia energe?tica propos-
tos, independentemente da variac?a?o nos para?metros de produc?a?o, com
um melhoramento dos indicadores relativamente uniforme ao longo do
perfil analisado. Os para?metros de produc?a?o com maior impacto so-
bre a pote?ncia gerada pelo ORC correspondem a?s vazo?es de ga?s e de
a?gua injetadas no reservato?rio, sendo essas as operac?o?es que demandam
maior pote?ncia e portanto uma maior produc?a?o de gases de exausta?o
nas turbinas. Em geral, a metodologia adotada pretende avaliar o im-
pacto de uma tecnologia para o melhoramento da eficie?ncia energe?tica



(nesse caso o ORC) em um processo industrial existente, considerando
a caracterizac?a?o detalhada do processo em questa?o e a variac?a?o dos
para?metros mais relevantes de produc?a?o, de tal forma que os resulta-
dos oferec?am um panorama mais amplo na hora de aplicar este tipo de
sistema.
Palavras-chave: Eficie?ncia Energe?tica, Processamento de O?leo e Ga?s,
Ana?lise Exerge?tica, Ciclo Rankine Orga?nico, FPSO.



ABSTRACT

The present dissertation contemplates the energy performance enhance-
ment of an oil and gas processing platform by means of the hypothetical
incorporation of an Organic Rankine Cycle (ORC). This thermodyna-
mic cycle would recover part of the waste heat associated with exhaust
gases coming from gas turbines in order to produce additional power,
allowing a decrease in their load and consequently in their fuel consump-
tion. The process modeling was developed with the aim of characte-
rizing the plant normal operation and thereby establish the reference
conditions for comparing its energy efficiency. With the information
obtained from the model, a detailed exergy analysis enabled the identi-
fication of the operations with greatest irreversibility and with potential
for the exergy losses recovering. In addition, it showed a great diffe-
rence between the exergy fluxes associated with produced oil and gas
streams when compared with the other streams associated with their
processing. Considering that, the use of three energy efficiency indi-
cators was analyzed, two of these indicators are related to the exergy
fluxes and the other with the energetic expense. On the other side, the
ORC system was defined taking into account the results of recent stu-
dies focused on the selection of the ORC working fluid and the ORC
configuration, aiming the best operating conditions framed into pro-
cess constraints. Considering the great variability of the production
parameters in this kind of installations, the comparison of the model
results with the ORC integrated was made along a production profile
that comprises the variation of five parameters independently: (i) oil
flow, (ii) production water flow, (iii) well pressure, (iv) injected gas flow
and (v) injected water flow. The results demonstrated that the imple-
mentation of the ORC improves the proposed indicators, independently
of the variation of the chosen production parameters. The energy im-
provement was found relatively uniform along the production profile.
The production parameters with a greater impact over the ORC output
correspond to the gas and water flows injected back into the reservoir.
These operations demand the highest amount of power and thus the
greatest production of exhaust gases at gas turbines. This procedure
pretends to evaluate the effect of an energy enhancement technology
(in this case the ORC) in an existing process, characterizing its beha-
vior under variable production conditions. In this way, the results can
give a wider panorama when applying this kind of systems for energy



performance improvement.
Keywords: Energy Efficiency, Oil and Gas Processing, Exergy Analy-
sis, Organic Rankine Cycle, FPSO.



LIST OF FIGURES

Figure 1 World oil and gas demand (IEA, 2012). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7

Figure 2 Production profiles of some Brazilian fields (SIMMONS,
2009). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8

Figure 3 Typical operation scheme of an oil and gas production
plant (WILKINSON, 2006). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11

Figure 4 Schemes of most common types of offshore platforms
(MAHONEY, 2013). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13

Figure 5 Basic operation scheme of an FPSO (WILKINSON, 2006). 14

Figure 6 Basic layout of an FPSO topside. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18

Figure 7 Example of an FPSO topside. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 19

Figure 8 Basic PFD of a typical FPSO process plant. . . . . . . . . . . . 20

Figure 9 Basic scheme of an ORC system . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22

Figure 10 Basic scheme of an regenerative ORC system . . . . . . . . . . 23

Figure 11 Types of fluids (HEBERLE; PREIBINGER; BRU?GGEMANN,
2012). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 25

Figure 12 Effect of the enthalpy of vaporization of the working fluid
(BAO; ZHAO, 2013). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 26

Figure 13 Difference between cycle efficiency and power output
(DECLAYE, 2009). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 27

Figure 14 Relation between the critical temperature and the pa-
rameter ? for various candidates (CHEN; GOSWAMI; STEFANAKOS,
2010). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 28

Figure 15 Determination of the normal boiling point (NBP) of each
pseudocomponent (ASPENTECH, 2011). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 37

Figure 16 Specific heat of crude fractions as a function of tempe-
rature and its standard specific gravity (MAXWELL, 1968). . . . . . . . . 39

Figure 17 Heat of combustion of crude fractions as function of its
standard specific gravity (MAXWELL, 1968). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40

Figure 18 Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the separation
plant. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 42

Figure 19 Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the boost system. 44

Figure 20 Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the gas injecti-
on/export system. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45

Figure 21 Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the power gene-



ration system. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 46

Figure 22 Operating parameters of gas turbines (SIEMENS AG, 2009). 47

Figure 23 Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the water injection
system. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 47

Figure 24 Analized production profiles. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 52

Figure 25 Model general algorithm. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 60

Figure 26 Power supply distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65

Figure 27 Rejected heat distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 66

Figure 28 Simplified Grassmann diagram of the plant, exergy flows
in MW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 69

Figure 29 Exergy destruction rate distribution for: (a)-Hysys mo-
del and (b)-EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 71

Figure 30 Exergy losses distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 71

Figure 31 Exergy efficiencies (?p) for Hysys and EES models. . . . . 74

Figure 32 Exergy efficiencies (?p) for Hysys and EES models. . . . . 74

Figure 33 Variation of (i) cyclopentane mass flow, (ii) ORC perfor-
mance, (iii) Rejected heat and (iv) ORC output with the evapora-
tion temperature of cyclopentane. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 76

Figure 34 Variation of the HTF outlet temperature and HTF mass
flow with the evaporation temperature of cyclopentane. . . . . . . . . . . . 77

Figure 35 T-s diagram of the ORC at different evaporation tempe-
ratures. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 78

Figure 36 Variation of ORC input and cyclopentane specific work
with the evaporation temperature. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 79

Figure 37 Total rejected heat vs. ORC Tev for selected scenarios. 82

Figure 38 Total rejected heat (i), power demand (i) and thermal
efficiency of power generation (ii) profiles. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 83

Figure 39 ORC input and output, MW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 84

Figure 40 ?P and ?: (i) for cases 0 through 15 and (ii) for cases 3
through 15. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 85

Figure 41 ?II variation along the production profile. . . . . . . . . . . . . . 87

Figure 42 Influence factor f for each production parameter. (i)
current configuration, (ii) ORC integrated. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 88

Figure 43 Influence factor f for each production parameter applied



in the ORC performance. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 89

Figure 44 Process flow diagram of a power subsystem turbine (A).107

Figure 45 Process flow diagram of the separation plant (B). . . . . . . 108

Figure 46 Process flow diagram of gas boosting subsystem (C). . . 109

Figure 47 Process flow diagram of gas injection/export subsystem
(D). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 109

Figure 48 Process flow diagram of ORC subsystem (F). . . . . . . . . . . 110

Figure 49 Process flow diagram of seawater injection subsystem
(H). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 110

Figure 50 Scheme of operation of EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 130

Figure 51 Scheme of operation of gas boost system in EES model. 131

Figure 52 Scheme of operation of gas injection/export system in
EES model. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 131

Figure 53 TBP curve and normal boiling point (NBP) of each pseu-
docomponent. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 155

Figure 54 Some physical properties and lower heating value (LHV)
of each pseudocomponent. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 157

Figure 55 Elemental composition of each pseudocomponent. . . . . . . 158

Figure 56 Specific heat of crude (oily phase). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 158





LIST OF TABLES

Table 1 RD&amp;amp;D needs for addressing WHR Barriers (BCS, 2008) . 9

Table 2 Simulation input data for separation plant. . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48

Table 3 Simulation input data for boost subsystem. . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48

Table 4 Simulation input data for gas injection/export subsystem. 49

Table 5 Simulation input data for power generation subsystem. . 49

Table 6 Simulation input data for seawater injection subsystem. . 49

Table 7 Model assumptions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49

Table 8 Oil characterization parameters . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50

Table 9 Gas composition . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50

Table 10 Subsystems exergy product definition. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 57

Table 11 Main physical properties of the cyclopentane . . . . . . . . . . . . 58

Table 12 ORC parameters and assumptions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 59

Table 13 Comparison of mass and energy balances of models. . . . . 64

Table 14 Power consumption per subsystem, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65

Table 15 Power supply distribution, %. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65

Table 16 Rejected heat per subsystem, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 66

Table 17 Exergy losses per subsystem, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 68

Table 18 Exergy destruction rate per subsystem, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . 68

Table 19 Exergy destruction rate distribution. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 70

Table 20 Exergy destruction rate distribution (only separation and
gas processes). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 70

Table 21 Exergy losses distribution. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 72

Table 22 Exergy performance indicators by system - Hysys model. 73

Table 23 Exergy performance indicators - EES model . . . . . . . . . . . . 73

Table 24 Effect of the ORC integration over some production pa-
rameters of the plant . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 80

Table 25 Production parameters profiles. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 81

Table 26 ORC Tev chosen for each case. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 81

Table 27 PFD nomenclature. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 105

Table 29 Mass balances per system in EES model, kg/h. . . . . . . . . . 137

Table 30 Mass balances per system in Hysys model, kg/h. . . . . . . . . 138

Table 31 Power demand distribution according to EES and Hysys



models, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 139

Table 32 Heat rejection distribution according to EES and Hysys
models, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 140

Table 33 Exergy balances per equipment. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 143

Table 34 Exergy losses per system, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 145

Table 35 Exergy destruction rate per equipment, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . 146

Table 36 Exergy balances per system in EES model, kW. . . . . . . . . 149

Table 37 Exergy balances per system in Hysys model, kW. . . . . . . . 150

Table 38 General exergy balance, kW. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 151

Table 39 Crude composition (oily phase). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 156



ACRONYMS

API American Petroleum Institute.

BOE Barrels of Oil Equivalent.

BSW Bottom Sediments and Water.

C Carbon element.

CHP Combined Heat and Power.

COSTALD Corresponding States Liquid Density.

DOE Department of Energy of United States.

EES Engineering Equation Solver.

EOS Equation of State.

FPSO Floating Production, Storage and Offloading unit.

FTP Flowing Tubing Pressure.

GOR Gas to Oil Ratio.

GWP Global Warming Potential.

H Hydrogen element.

HHV Higher Heating Value or Gross heat of combustion.

HTF Heat Transfer Fluid.

IEA International Energy Agency.

LHV Lower Heating Value or Net heat of combustion.

N Nitrogen element.

NBP Normal Boiling Point.

O Oxygen element.

ODP Ozone Depletion Potential.

ORC Organic Rankine Cycle.



ORVC Organic Rankine–Vapor Compression.

PFD Process Flow Diagram.

PPD Pinch Point Difference.

PR Peng-Robinson.

PVT Pressure-Volume-Temperature.

RD&amp;amp;D Research, Development and Demonstration.

S Sulfur element.

SG Specific Gravity.

TBP True Boiling Point.

TEG Triethylene glycol.

WHR Waste Heat Recovery.



NOMENCLATURE

Roman Letters

B Exergy flow, kW.

b Mass specific exergy, kJ/kg.

b? Molar specific exergy, kJ/kmol.

f Parameter influence factor.

H Enthalpy flow, kW.

h Mass specific enthalpy, kJ/kg.

HHV Higher heating value, kJ/kg.

K Watson UOPK factor.

LHV Lower heating value, kJ/kg.

m Mass flow, kg/s.

n Molar flow, kmol/s.

P Pressure, kPa.

Q Heat flow, kW.

S Entropy flow, kW/K.

s Mass specific entropy, kJ/kg-K.

SG Specific gravity (15?C/15?C).

T Temperature, ?C.

v Liquid volumetric flow, m3/s.

x Mass fraction.

y Subsystem contribution fraction.

z Molar fraction.



Greek Letters

? Exergy correction factor for oil fractions.

? Finite difference.

? Exergy performance indicator.

? Activity coefficient.

?P Degree of thermodynamic perfection.

?II Exergy performance indicator.

? Energy performance indicator, MJ/sm3 oil.

? Production parameter.

? ?s/?T - inverse of the slope of the vapor saturation
curve in T-s diagram, J/kg-K2.

? Acentric factor.

Subscripts

0 Dead state conditions, T0 = 25
?C, P0 = 101.325 kPa.

avg. Average.

b Boiling point.

C Carbon element.

c Critical point.

ch Chemical.

D Destruction.

F Fuel, Consumed.

GAS Gas injection/injection subsystem.

gen Generated.

H Hydrogen element.

i,j,k,m Item i / j / k / m.

in Inlet.



L Losses.

mix Mixture.

N Nitrogen element.

n Normalized.

O Oxygen element.

oil Oil / Oil fraction.

out Outlet.

P Products.

phys Physical.

PS Product streams.

r Reduced property.

S Sulfur element.

SEA Seawater injection subsystem.

Superscripts

o Property evaluated at dead state conditions.

m Mixture.

v Vapor phase.

Others

?mixb Specific mixing exergy, kJ/kg.

?fG
? Standard free energy of formation, kJ/kg.

?rG
? Gibbs free energy of reaction, kJ/kg.





CONTENTS

1 INTRODUCTION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1
1.1 OBJECTIVES . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4
2 BIBLIOGRAPHIC REVIEW . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
2.1 BACKGROUND . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
2.2 OIL AND GAS PRODUCTION PLANTS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
2.2.1 Operation and types . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
2.2.2 Process description . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12
2.2.3 Oil Characterization . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18
2.3 ORGANIC RANKINE CYCLE (ORC) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21
2.3.1 Fundamentals . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22
2.3.2 Working fluid selection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24
2.3.2.1 Types of working fluids . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24
2.3.2.2 Enthalpy of vaporization . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 25
2.3.2.3 Density . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 27
2.3.2.4 Critical temperature . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 27
2.3.2.5 Chemical stability and corrosiveness of the fluid . . . . . . . . 28
2.3.2.6 Environmental aspects . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29
2.3.2.7 Safety . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29
2.4 EXERGY ANALYSIS OF OIL AND GAS PLATFORMS . . . 29
2.5 INTEGRATION OF ORC IN OIL AND GAS PLATFORMS 30
3 METHODOLOGY . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33
3.1 OIL CHARACTERIZATION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 35
3.1.1 Physical Properties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 35
3.1.1.1 Hysys cases . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 36
3.1.1.2 EES cases . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 38
3.1.2 Chemical exergy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 38
3.2 PLANT MODELING . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 42
3.2.1 Plant description . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 42
3.2.1.1 Separation plant . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 42
3.2.1.2 Boost system . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 43
3.2.1.3 Gas injection/export system . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 44
3.2.1.4 Power generation system . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45
3.2.1.5 Seawater injection system . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 46
3.2.2 Input data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48
3.2.2.1 Fluids data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50
3.2.3 EES case . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 51
3.2.4 Production parameters profiles . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 51



3.3 EXERGY ANALYSIS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 51
3.3.1 Exergy calculation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 51
3.3.2 Plant exergy balances . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 53
3.3.3 Exergy and energy efficiency indicators . . . . . . . . . . . . 54
3.3.3.1 Overall indicators . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 54
3.3.3.2 Subsystems indicators . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56
3.4 ORC MODELING . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56
3.4.1 fluid selection . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56
3.4.2 Configuration . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 58
3.4.3 Integration with plant model and parameters of

operation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 58
4 RESULTS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 63
4.1 OIL CHARACTERIZATION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 63
4.2 MODEL DEVELOPMENT . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 63
4.3 EXERGY ANALYSIS . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 67
4.3.1 Exergy balance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 67
4.3.2 Exergy performance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 72
4.4 ORC COUPLED TO THE PLANT . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 75
4.5 PRODUCTION PARAMETER PROFILES . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 80
4.5.1 ORC working Tev establishment . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 80
4.5.2 Influence of production parameters over the plant

performance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 82
4.5.3 Influence of the production parameters over ORC

performance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 89
5 DISCUSSION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 91
6 CONCLUSION . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 95
REFERENCES . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 97
APPENDIX A -- Hysys model nomenclature . . . . . . . . . . . 105
APPENDIX B -- Hysys code . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 113
APPENDIX C -- EES case development . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 129
APPENDIX D -- Exergy balances per equipment . . . . . . . 143
APPENDIX E -- Oil characterization results . . . . . . . . . . . 155



1

1 INTRODUCTION

Recently, the enhancement of the energy efficiency in the oil in-
dustry has attracted much attention, mainly due to the different chal-
lenges coming from three current circumstances: (i) the growing oil
and gas demand, (ii) the necessity of reducing CO2 and other green-
house gas emissions and (iii) the increasing production costs. According
to a recent forecast done by the International Energy Agency (IEA),
considering the existing policy commitments and assuming the imple-
mentation of those recently announced, by 2035 the world oil demand
will increase around 15% and a remarkable rise of 50% is projected for
gas demand (IEA, 2012). On the other hand, a gradual enforcement of
the existing legislation and the establishment of new commitments re-
lated to the pollution control are expected in order to avoid a dangerous
climate change, limiting consequently the CO2 emissions generated by
the industry (IEA, 2008; LUDENA; MIGUEL; SCHUSCHNY, 2012). These
factors are aggravated by the rapid depletion of the known reserves of
oil and gas (SIMMONS, 2009; IEA, 2012) and the increasing costs associ-
ated with the development of the new oil and gas fields (SHIMAMURA,
2002; BULLER, 2009).

The offshore production has been an important part of the de-
velopment of the oil and gas industry during the past two decades,
about 33% of world oil production by 2007 was obtained from offshore
platforms (KOCAMAN, 2008) and its contribution is projected to be
relatively stable until 2035. Considering that over 45% of currently
known oil resources are located under the sea and about a quarter of
these resources corresponds to deepwater (water with a depth of 400
meters or above), a production growth of 81% is estimated for this
type of fields (IEA, 2012). It should be noted that this notable figure
is predicted even considering the technical difficulties and high costs
inherent to the exploitation of oil and gas at remote locations.

Diverse types of offshore installations have been spread around
the world, of which the floating platforms are the most suitable for
deepwater production (BARTON, 2009; KINNEY, 2012). Among them,
the Floating Production, Storage and Offloading (FPSO) units present
technical advantages especially in the development of short-lived and
marginal fields in remote locations where fixed platforms were imprac-
tical and uneconomical (SHIMAMURA, 2002; GORDON, 2012). Nowa-
days, Petrobras has the second largest number of FPSO units (about
10 owned and 30 operated), representing about 15% of all the existing



2

worldwide (MAHONEY; KITHAS, 2013; CRAGER, 2010).
The main purpose of the production plant on an FPSO is to sep-

arate the well fluid into oil, gas and water meeting the specifications for
their export or further treatment. The most common operations carried
out for the separation of these streams includes (ARNOLD; STEWART,
2008): (i) well fluid gathering and well pressure reduction, (ii) gravity
separation, (iii) oil treatment and storage, (iv) gas compression and
dehydration and (v) water treatment and pumping. Depending on the
specific characteristics of the well fluid and field development, the FPSO
may contain operations like (BOTHAMLEY, 2004): (i) gas lift/injection,
(ii) gas liquefaction and storage, (iii) gas export via pipelines, (iv) gas
flaring or (v) seawater treatment and injection.

These installations include the production of the energy required
by their own processes, using a part of the oil (or gas) produced in the
plant as fuel for the generation of power, cold and heat. Improving the
use of this energy through the plant will reduce the fuel consumption,
which has important benefits like the abatement of pollutant emissions
and the reduction of operating costs. In that direction, the IEA (2008)
has shown the combined heat and power (CHP) as a good alternative
to increase the energy efficiency in various industrial sectors in the
short term. By other side, the Department of Energy of United States
(DOE) (BCS, 2008) has presented the main opportunities, challenges
and barriers to the research, development and demonstration (RD&amp;amp;D)
for the development of technology related with waste heat recovery
(WHR) in some industries.

Numerous investigations have been focused on the utilization
of the waste heat to activate thermodynamic cycles supplying power,
cold or upgraded heat (LITTLE; GARIMELLA, 2011; DENG; WANG; HAN,
2011). Among these systems, the organic Rankine cycle (ORC) is a rec-
ognized technology for power generation that already has been used to
improve the efficiency in many industrial operations (TCHANCHE et al.,
2011). Particularly, the integration of ORC in offshore processing plat-
forms has been the focus of a handful of recent studies (LARSEN et al.,
2013; PIEROBON et al., 2013; PIEROBON; NGUYEN, 2012a). However,
these studies have not considered the inherent variation in the plat-
form process conditions along its lifespan. Consequently, more work is
needed in order to determine the actual advantages of the ORC inte-
gration under variable production circumstances within the platform.

The application of exergy concept and the exergy balance is a
well-known and accepted technique employed to delimit and quantify



3

the energy efficiency in chemical and physical operations, which deter-
mines the maximum useful work obtainable from a system interacting
with its surroundings, as well its potential destroyed by irreversibil-
ity (SZARGUT; MORRIS; STEWARD, 1988). Despite its usefulness, this
method has not yet been fully adopted in many industrial sectors –
including the petrochemical segment, principally due to the absence of
a strategy of implementation, the low priority given and the lack of
information to work with such kind of analysis (GRIP et al., 2011).

Considering the usefulness of the exergy balance and the cur-
rent situation of the offshore industry, this study formulates an exergy
analysis of a Brazilian FPSO to characterize its energy performance,
and then analyzes the effect of the incorporation of an ORC over its
efficiency. The development of this work contemplates the following
subjects: (i) production plant and ORC modeling, (ii) calculation of
the exergy associated with petroleum and its fractions, (iii) use of ad-
equate energy performance indicators, (iv) coupling of the ORC to the
plant and (v) effect of the main production parameters over the en-
ergy efficiency of the plant. The document is organized in sections as
described in the paragraphs below.

The first section corresponds to the bibliographic review, where
the main concepts and theoretical basis are summarized. This section
covers aspects as the oil and gas production, the ORC operation and
its utilization in the waste heat recovery.

The methodology section describes the steps proposed in order
to obtain the results expected in this work. The process model was
developed considering the design conditions of the plant, in order to
establish the magnitude of its operations as well as their mass and
energy balances. Next, a rigorous exergy analysis was carried out in
order to identify the operations and processes with the greatest irre-
versibility and the highest exergy losses. Based on these results, various
performance indicators were proposed for the comparison of the energy
efficiency of the plant when coupling the ORC. The configuration and
the working fluid of this system were established based on previous
studies focused on its optimization (BRANCHINI; PASCALE; PERETTO,
2013; PIEROBON et al., 2013). Finally, the behavior of the proposed in-
dicators was analyzed along a production profile formed by 16 scenarios
varying five production parameters independently. the parameters con-
sidered are: (i) produced oil flow, (ii) production water flow, (iii) well
pressure, (iv) injected gas flow and (v) injected water flow.

The third section summarizes and discusses the obtained results
in order to recognize the impact of the ORC over the energy perfor-



4

mance of the plant accounting the variation of its main production
parameters.

Finally, in the conclusion section, the main findings of this work
are presented. The main contribution of the present study consists in
the proposal of a procedure aiming the effect of an energy enhancement
technology (in this case the ORC) in an existing process, characterizing
its behavior under variable production conditions. In this way, the
results can give a wider panorama when applying this kind of systems
where it could lead a great impact increasing the energy efficiency (e.g.
offshore oil and gas processing).

1.1 OBJECTIVES

In accordance with the outlined scope, the main purpose of this
study is to identify clearly the effect of an ORC over the energetic
efficiency of an offshore platform along a variable production profile,
such that the influence of each production parameter can be analyzed
separately. The following aims are contemplated in order to achieve
this purpose:

1. Develop the process model in order to determine the mass and
energy balances of each operation within the process. The model
must be adequate to analyze the behavior of the process condi-
tions under variable inputs, within the design constraints of the
plant.

2. Carry out an exergy analysis of the plant in order to quantify the
exergy fluxes within the plant as well as the irreversibility in each
operation and the potential exergy losses to be recovered by the
ORC. This analysis includes the proper calculation of the exergy
fluxes associated with hydrocarbon streams (i.e. petroleum and
its fractions).

3. Choose appropriate exergy performance indicators, in order to
make evident the effect of the chosen production parameters over
the plant efficiency. These indicators must be related with the
plant purpose and operation.

4. Develop the integrated model (the production plant with inte-
grated ORC) and quantify the effect over the energy efficiency of
the platform. This effect will be established by comparison of the
indicators proposed in the item above.



5

5. Determine the behavior of the exergy efficiency indicators under
variable operating conditions, such that the convenience of the
ORC implementation under different production scenarios can
be established.



6



7

2 BIBLIOGRAPHIC REVIEW

2.1 BACKGROUND

According to the data published by IEA (2012), the world oil
and gas demand by 2035 will grow about 2.75 million of cubic meters
per day and 1765 billion of cubic meters per year respectively, with-
out considering future changes in current environmental policies (see
Fig. 1). This fact seems to be positive for oil and gas market, but this
would be true if the current sources of oil and natural gas were enough
to meet these goals. The present situation indicates that the proved oil
and gas reserves are being rapidly depleted and are not enough to sup-
ply projected demand. In order to illustrate that, Fig. 2 presents the
production profiles of some fields located in Brazil (SIMMONS, 2009).
It would be necessary to find new oil and gas resources, but from the
information presented by Barton (2009) and Shimamura (2002), it can
be inferred that it is becoming more difficult to find new reservoirs
with an acceptable technical and economic feasibility. This signifies
that costs associated with oil and gas production will tend to increase,
which would imply a serious impact over the oil and gas market, and
consequently over the world economy.

Figure 1 – World oil and gas demand (IEA, 2012).



8

Figure 2 – Production profiles of some Brazilian fields (SIMMONS, 2009).

By the other hand, over the past three decades, the climate
change has become the most influencing aspect relating to the hu-
mankind sustainability and has compelled governments and policy mak-
ers to create commitments about the reduction of CO2 and other pollu-
tant emissions (LUDENA; MIGUEL; SCHUSCHNY, 2012). These premises
affect in a great extent the operation of the oil and gas plants, promot-
ing the investment in cleaner and more efficient systems of production.
Considering the goals established about economic and environmental
aspects, the use of technologies in order to improve the energy efficiency
of new as well as existing plants will be become a requisite more than
a choice for this industry.

In that way, DOE through BCS (2008), indicates the WHR as a
good alternative to affront this challenging scenario, considering that
as much as 20% to 50% of the energy consumed by the industrial sec-
tor is ultimately lost via waste heat. According to this reference, the
current profile of utilization of WHR is delineated mainly by the follow-
ing characteristics: (i) WHR frequently implemented, but constrained
by factors such as costs and temperature limits, (ii) most unrecovered
heat is at low temperatures and (iii) there are sectors where WHR is not
common due to factors such as chemical composition of heat carriers or



9

economic aspects required for recovery. Given that, Tab. 1 summarizes
WHR opportunities and addressed barriers in order to guide RD&amp;amp;D
works.

Table 1 – RD&amp;amp;D needs for addressing WHR Barriers (BCS, 2008)

RD&amp;amp;D Opportunity Barriers Addressed

L
o
n
g

P
a
y
b
a
ck

P
e
ri

o
d
s

M
a
te

ri
a
l

C
o
n
st

ra
in

ts
a
n
d

C
o
st

s

M
a
in

te
n
a
n
c
e

C
o
st

s

E
c
o
n
o
m

ie
s

o
f

S
c
a
le

L
a
ck

o
f

E
n
d

u
se

s

H
e
a
t

T
ra

n
sf

e
r

R
a
te

s

E
n
v
ir

o
n
m

e
n
ta

l
C

o
n
c
e
rn

s

P
ro

c
e
ss

C
o
n
tr

o
l

a
n
d

P
ro

d
u
c
t

Q
u
a
li
ty

P
ro

c
e
ss

sp
e
c
ifi

c
C

o
n
st

ra
in

ts

In
a
c
c
e
ss

ib
il
it

y

Develop low cost, novel mate-
rials for resistance to corrosive
contaminants and to high tem-
peratures

X X

Economically scaledown heat
recovery equipment

X X X

Develop economic heat recov-
ery systems that can be easily
cleaned after exposure to chem-
ically active gases

X X X

Develop novel manufacturing
processes that avoid introduc-
ing contaminants into offgases
in energy intensive manufactur-
ing processes

X X X X X

Develop low cost dry gas clean-
ing systems

X X X X X

Develop and demonstrate low
temperature heat recovery tech-
nologies, including heat pumps
and low temperature electricity
generation.

X

Develop alternative end uses for
waste heat

X



10

Table 1 – RD&amp;amp;D needs for addressing - WHR Barriers (BCS, 2008)

RD&amp;amp;D Opportunity Barriers Addressed

L
o
n
g

P
a
y
b
a
ck

P
e
ri

o
d
s

M
a
te

ri
a
l

C
o
n
st

ra
in

ts
a
n
d

C
o
st

s

M
a
in

te
n
a
n
c
e

C
o
st

s

E
c
o
n
o
m

ie
s

o
f

S
c
a
le

L
a
ck

o
f

E
n
d

u
se

s

H
e
a
t

T
ra

n
sf

e
r

R
a
te

s

E
n
v
ir

o
n
m

e
n
ta

l
C

o
n
c
e
rn

s

P
ro

c
e
ss

C
o
n
tr

o
l

a
n
d

P
ro

d
u
c
t

Q
u
a
li
ty

P
ro

c
e
ss

sp
e
c
ifi

c
C

o
n
st

ra
in

ts

In
a
c
c
e
ss

ib
il
it

y

Develop novel heat exchanger
designs with increased heat
transfer coefficients

X X X

Develop process specific heat re-
covery technologies

X X X X X X

Reduce the technical challenges
and costs of process specific feed
preheating systems

X X X X X

Evaluate and develop oppor-
tunities for recovery from un-
conventional waste heat sources
(e.g., sidewall losses)

X X

Promote new heat recovery
technologies such as solid state
generation.

X X

Promote low cost manufactur-
ing techniques for the technolo-
gies described above

X X X X X X X X X X

Within this context, the contribution of the present work is fo-
cused on the demonstration of a heat recovery technology for electricity
generation, addressing its specific use in offshore platforms. Among the
different options that are being outlined in academic publications, the
development of the ORC technology for WHR in oil and gas production
plants represents an interesting short-term solution for their energy ef-
ficiency improvement. Thus, next sections introduce some key concepts
concerning the operation of oil and gas production plants, its energy
efficiency, the ORC systems and their process modeling.



11

2.2 OIL AND GAS PRODUCTION PLANTS

2.2.1 Operation and types

It is well known that the crude oil and natural gas are the main
feedstock of innumerable industries and they are extracted from sedi-
mentary basins, where they have been formed and trapped for over tens
of millions of years (WILKINSON, 2006). The only way to extract them
is by drilling, that implies a withdrawal of diverse materials as water,
sands and salts together with the well fluid. These impurities need to
be removed from crude (or gas) before being processed at refineries or
used as fuels. This configures the main purpose of the production plant,
that consist in separating the well fluid into oil, gas and water meeting
the specifications for their export or further treatment or disposal.

The physical and chemical characteristics of crude and gas can
vary widely from field to field, influencing the process scheme and con-
ditions of the production plant. A typical scheme of operation is shown
in Fig. 3, nevertheless some stages can be added or omitted depending
on the crude and gas characterization (see section 2.2.3).

Figure 3 – Typical operation scheme of an oil and gas production plant
(WILKINSON, 2006).

It is difficult to classify production plants, because they differ due



12

to production rates, fluid properties, sale and disposal requirements,
location, and operation mode (ARNOLD; STEWART, 2008). Consider-
ing only location, production facilities can be separated into two main
groups: onshore and offshore installations. According IEA (2012), the
growth potential of the offshore installations (or platforms) is signifi-
cantly greater, given the estimation of remaining recoverable conven-
tional oil under the sea of about 1200 billion barrels (about 45% of total
estimated). Particularly, deepwater production (offshore platforms op-
erating in water depths in excess of 400 m) reports an expansion from
4.8 million of barrels per day in 2011 to about 8.7 million of barrels per
day by 2035.

Different types of platforms have been developed, some of these
being more adequate to the production at deepwater. Considering the
type of anchoring employed, Fig. 4 presents the schemes of various
types of platforms. Among these types, the FPSO units present several
advantages as (SHIMAMURA, 2002):

• Adaptability for water depth.

• Early deployment.

• These units are self-contained.

• These units are movable and relocatable.

• Can be combined with other offshore facilities.

• Their use can expand oil trading.

• Has segregated storage.

As the industry tackles deeper and deeper water, FPSOs con-
nected to subsea wellheads are replacing fixed platforms as the main
development technique. Figure 5 shows a more detailed scheme of an
FPSO unit (WILKINSON, 2006).

Currently, Brazil accounts 28 FPSO units of 147 existing world-
wide (reported until august 2013) and its national oil company Petro-
bras has a notable participation in FPSO market, accounting 10 owned
and operated units (MAHONEY; KITHAS, 2013).

2.2.2 Process description

The subsystems (blocks) presented in Fig. 3 can be briefly de-
scribed as follows (ARNOLD; STEWART, 2008):



13

Figure 4 – Schemes of most common types of offshore platforms (MA-
HONEY, 2013).



14

Figure 5 – Basic operation scheme of an FPSO (WILKINSON, 2006).

1. Gathering system

The production systems begins at the wellhead, which should
include at least a valve called choke. Most of the pressure drop
between the well flowing tubing pressure (FTP) and the initial
separator operating pressure occurs across this valve. The choke
opening determines the flow through the wellhead and permits a
rough control over the depletion rate of well.

When two or more wells are commingled in a production plant,
it is necessary to install a piping arrangement called manifold, in
order to allow flow from any one well to be isolated and diverted
towards the test production systems.

2. Separation system

The function of separators and other equipment in this system
is to make a gross separation of gas, and water from oil. This
separation takes place due to the difference of densities between
the aqueous, oily and gas phases. Heating of the inlet stream
promotes this separation, up to some degree depending on the
composition and water content of oil. Generally, this operation



15

is accomplished in multiple pressure stages with the purpose of
stabilizing the major quantity of light hydrocarbon molecules in
the oil phase. In a given separator, a higher pressure favors liquid
yield, but incorporates too light components into oil that will be
lost in atmospheric storage. On the other hand, a lower pressure
favors medium component losses through the gas outlet.

3. Oil Treatment system

The purpose of this system is to reduce the water content of oil
down to the sales requisite (generally 1% BSW or less). Generally,
it implies heating of oil stream and sometimes the application of
electrostatic fields. The grade of heating and electrostatic treat-
ment depends on the trend to form stable emulsions between the
oil and water. This stage is commonly done at a pressure slightly
higher than the atmosphere in order to promote its vapor stabi-
lization.

4. Storage system

In the FPSO this system corresponds to the tanker (incorporated
in the unit), where the oil is accumulated until it is dispatched to
external tankers or to other installations via pipeline.

5. Gas dehydration system

This system removes the humidity from gas, in order to meet the
sales or injection specification. The dehydration is accomplished
generally by contact with a dehydrating agent as triethylene gly-
col (TEG) or methanol. Depending on the available gas pressure
and its water content, an intermediate compression stage (boost-
ing) can be needed before this operation.

6. Compression

This system must provide the required pressure to the gas stream
in order to accomplish any of the following operations:

• Gas export (pipeline): When possible, the major part of the
separated gas is sold and exported onshore via pipelines.
The capacity of compressors and therefore their power con-
sumption depends on the gas flow and the pressure drop
through the lines. It is common to find subsea gas lines up
to 200 km long (WILKINSON, 2006).

• Gas re-injection: It consists in a way of achieving a supple-
mentary oil recovery maintaining the reservoir pressure by



16

returning the natural gas back through strategically placed
wells in the field. This technique bolsters the main drive as
long as possible.

• Gas lift: It involves increasing the amount of gas produced
with the oil by injecting gas directly into the flowing column
in a well rather than into the reservoir. Gas lift is accom-
plished by using special valves set up at various depths and
then controlling the amount of gas entering the flow stream.
The increase in gas/oil ratio reduces the pressure needed to
drive the oil to the surface (WILKINSON, 2006).

7. Flare system

This system has two basic functions: (i) vents and/or burn safety
the excess of gas of the plant when there is a surplus, and (ii) re-
ceives and directs the gas and vapors expelled from safety devices
when an overpressure occurs. Normally, continuous gas venting
or burning is avoided mainly due to environmental restrictions.

8. Oily water separation system

This system takes the oil and solid traces away from the produc-
tion water stream in order to meet the specifications to be dis-
posed overboard. Normally, this is accomplished using settling,
aeration and other related equipment.

9. Filtration system

This system separates smaller particles than the former stage and
is accomplished by means of membranes, activated coal and other
filtering media. The purpose of the filtration system is to meet
the water specifications requirements in order to be injected back
to the reservoir. In addition, it is common to take and filter
directly seawater and discard all the production water.

10. Deareation system

This system removes the dissolved gas from filtrated water in
order to avoid the growth of aerobic bacteria that can favor a
collapse of the reservoir.

11. Pumping and water injection system

The treated water is injected back into the reservoir to maintain
the reservoir pressure and thus take a secondary oil recovery. The
power consumed by this system depends on the injection depth



17

and the required water flow. Generally, several pumping stages
are necessary to achieve the required pressure rise.

There are other subsystems that are not included in Fig. 3, but
also are necessary in the plant operation:

• Safety system
Includes alarms, automatic shutdowns, back-up units, flare stacks
(as mentioned above) and firefighting equipment, plus strict ad-
ministrative procedures and frequently practiced emergency con-
tainment and evacuation plans.

• Utility systems
Include power generation and facilities for normal services, all of
which can be, and frequently are, powered by gas or oil being
processed in the plant.

Commonly, the power generation system of an FPSO unit consists
in a set of turbines (gas or diesel fueled) working at part-load for
availability and reliability reasons.

The above-mentioned operations can vary according with the
main purpose of the platform. According to the work of Bothamley
(2004), which summarizes the primary options available for offshore
processing, the majority of the offshore platforms falls into the following
two categories:

• Stabilized, crude meeting sales specifications and dehydrated gas
produced offshore.

• Unstabilized, wet crude and dehydrated gas produced offshore.

Additionally, there is a relatively small number of oil platforms
offshore that employ additional gas processing, (e.g. Hydrocarbon dew
point control, natural gas liquids recovery or liquefaction of natural
gas) in order to produce both oil and gas products meeting sales spec-
ifications.

Figure 6 presents a typical layout of the process plant on board of
an FPSO, showing the distribution of the main subsystems of the plant.
On the other hand, a photograph of an FPSO topside is presented in
Fig. 7 in order to illustrate the equipment arrangement within the plant.

In order to analyze the streams and processes that are performed
within a plant, a simplified PFD (Process Flow Diagram) is presented



18

Figure 6 – Basic layout of an FPSO topside.

in Fig. 8. This scheme corresponds to an FPSO operating in the San-
tos basin (WASCO, 2012), which is analyzed in the present work. Ap-
pendix A presents the complete scheme of operation, which includes
secondary material and energy streams, as well as the operations within
each subsystem (shown as blocks in Fig. 8). The symbols and nomen-
clature used are also presented there. A detailed process description is
presented in Sec. 3.2.1.

2.2.3 Oil Characterization

This subsection introduces the most common methods for char-
acterizing crude oils and petroleum fractions, and for estimating their
thermophysical properties. In order to simulate properly the oil-related
processes, it is necessary to have a good understanding of the com-
position information and thermophysical properties of crude oils and
petroleum fractions. However, the complexity of molecular composi-
tion of crude oils and petroleum fractions makes it hardly possible to
identify individual molecules. Instead, there are standardized methods
to characterize crude oils and petroleum fractions, which are commonly
compiled in a technical summary known as crude assay.

A typical crude assay includes two types of information for an oil
sample: (i) bulk properties and (ii) fractional properties. Bulk prop-
erties include specific gravity, sulfur content, nitrogen content, metal
(Ni, V, Fe etc.) content, Watson (UOP) K factor, C/H ratio, pour
point, flash point, freeze point, smoke point, aniline point, cloud point,



19

Figure 7 – Example of an FPSO topside.

viscosity, carbon residue, light hydrocarbon yields (C1-C4), acid num-
ber, refractive index, lower and higher heating values and boiling point
curve. The most representative bulk properties are briefly described in
following paragraphs.Chang, Pashikanti e Liu (2012) presents a detailed
description of all above-mentioned properties.

Specific gravity (SG) : generally is measured using the API (Amer-
ican Petroleum Institute) gravity to specify the specific gravity of the
crude oil as ?API = (141.5/SG) ? 131.5. SG is the specific gravity
defined as the ratio of the density of the crude oil to the density of
water both measured at 15.6 ?C (60 ?F). The API gravity reports a
value lower than 10?API for very heavy crudes, from 10 to 30?API for
heavy crudes, from 30 to 40?API for medium crudes, and a value above
40?API for light crudes.

Gross heat of combustion or higher heating value (HHV): is the
amount of heat released by the complete combustion of a unit quantity
of fuel. The gross heat of combustion is obtained by cooling down all
products of the combustion to the temperature before the combustion,
and by condensing all the water vapor formed during combustion.



20

Figure 8 – Basic PFD of a typical FPSO process plant.

Net heat of combustion or lower heating value (LHV): is obtained
by subtracting the enthalpy of vaporization of the water vapor formed
by the combustion from the higher heating value.

True boiling point (TBP) distillation curve: results from using
the U. S. Bureau of Mines Hempel method and the ASTM D-285 test
procedure. However, there is a trend toward applying the ASTM D2892
procedure, instead of the TBP. A key result from a distillation test is
the boiling point curve, that is, the boiling point of the oil fraction
versus the fraction of oil vaporized.

Watson (UOP) K factor : Is an approximate index of paraffinic-
ity, with higher values corresponding to a high degree of saturation. It
is related to the mean average boiling point by the following expression
(WATSON; NELSON, 1933):



21

K =
1.216 3

?
Tb,avg.

SG
(2.1)

where

K: Watson UOPK factor.
Tb,avg.: Mean Average Boiling Point, K.
SG: Bulk specific gravity (15?C/15?C).

This factor must be between 8 (highly aromatic or naphthenic)
and 15 (highly paraffinic)(ASPENTECH, 2011).

By the other hand, fractional properties of the oil sample re-
flect the property and composition for specific boiling-point range to
properly refine it into different end products such as gasoline, diesel
and raw materials for chemical process. Fractional properties usually
contain paraffins, naphthenes and aromatics (PNA) contents, sulfur
content, nitrogen content for each boiling-point range, octane number
of gasoline, freezing point, cetane index and smoke point for kerosene
and diesel fuels. These properties and methods to obtain them are
detailed by Chang, Pashikanti e Liu (2012).

Two indicators affect directly the material balance of the plant:
the bottom sediments and water (BSW) and the gas to oil ratio (GOR).
BSW corresponds to the volumetric ratio of water extracted together
with the well fluid (expressed as a percentage) and GOR is the ratio of
volumetric flow of produced gas to the volumetric flow of crude oil for
crude oil and gas mixture at standard conditions (measured at T=15?C
and P=101.325 kPa). The importance of these parameters is associated
with their variability over the period of development of a field.

2.3 ORGANIC RANKINE CYCLE (ORC)

According to Chen, Goswami e Stefanakos (2010), Bao e Zhao
(2013) and Little e Garimella (2011), previous studies have analyzed
various advanced thermodynamic cycles such as the ORC, supercritical
Rankine cycle, Kaline cycle, Goswami cycle, Maloney-Robertson cycle
and trilateral flash cycle for the conversion of heat into available power.

Particularly, the ORC appears with some key advantages when
compared with Kalina cycle and trilateral flash cycle (BAO; ZHAO,
2013):

• ORC has simpler structure.

• ORC presents less expansion complexity.



22

• ORC has a high reliability.

• ORC has a simpler maintenance.

In addition, with the aim to improve the energy efficiency, the
ORC can be easily combined with other thermodynamic cycles such
as thermo-electric generator, fuel cell, internal combustion engine, mi-
croturbines, seawater desalinization system, Brayton cycle, and gas
turbine-modular helium reactor. Furthermore, it also can be used as
prime movers of combined cooling and power systems as the ORVC
(Organic Rankine–Vapor Compression) cycle.

2.3.1 Fundamentals

The ORC, which has the same configuration as conventional
steam Rankine cycle but uses organic substances with low boiling points
as working fluids, can use various types of heat source. Tchanche et
al. (2011) present a review of some ORC applications such as indus-
trial waste heat, solar energy, geothermal energy, biomass energy, ocean
energy, etc. Figure 9 shows the basic scheme of operation of the ORC.

Figure 9 – Basic scheme of an ORC system

The ORC working fluid (state F05) is fed to the pump (P-F01)
that increases its pressure (state F06) and leads the fluid to the econo-
mizer (E-F03) where it reach its saturation temperature (F08). Next,
the fluid across the evaporator (E-F02), wherein the fluid phase change



23

occurs (state F09). Normally, the saturated vapor is then superheated
across E-F01 and expanded in T-F01 (state F11), which produces the
shaft work of the cycle (WT-F01). It should be noted that the heat
consumed by the economizer, the evaporator and the superheater is
supplied by the waste heat source (directly or indirectly). Finally, the
vapor stream from expander outlet is condensed in E-F05 , and re-
turned back to the pump. Depending on the characteristics of the
expansion of fluid (explained in sec. 2.3.2), it may be appropriated the
use of a regenerator, which transfers heat from the expander outlet to
the economizer inlet. Figure 10 shows the configuration and the cycle
of a regenerative ORC.

Figure 10 – Basic scheme of an regenerative ORC system

Compared with the conventional Rankine cycle, the ORC demon-
strates several advantages such as (TCHANCHE et al., 2011):

• Commonly, it is necessary a lesser amount of heat during the
evaporation process.

• The evaporation process takes place at lower pressure and tem-
perature.

• Particularly for dry fluids, the expansion process ends in the vapor
region and hence the superheating is not required and the risk of
blade erosion is avoided.



24

• The smaller temperature difference between evaporation and con-
densation also means that the pressure drop ratio will be smaller,
thus simple single stage turbines can be used.

2.3.2 Working fluid selection

One of the most important aspects in the development of ORCs
is the working fluid selection. The quantity of generated power, the
energy efficiency and economic viability of the ORC are strongly af-
fected by the working fluid choose. A working fluid must not only have
the necessary thermo-physical properties that match the application
but also possess adequate chemical stability in the desired temperature
range. There are numerous investigations carried out about the screen-
ing, comparison and selection of the best candidates. Particularly Bao
e Zhao (2013), and Chen, Goswami e Stefanakos (2010) have reviewed
extensively the research done in this area and their work is the main
information source of following subsections.

2.3.2.1 Types of working fluids

The working fluids can be categorized according to the vapor
saturation curve. This characteristic affects the fluid applicability, cycle
efficiency and arrangement of ORC equipment. There are three types
of vapor saturation curves in the temperature-entropy (T-s) diagram:
(i) dry fluids with a positive slope, (ii) wet fluids with a negative slope
and (iii) isentropic fluids with nearly infinitely slopes. Figure 11 shows
the T-s diagrams for these three types of fluids.

The manner how this characteristic influences the performance
and the number of equipment within the ORC is related with the con-
densation in the expander outlet. A wet fluid condensates during the
expansion process because the negative slope of its vapor saturation
curve. This effect must be avoided since the presence of liquid inside
expander may damage its blades and reduces its isentropic efficiency.
Normally a superheating is required before the fluid enters to the ex-
pander, implying an increasing cost of the system and a reduction its
efficiency.

On the other side, the main advantage of the dry and isentropic
fluids consist in that they expand without phase change, thus super-
heating is not required. In spite of this, a slight superheating is rec-



25

Figure 11 – Types of fluids (HEBERLE; PREIBINGER; BRU?GGEMANN,
2012).

ommended to guarantee only vapor at expander outlet. Moreover, in
the case of dry fluid, generally a regenerator is used in order to reduce
the condenser load and increase the efficiency of the cycle, which im-
plies an increasing complexity and cost. This preliminarily indicates
isentropic fluids as the most interesting candidates to be implemented
in an ORC. However, a more detailed analysis (HUNG et al., 2010) has
indicated that wet fluids with very steep saturated vapor curves have
better overall performance in energy conversion efficiencies than dry
fluids and isentropic fluids. In spite of that, they are not always suit-
able for ORC systems when other thermophysical properties are taken
into consideration.

A practical indicator used to visualize how ”dry” or ”wet” a
working fluid is, consists in the inverse of the vapor saturation curve
slope (?T/?s). Defining ? = ?s/?T , the type of fluid can be classified
by its value, i.e. ? &amp;lt;0 corresponds to a wet fluid, ? = 0 corresponds
to an isentropic fluid and ? &gt; 0 to a dry fluid.

2.3.2.2 Enthalpy of vaporization

High enthalpy of vaporization enables most of the available heat
to be added to the ORC and produces a larger quantity of work per



26

unit of circulating fluid with the evaporation temperature and other
parameters defined (CHEN; GOSWAMI; STEFANAKOS, 2010). However,
when the heat source is the waste heat, organic fluids with lower specific
vaporization heat are preferred. As explained by Bao e Zhao (2013), a
lower specific heat of vaporization allows the temperature profile across
the economizer-evaporator-separator to be closer to the waste heat pro-
file, which means less irreversibility through the process, thus better
performance of the ORC. This is shown in Fig. 12, where the pinch
point difference (PPD) is indicated.

Figure 12 – Effect of the enthalpy of vaporization of the working fluid
(BAO; ZHAO, 2013).

Declaye (2009) mentions that the purpose of an ORC for waste
heat recovery is not always meet the best energy efficiency, but produce
the greater amount of power and presents the case illustrated in Fig. 13.
This system recovers heat coming from a hot water source at 105 ?C
using a ketone as working fluid. The operation conditions in the second
case (right side) demonstrated the worst efficiency (more irreversibility)
but generated more than three times the power reported by the first
case (left side).



27

Figure 13 – Difference between cycle efficiency and power output (DE-
CLAYE, 2009).

2.3.2.3 Density

This parameter has a great impact over the sizing, and thus over
the initial investment of the ORC equipment. Considering that a low
density leads to a higher volume flow rate, the pressure drop in the
heat exchangers is increased (thus the power consumed by the pump)
and the size of the expander must be increased.

2.3.2.4 Critical temperature

Previous study (BRUNO et al., 2008) has demonstrated that em-
ploying a fluid with higher critical temperature results in higher effi-
ciency but lower condensing pressure, when the optimum high and low
pressure were determined in order to meet the maximum first law effi-
ciency of the saturated cycle. However, a high critical temperature also
involves working at specific vapor densities much lower than the critical
density. This reduced density shows a great impact on the design of
the cycles, since the components need to be oversized (QUOILIN et al.,
2012).

In a general way, the critical point of a working fluid suggest the
proper operating temperature range for the working fluid in liquid and



28

vapor forms. Figure 14 presents a relation between the critical temper-
ature and the parameter ? for various working fluids studied previously,
according to the review done by Chen, Goswami e Stefanakos (2010).

Figure 14 – Relation between the critical temperature and the param-
eter ? for various candidates (CHEN; GOSWAMI; STEFANAKOS, 2010).

2.3.2.5 Chemical stability and corrosiveness of the fluid

Organic fluids usually suffer chemical deterioration at high tem-
peratures. Thus, commonly the maximum operating temperature is
limited by the chemical stability of the working fluid. In addition, as
mentioned by BCS (2008), the corrosion and scaling inside of the equip-
ment associated with waste heat recovery is an important barrier to the
implementation of these systems. Hence, the working fluid should be
as chemically stable and non-corrosive as possible.

In many cases, the stability characteristics of the working fluid
have promoted the use or intermediate fluid in order to transfer heat



29

from higher temperature sources at a lower temperature level.

2.3.2.6 Environmental aspects

The main environmental parameters are: (i) the ozone deple-
tion potential (ODP) and (ii) global warming potential (GWP), which
represent substances potential to contribute to ozone degradation and
global warming. Due to environmental concerns, some working fluids
have been phased out, such as R-11, R-114 and R-115, while some
others are being phased out in 2020 or 2030 (CHEN; GOSWAMI; STE-
FANAKOS, 2010). This criterion can be used in order to screen prelim-
inarily the working fluids candidates and discard those that must be
avoided by international protocols.

2.3.2.7 Safety

This parameter is related to the level of danger when dealing
with the working fluid. Generally, characteristics as non-corrosive, non-
flammable and non-toxic are expected, but are not practically found for
a specific candidate. Particularly for longer alkanes, autoignition is a
problem at temperatures above 200?C.

Another important thermodynamic property is the freezing point
of the fluid, which must be below the lowest operating temperature in
the cycle. The fluid must also work in an acceptable pressure range.
Very high pressure or high vacuum has a tendency to impact the relia-
bility of the cycle or increase the cost (CHEN; GOSWAMI; STEFANAKOS,
2010).

2.4 EXERGY ANALYSIS OF OIL AND GAS PLATFORMS

Relatively few works have been focused on analyzing the exergy
performance of the oil and gas production installations. Oliveira e
Hombeeck (1997) studied a Brazilian platform, whose process includes
the crude heating using a WHR system in combination with a furnace
in order to improve the separation of phases. Also the gas compression
system and the oil pumping system were included. Their analysis indi-
cated the compression and the separation as the most exergy-consuming
processes within the plant. In the same way, the worst exergy efficiency
was reported for the separation operation (22%) due to the high tem-



30

perature difference between the crude and exhaust gases. This work
was conducted using Hysim (predecessor of Hysys) and an overall ex-
ergy efficiency of 9.7% was obtained.

By other side, Silva (2008) developed an exergy analysis of two
Brazilian production installations, one located onshore and another lo-
cated offshore. The methodology proposed in this dissertation adopts
the entire plants as the combination of three independent systems:
(i) the separation module, (ii) the gas compression module and (iii)
the power generation module. The reported efficiencies for the base
case were 24.9% using the thermodynamic degree of perfection (?P –
see Sec. 3.3.3) and 7.9%, reported as the actual exergy efficiency. The
software used in this dissertation was EES.

Voldsund et al. (2010) simulated a specific North Sea offshore
platform by using Hysys. The platform analyzed included separation,
recompression (boost), gas injection and oil pumping systems. Results
indicated the gas boost and injection as the systems with largest ex-
ergy destruction. In this case, an overall exergy efficiency of 32% was
reported and the main exergy losses were associated with the gas recy-
cling in compressors.

More recently, Nguyen et al. (2013) simulated a platform includ-
ing auxiliary systems as the gas dehydration unit, production manifold
and production water treatment. Results were obtained combining
three different programs: (i) Aspen plus for the processing plant, (ii)
DNA for modeling the gas turbines and (iii) Hysys for modeling the
dehydration unit. The authors separated the analysis of the processing
plant from that carried out for power generation system, and pointed
out the gas injection as the process with highest exergy destruction
when the combustor chambers of the power generation system are not
considered. Analogously, the largest exergy losses were found in the
exhaust gases outlet.

2.5 INTEGRATION OF ORC IN OIL AND GAS PLATFORMS

Currently, publications concerning the use of ORC systems in
the WHR within offshore facilities are limited. Pierobon e Nguyen
(2012b) modeled an ORC system for the WHR from the exhaust gases
coming from a SGT-500 turbine used in a platform located at North
Sea. Their methodology was focused on the working fluid selection of
the cycle, in order to obtain a higher power output. The results indi-
cated cyclohexane as the best candidate among four chosen candidates,



31

which reported a thermal efficiency enhancement of 12.9% considering
the combined cycle. Posteriorly Pierobon et al. (2013) conducted an op-
timization analysis aiming the reduction of the size of the components
that make up the same ORC system meeting the maximum thermal
efficiency. The results pointed out the acetone and the cyclopentane
as two optimal working fluids, the later reporting a greater thermal
efficiency.



32



33

3 METHODOLOGY

In order to investigate the behavior of the operation conditions
of the plant, a process simulation is carried out to determine the mass
and energy balances of each subsystem involved. This simulation was
developed considering the design parameters supplied in its engineering
documentation (WASCO, 2012), whose values correspond to the occu-
pation of 100% of the capacity of the plant. Missing information were
properly set according to specific literature (MAXWELL, 1968; ARNOLD;
STEWART, 2008). The model was developed using two well-known engi-
neering software with two different levels of detailing and different crite-
ria applied; the chosen alternatives were Hysys and Engineering Equa-
tion Solver (EES). Specifically, Hysys (or its former version Hysim) has
been used in previous works to develop exergy analysis of oil produc-
tion plants, (e.g. Nguyen et al. (2012), Pierobon e Nguyen (2012b),
Oliveira e Hombeeck (1997)), mainly due to its algorithms for model-
ing crude oil and its fractions from standardized data. On the other
hand, numerous academic studies focused on ORC have been devel-
oped different analysis using EES (e.g. Li, Wang e Du (2012), Little e
Garimella (2011)), because of its capability to work with the thermo-
dynamic properties of common substances as continuous functions, as
well as other multi-purpose characteristics. The data calculated using
both programs are presented with the purpose of enabling the identi-
fication of the differences between the obtained results and to provide
a contribution for future works that contemplate the use of Hysys or
EES for this type of simulation.

Based on the energy balance of the plant, the heat losses as well
the power demand in all operations in the plant were quantified. The
possible sources to activate the ORC and its potential of use were iden-
tified in accordance with these results. In addition, appropriate exergy
balances were developed with the intention of determining the actual
potential of utilization of these sources (specifically, the exergy of the
waste heat corresponds to the maximum amount theoretically attain-
able by the ORC) and to identify the operations where an improvement
would have a greater impact on the energy efficiency of the plant.

Special attention was taken in the calculation of the exergy using
Hysys, mainly due to the coherence required between the method used
by this program for modeling the physical properties of crude fractions
and the method of estimation of its chemical properties (including its
chemical exergy). Considering the basic information commonly used



34

to characterize a crude oil, a hybrid strategy was adopted integrating
previous studies and establishing some assumptions based on available
literature. This strategy was developed in the following steps: (i) esti-
mation of the molecular weight distribution and physical properties of
crude in accordance with the method proposed by Whitson (1983) and
Twu (1984), (ii) estimation of the higher heating value (gross calorific
value) of each fraction according Maxwell (1968) data, (iii) estimation
of the elemental composition of each fraction using the Boie equation
apud. Ringen, Lanum e Miknis (1979) and (iv) estimation of the chem-
ical exergy considering each fraction as a liquid technical fuel according
the method described by Szargut, Morris e Steward (1988) and Rivero,
Rendon e Monroy (1999).

The same operating conditions were used in the EES model, but
adopting a simpler strategy to model the crude fractions: physical and
chemical properties of whole crude oil were determined using Maxwell
(1968) data; then its chemical exergy was approximated to its LHV as
mentioned by Rivero, Rendon e Monroy (1999). The main drawback
of this methodology is that the mass transfer between the liquid and
vapor phases is not quantified due to the omission of the composition
and the equilibrium of phases. Another remarkable difference between
the models, is that in the case of Hysys, where the crude is modeled
as a mixture of several hydrocarbon fractions, the calculation of the
total exergy of material streams includes the mixing exergy term –as
proposed by Hinderink et al. (1996), in order to incorporate the exergy
destruction associated with the entropy generated by mixing. This
term was not necessary in the EES model, since the compositions of
the material streams remains constant through the plant.

Once the exergy analysis of the plant was completed, the losses
and destruction of exergy in each operation were established, so that
the energy efficiency of the process scheme can be compared adequately
with that incorporating the ORC. In that way, this work proposes the
use of three indicators: two related to exergy efficiency and another as-
sociated with the energy consumption per volumetric unit of produced
oil.

Considering the great variability of the production parameters in
this kind of installations, a comparison of the results using the ORC was
made along a production profile. This profile is formed by 16 scenarios,
and comprises the variation of five parameters independently: (i) oil
flow, (ii) production water flow, (iii) well pressure, (iv) injected gas
flow and (v) injected water flow.

The incorporation of the ORC system was proposed recovering



35

waste heat from the exhaust gases coming from the gas turbines and the
power generated by this system was discounted from their total load.
With the purpose of taking advantage of the current configuration of the
plant, the ORC was modeled coupled to the HTF (Heat Transfer Fluid)
circulation system (described below). By the other side, cyclopentane
was selected as the ORC working fluid based on the results of a recent
study focused on the optimization of this cycle (PIEROBON et al., 2013).
The operation scheme of the ORC was established based on its vapor
saturation curve, as explained in sec. 2.3.2.1.

This methodology contemplates the combination of various pro-
cedures in order to obtain a reliable panorama of the energy perfor-
mance of an oil and gas production platform and its improvement using
an innovative technology as the ORC. These procedures were adapted
considering a small availability of information about the characteriza-
tion of the well fluids, a fact that is common in this industry.

3.1 OIL CHARACTERIZATION

3.1.1 Physical Properties

In order to obtain a reliable simulation of the production plant,
an important key is the proper calculation of the thermophysical prop-
erties of the crude oil and petroleum fractions. The algorithms of cal-
culation included in Hysys permit to estimate these properties directly
from the standard data obtained from laboratory and its method is
broadly accepted in the oil industry. On the other hand, Maxwell
(1968) is a great compendium of thermophysical and chemical prop-
erties based on experimental data of various petroleum fractions with
different characteristics, and it can be used as a good reference to easily
characterize a crude (or fraction) from basic information. On account
of that, this reference was used for the estimation of the thermophysical
and chemical properties in the simulation case developed in EES. The
comparison of values obtained from these two methods will permit to
validate the order of magnitude of the results and to distinguish how
the grade of detail used in crude characterization affects its calculated
parameters.



36

3.1.1.1 Hysys cases

The algorithm used by Hysys to characterize the crude and its
fractions can be outlined as follows (ASPENTECH, 2011):

1. An adjusted TBP curve is generated from two of the following
bulk properties of crude (user supplied): (i) standard specific
gravity, (ii) Watson UOPK characterization factor and (iii) molec-
ular weight. Hysys uses the methodology proposed by Whit-
son (1983), where the molar distribution of crude (mole frac-
tion/molecular weight relation) is adjusted as a three-parameter
gamma probability function. These parameters are dependent on
the molecular weight of crude, which can be calculated from its
UOPK factor and its standard specific gravity.

2. From this curve, several pseudocomponents are generated accord-
ing the following procedure, as explained by Chang, Pashikanti e
Liu (2012):

• The curve is cut into an arbitrary number of intervals in or-
der to define the number of pseudocomponents. The recom-
mended number of intervals can vary from 8 to 30 depending
on the boiling point range of the curve.

• The normal boiling point (NBP) is determined for each in-
terval by equalizing the areas between the TBP curve and
a horizontal line representing the NBP temperature. This
is shown in Fig. 15, with the gray areas representing the
equalized areas.

• The density distribution of pseudocomponents is calculated
assuming a constant UOPK factor throughout the entire
boiling range.

3. Main thermophysical properties are calculated for each pseudo-
component from its specific gravity, boiling point and UOPK fac-
tor. The models used by Hysys to determine these properties are
explained by Chang, Pashikanti e Liu (2012) and are summarized
as follows:

• Molecular weight and critical properties: Corresponds to the
model proposed by Twu (1984), which uses correlations for
the molecular weight, specific gravity and critical properties
of a group of pure n-alkanes ( C1 to C100) as a reference



37

Figure 15 – Determination of the normal boiling point (NBP) of each
pseudocomponent (ASPENTECH, 2011).

system. These correlations are adjusted appropriately by
the inclusion of a correction term depending on the boiling
temperature and specific gravity of each pseudocomponent.

• Acentric factor: The expression used in for the calculation
of acentric factor is shown in Eq. 3.1.

? = ?log
10

(
Pv

?

r

)
? 1.0 (3.1)

where ? corresponds to the acentric factor and Pv
?

r corre-
sponds to the reduced pressure at a reduced temperature
(Tr) equivalent to 0.7.

• Density (liquid phase): Even when Hysys uses an equation
of state approach for refinery modeling (i.e. Peng-Robinson
method), density of each pseudocomponent (liquid) is calcu-
lated independently to ensure accurate results. Specifically,
the method chosen for the calculation of the density of liq-
uids in the developed model is the Spencer-Danner method
with corresponding states liquid density (COSTALD) cor-
rection for pressure.

• Heat capacity (vapor phase): represents the vapor heat ca-
pacity of the pseudocomponent at a given standard condi-
tion. The standard conditions typically refer to 15 ?C and 1
atm. The heat capacities of hydrocarbons do not vary signif-
icantly over a wide range of temperatures, so very accurate



38

heat capacities are not necessary for good modeling results.
The procedure used by Hysys in this case corresponds to the
Lee-Kesler method.

• Heat capacity (liquid phase): The method used by Hysys
to calculate the heat capacity of pseudocomponents (liquid
phase) corresponds to the Lee-Kesler method when 145 K
&amp;lt;T &amp;lt;0.8 Tc and a correlation recommended by API when
Tr &amp;lt;0.85.

• Thermodynamic model: The chosen method to model the
PVT (Pressure-Volume-Temperature) behavior of the pseu-
docomponents and their mixtures was the Peng-Robinson
EOS (Equation of State). This cubic equation requires three
main properties: critical temperature, critical pressure and
acentric factor. In general, the interaction parameters for
pseudocomponents can be set to 0 without changing model
results.

3.1.1.2 EES cases

The algorithm implemented in EES incorporates data obtained
from Maxwell (1968) depending on the calculation needed to analyze
the physical exergy of oil. Basically, the only information needed to
the estimation of enthalpy and entropy of oil was a correlation of the
specific heat as a function of temperature. Figure 16 reproduces the
data found in this reference.

3.1.2 Chemical exergy

The calculation of the chemical exergy of oil was carried out
based partly on the procedure initially proposed by Szargut, Morris e
Steward (1988) and then adjusted by Rivero, Rendon e Monroy (1999)
that relates the chemical exergy of oil fractions with their elemental
composition and LHV. This procedure considers molecular structures
of oil fractions as formed principally by C (carbon), H (Hydrogen),
N (Nitrogen), O (Oxygen) and S (sulfur) atoms. Since this informa-
tion is not commonly available in routine crude analysis (including the
crude studied in this work), the incorporation of other techniques was
needed in order to estimate adequately these properties from known
data. In the case of the heat of combustion, data were obtained from



39

Figure 16 – Specific heat of crude fractions as a function of temperature
and its standard specific gravity (MAXWELL, 1968).

Maxwell (1968), where the LHV and HHV can be estimated directly
from the specific gravity of the pseudocomponent and its UOPK factor;
Fig. 17 reproduces the data for a UOPK factor of 12. On the other
hand, the elemental composition was determined using the Boie equa-
tion (Eq. 3.2) apud. Ringen, Lanum e Miknis (1979) that relates the
elemental composition of a crude fraction with its HHV.

HHVi = 35170 xC,i + 116252 xH,i + 6280.5 xN,i

+ 10467.5 xS,i ? 11095.5 xO,i (3.2)

where HHVi is the higher heating value (kJ/kg) of the pseudo-
component i. xC,i, xH,i, xN,i, xS,i and xO,i correspond to its mass
fractions of C, H, N, S and O respectively.

The values of the sulfur and nitrogen content was assumed based



40

Figure 17 – Heat of combustion of crude fractions as function of its
standard specific gravity (MAXWELL, 1968).

on a crude analysis available online (BG Group, 2012), that corresponds
to a field located relatively next to the studied platform. These values
were assumed constant and oxygen content was adjusted to meet the
molecular weight of each pseudocomponent. Once the elemental com-
position was determined, the correction factor ? is calculated using the
expression presented by Rivero, Rendon e Monroy (1999) (see Eq. 3.3).

?i = 1.0401 + 0.0864 ·
xH,i
xC,i

+ 0.0216 ·
xO,i
xC,i

+ 0.2169 ·
xS
xC,i

·
(

1 ? 1.0314 ·
xH,i
xC,i

)
+ 0.0214 ·

xN
xC,i

(3.3)

The specific chemical exergy of each pseudocomponent (bch,i) is
then calculated using eq. 3.4.

bch,i = ?i · LHVi (3.4)

where LHVi corresponds to the lower heating value of pseudo-
component i (kJ/kg).



41

The referenced method establishes the specific chemical exergy
(b?ch) of a mixture (in molar basis) as the sum of the contribution of
each component plus a compositional term, as shown in Eq. 3.5.

b?ch,oil =
?

zi · b?ch,i + R T0
?

zi ln (zi · ?i) (3.5)

where b?ch,oil corresponds to the specific chemical exergy of the
oil fraction in kJ/kmol. zi and ?i correspond to the molar fraction and
activity coefficient of the component i.

However, in this work the compositional addend was replaced
by a term called mixing exergy (?mixb) as proposed by Hinderink et
al. (1996), which quantifies the effect of the composition over the total
exergy of a multicomponent stream. As shown in Eq. 3.6, this term
corresponds to the difference between the sum of the exergy contribu-
tion of each component and the total exergy of the stream (bm). Its
calculation is explained in Sec. 3.3.1.

?mixb = b
m ?

?
xi · bi (3.6)

In accordance with this adoption, the specific chemical exergy
of crude was defined simply as the sum of the contribution of each
component (in mass basis) as shown in Eq. 3.7.

bch,oil =
?

xi · bch,i (3.7)

In the case where the components are known (e.g. methane), the
specific chemical exergy was determined from the standard chemical
exergy data available in (SZARGUT; MORRIS; STEWARD, 1988). Analo-
gously to eq. 3.7, a more general expression (see Eq. 3.8) was adopted
for streams including known components as well as the pseudocompo-
nents.

bch =
?

xi · bch,i +
?

xj · bch,j (3.8)

where bch,i and bch,j correspond to the specific chemical exergy
associated with the pseudocomponents and associated with the known
components respectively (kJ/kg).

Appendix B shows the code integrated to Hysys for implement-
ing the calculation of the chemical exergy of each material stream.
Conversely, for the cases developed using EES, the specific chemical
exergy was approximated to the LHV of whole crude (i.e. without con-
sidering its composition), accordingly with Rivero, Rendon e Monroy
(1999) when no compositional data were available.



42

3.2 PLANT MODELING

3.2.1 Plant description

3.2.1.1 Separation plant

Figure 18 – Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the separation plant.

As mentioned above, the considered production plant corresponds
to an FPSO located at the Santos basin (Brazil). The main purpose of
the process is to separate the well fluid into oil, gas and water meet-
ing the specifications for their export/further treatment. Figure 18
presents a simplified scheme of operation, a more detailed scheme is



43

presented in Appendix A. The well fluid (FLUID) is throttled through
a choke (valve L-B00) to meet the pressure level of the first separation
stage, which is formed by the heat exchanger E-B01, where the well
fluid is preheated with the exported oil stream (B09) and the separator
V-B01, where significant amounts of gas (B11) and water (B21) are
removed from the oil stream (B03). Next, the oil stream is throttled
trough valve L-B01 and heated in the heat exchanger E-B02 in order
to promote further separation of gas and water in the separator V-B02
(streams B12 and B23 respectively). The heat is supplied to E-B02 by
the circulation of a heat transfer fluid (streams E07 and E01), which
withdraws heat from the exhaust gases coming from the power gener-
ation subsystem through the heat exchanger E-E01. The separation
is accomplished with an electrostatic separator for meeting the final
specifications of the oil stream (not shown) and a further separation in
separator V-B03 at lower pressure. Then, the oil is pumped (P-B01)
through E-B01 and dispatched to the tankers (stream OIL), previous
cooling with seawater in the cooler E-B02. By the other hand, the wa-
ter separated in V-B02 (B23) is pumped back (P-B02) and mixed with
the inlet wellfluid in order to promote the phases separation prior to
the first separation stage. The main production water stream coming
from V-B01 is directed to the water treatment system (not shown) to
meet the required conditions for its disposal, then is throttled through
valve L-B04 and cooled with seawater in cooler E-B04 before being
discharged on board.

3.2.1.2 Boost system

The gas separated in V-B01, V-B02 and V-B03 is directed to the
gas boost subsystem (BOOST), where the streams at lower pressures
are compressed up to an intermediate pressure level before being com-
pressed for injection/export in the gas injection subsystem (GAS INJ.).
A simplified scheme of the gas boost system is presented in Fig. 19, a
more detailed scheme is presented in Appendix A.

The gas coming from V-B03 (B14) is compressed by C-C01 up
to second separation stage pressure (stream B12), then both streams
are mixed and cooled with seawater through cooler E-C01. The liq-
uids formed by condensation are removed from the gas stream in the
separator V-C01 and sent back to V-B03 (B26). Next, the gas stream
(C06) is compressed (C-C02) up to an intermediate pressure slightly
less than the first separation stage (stream B11) and is cooled with



44

Figure 19 – Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the boost system.

seawater in E-C02. The condensates separated (V-C02) are returned
to V-C01. The boost compression train works recirculating a portion
of gas to V-B02 (B29). Then, the gas coming from V-B01 is regulated
through valve L-C01 and mixed with the boosted gas (C10).

3.2.1.3 Gas injection/export system

The gas stream coming from boost subsystem (B17) is directed
to the gas injection system (GAS INJ.), where the gas is compressed
and dehydrated in order to meet the requirements to be injected back
to the reservoir or sent to onshore facilities via pipeline. A simplified
scheme of operation is shown in Fig. 20, a more detailed scheme is
presented in Appendix A.

In a similar manner to the boost subsystem, the gas injection
train consists of four compression stages (C-D01/C-D02/C-D03/C-D04),
each one accomplished with a gas cooling (air coolers F-D01/F-D02/F-
D03/F-D04 respectively) and the subsequent separation of condensates,
which are returned back to the previous stage (streams B27, D12, D13
and D15 respectively). Before the fourth stage, the dehydration sub-
system (DEH) removes the humidity from the gas stream using TEG
(triethylene glycol) as absorbent. Fuel gas (stream B18) used in power
generation subsystem (POWER) is derived from the dehydrated gas



45

Figure 20 – Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the gas injection/-
export system.

stream (D24). This stream is regulated by the valve L-D01 according
to the fuel demand of the gas turbines. A portion of the compressed
gas is recirculated to the compression train suction (stream D19), in or-
der to maintain the necessary operating parameters of the equipment.
The compressed gas (stream GAS) is then injected into the reservoir
or exported via pipeline.

3.2.1.4 Power generation system

The required energy for the operation of the plant is supplied
by the power generation system, which is formed by two gas turbines
Siemens SGT-400 operating at part load. Figure 21 shows the working
scheme of these turbines. The power cycle was modeled as two com-
pression stages and a third stage supplying the power to the plant. The
operating parameters were adjusted according to the curves provided
by supplier (SIEMENS AG, 2009), as shown in Fig. 22.

The maximum output per turbine was limited to 11 MW, such
that when the demand of the plant does not exceed this value, only one



46

Figure 21 – Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the power generation
system.

turbine is considered in operation. Consequently, when the demanded
power in plant exceeds 11 MW, the second turbine enters in operation
sharing the 50% of the total load.

3.2.1.5 Seawater injection system

On the other side, in order to promote the oil recovery from the
reservoir, the analyzed FPSO has a seawater treatment and injection
system that is outlined in Fig. 23. A part of the injected water is recir-
culated to the pump suction to guarantee the minimum flow necessary
for the secure operation of the equipment.

Based on the results of previous works (NGUYEN et al., 2012, 2013;
VOLDSUND et al., 2010), the following process subsystems were neglected
in the plant model, due to their small energy demand when compared
to the main operations described above:

• Gas dehydration system.

• Production water treatment.

• Seawater treatment.



47

Figure 22 – Operating parameters of gas turbines (SIEMENS AG, 2009).

Figure 23 – Basic PFD (Process Flow Diagram) of the water injection
system.



48

3.2.2 Input data

Tables 2 through 6 presents the main operation parameters of
each subsystem in the plant. As mentioned above, these conditions
do not exceed the design constraints of the process reported in this
engineering documentation (WASCO, 2012).

Table 2 – Simulation input data for separation plant.

Parameter Units Value

Well pressure kPa 3000
Manifold pressure kPa 1500
Inlet temperature ?C 55
Inlet vol. Flow - Liq. Phases sm3/day(1) 12800
Gas molar flow Nm3/day(2) 1500000
BSW % 29.7
Oil heating temperature ?C 81
3rd stage pressure kPa 101.3
Oil export temperature ?C 55
Oil export pressure kPa 175
Water export temperature ?C 55

(1)Standard cubic meters per day.
(2)Normal cubic meters per day.

Table 3 – Simulation input data for boost subsystem.

Parameter Units Value

Boost discharge pressure kPa 1300
Compressor adiab. efficiency % 65*
Gas cooling temperature ?C 40
Boost recycle mass % % 15

*Assumed.

Table 7 summarizes the main assumptions adopted in the devel-
oped model. In general, the model considers a steady state of opera-
tion (no variations with time) and all the streams and operations meets
thermodynamic equilibrium.



49

Table 4 – Simulation input data for gas injection/export subsystem.

Parameter Units Value

Gas injection pressure kPa 20000
Compressor adiab. efficiency % 65
Gas cooling temperature ?C 40
Injection recycle mass % % 15
Fuel gas pressure kPa 1500
Fuel gas temperature ?C 55

Table 5 – Simulation input data for power generation subsystem.

Parameter Units Value

Inlet air temperature ?C 25
Inlet air pressure kPa 101.3
Outlet net power MW 7.2
Exhaust gases temperature ?C 525.4
Turbine heat input MW 24.5
Exhaust mass flow kg/s 30.4

Table 6 – Simulation input data for seawater injection subsystem.

Parameter Units Value

Seawater vol. Flow sm3/day 12000
Seawater injection pressure kPa 20000
Injection pump adiab. efficiency % 75
Seawater injection recycle % 15

Table 7 – Model assumptions

Parameter Units Value

Exchangers ?P kPa 50
Pumps adiab. efficiency % 75
HTF hot temperature ?C 300
HTF circulating pressure kPa 1000
E-B02 HTF ?T ?C 20
Exhaust gas min. allow. temp. ?C 150
E-B01 pinch point difference ?C 10



50

3.2.2.1 Fluids data

Tables 8 and 9 summarizes the data used for the characterization
of the well fluid. These data correspond to the minimal information
necessary to characterize the phases (oily phase, aqueous phase and gas
phase) conforming the fluid. The aqueous phase was modeled as pure
water and a total immiscibility with the oily phase was considered.

Table 8 – Oil characterization parameters

Parameter Units Value

Standard density kg/m3 874.4
Standard density ?API 30
Watson UOPK – 12
Sulphur Content %wt. 0.362
Nitrogen Content ppm 3136
Viscosity at 100 ?F cP 8
Viscosity at 210 ?F cP 1.5

Table 9 – Gas composition

Component Mol. Fraction

CO2 0.0516
Nitrogen 0.0064
Methane 0.7824
Ethane 0.0944
Propane 0.0412
n-butane 0.0152
n-pentane 0.0049
n-hexane 0.0019
n-heptane 0.002

Pure substances and their mixtures present within the process
were modeled using the PR (Peng-Robinson) equation of state, except
for the HTF (dowtherm A), which was modelled using the available
information from supplier (DOW Chemical, 2001).

In the same way, the chemical exergy of pure substances involved
in the process were assumed as its standard chemical exergy as proposed
by Szargut, Morris e Steward (1988), except for the HTF, whose chem-



51

ical exergy was approximated to its LHV, reported by supplier (DOW
Chemical, 2001). The corresponding value is 36,05 MJ/kg.

3.2.3 EES case

Appendix C presents the model developed in EES. As mentioned
above, its conception was simpler than the model done using Hysys (de-
scribed in this section). The comparison of results using both models
can be used to examine the influence of the detailing level in the cal-
culation of the exergy efficiency of the plant.

3.2.4 Production parameters profiles

With the aim of analyzing the influence of the main production
variables over the impact of an integrated ORC in the studied FPSO,
different profiles were proposed. As shown in Fig. 24, these profiles
were developed in 16 scenarios such that each variable could be ana-
lyzed separately. As mentioned above, the chosen variables were: (i)
oil flow varying from 800 up to 9000 standard m3/d, (ii) Gas flow vary-
ing from 1.5 up to 2 million of Nm3/d, (iii) production water flow,
varying from 200 up to 4000 standard m3/d, (iv) seawater flow varying
from 12000 up to 18000 standard m3/d and (v) well pressure varying
from 3000 down to 1500 kPa. As stated earlier, the standard condi-
tions for liquid volumetric flow are referred to T=15?C and P=101.325
kPa. Similarly, the gas volumetric flow (Nm3/d) is referred at normal
conditions (T=0?C and P=101.325 kPa).

3.3 EXERGY ANALYSIS

3.3.1 Exergy calculation

As previously mentioned, the formulation adopted for the calcu-
lation of total exergy of the material streams within the process corre-
sponds to that proposed by Hinderink et al. (1996). The specific exergy
of a multicomponent stream (b) is expressed as shown in Eq. 3.9.

b = bchem + bphys + ?mixb (3.9)

where bchem , bphys and ?mixb correspond to the specific chem-



52

Figure 24 – Analized production profiles.

ical exergy, the specific physical exergy and the mixing exergy respec-
tively. Eq. 3.8 is used for the calculation of bchem, as explained in
Sec. 3.1.2. By other side, the Eq. 3.10 is used for the calculation of
bphys, as explained by Szargut, Morris e Steward (1988).

bphys = ?h ? T0 ?s (3.10)

where ?h = h ? ho and ?s = s ? so, considering h and s as
the current specific enthalpy and the specific entropy of the stream
respectively. On the other hand, ho and so correspond to the specific
enthalpy and specific entropy of the stream evaluated at dead state
conditions, which were defined at T0 = 25

?C and P0 = 101.325 kPa.



53

Appendix B shows the code developed for implementing the calculation
of the physical exergy of a material stream using Hysys. This code was
developed based on the work of Abdollahi-Demneh et al. (2011).

Eq. 3.11 presents the calculation of ?mixb, which represents the
exergy destroyed due to the entropy generation during a non-ideal mix-
ing process at isothermal and isobaric conditions. This term is com-
monly negative and its use permits to isolate the net effect of a sepa-
ration process over the exergy flow associated with a multicomponent
stream (HINDERINK et al., 1996).

?mixb = ?mixh ? T0 ?mixs (3.11)

considering ?mixh = h
m ?

?
xi hi and ?mixs = s

m ?
?
xi si,

where hm and sm correspond to the molar enthalpy and the molar
entropy of the mixture respectively. hi and si are the molar enthalpy
and the molar entropy of the component i at the same conditions of
the mixture respectively. Appendix B shows the code integrated to
Hysys for implementing the calculation of the mixing exergy of each
material stream. Adopting this procedure, Eq. 3.9 for calculation of
the total exergy of a multicomponent stream is reformulated as shown
in Eq. 3.12.

b =
?

xi bchem,i + ((h ? ho) ? T0 (s ? so))

+
((
hm ?

?
xi hi

)
? T0

(
sm ?

?
xi si

))
(3.12)

3.3.2 Plant exergy balances

Appendix D presents the formulation of the exergy balance for
each equipment conforming the plant. Exergy losses (BL) are associ-
ated with those material and energy streams that are not part of the
desired product of the plant/subsystem. Conversely, destroyed exergy
(BD) is associated with the entropy generation (irreversibility) present
in each process. Eq. 3.13 presents the relation between the destruction
of exergy and the entropy generated during a non-reversible operation
(CENGEL; BOLES, 2010). Given that Hysys calculates the entropy of
the material streams directly according to the chosen thermodynamic
package and by other side the implementation of the exergy calculation
must be done through a programing block, this expression can be useful



54

to check the consistency of obtained data. Values of BD obtained from
the exergy balance of each equipment must match with that calculated
using the entropy values reported by Hysys.

BD = T0 · Sgen (3.13)

where

Sgen = (Sout ? Sin) ?
? Q

T

3.3.3 Exergy and energy efficiency indicators

3.3.3.1 Overall indicators

Given the scheme of operation of the whole plant shown in
Fig. 18, the desired effects of the process can be divided in the fol-
lowing items:

• Remove water and gas incorporated together with the oil in the
inlet fluid stream.

• Compress the gas stream for further use.

• Pump the seawater to be injected into the reservoir.

As it can be inferred from previous works (HINDERINK et al.,
1996; SILVA et al., 2012), the decrease of the mixing term in Eq. 3.9 also
represents a chemical exergy increment when conceived as (RIVERO;
RENDON; MONROY, 1999). This increase of exergy constitutes the main
effect (product) of separation process when considering a mixture and
its components at equilibrium (SILVA, 2008).

Adopting the concept presented by Bejan (1996), the exergy as-
sociated with the entire product (or effect) of the plant (BP ) was ex-
pressed by the sum of the exergy effects related to the above-mentioned
items, as shown in Eq. 3.14.

BP = ?Bmix + ?Bphys,GAS + ?Bphys,SEA (3.14)

considering

?Bmix = ?mixBF LUID ? (?mixBOIL + ?mixBGAS)



55

where ?mixBi = mi ?mixbi is the exergy of mixing of stream i
(i.e. streams named FLUID, OIL and GAS in the model scheme –see
Fig. 18); here mi corresponds to its mass flow. Analogously,

?Bphys,GAS =mGAS bphys,GAS ? (mB11 bphys,B11
+ mB12 bphys,B12 + mB14 bphys,B14)

?Bphys,SEA =mH02 · bphys,H02 ? mH01 · bphys,H01

Considering that a great extent of the exergy contained in the
streams of interest (i.e. oil, gas and injected water streams) are supplied
initially with the inlet streams, the consumed exergy BF was expressed
as the sum of BP and the difference between the exergy associated with
inlet streams (Bin) and the exergy associated with product streams
(BP S). Eq. 3.15 presents the exergy indicator chosen to evaluate the
performance of the plant.

?II =
BP
BF

(3.15)

considering BF = BP + (Bin ? BP S) and

Bin = BF LUID + BAIR + BH01

BP S = BOIL + BGAS + BH02

As mentioned in previous works (SILVA et al., 2012; SILVA, 2008),
another exergy indicator that can be used for this kind of processes is
the degree of perfection ?P . This index was defined by Szargut, Morris e
Steward (1988) and relates the exergy of the products of interest leaving
the system (BP S) and the inlet exergy (Bin) as shown in Eq. 3.16.

?P =
BP S
Bin

(3.16)

Alternatively, with the aim to demonstrate the energy efficiency in
terms that can be associated with production variables, this study
propose the indicator ? that represents the energy consumption per
standard cubic meter of exported oil. This indicator is presented in
Eq. 3.17. It can be easily converted to fuel gas consumption or to
energy consumption expressed in BOE (barrels of oil equivalent1) per
volumetric unit of produced oil.

1The BOE is a unit of energy based on the approximate energy released by
burning one barrel of crude oil and it is equivalent to about 1.7 MWh.



56

? =
mB18 · LHVB18

vOIL
(3.17)

where vOIL corresponds to the standard volumetric flow of pro-
duced oil in m3/s.

3.3.3.2 Subsystems indicators

Analogously, BP,i was defined for each subsystem i in order to
obtain the exergy indicators ?p,i and ?i associated with each process.
As shown in Eq. 3.18, ?i corresponds to the second law efficiency (?II,i)
but formulated using the irreversibility (BD,i) and the exergy losses
(BL,i) calculated for each process. In that way, Tab. 10 shows the
formulation of BP,i for each subsystem. Evidently, the value of ? for
the entire plant must be equal to ?II (explained in the previous section)
to be coherent with the definition presented by Bejan (1996).

?i =
BP,i

BP,i + BL,i + BD,i
(3.18)

here BF,i = BP,i + BL,i + BD,i.

3.4 ORC MODELING

3.4.1 fluid selection

As explained in Sec. 2.3.2, numerous works had analyzed differ-
ent ORC working fluids candidates with the purpose of determining
the best candidate taking into account different fluid characteristics as
the slope of the vapor saturation curve, critical properties, enthalpy
of vaporization, density, specific heat and others related to environ-
mental aspects as ODP (ozone depletion potential) or GWP (global
warming potential)(CHEN; GOSWAMI; STEFANAKOS, 2010; BAO; ZHAO,
2013). This work is focused on the use of cyclopentane as working
fluid based on the results of a recent study (PIEROBON et al., 2013),
where cyclopentane was indicated as the best option when accounting
the ORC power output and the size of ORC equipment as choosing
criteria. Despite its flammable and toxicological characteristics, it is
important to remark that the plant already deals with this type of
substances (i.e. hydrocarbons) in its main processes and it would be



57

Table 10 – Subsystems exergy product definition.

System Streams

Separation plant i j

BP =
?
i

?mixBi ?
?
j

?mixBj

OIL FLUID
B11 A07a
B13 A07b
B15 B18

B20a B26
B20b B27

B29

Gas turbines i?
i

Wi WT-A03a

WT-A03b

Gas boost system i j k m

BP =
?
i

Bphys,i ?
?
j

Bphys,j

+
?
k

?mixBk ?
?
m

?mixBm

C10 B13 B16 B11
B29 B15 B29 B13

B15

Gas injection system i j

BP =
?
i

?mixBi + Bphys,i ?
?
j

?mixBj + Bphys,j GAS B17
B18

Seawater injection system i j

BP =
?
i

Bphys,i ?
?
j

Bphys,j H02 H01

ORC system i

Wi WT-F01



58

not necessary to make important modifications due to safety issues.
Table 11 summarizes the main properties of this substance.

Table 11 – Main physical properties of the cyclopentane

Property Units Value

Molecular wt. 70.14
Critical temperature ?C 234
Critical pressure kPa 4506
? J/kg-K2 1.04
Type of T-s vapor saturation curve Dry
Freezing point ?C -93
Autoignition temperature ?C 361

3.4.2 Configuration

The operation scheme of the ORC working with cyclopentane
is determined by the slope of its saturated vapor line in the T-s dia-
gram. Since this slope is positive (as seen in Tab. 11), the expansion
process (F10 – F11 in Fig. 10 – Sec. 2.3) results in an overheated vapor
stream at the turbine outlet. This means that the incorporation of an
intermediate regenerator (E-F04) is convenient in order to take some
advantage of the remaining energy associated with this stream.

It can be noted that superheating of vapor at turbine inlet (E-
F01) is not necessary theoretically. However, this study contemplates a
slight superheating of vapor in order to avoid any condensation at the
turbine intake.

3.4.3 Integration with plant model and parameters of opera-
tion

In accordance with previous works focused on the exergy anal-
ysis of oil and gas production platforms, the most appropriate use of
ORC systems in these installations consist in recovering exergy from the
exhaust gases coming from gas turbines or from processes associated
with combustion (PIEROBON; NGUYEN, 2012a; NGUYEN et al., 2013).
Considering the operation scheme of the analyzed FPSO, this study
proposes the integration of the ORC within the existing HTF circuit,



59

in order to take some advantage and reduce the number of modifica-
tions to the operating scheme of existing installations. The ORC was
located downstream of exchanger E-B02 (HTF side) at the valve L-E01
position.

Evidently, when the ORC is integrated within the model, a re-
lationship is established between the amount of energy taken from ex-
haust gases, the HTF mass flow rate, HTF temperature levels and the
ORC system performance. This correlation makes necessary to update
their corresponding values in order to take an acceptable advantage.
Likewise, the internal parameters of the ORC that influence directly its
output (e.g. evaporation temperature, working fluid mass flow, tem-
perature of condensation, etc.) must be adjusted properly according
to established criteria. In that way, Tab. 12 presents the assumptions
used in this paper for the variables affecting the ORC performance.

Table 12 – ORC parameters and assumptions

Parameter Units Value

Condensation pressure kPa 110
HTF maximum temperature ?C 300
Regenerator pinch point ?C 5
Superheating ?C 1
Expander adiabatic efficiency % 65
Pump adiabatic efficiency % 75
Economizer pinch point ?C 5
Heat exchangers ?P (tubeside) kPa 50
Heat exchangers ?P (shellside) kPa 25

Particularly, the evaporation temperature of cyclopentane within
the cycle was analyzed varying it from an established minimum tem-
perature (180 ?C) up to its critical temperature. This was done with
the aim of finding an appropriate evaporation temperature at which
the flow rate and rejected heat were reduced in each scenario.

Considering a centralized power distribution (i.e. all the power
demand of the plant is supplied by only one power distribution sys-
tem), the power generated by the ORC was subtracted from the total
power demand and the remainder was supplied by existing turbines.
These assumptions together with the turbines operation configure the
calculation algorithm for each scenario, as presented in Fig. 25. The
nomenclature used in this figure is listed as follows:



60

• Processes:
A.–Update overall mass and energy balances.
B.–Calculate operation parameters of 2 turbines.
C.–Calculate operation parameters of 1 turbine.
D.–Calculate operation parameters of ORC.

Figure 25 – Model general algorithm.



61

• Data:
1. Operation parameters of the plant (e.g. BSW, GOR, etc.).
2. Power demand of the plant.
3. Air temperature and pressure.
4. Exhaust gases flow and temperature.
5. Exergy for activate the ORC.
6. ORC parameters (e.g. Tev, PPDs, etc.).
7. ORC output.
8. Model results (e.g. exergy flows, heat flows, etc.).

• Conditions:
C1. Is the total power demand less than 11 MW?.
C2. All material and energy balances converged?.



62



63

4 RESULTS

4.1 OIL CHARACTERIZATION

Appendix E summarizes the results about the oil characteriza-
tion. Despite its importance for obtaining accurate results, this infor-
mation was compiled in a separate section because it is not considered
as a fundamental part within the aims of the present work.

4.2 MODEL DEVELOPMENT

The mass and energy balances of the plant enable the quantifi-
cation of the power requirements as well as the heat rejected in each
operation involved in the process. Although currently there are no data
available from field to corroborate the model, the comparison with the
results of previous studies can give an idea about the size of the plant
and the consistency of the model. Particularly, the platform analyzed
by Nguyen et al. (2012) has a similar configuration to that studied in
this work. Table 13 presents some results for both models developed
(using Hysys and EES) together with the results obtained from this
reference. As stated above, the great variability of the well fluid prop-
erties and production characteristics from field to another make each
installation unique and this fact makes difficult the validation of the
results of a plant model with the data from another.

By the other hand, the power consumption breakdown (pre-
sented in Tab. 14), indicates how the energy is distributed among the
subsystems and the load of each one within the entire system. Particu-
larly, the injection operations (i.e. gas and seawater) presented a value
far above from that reported to the separation plant. In general, the
results obtained using EES were appreciably smaller than those using
Hysys, except for the gas boosting where the gas compressed had a
lower molecular weight in the EES case. The power distribution (as
percentages) is presented in Tab. 15, which is practically in accordance
with those reported by Nguyen et al. (2012). Analogously, Fig. 26 ex-
hibits the results obtained by both models. Considering the differences
about the size of the plants, the proportion and the conditions of the
oil, gas and water flows as well as the subsystems considered in the
models, the results obtained here are noticeably in line with the model
developed for the platform located at North Sea.



64

Table 13 – Comparison of mass and energy balances of models.

Parameter Nguyen, 2012 This work

EES Hysys

Platform localization North Sea Brazil Brazil
Considered Operations
Production manifolds yes no yes
Crude oil separation yes yes yes
Oil pumping and export yes yes yes
Oil heating by furnace no no no
Gas re-compression (boost) yes yes yes
Gas dehydration yes no no
Gas injection/exportation yes yes yes
Wastewater treatment yes no no
Seawater injection yes yes yes
Power generation yes yes yes
Recycling streams yes no yes

Size of the plant
Oil produced, sm3/h 156-457 375 75-375
Gas produced, 103·Nm3/h 190-320 63.5 62.5-87.5
Water produced, sm3/h 50-123 158.3 8.3-158.3
Seawater injected, sm3/h 900-2900 500 500-750
Seawater inj. Pressure, MPa 11.5 20 20
Gas export pressure, MPa 15-25 20 20
Power demand, MW 18-23.5 13 14.2-20.6
Separation stages 4 3 3

Fluid parameters
Oil spec. Gravity, ?API 39.9 30 30

Software Aspen plus EES Hysys
Hysys
DNA



65

Table 14 – Power consumption per subsystem, kW.

System Value

EES Hysys

Oil pumping and export 20.1 151.6
Gas re-compression (boost) 358.8 317.4
Gas injection/exportation 8908 9531.1
Seawater injection 3685.2 4568.9

Table 15 – Power supply distribution, %.

System Nguyen, 2012 This work

EES Hysys

Oil pumping and export 0.98-3.1 0.15 1.04
Gas re-compression (boost) 4.74-9.8 2.77 2.18
Gas injection/exportation 51.37-64.46 68.67 65.42
Seawater injection 29.79-38.79 28.41 31.36

Figure 26 – Power supply distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model.

Another result coming from the energy balance of the plant is
the rejected heat breakdown, which enabled the identification of the



66

main heat sources that can be used to activate the ORC system. As
can be seen in Tab. 16, the power generation system is responsible for
over the half of the total heat rejection in the plant (see also Fig. 27).
Here, the largest heat discharge to the atmosphere corresponds to the
exhaust gas stream, which has a calculated temperature of 471 ?C. It
can be inferred that this heat source is the most suitable to activate
the ORC.

Table 16 – Rejected heat per subsystem, kW.

System

EES Hysys

Value % Value %

Separation plant 2994 7.90 3029 7.61
Gas turbines* 25066 66.12 22656 56.94
Gas boost system 436 1.15 694 1.74
Gas injection 9412 24.83 13407 33.70
Seawater injection 0 0.00 0 0.00

Total 37909 39786

*With a min. allowed temp. of 150 ?C for exhaust gases.

Figure 27 – Rejected heat distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model.

Detailed results of mass and energy balances (accounting for each



67

equipment separately) are presented in Appendix C. Examining these
results for the Hysys case, a minor imbalance of 22 kg/h was identified
within the power generation system. This imbalance was caused by
the omission of the traces of pseudocomponents in the fuel gas stream,
with the aim to enable the calculation sequence of the Gibbs reactors
simulating the combustor chambers of the turbines. Since the data
of the Gibbs energy of formation (?fG

?) of the pseudocomponents
are unknown, the internal algorithm of calculation does not attain a
minimum Gibbs free energy for the combustion reaction (?rG

?) and
the composition of the products cannot be determined. Given that
the amount of pseudocomponents in the fuel gas is negligible (most of
them have a high molecular weight) and according to Hinderink et al.
(1996) the estimation of their ?fG

? may result in an inconsistent set
of standard chemical exergies, their mass fractions were approximated
to 0. Future work should include an appropriate procedure to estimate
the ?rG

? of a hydrocarbon pseudocomponent combustion adequately.

4.3 EXERGY ANALYSIS

4.3.1 Exergy balance

As mentioned earlier, the exergy balance of the plant enables
the recognition of the processes with greatest exergy destruction as
well as the quantification of the losses discharged to the atmosphere.
By means of this analysis, it is possible to establish the reference case
and the parameters of comparison in order to demonstrate the effect
of the ORC system along the proposed production profile. In a similar
way to mass and energy balances, Tab. 17 and Tab. 18 presents the
results of the exergy balances obtained using Hysys and EES. Given
that the existing WHR system recovers part of the energy associated to
exhaust gases and is considered part of the separation plant, the exergy
losses associated with this stream are not accounted for in the power
generation system, but in the separation plant. Detailed results (bal-
ances per equipment) are presented in Appendix D. Due to the mass
flow imbalance previously discussed for the power generation system, a
difference of 271 kW was identified in its exergy balance. Considering
the magnitude of the involved flows and the high specific exergy value
of the fuel gas stream, this value represents a minor deficit in the exergy
calculations and is not significant for the analysis of the performance
of the plant.



68

Table 17 – Exergy losses per subsystem, kW.

System Value

EES Hysys

Separation plant 20062.8 16968.2
Gas turbines 1006.3 758.3
Gas boost 83.4 104.2
Gas injection 1590.3 1981.2

Total 22742.7 19811.9

Likewise the results obtained by Nguyen et al. (2012), the great-
est exergy losses are associated with the exhaust gases coming from gas
turbines. Similarly, when the combustor chambers in the power gen-
eration subsystem are not considered, the largest exergy destruction
takes place in separation plant (mainly caused by pressure reduction
in manifold) and in the gas injection compressors. This observation is
in accordance with the previous analysis carried out by Nguyen et al.
(2013) and Voldsund et al. (2010) for fixed platforms in North Sea.

Table 18 – Exergy destruction rate per subsystem, kW.

System Value

EES Hysys

Separation plant 2064.5 3879.9
Gas turbines 17345.6 19795.1
Gas boost system 95.2 309.6
Gas injection system 2713.3 3592.6
Seawater injection system 933.4 1313.8

Total 23152.0 28891.1

The Sankey diagram is a graphical representation of any type of
flow or transfers (e.g. material, energy, exergy, emissions, costs, etc.)
through a series of processes, in which the width of the arrows is shown
proportionally to the flow quantity. In this case, this diagram is used
to visualize the relation between the exergy flows within the plant and
the proportion of their magnitudes (commonly called Grassmann dia-
gram when refers to exergy flows). From the Grassmann diagram for
the Hysys case displayed in Fig. 28 it can be seen that the exergy bal-



69

ance is largely dominated by exergy associated with the oil and gas
streams when compared with the others associated with their process-
ing. This behavior is related with the high specific chemical exergy
associated with these streams. Given that any improvement in the en-
ergy efficiency of the plant would modify the rest of the streams, it
appears that the shape and the proportion of this diagram are unlikely
to change. Subsequently, it is reasonable that an exergy performance
indicator for this type of installations were process-oriented and rep-
resents how far a process is from ideality. In that way, exergy flows
should not be considered entirely as exergy products or fuels in order
to avoid values too high or too low for performance indicators.

Figure 28 – Simplified Grassmann diagram of the plant, exergy flows
in MW.

Analogously to the energy balances of the plant, the individual
contribution of each system in the total exergy destruction of the plant
can be calculated using the Eq. 4.1 and can serve for comparison with
previous studies. In that way, Tab. 19 presents the corresponding data
of the present work together with those reported by Nguyen et al.



70

(2012). Distributions of the destroyed exergy and exergy losses for both
models are exhibited in Figs. 29 and 30 respectively. Additionally, data
obtained considering only the separation plant, the gas boosting and
the gas injection were compared with those reported by Voldsund et al.
(2010) (see Tab. 20). The exergy destruction sharing displayed values
very close to the data obtained by the first reference, especially for the
case developed in Hysys. However, in the second comparison the values
shown a considerable discrepancy with the data published. This can be
associated with the great difference between the operation conditions
and the fact that the inlet manifold (where a sudden expansion of well
fluid occurs) is not considered by the author. By other side, concerning
the exergy losses that take place in the plant (see Tab. 21), results
suggest that the exergy losses sharing is associated directly with the
production parameters of the plant.

yD,i =
BD,i?
BD,i

yL,i =
BL,i?
BL,i

(4.1)

Table 19 – Exergy destruction rate distribution.

System yD,i This work

Nguyen, 2012 EES Hysys

Separation plant 0.16-0.18 0.089 0.134
Gas turbines 0.65-0.68 0.749 0.685
Gas boost system 0.033-0.042 0.004 0.011
Gas injection system 0.076-0.101 0.117 0.124
Seawater injection system 0.03-0.035 0.040 0.045

Table 20 – Exergy destruction rate distribution (only separation and
gas processes).

System yD,i This work

Voldsund, 2010 EES Hysys

Separation plant 0.23 0.424 0.499
Gas boost system 0.11 0.020 0.040
Gas injection system 0.66 0.557 0.462



71

Figure 29 – Exergy destruction rate distribution for: (a)-Hysys model
and (b)-EES model.

Figure 30 – Exergy losses distribution for: (a)-Hysys model and (b)-
EES model.



72

Table 21 – Exergy losses distribution.

System yL,i This work

Nguyen, 2012 EES Hysys

Exhaust gases 0.914 0.796 0.743
Cooling water 0.065 0.091 0.126
Flared gases 0.012 0.000 0.000
Production water 0.009 0.113 0.131

4.3.2 Exergy performance

From the definition of the exergy performance indicators pre-
sented in Sec. 3.3.3.2, it is possible to demonstrate how the consumed
exergy is effectively transferred to obtain the desired effect (or prod-
ucts) of the plant. Tabs. 22 and 23 summarize the data related to the
exergy performance obtained from models developed using Hysys and
EES respectively. Particularly, the formulation presented in Eq. 4.2 was
applied to the exergy balance obtained with the EES model in order to
obtain comparable data. Despite compositional changes were not taken
into account, there is a change in the mixing term due to the phase sep-
aration. As pointed by Silva et al. (2012), this term corresponds to the
main product of separation processes.

?mixBj = nj

(
R T0

?
zi ln (zi · ?i)

)
(4.2)

where nj corresponds to the molar flow of stream j in kmol/s
and ?i (i.e. activity coefficient of component i) were approximated to
1. ?mixBj is given in kJ/s.

Figures 31 and 32 display the exergy efficiencies (?p and ? re-
spectively) for each subsystem obtained by both models. Regarding
the degree of thermodynamic of perfection, the system with the worst
performance within the processing plant (i.e. without considering the
combustor chambers) corresponds to the seawater injection system fol-
lowed by the gas injection for both models. This behavior is related
to the proportion between the outlet exergy and the unused exergy
(i.e. losses or destruction) by the operation; the lower the outlet ex-
ergy magnitude, worse the exergy performance is. Thus, for processes
with outlets with high exergy content (e.g. gas streams) an amount of
unused exergy does not have a significant impact over ?p. While pro-



73

Table 22 – Exergy performance indicators by system - Hysys model.

System ?p ?

Separation plant 0.9957 0.008
Gas turbines 0.2808 0.281
Gas boost system 0.9957 0.030
Gas injection system 0.9919 0.403
Seawater injection system 0.8857 0.553

Whole plant 0.9897 0.124

Table 23 – Exergy performance indicators - EES model

System ?p ?

Separation plant 0.9953 0.004
Gas turbines 0.2563 0.256
Gas boost system 0.9958 0.504
Gas injection system 0.9943 0.517
Seawater injection system 0.9120 0.747

Whole plant 0.9901 0.137

cesses with products with relatively low exergy content (e.g. seawater
streams) have a ?p more sensible to their unused exergy.

By other side, considering the exergy indicator ? for each subsys-
tem within the processing plant, the separation plant appears with the
lowest exergy performance. This is related with the exergy-dissipative
operations (i.e. pressure reduction, mixing and recirculation) that
dominate the separation plant. Analogously, it can be inferred that
the discrepancies between the values reported by the models are as-
sociated with the recirculation modeling. While in EES model these
streams were not considered, in Hysys were considered as exergy losses
for each specific operation.

Particularly for the gas turbines, the value of ?p equals the ?
value. This is related to the power produced by this system and the
performance reported for the equipment. The difference between the
reported values from both models corresponds to the operation point
of turbines. While the power required by the plant in EES was 12.97
MW, the power requirement in Hysys was 14.57 MW.

Regarding the overall exergy performance, the results were con-
sistent for both models. EES reports higher performance indicators,



74

Figure 31 – Exergy efficiencies (?p) for Hysys and EES models.

Figure 32 – Exergy efficiencies (?p) for Hysys and EES models.



75

probably associated with the calculation of the specific chemical ex-
ergy of the oil streams for ?p and with the calculation of mixing exergy
for ?. In the first case, the sum of component contributions to obtain
bch,oil (Hysys case) was greater than the calculation of this considering
the oil as a unique substance (EES case). Consequently, this affects
directly the ratio between the outlet exergy and unused exergy (thus
?p). By other side, considering that the oily and aqueous phases were
treated as pure substances in EES (i.e. ?mixBj = 0), the mixing term
difference between products and inlets was greater than that reported
using Hysys.

4.4 ORC COUPLED TO THE PLANT

There are multiple considerations and variables to define in order
to model adequately the operation of the ORC and its incorporation to
an existing system. Given the extensive literature dedicated to explore
the performance of this system and the focus of this work, the ORC
modeled to be included into the studied plant was defined based on pre-
vious studies that indicate cyclopentane as the best choice when there
is a comprise between performance, compactness and economic revenue
(PIEROBON et al., 2013; LAI; WENDLAND; FISCHER, 2011). However, the
integration of the cycle still has various degrees of freedom to adjust its
service within the plant. As can be deduced from the information pre-
sented in Sec. 3.4.3, following criteria were applied in the Hysys model
with the purpose of reducing conveniently the number of degrees of
freedom when calculating the performance of the integrated ORC.

• The maximum HTF temperature was set to 300?C (stream E07).

• The mass flow of HTF is calculated to meet a pinch point of 10?C
in the heat exchanger E-E01.

• The ORC working fluid flow and HTF outlet temperature (stream
E02) are updated to meet the pinch point restrictions of the heat
exchangers within the ORC system.

• A superheating of 1?C was set at E-F01 (ORC subsystem).

• A pinch point of 5?C was set for the regenerator E-F04.

• The evaporator pinch point is updated to meet a minimum ap-
proach of 5 ?C between the cyclopentane temperature profile and
the HTF temperature profile.



76

• The ORC output is subtracted from total plant demand, and the
operation conditions of gas turbines are updated according to this
value.

With the adoption of these criteria, the ORC system is modeled
completely defining only the evaporation temperature at E-F02. In
that way, a set of 20 temperatures ranging from 180?C up to 235.5?C
were run in order to examine the behavior of the energy and exergy
parameters of the cycle and choose a convenient evaporation temper-
ature. As it can be seen in Fig. 33, the examined parameters were:
(i) cyclopentane mass flow, (ii) ORC exergy performance, (iii) Total
rejected heat and (iv) ORC output.

Figure 33 – Variation of (i) cyclopentane mass flow, (ii) ORC perfor-
mance, (iii) Rejected heat and (iv) ORC output with the evaporation
temperature of cyclopentane.



77

An inspection of the figures on the left side indicates a local min-
imum of the working fluid mass flow and the plant rejected heat in the
proximity of its critical point (226.8?C). Conversely, the performance
and the output of the cycle demonstrate a continuous increase with the
evaporation temperature (Tev). This behavior apparently refutes the
results obtained by Declaye (2009) described previously in Sec. 2.3.2.2.
However, as explained by Invernizzi, Iora e Silva (2007), when the criti-
cal temperature (Tc) of the working fluid is lower than that of the heat
source (as in this case), the resulting optimum Tev is very close to its
Tc. On the contrary, if Tc is higher than the maximum temperature
of the heat source (as ketone in the example earlier shown), optimum
Tev should be determined in order to maximize the ORC output.

In order to investigate the behavior of the curves shown previ-
ously, an examination of the ORC operation conditions and the HTF
outlet temperature was carried out. An inspection of Fig. 34 indicates
a local maximum of HTF outlet temperature (TE02) close to the Tev
where the heat rejected by the plant reported a minimum.

Figure 34 – Variation of the HTF outlet temperature and HTF mass
flow with the evaporation temperature of cyclopentane.



78

Analogously, operation conditions of the cycle using the mini-
mum and the maximum evaporation temperatures (180?C and 235.6?C
respectively) were compared with those calculated with a Tev = 226.8

?C
in the T-s diagram. As can be seen from Fig. 35(i), the higher the Tev,
the larger the ?P in the expander and the higher the temperature of
the expander outlet (stream F11). Consequently, there is an increment
of the ORC output (see Fig. 33(iv)) with the simultaneous reduction
of its heat input, inherent to the load reduction in gas turbines (see
Fig. 36). As the heat input decreases, the working fluid mass flow
should be reduced to meet the energy balance of the cycle compo-
nents with the established constraints (see Fig. 33(i)). As illustrated in
Fig. 36, the increase of ORC output simultaneously with the decrease
of the cyclopentane mass flow implies a rise in its specific work.

Figure 35 – T-s diagram of the ORC at different evaporation tempera-
tures.

Taking into account the temperature rise at the expander outlet,
the heat capacity flows and the PPD constraints for E-F03 (economizer)
and E-F04 (regenerator), an increase of Tev results in an increase of
TE02. As this temperature increases, the HTF temperature difference
at E-E01 decreases and its circulating mass flow should be increased in
order to meet the energy balance of the equipment with its specified
PPD.

By other side, the behavior of the results suggests that there is a
maximum TE02 (see Figs 34 and 35(ii)) reported at a Tev in the prox-



79

Figure 36 – Variation of ORC input and cyclopentane specific work
with the evaporation temperature.

imity of 226.8?C in which the cyclopentane mass flow and the rejected
heat display a minimum value (see Fig 33(i)-(iii)). It could be inferred
that the location of this point is influenced by the performance of the
cycle together with the gas turbines operation, which is determined by
the whole plant demand.

In this way, the ORC working Tev was set at the temperature
that reports the minimum mass flow and rejected heat among the 20
analyzed temperatures (from 180?C up to 235.6 ?C) in each analized
scenario. For this case a Tev of 226.8

?C was set for the ORC system,
which reports an output of 3.48 MW.

With the aim of showing the effect that the ORC has over the op-
eration of the plant, a comparison of some key parameters is presented
in Tab. 24. In general, the inclusion of the ORC within the plant has
a positive impact over its performance. The improvement of thermal
efficiency of the power generation and the reduction of the heat rejec-
tion of the plant were remarkable, although fuel savings and reduction
of CO2 emissions are the most interesting improvements environmen-
tally and economically speaking. Concerning the exergy performance



80

indicators, the operation of the ORC system has a greater impact over
the chosen ?II , which would be the most appropriate to demonstrate
its influence over the plant performance.

Table 24 – Effect of the ORC integration over some production param-
eters of the plant

Parameter Base Base +ORC % Diff.

Power demand, kW 14459 14821 2.50
Heat rejected, kW 39662 33177 -16.35
Fuel consumption, 103 Nm3/d 106.2 90.4 -14.93
?, MJ/m3 oil 19.44 16.54 -14.93
Exhaust mass flow, kg/s 60.85 56.31 -7.45
Thermal efficiency 0.2946 0.3550 20.50
?P 0.9897 0.9913 0.16
?II 0.1250 0.1461 16.91

4.5 PRODUCTION PARAMETER PROFILES

Given the chosen performance indicators and based on the ob-
tained results concerning the integration of the ORC within the plant,
an analysis of the behavior of the plant performance when varying pro-
duction parameters is done by comparing the base case with that with
the ORC incorporated. These results can bring a better understand-
ing of the effect of the ORC over the performance of the plant under
changing operation conditions, which is the most common situation in
this type of installation. As described earlier in Sec. 3.2.4, the perfor-
mance of the plant was evaluated along an arbitrary production profile
formed by 16 cases varying 5 production parameters separately, such
that each parameter was modified (increased or reduced) independently
along 4 cases. Table 25 presents the chosen production parameters to-
gether with their variation ranges and associated cases. The base case
analyzed in previous sections corresponds to the case N? 6.

4.5.1 ORC working Tev establishment

Prior to the evaluation of the production profile, it is necessary
to establish the ORC working Tev in each scenario. In that way, Tab. 26



81

Table 25 – Production parameters profiles.

Parameter Range Cases Behavior

Produced oil, m3/d 1800 - 9000 0 - 3 increased
Production water, m3/d 200 - 3800 3 - 6 increased
Well pressure, kPa 1500 - 3000 6 - 9 decreased
Gas injected, 10 6· Nm3/d 1.5 - 2.1 9 - 12 increased
Seawater injected, m3/d 12000 - 18000 12 - 15 increased

presents the selected temperatures using the criterion described in the
previous section. By the other side, Fig. 37 displays the curves of
the total rejected heat as a function of ORC Tev for some reference
scenarios with the aim of illustrating the adopted method and show
the local minimum found in each case.

Table 26 – ORC Tev chosen for each case.

Case Tev Min. Heat, kW

0 226.8 32097
1 229.7 32383
2 226.8 32658
3 229.7 32929
4 229.7 33028
5 229.7 33118
6 226.8 33177
7 229.7 33180
8 229.7 33183
9 229.7 33180
10 229.7 36085
11 229.7 38961
12 226.8 41829
13 226.8 41829
14 226.8 43042
15 229.7 43641

As can be seen, the minimum heat rejected by the plant is appar-
ently located at a Tev between 223.8 and 232.6

?C independently the
operation conditions of the plant (the values found for Tev were 226.8
?C in some cases and 229.7 ?C in the others). This range is relatively
wide (8.8 ?C) and it is not possible to conclude where the minimum



82

is located because the number of points within the analyzed Tev range
were not enough to obtain a narrower range for its location. An al-
gorithm of optimization can be applied in further analysis in order to
calculate its value with more accuracy and determine if it is constant
independently to the operation parameters of the plant.

Figure 37 – Total rejected heat vs. ORC Tev for selected scenarios.

4.5.2 Influence of production parameters over the plant per-
formance

Concerning the power plant demand, it can be seen in Fig. 38(i)
that is widely dominated by the injection of gas and seawater. The



83

reduction of well pressure evidently has no effect over the power supply
to the plant and the pumping work (produced oil and production water)
is not appreciable when compared with the injection processes. By the
other hand, the integration of the ORC system gives a slight increase
of power demand due to its pumping work. Analogously, the rejected
heat presents a great dependence with the operation that reports the
larger energy consumption, which is logical since the greater demand,
the higher the power generated by the gas turbines, thus more is the
fuel burned and the exhaust gases rejected. The rejection of heat is
notably reduced by the ORC integration, a reduction of about 15.4-
18.5% is reported along the entire production profile. Evidently, an
increase of the work supplied by the ORC implies a reduction of the
waste heat of the plant.

Figure 38 – Total rejected heat (i), power demand (i) and thermal
efficiency of power generation (ii) profiles.

By other side, the thermal efficiency of the power generation
within the plant is presented in Fig. 38(ii). Initially for cases 0 to
3, there is a little increase in thermal efficiency when the ORC is not
included. However, the opposite is found when this system is operating.
This behavior could be associated with the heat withdrawal in the
heat exchanger E-B02: as the oil or water flow increases, the heat
transferred to the well fluid in this equipment also increases. Thus, the
exergy transferred by the HTF for activating the ORC diminish with
the inherent decrease in ORC output (as illustrated in Fig. 39).

Analogously to the power demand and rejected heat, the thermal



84

Figure 39 – ORC input and output, MW.

efficiency of the plant is strongly influenced by the injection of gas and
seawater processes. Also considering that the inherent efficiency of the
gas turbines increases as their load increases, a notable enhancement
of about 20-24.4% is obtained along the entire profile when applying
the ORC system for WHR.

The degree of thermodynamic perfection ?P together with the
proposed indicator ? are particularly influenced by the quantity of the
produced oil in the plant (see Fig. 40(i)). It is likely that this behavior
is linked with the great exergy content of oil and to the rapid decrease of
the ratio between the consumed energy and oil production respectively.
The influence of the other parameters over ?P and ? is illustrated in
Fig. 40(ii), where the first three cases were omitted. An increase in
the production water flow reduces marginally ?P , which is associated
with the inherent increase of the exergy losses. While it practically has
no effect over the ? value. A similar situation is reported for the well
pressure, but its decrease slightly improves the value of ?P evidently due
to the reduction of the exergy destroyed at inlet manifolds (represented
by valve L-B00).

By the other hand, the injection of gas and water has a greater
impact over these indicators. It seems that he increase of gas and
water flows implies a decrease of ?P , and an increase in ?. It could



85

Figure 40 – ?P and ?: (i) for cases 0 through 15 and (ii) for cases 3
through 15.



86

be linked to the greater exergy losses rejection in the injection systems
and the increment of the energy consumption respectively. Anew, the
application of ORC seems to be favorable for the performance of the
plant independently of the operation conditions. The improvement was
around 0.15-0.59% and 15.8-18.4% for ?P and ? respectively.

In general, the exergy performance indicator ?II exhibits a greater
variation along the production profile than ?P and ? (see Fig. 41). As
it can be seen in Fig. 41(i), the shape of the curve for the plant with
the ORC incorporated is approximately the same as that displayed in
the base case. However, this graph was split into case groups depend-
ing on the varying parameter in order to obtain a better resolution.
First, it seems that the behavior of ?II displays the same effect that
?I in the first three cases (see Fig. 41(ii)), where the decrease of the
performance efficiency is related to the amount of heat withdrawn by
the HTF to activate the ORC. However, between the third and fourth
case, there is a sudden rise in the ?II value. The causes of this behavior
are not clear, but it can be attributable to the simultaneous influence
of the separation addend (which is increasing) and the decline of ORC
output on the indicator ?II . In the same way, the behavior of ?II with
respect to the production water flow and well pressure can be seen in
Fig. 41(iii) and (iv) respectively. While the increase of the production
water flow results in a decrease of the exergy efficiency due clearly to
the growth of the exergy losses associated with this stream, a reduction
of well pressure prior to manifold valves demonstrate an improvement
of ?II . It could be linked to the reduction of the destroyed exergy at
this point.

By other side, the rise of the injected gas and seawater flows
increments the value of the overall ?II . It could be explained by the
increment of the ratio between the product exergy and the consumed
exergy as the gas or seawater flow increases in each subsystem. In
addition, the ORC contribution seems to be uniform along these profiles
as illustrated in Figs. 41(v) and 41(vi).

With the purpose of comparing the influence of the analyzed pro-
duction parameters over the exergy efficiency of the plant and contrast
it with that using the coupled ORC, an influence factor f is introduced
for each segment shown in Fig. 41 using the following expression:

f =

??????II??n
???? (4.3)

where ?n corresponds to the normalized production parameter



87

Figure 41 – ?II variation along the production profile.



88

(i.e. ? represents the oil flow, well pressure, water flow, etc.). As
can be seen from Fig. 42(i), the amount of injected seawater seems
to be the variable with the greatest weight over the exergy indicator
?II (i.e. a variation of seawater flow results in a greater variations of
?II when compared with the other parameters), independently to the
variation of the other production parameters. In contrast, the produced
oil has the lowest influence over this indicator when no ORC is used
and its impact presents a slight decline as this flow increases. By other
side, the effect of the injected gas increase and the production water
decrease is intermediate and presents a minimal drop as the injected gas
increases while the effect of the production water seems to be constant.
Analogously, the influence of the well pressure over ?II appears to be
greater as its value decreases.

Figure 42 – Influence factor f for each production parameter. (i) cur-
rent configuration, (ii) ORC integrated.

It can be inferred from Fig. 41 that the improvement of ?II of



89

the plant using the ORC was around 14-17% along the entire profile.
Despite its contribution apparently was uniform in whole the range,
data presented in Fig. 42(ii) suggest that the impact of the produc-
tion parameters over the plant performance using the ORC was altered
when compared with the current configuration. The increase of ?II is
dominated principally by the amount of injected water, except when
the flow of production water approaches its minimum value (point at
upper right corner). Analogously, as the injected gas flow and well
pressure increase, their impact over the exergy performance decrease.
The influence of oil flow along the profile is not very clear probably
due to the simultaneous effect of the ORC output and the separation
addend in the definition of ?II . A further analysis can be conducted
in order to analyze the impact of these parameters separately over the
exergy performance as defined in this work.

4.5.3 Influence of the production parameters over ORC per-
formance

Figure 43 – Influence factor f for each production parameter applied
in the ORC performance.



90

As mentioned earlier, when an ORC system is used as WHR
system, it is more advantageous to obtain a greater output than a
greater efficiency. Consequently, the variable analyzed to determine
the influence of the production parameters over the performance of
this system was its power output (as illustrated in Fig. 39). In general,
it was found that the oil and water flows have a negative impact over
the ORC input. As mentioned previously, the greater the fluid flow,
the lower the amount of heat for activating the ORC; thus the lower its
output. Analogously, well pressure has no practical effect over the ORC
output and the injection of gas and seawater dominates noticeably the
performance of this system. Evidence for this is presented in Fig. 43,
where the influence factor introduced previously was applied to the
ORC output.

As noted earlier, the parameter with the greatest influence over
ORC performance is the gas injection/export followed by the seawater
injection, except when the oil flow is low enough to promote the amount
of heat transferred to the ORC (a situation that is unlike given the main
purpose of the plant). This tendency is evidently caused by the power
consumed by both injection operations. The greater the amount of
gas (or water) to be injected, greater the required power of the plant
and more gas is burned in turbines, which produce more exhaust gases;
thus more available heat to activate the cycle. In contrast, although
the effect of the reduction of water flow increases along the profile,
this is not enough to overcome the effect of the injection processes.
As predicted before, the effect of the reduction of well pressure has no
inference over the performance of ORC.



91

5 DISCUSSION

Previous works focused on the implementation of ORC technol-
ogy for WHR in offshore platforms have demonstrated its usefulness
under specified conditions in particular platforms (LARSEN et al., 2013;
PIEROBON; NGUYEN, 2012b; PIEROBON et al., 2013). However, these
studies have not considered the inherent variation in the platform pro-
cess conditions along its lifespan and by the other side, the exergy
analysis for identifying the operations that more strongly demote the
efficiency of a process has not been fully adopted in this type of indus-
try. In that way, this work implements the exergy analysis approach
to examine the effect of an ORC over the performance of a Brazilian
FPSO under varying production conditions.

The adopted procedure dealt with the adequate exergy calcula-
tion of petroleum fractions and their mixtures as well as the formula-
tion of an appropriate performance indicator associated with the main
tasks of the plant. The calculation routines were implemented using
two computer programs: Hysys and EES. Particularly, the most signif-
icant simplifications were applied to the EES algorithm and the results
demonstrated a good agreement for both models concerning the over-
all plant efficiency. However, there were discrepancies when analyzing
the efficiency of plant subsystems, apparently caused mainly by the
omission of recycle streams in the EES routine.

When the procedure for oil characterization were assuming a
group of pseudocomponents, it is recommended to incorporate the cal-
culation of chemical exergy of these hypothetical compounds together
with their Gibbs free energy (?fG

o), in order to avoid uncertainties
when a chemical reaction were carrying out within the model. How-
ever, it is important to emphasize the fact that all the exergy balances
done in this work were corroborated using the relation between the
generated entropy Sgen and the destroyed exergy BD (see Sec. 3.3.2),
showing a good agreement.

Analogously, the ORC system was modeled attached to the exist-
ing HTF circuit, taking part of the exergy of the exhaust gases coming
from the gas turbines in order to produce additional power. The ORC
working fluid chosen was the cyclopentane and its evaporation temper-
ature was set aiming a minimum amount of rejected heat. Next, the
complete model (plant + ORC) was compared with the current configu-
ration through a hypothetical profile, varying (i) the produced oil flow,
(ii) the production water flow, (iii) the well pressure, (iv) the gas in-



92

jected and (v) the seawater injected flow, within the design constraints
of the plant.

Evaluation of the power demand, total rejected heat and ther-
mal efficiency of the plant indicates a wide influence of the amount of
gas and seawater injected back to the reservoir. This observation is in
agreement with previous studies (NGUYEN et al., 2013; VOLDSUND et
al., 2010) and is associated with the increase of burned gas (thus the
exhaust gases) and the rise of the power load at gas turbines. Particu-
larly, the ORC output and its contribution is influenced by the oil and
production water flows. It must be related with the amount of heat
withdrawn from the HTF in heat exchanger E-B02. The greater the
oil (or water) flow, the lesser the available heat to activate the ORC.
In the same way, the injection of gas and water appear to have the
greatest effect over the performance indicators ?P and ? when the oil
flow is not considered.

The use of the degree of thermodynamic perfection ?P , was com-
pared with another exergy indicator ?II . Although the behavior of the
results was similar, the figures obtained using ?II , make more evident
the effect of the variation of the plant operation conditions over its
performance.

Obtained results show that the ORC integration has a substan-
tial contribution to the performance of the plant and its magnitude
remains approximately homogeneous along the entire profile. A com-
parison of the influence of the production parameters over the exergy
efficiency pointed the seawater injection flow out as the parameter with
the greatest impact over the indicator when the ORC is not installed.
However, the incorporation of the ORC demonstrates an increase of the
influence of the other parameters; especially of the production water
flow. By other side, the production variable that affects more markedly
the ORC output is the injected gas flow, which is directly associated
with the increment of the exergy carried to the ORC.

The data presented in this work are in line with previous studies
focused on the exergy analysis of offshore platforms and the use of ORC
the system for improving their energetic performance. Additionally, a
primary comparison of the incidence of chosen production variables
was carried out, demonstrating that their impact over the plant perfor-
mance depends basically on their magnitude. Particularly in this case,
the water injection flow was identified as the most dominant variable
determining the performance of the plant. It could be associated with
the fact that this operation has the best performance among the sub-
systems of the plant and has the second largest power demand within



93

the plant. Although this observation corresponds to the analyzed plant
specifically, this type of comparison offers a wider panorama concern-
ing to what parameter is strongly-affecting the energy performance of
the plant at given circumstances. In the same way, this approach may
be used to analyze other types of production platforms with different
configurations and processes involved. For example, for oils that have
high salt content where a secondary ”washing” stage is included, the
exergy contribution of the salt content should be considered at inlet
stream(s) and its separation must be evident in the performance indi-
cator. Another case can be the case of heavy crudes or with trend to
form emulsions, where more heating is needed to perform the separa-
tion of the water from the oil; here the exergy indicator proposed in this
work could be strongly influenced by the amount of heat involved in
the separation stage (as anticipated in the work of Oliveira e Hombeeck
(1997)).

Analogously, the performance of the ORC system was evaluated
together with the variation of the production parameters of the plant.
This innovative approach can bring a better idea of the most appropri-
ate size of the ORC system when applied to this type of installations,
which would not be necessarily one with the optimal size under a spe-
cific condition, but one that best fulfills the plant requirements and
constraints along its lifespan.

The understanding of the behavior of the performance of the
plant with variable production conditions –as proposed in this study,
could have an important contribution concerning the analysis of actual
production profiles and the establishment of the actual convenience
of an ORC system given an actual production forecast. In that way,
it would be necessary a validation of the proposed methodology with
known profiles (record) of plants already established. Further analysis
can be conducted considering performance, control and economic opti-
mization strategies, fluid selection and more detailed comparison of the
production variables aiming the fabrication and installation of suitable
ORC systems in this industry.



94



95

6 CONCLUSION

The present work demonstrated the advantage of implementing
an ORC as WHR system in an existing offshore platform under variable
production conditions. It was found that the ORC has a positive im-
pact over the performance of the plant independently of their operation
conditions and its contribution seems to be homogeneous and not very
influenced by production parameters of the plant. Specifically, it was re-
ported an improvement of 14-17% in the exergy performance indicator
and a reduction of 15.8-18.4% for the fuel consumption. These figures
evidently imply a reduction of the environmental impact of the plant,
proved by the inherent reduction of exhaust gases emissions and the
reduction of rejected heat to the atmosphere (calculated as 15.4-18.5%
based on current conditions). It would be interesting to complement
these results with an economic analysis (i.e. costs assessment, payback
period, etc.) aiming the feasibility of implementation of this system.
By other side, a comparison of the influence of the production param-
eters over the performance of the analyzed plant indicated the gas and
seawater injection as the most influencing operations over the exergy
performance of the plant.

The main contribution of the present work consists in a pro-
cedure that considers variable operation parameters along the plant
lifespan, aiming a wider panorama for exergy analysis and the appli-
cation of ORC (or other technologies) systems in existing installations
subject to large variations in their process conditions. Additionally, its
application could offer a better understanding of the features that more
strongly demote their efficiency under particular circumstances.

Regarding the modeling of the plant, qualitatively it was found
that overall performance can be directly estimated omitting the com-
position analysis of the petroleum. However, when assessing the indi-
vidual performance of the equipment (or subsystems) of the plant, it
is strongly recommended to consider the composition of the petroleum
since it affects importantly the exergy indicators, especially when a
separation of phases are involved. In that way, the approach proposed
in this work can be useful for selecting an adequate software depend-
ing on the required level of detailing. Analogously, when all the data
of the plant were available, it is advisable to develop and corroborate
the model, including all the components of the plant aiming additional
applications for the unused exergy. For more advanced studies, it is
desirable to give the same thermodynamic basis for the calculation of



96

chemical exergy and the composition of petroleum fractions (avoiding
the use of empirical expressions), in such a way that discrepancies when
considering chemical reactions are prevented.

It is recommended to develop a supplementary optimization al-
gorithm aiming the most suitable Tev for the ORC, meeting the max-
imum exergy efficiency of the plant. Nevertheless, the results of the
present work constitute a reference basis for further analysis focused
on the optimization of the project taking into account the minimiza-
tion of the volume and cost of ORC components such that it fulfills the
process requirements along a variable production profile. By other side
an environmental impact analysis (e.g. LCA or exergo-environmental
analysis) could be useful in order to demonstrate and justify the inte-
gration of this type of technologies beyond economic issues.

In order to promote the application of this type of technologies,
the examination of commercially available equipment would be advan-
tageous, such that the ORC modelling corresponds to real cycles and
can address the choice of actual alternatives.



97

REFERENCES

ABDOLLAHI-DEMNEH, F. et al. Calculating exergy in flowsheeting
simulators: A HYSYS implementation. Energy, Elsevier Ltd, v. 36,
n. 8, p. 5320–5327, ago. 2011.

ARNOLD, K.; STEWART, M. Surface Production Operations: Design
of Oil Handling Systems and Facilities. 3. ed. Burlington: Gulf
Professional, 2008. 722 p.

ASPENTECH. Aspen HYSYS: Simulation Basis Guide. Burlington:
[s.n.], 2011. 570 p.

BAO, J.; ZHAO, L. A review of working fluid and expander selections
for organic Rankine cycle. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews,
Elsevier, v. 24, p. 325–342, ago. 2013.

BARTON, C. M. An overview of offshore concepts. In: Expanding
Facilities Knowledge Workshop. Houston, TX: SPE, 2009. 195 Slides.

BCS. Waste Heat Recovery: Technology and Opportunities in U.S.
Industry. [S.l.]: DOE, 2008. 112 p.

BEJAN, A. Thermal Design and Optimization. USA: Wiley, 1996.
532 p.

BG Group. Lula Crude Oil Assay. 2012.&amp;lt;http://www.bg-
group.com/CrudeOilAssays/Brazil/Pages/Lula.aspx&gt;.

BOTHAMLEY, M. Offshore processing options for oil platforms. In:
Proceedings of SPE Annual Technical Conference. Houston, TX: SPE,
2004. p. 17.

BRANCHINI, L.; PASCALE, A. d. D.; PERETTO, A. Systematic
comparison of ORC configurations by means of comprehensive
performance indexes. Applied Thermal Engineering, v. 61, n. 2, p.
129–140, nov. 2013.

BRUNO, J. C. et al. Modelling and optimisation of solar organic
rankine cycle engines for reverse osmosis desalination. Applied
Thermal Engineering, v. 28, n. 17-18, p. 2212–2226, 2008.

BULLER, A. T. Oil and gas technologies. In: Technology Guide.
Berlin: Springer, 2009. cap. 8, p. 318–323.



98

CENGEL, Y.; BOLES, M. Thermodynamics - An engineering
approach. [S.l.]: McGraw-Hill, 2010. 881 p.

CHANG, A.; PASHIKANTI, K.; LIU, Y. Characterization , Physical
and Thermodynamic Properties of Oil Fractions. In: Refinery
Engineering: Integrated Process Modeling and Optimization. [S.l.]:
Wiley, 2012. cap. 1, p. 1–56.

CHEN, H.; GOSWAMI, D. Y.; STEFANAKOS, E. K. A review
of thermodynamic cycles and working fluids for the conversion of
low-grade heat. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews, Elsevier
Ltd, v. 14, n. 9, p. 3059–3067, 2010.

CRAGER, B. Floating production systems for offshore oil and gas
fields. In: Expanding Facilities Knowledge Workshop. Houston, TX:
SPE, 2010. 47 slides.

DECLAYE, S. Design , optimization and modeling of an organic
Rankine cycle for waste heat recovery. 92 p. Thesis (Graduac?a?o) —
University of Liege, Lie?ge, 2009.

DENG, J.; WANG, R.; HAN, G. A review of thermally activated
cooling technologies for combined cooling, heating and power systems.
Progress in Energy and Combustion Science, v. 37, n. 2, p. 172–203,
abr. 2011.

DOW Chemical. Dowtherm A product information. [S.l.], 2001.

GORDON, B. Floating Production, Storage and Offloading (FPSO)
Facilities. In: Lillehammer Energy Claims Conference. Lillehammer:
CCSL, 2012. 30 slides.

GRIP, C. et al. Possibilities and problems in using exergy expressions
in process integration. In: Proceedings of Renewable Energy Congress.
Linko?ping, Sweden: Linko?ping University, 2011. p. 1605–1612.

HEBERLE, F.; PREIBINGER, M.; BRU?GGEMANN, D. Advanced
ORC fluid research for cycle efficiency improvement. In: International
Symposium on Advanced Waste Heat Valorisation Technologies.
Kortrijk: [s.n.], 2012. 26 Slides.

HINDERINK, A. P. et al. Exergy analysis with a flowsheeting
simulator -I. Theory; calculating exergies of material streams.
Chemical Engineering Science, v. 51, n. 20, p. 4693–4700, 1996.



99

HUNG, T. et al. A study of organic working fluids on system efficiency
of an ORC using low-grade energy sources. Energy, Elsevier Ltd,
v. 35, n. 3, p. 1403–1411, 2010.

IEA. Combined heat and power: Evaluating the benefits of greater
global investment. Paris: OECD/IEA, 2008. 39 p.

IEA. World energy outlook. Paris: OECD/IEA, 2012. 668 p.

INVERNIZZI, C.; IORA, P.; SILVA, P. Bottoming micro-Rankine
cycles for micro-gas turbines. Applied Thermal Engineering, v. 27,
n. 1, p. 100–110, jan. 2007.

KINNEY, B. Field development options / selection strategy. In:
Expanding Facilities Knowledge Workshop. Houston, TX: SPE, 2012.
78 slides.

KOCAMAN, A. Offshore Concept Selection. In: Expanding Facilities
Knowledge Workshop. Houston, TX: SPE, 2008. 72 slides.

LAI, N. A.; WENDLAND, M.; FISCHER, J. Working fluids for
high-temperature organic Rankine cycles. Energy, Elsevier Ltd, v. 36,
n. 1, p. 199–211, 2011.

LARSEN, U. et al. Design and optimisation of organic Rankine cycles
for waste heat recovery in marine applications using the principles of
natural selection. Energy, Elsevier Ltd, p. 1–10, abr. 2013.

LI, Y.-R.; WANG, J.-N.; DU, M.-T. Influence of coupled pinch point
temperature difference and evaporation temperature on performance
of organic Rankine cycle. Energy, v. 42, n. 1, p. 503–509, jun. 2012.

LITTLE, A. B.; GARIMELLA, S. Comparative assessment of
alternative cycles for waste heat recovery and upgrade. Energy, v. 36,
n. 7, p. 4492–4504, 2011.

LUDENA, C.; MIGUEL, C. de; SCHUSCHNY, A. Climate change
and reduction of CO2 emissions. Environment and development series,
CEPAL, n. 150, p. 47, 2012.

MAHONEY, C. N. 2013 deepwater solutions &amp;amp; records for concept
selection. Offshore Magazine, WoodGroup Mustang, 2013.

MAHONEY, C. N.; KITHAS, K. 2013 Worldwide surve of floating
production, storage and offloading (FPSO) units. Offshore Magazine,
WoodGroup Mustang, Houston, 2013.



100

MAXWELL, J. B. Data Book on Hydrocarbons: Application to Process
Engineering. Malabar: Krieger, 1968. 259 p.

NGUYEN, T.-V. et al. Exergetic assessment of energy systems on
North Sea oil and gas platforms. Energy, Elsevier, p. 1–14, 2013.

NGUYEN, T. van et al. Modelling and analysis of offshore energy
systems on North Sea oil and gas platforms. In: Proceedings of the
53rd SIMS conference on Simulation and Modelling. Reykjavik: [s.n.],
2012. p. 16.

OLIVEIRA, S. de; HOMBEECK, M. van. Exergy analysis of
petroleum separation processes in offshore platforms. Energy
Conversion Management, v. 38, n. 15, p. 1577–1584, 1997.

PIEROBON, L. et al. Multi-objective optimization of organic Rankine
cycles for waste heat recovery : Application in an offshore platform.
Energy, Elsevier, v. 58, n. 1, p. 538–549, 2013.

PIEROBON, L.; NGUYEN, T. van. Technologies for waste heat
recovery in offshore applications. In: Energieffektivisering for
fremtiden. Lyngby: [s.n.], 2012. Poster.

PIEROBON, L.; NGUYEN, T. van. Waste heat recovery for offshore
application. In: 1st International Symposium on Advanced Waste Heat
Valorisation Technologies. Kortrijk, Poland: [s.n.], 2012. Poster.

QUOILIN, S. et al. Working fluid selection and operating maps
for Organic Rankine Cycle expansion machines. In: International
Compressor Engineering Conference. Purdue: [s.n.], 2012.

RINGEN, S.; LANUM, J.; MIKNIS, F. P. Calculating heating values
from elemental compositions of fossil fuel. Fuel, v. 58, p. 69–71, 1979.

RIVERO, R.; RENDON, C.; MONROY, L. The exergy of crude
oil mixtures and petroleum fractions : calculation and application.
International Journal of Applied Thermodynamics, v. 2, n. 3, p.
115–123, 1999.

SHIMAMURA, Y. FPSO / FSO : state of the art. Journal of Marine
Science and Technology, v. 7, p. 59–70, 2002.

SIEMENS AG. SGT-400 Industrial Gas Turbine. Houston, TX, 2009.
4 p.&amp;lt;http://www.energy.siemens.com/&gt;.



101

SILVA, J. A. da et al. On the exergy determination for petroleum
fractions and separation processes efficiency. In: 14th Brazilian
Congress of Thermal Sciences and Engineering. Rio de Janeiro:
ABCM, 2012. v. 0, n. 1.

SILVA, M. V. da. Eficie?ncia exerge?tica de unidades estaciona?rias de
produc?a?o de petro?leo. 152 p. Thesis (Master degree) — COPPE–UFRJ,
Rio de Janeiro, 2008.

SIMMONS, M. R. Has oil and gas collapse sealed fate of peak oil?
In: Gulf Coast Chapter - PF&amp;amp;C Study Group Meeting. Houston, TX:
SPE, 2009. 50 slides.

SZARGUT, J.; MORRIS, D. R.; STEWARD, F. R. The exergy
concept and exergy losses. In: Exergy analysis of thermal, chemical,
and metallurgical processes. [S.l.]: Hemisphere, 1988. cap. 1, p. 332.

TCHANCHE, B. F. et al. Low-grade heat conversion into power using
organic Rankine cycles - A review of various applications. Renewable
and Sustainable Energy Reviews, Elsevier, v. 15, n. 8, p. 3963–3979,
2011.

TWU, C. H. An internally consistent correlation for predicting the
critical properties and molecular weights of petroleum and coal-tar
liquids. Fluid Phase Equilibria, Elsevier, v. 16, n. 2, p. 137–150, 1984.

VOLDSUND, M. et al. Exergy analysis of the oil and gas separation
processes on a North sea oil platform. In: Proceedings of the
23rd International Conference on Efficiency, Cost, Optimization,
Simulation and Enviromental Impact of Energy Systems. Lausanne:
[s.n.], 2010. p. 303–310.

WASCO. Process description FPSO Cidade de Itaja??. Singapore, 2012.
23 p.

WATSON, K.; NELSON, E. F. Improved methods for approximating
critical and thermal properties of petroleum fractions. In: Symposium
on physical properties of hydrocarbon mixtures. Washington: ACS,
1933. p. 880–887.

WHITSON, C. H. Characterizing Hydrocarbon Plus Fractions. SPE
Journal, v. 23, n. 4, p. 683–694, 1983.

WILKINSON, R. Speaking oil &amp;amp; gas. Australia: BHP, 2006. 194 p.



102



APPENDIX A -- Hysys model nomenclature





105

A.1 NOMENCLATURE

This appendix presents the full scheme used in Hysys to simulate
the plant (see Sec. A.2) and the nomenclature is introduced in order to
improve the understanding of the model. In that way, Tab. 27 lists all
the items included within the PFD (Process Flow Diagram) together
with their used symbols and acronyms. Here, the letter S refers to the
subsystem wherein the equipment or stream is: A– power generation
subsystem, B– separation plant, C– boost compression subsystem, D–
gas injection/export subsystem, E– HTF circuit, F– ORC subsystem
and H– seawater injection subsystem. In the case of work and heat
flows, the letter Z refers to the associated equipment and correspond
to the letter that identifies it (i.e. bold letters in acronym column). For
example HE-B05 identifies the heat flow (H) associated with the heater
(E) E-B05, which is part of the separation subsystem (B). 00 refers to
the item numeration.

Table 27 – PFD nomenclature.

Item Figure Acronym

Material stream S00

Heat flow HZ-S00

Work flow WZ-S00

Three phase sepa-
rator

V-S00

Air cooler F-S00

Combustor R-A00

Compressor C-S00



106

Table 27 – PFD nomenclature (cont.).

Item Figure Acronym

Cooler E-S00

Expander T-S00

Heat exchanger E-S00

Heater E-S00

Mixer M-S00

Pump P-S00

Recycle R-S00

Separator V-S00

Subsystem As named.

Tee Y-S00

Valve L-S00



107

A.2 PROCESS FLOW DIAGRAMS

Figures 44 through 49 present the process flow diagrams of the
separation plant and its subsystems, including secondary streams as
recycles and condensates separated from gas streams. Second turbine
is also shown together with the split of fuel gas stream (B18) and the
mixing of the exhaust gas streams (A07a and A07b).

Figure 44 – Process flow diagram of a power subsystem turbine (A).



108

Figure 45 – Process flow diagram of the separation plant (B).



109

Figure 46 – Process flow diagram of gas boosting subsystem (C).

Figure 47 – Process flow diagram of gas injection/export subsystem
(D).



110

Figure 48 – Process flow diagram of ORC subsystem (F).

Figure 49 – Process flow diagram of seawater injection subsystem (H).



APPENDIX B -- Hysys code





113

B.1 INTRODUCTION

Within the calculation subroutines of Hysys, the calculation of
the exergy associated to a stream is not included. Consequently, it was
necessary to incorporate a programing code in order to call the values
calculated by the software (e.g. enthalpy, entropy, etc.) and create new
functions to perform the exergy calculation. In accordance with the
proposed methodology, it was necessary to calculate the physical, the
chemical and the mixing exergy separately to obtain the overall exergy
flow of a stream. The following sections present the code incorporated
within the program to execute these routines.

On the other hand, in order to run the cases it was necessary
to create a code to combine adequately the calculation of the opera-
tion conditions of the power subsystem, the separation plant and the
ORC subsystem simultaneously in order to attain the overall model
convergence. This code is presented in Sec. B.7.

B.2 SET DEAD STATE FOR ALL THE STREAMS

B.2.1 Temperature

Sub V a r i a b l e C h a n g e d ( )
On Error GoTo e r r o r h a n d l e r
Dim MS As S t r e a m s
Dim ST As P r o c e s s S t r e a m
Dim X As I n t e r n a l V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r
Dim T0 As Double
T0=a c t i v e v a r i a b l e w r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
Set MS=a c t i v e o b j e c t . F l o w s h e e t . M a t e r i a l S t r e a m s
For Each ST I n MS
Set X=ST . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ”AmbTemp” )
X . V a r i a b l e . S e t V a l u e ( T0 )
Next ST
E r r o r H a n d l e r :

End Sub

B.2.2 Pressure

Sub V a r i a b l e C h a n g e d ( )



114

On Error GoTo e r r o r h a n d l e r
Dim MS As S t r e a m s
Dim ST As P r o c e s s S t r e a m
Dim X As I n t e r n a l V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r
Dim P0 As Double
P0=a c t i v e v a r i a b l e w r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
Set MS=a c t i v e o b j e c t . F l o w s h e e t . M a t e r i a l S t r e a m s
For Each ST I n MS
Set X=ST . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ” AmbPress ” )
X . V a r i a b l e . S e t V a l u e ( P0 )
Next ST
E r r o r H a n d l e r :

End Sub

B.3 PHYSICAL EXERGY

Sub P o s t E x e c u t e ( )
On Error GoTo E r r o r H a n d l e r
Dim Stream As F l u i d
Dim Exergy As R e a l V a r i a b l e
Set Stream = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Set Pure = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Set Exergy = A c t i v e V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e
Set X=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ”AmbTemp” )
T0=X . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
Set X=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ” AmbPress ” )
P0=X . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
Set T=a c t i v e o b j e c t . Temperature
Set P=a c t i v e o b j e c t . P r e s s u r e

I f ( Stream . V a p o u r F r a c t i o n . IsKnown And Stream .
P r e s s u r e . IsKnown And Stream . MolarFlow . IsKnown
And T0&lt;&gt;(?32767+273.15) And Stream .
M o l a r F r a c t i o n s . IsKnown ( 0 ) ) Then

Dim compounds As HYSYS . Components
Dim comp As HYSYS . Component
Dim MassFrac As V a r i a n t
Dim MassPure As V a r i a n t
Dim compH , compH0 , comE As Double
Dim compS , compS0 , compE As Double
MassFrac =Stream . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e



115

MassPure=Pure . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e
Set compounds = Stream . Components
Set P u r e s = Pure . Components
comE=0

For v a r = 0 To compounds . Count?1
For i = 0 To P u r e s . Count?1

MassPure ( i )=0
Next i
MassPure ( v a r )=1
Pure . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e=MassPure

I f Pure . TPFlash ( Pure . TemperatureValue , Pure .
P r e s s u r e V a l u e )=fsFlashOK Then

compH=Pure . MassEnthalpy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg ” )
compS=Pure . MassEntropy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg?C” )
Pure . Temperature . S e t V a l u e ( T0 , ”C” )
Pure . P r e s s u r e . S e t V a l u e ( P0 , ”kPa” )
Pure . TPFlash ( )
compH0=Pure . MassEnthalpy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg ” )
compS0=Pure . MassEntropy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg?C” )
compE=(compH?compH0 )?(T0 + 2 7 3 . 1 5 ) ?( compS?compS0 )
comE=comE+MassFrac ( v a r ) ?compE
Pure . Temperature . S e t V a l u e (T, ”C” )
Pure . P r e s s u r e . S e t V a l u e (P , ”kPa” )
End I f

Next v a r
Exergy . S e t V a l u e ( comE? Stream . MassFlow . GetValue ( ” kg /

s ” ) , ” kJ / s ” )
Else

Exergy . Erase ( )
E r r o r H a n d l e r :

End I f
End Sub

B.4 CHEMICAL EXERGY

’ C h e m i c a l E x e r g y With Heat Flow U n i t
Sub P o s t E x e c u t e ( )
On Error GoTo E r r o r H a n d l e r
Dim Stream As F l u i d
Dim Exergy As R e a l V a r i a b l e



116

Set Stream = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Set Exergy = A c t i v e V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e
I f ( Stream . V a p o u r F r a c t i o n . IsKnown And Stream .

P r e s s u r e . IsKnown And Stream . MolarFlow . IsKnown
And T0&lt;&gt;(?32767+273.15) And Stream .
M o l a r F r a c t i o n s . IsKnown ( 0 ) ) Then

Dim Comps As HYSYS . Components
Dim Comp As HYSYS . Component
Dim MolFrac As V a r i a n t
Dim Comchem As Double
MolFrac =Stream . M o l a r F r a c t i o n s V a l u e
Set Comps = Stream . Components
Comchem=0
For v a r = 0 To Comps . Count?1

Set Comp = Comps . Item ( v a r )
I f MolFrac ( v a r )=0 Then
Comchem=Comchem+MolFrac ( v a r ) ?Comp .

G e t U s e r P r o p e r t y ( ”Mol Chm Ex . ” )
Else
Comchem=Comchem+MolFrac ( v a r ) ?Comp .

G e t U s e r P r o p e r t y ( ”Mol Chm Ex . ” ) ’+MolFrac ( v a r )
?Log ( MolFrac ( v a r ) )

End I f
Next v a r
Exergy . S e t V a l u e ( Comchem? Stream . MolarFlow . GetValue (

” kgmole / s ” ) , ” kJ / s ” )
Else

Exergy . Erase ( )
E r r o r H a n d l e r :

End I f
End Sub

B.5 MIXING EXERGY

Sub P o s t E x e c u t e ( )
On Error GoTo E r r o r H a n d l e r
Dim Stream As F l u i d
Dim Exergy As R e a l V a r i a b l e
Set Stream = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Set Pure = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Set Exergy = A c t i v e V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e



117

Set X=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ”AmbTemp” )
T0=X . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )

I f ( Stream . V a p o u r F r a c t i o n . IsKnown And Stream .
P r e s s u r e . IsKnown And Stream . MolarFlow . IsKnown
And T0&lt;&gt;(?32767+273.15) And Stream .
M o l a r F r a c t i o n s . IsKnown ( 0 ) ) Then

Dim Comps As HYSYS . Components
Dim Comp As HYSYS . Component
Dim MassFrac As V a r i a n t
Dim MassPure As V a r i a n t
Dim ComH As Double
Dim ComS As Double
MassFrac =Stream . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e
MassPure=Pure . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e
Set Comps = Stream . Components
Set P u r e s = Pure . Components
ComH=0
ComS=0

For v a r = 0 To Comps . Count?1
For i = 0 To P u r e s . Count?1

MassPure ( i )=0
Next i
MassPure ( v a r )=1
Pure . M a s s F r a c t i o n s V a l u e=MassPure

I f Pure . TPFlash ( Pure . TemperatureValue , Pure .
P r e s s u r e V a l u e )=fsFlashOK Then

ComH=ComH+MassFrac ( v a r ) ?Pure . MassEnthalpy .
GetValue ( ” kJ / kg ” ) ? Stream . MassFlow . GetValue ( ”
kg / s ” )

ComS=ComS+MassFrac ( v a r ) ?Pure . MassEntropy .
GetValue ( ” kJ / kg?C” ) ? Stream . MassFlow . GetValue
( ” kg / s ” )

End I f
Next v a r
DeltaH=Stream . MassFlow . GetValue ( ” kg / s ” ) ? Stream .

MassEnthalpy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg ” )?ComH
D e l t a S=Stream . MassFlow . GetValue ( ” kg / s ” ) ? Stream .

MassEntropy . GetValue ( ” kJ / kg?C” )?ComS
DeltaE=DeltaH?(T0 + 2 7 3 . 1 5 ) ? D e l t a S



118

Exergy . S e t V a l u e ( DeltaE , ” kJ / s ” )
Else

Exergy . Erase ( )
E r r o r H a n d l e r :

End I f
End Sub

B.6 OVERALL EXERGY

Sub P o s t E x e c u t e ( )
On Error GoTo E r r o r H a n d l e r
Set Stream = A c t i v e O b j e c t . D u p l i c a t e F l u i d
Dim Exergy As R e a l V a r i a b l e
Set Exergy = A c t i v e V a r i a b l e W r a p p e r . V a r i a b l e
chem=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ” Chemical Exergy

” ) . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
phys=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ” P h y s i c a l e x e r g y

” ) . V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
mix=a c t i v e o b j e c t . G e t U s e r V a r i a b l e ( ” Mixing Exergy ” ) .

V a r i a b l e . GetValue ( )
I f ( Stream . V a p o u r F r a c t i o n . IsKnown And Stream .

P r e s s u r e . IsKnown And Stream . MolarFlow . IsKnown
And T0&lt;&gt;(?32767+273.15) And Stream .
M o l a r F r a c t i o n s . IsKnown ( 0 ) ) Then

Exergy . S e t V a l u e ( chem+phys+mix )
Else
Exergy . Erase ( )
E r r o r H a n d l e r :
End I f
End Sub

B.7 INTEGRATION CODE

B.7.1 Base case (without ORC integrated)

Sub Main
Dim hyCase As S i m u l a t i o n C a s e
Dim hySS As S p r e a d s h e e t O p
Dim a As V a r i a n t
a =0.01



119

’ d e f i n e s p r e a d s h e e t s
Set hyCase = A c t i v e C a s e
Set i n p u t s = hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

INPUTS?B00” )
Set o u t p u t s=hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

OUTPUTS?B00” )
Set r e s u l t s = hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

RESULTS” )
On Error GoTo e r r o r h a n d l e r
For i= 1 To 16

’ s t o p s o l v e r
hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=F a l s e
’ c h a n g e v a r i a b l e s
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ f l u i d f l o w
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’BSW
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 3 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ Gas f l o w
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 4 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ P r e s s u r e
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 5 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ I n j e c t e d w a t e r
’ I f i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . CanModify=

True Then
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . E r a s e
’ E l s e
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 0 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . E r a s e
’ End I f
’ I f r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e&amp;lt;1500 Then
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e =0
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ?50
’ E l s e
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e =1500
’ End I f
’ s t a r t s o l v e r
hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=True
’ a d j u s t t u r b i n e p a r a m e t e r s
p o i n t 1 :
I f Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e ?i n p u t s . C e l l



120

( 4 , 2 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a And Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 ) .
C e l l V a l u e?i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a And
Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e?i n p u t s . C e l l
( 4 , 2 9 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a Then

’ MsgBox ”OK”
Else
hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=F a l s e
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 7 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t t e m p e r a t u r e
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 8 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t mass f l o w
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 9 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ Heat l o a d
hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=True
I f hyCase . S o l v e r . I s S o l v i n g=F a l s e Then GoTo

p o i n t 1
End I f
’ o b t a i n r e s u l t s
’ hyCase . S o l v e r . C a n S o l v e=F a l s e
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 4 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a p
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 5 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a I I
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 9 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 6 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ Xi
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 7 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t mass f l o w
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 8 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ f u e l c o n s u m p t i o n
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 9 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a I , t u r b
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 0 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ y L SGT?400a
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 1 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ y L SGT?400b
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 2 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ y L BOOST
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 3 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ y L GAS INJ
r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 4 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ y L E?B03



121

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L E?B04

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 9 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L A09

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 7 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L WATER

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 0 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ R e j e c t e d h e a t

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 1 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ Power demand

r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ T o t a l e x e r g y l o s s e s

Next i
MsgBox ”OK”

e r r o r h a n d l e r :
End Sub

B.7.2 Cases with ORC integrated

Sub Main
Dim hyCase As S i m u l a t i o n C a s e
Dim a As V a r i a n t
a =0.01
’ d e f i n e s p r e a d s h e e t s
Set hyCase = A c t i v e C a s e
Set i n p u t s = hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

INPUTS?B00” )
Set o u t p u t s=hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

OUTPUTS?B00” )
Set r e s u l t s = hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”

RESULTS” )
Set ORC=hyCase . F l o w s h e e t . O p e r a t i o n s . Item ( ”ORC

MASTER” )
On Error GoTo e r r o r h a n d l e r
For i= 16 To 16

hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=F a l s e ’ s t o p s o l v e r
’ c h a n g e p l a n t v a r i a b l e s
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 1 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ f l u i d f l o w
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 2 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’BSW



122

i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 3 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ Gas f l o w

i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ I n j e c t e d w a t e r

i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 4 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ P r e s s u r e

’ I f i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . CanModify=
True Then

’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . E r a s e
’ E l s e
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 0 ) . I m p o r t e d V a r i a b l e . E r a s e
’ End I f
’ I f r e s u l t s . C e l l ( i , 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e&amp;lt;1500 Then
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e =0
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ?50
’ E l s e
’ i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e =1500
’ End I f
’ c h a n g e ORC v a r i a b l e s
For j= 20 To 20
ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 0 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ORC e v a p o r a t i o n temp
’ s t a r t s o l v e r
hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=True

’ a d j u s t t u r b i n e p a r a m e t e r s
p o i n t 1 :
I f Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e ?i n p u t s . C e l l

( 4 , 2 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a And Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l
( 1 , 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e?i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e
)&lt;a And Abs( i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e?
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a And Abs(
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e?i n p u t s . C e l l
( 6 , 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e )&lt;a Then

’ MsgBox ”OK”
Else

hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=F a l s e
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 6 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t t e m p e r a t u r e
i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 7 ) .

C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t mass f l o w



123

i n p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 8 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ Heat l o a d

i n p u t s . C e l l ( 4 , 2 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=i n p u t s . C e l l ( 6 , 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e

hyCase . S o l v e r . CanSolve=True
I f hyCase . S o l v e r . I s S o l v i n g=F a l s e Then GoTo

p o i n t 1
End I f
’ o b t a i n ORC r e s u l t s

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 4 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC E x e r g y L o s s e s

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC R e j e c t e d Heat

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC Power

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 7 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC E x e r g y D e s t r u c t i o n

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 0 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’E?F01 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 1 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’E?F02 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 2 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’E?F03 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 3 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’E?F04 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 2 9 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 4 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’P?F01 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’T?F01 y D

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e t h a I ,ORC

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 1 8 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e t h a I I ,ORC

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 0 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC E v a p o r a t i o n p i n c h

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 1 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC E c o n o m i z e r p i n c h

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 2 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC P r e s s u r e

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 3 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC mass f l o w



124

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 3 , 1 7 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ORC i n p u t

ORC. C e l l ( j , 3 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=ORC. C e l l ( 1 , 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’HTF mass f l o w

’ o b t a i n PLANT r e s u l t s
’ C o n s o l i d a t e t a b l e

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 4 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a p

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a I I

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ Xi

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 7 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e x h a u s t mass f l o w

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 8 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ f u e l c o n s u m p t i o n

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 9 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ e t a I , t u r b

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 0 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L SGT?400a

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 1 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L SGT?400b

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 8 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 2 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L BOOST

ORC. C e l l ( j , 4 9 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 3 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L GAS INJ

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 0 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 4 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L E?B03

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 1 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 5 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L E?B04

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 2 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 6 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L A09

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 3 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 7 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L WATER

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 4 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 1 , 2 8 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ y L ORC

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 5 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 0 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ R e j e c t e d h e a t

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 6 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 1 ) .
C e l l V a l u e ’ Power demand

ORC. C e l l ( j , 5 7 ) . C e l l V a l u e=o u t p u t s . C e l l ( 3 , 2 ) .



125

C e l l V a l u e ’ T o t a l e x e r g y l o s s e s
Next j
k=i ?1
MsgBox( ” copy t o e x c e l ”&amp;amp;k&amp;amp;” i t e r a t i o n ” )
Stop

Next i
e r r o r h a n d l e r :

End Sub



126



APPENDIX C -- EES case development





129

C.1 INTRODUCTION

This appendix summarizes the development of the model using
the software EES (Engineering Equation Solver). In general, this model
takes the same inputs of that developed using Hysys. However, its
approach is simpler and is based on various simplifying assumptions.
The purpose of this development is to offer a comparison framework to
the model developed in Hysys and investigate how the level of detailing
of the model affect the pretended results of the simulations. Following
sections present the main assumptions adopted and the results obtained
using this program.

C.2 ASSUMPTIONS

The main assumptions adopted in the development of the model
are listed as follows:

•Continuous operation, with constant conditions (steady state regime).

•Constant thermophysical properties of oil during the separation
processes.

•The power generation system is modeled as one turbine operating
in accordance with the data reported for the SGT-400 model (Its
parameters are adjusted to represent both existing turbines).

•Gases are considered ideal.

•There are no interfacial or chemical interactions between the fluid
phases (i.e. oil, gas and water).

•Constant composition of the associated gas through the whole
process. This implies that the saturation of the gas stream with
water is neglected and gas dehydration is discarded.

The last two assumptions cause the well fluid to be modeled as
the sum of three unmixed flows (i.e. oil, gas and water), which physi-
cally does not represent adequately the equilibrium between phases and
cause the separation stages to be unnecessary hypothetically. However,
considering that all hydrocarbons entering the plant are recognized ei-
ther as a product or as consumed fuel within the process, the results
related to the overall behavior of the plant may be comparable with
those calculated by a detailed model.



130

C.3 SCHEME OF OPERATION

Figure 50 – Scheme of operation of EES model.



131

Figure 50 presents the scheme of operation considered in the
model developed using EES. Analogously, Figs. 51 and 52 show the
schemes contemplated for the gas boosting system and gas injection/-
export respectively.

Figure 51 – Scheme of operation of gas boost system in EES model.

Figure 52 – Scheme of operation of gas injection/export system in EES
model.

C.4 SOLUTION

The following list presents the values obtained for variables cal-
culated by the model (as reported in the program) .

AO = 7.100 × 10?13 API = 30
? = 7.089 BSW = 29.68
B00 = 2.8001 [MJ/s] B01 = 2.8001 [MJ/s]



132

B02 = 22.5130 [MJ/s] B03 = 47.8084 [MJ/s]
B03A = 70.2451 [MJ/s] B04 = 54.4178 [MJ/s]
B05 = 19.2869 [MJ/s] B06 = 17.2914 [MJ/s]
B07 = 4618.9236 [MJ/s] B08 = 4619.2034 [MJ/s]
B09 = 3910.6909 [MJ/s] B10 = 3911.1328 [MJ/s]
B11 = 3869.0674 [MJ/s] B12 = 3869.0755 [MJ/s]
B13 = 3868.6933 [MJ/s] B14 = 705.5958 [MJ/s]
B17 = 747.7656 [MJ/s] B19 = 2.5892 [MJ/s]
B20 = 2.5957 [MJ/s] B21 = 0.0951 [MJ/s]
B22 = 0.0959 [MJ/s] B23 = 1.2936 [MJ/s]
B50 = 12.6575 [MJ/s] B51 = 29.3320 [MJ/s]
B52 = 12.7281 [MJ/s] B53 = 42.0524 [MJ/s]
B54 = 42.0253 [MJ/s] B55 = 42.2273 [MJ/s]
B56 = 42.1709 [MJ/s] B57 = 750.0633 [MJ/s]
B58 = 749.3655 [MJ/s] B59 = 751.4806 [MJ/s]
B60 = 751.0196 [MJ/s] B61 = 753.1346 [MJ/s]
B61A = 704.9931 [MJ/s] B62 = 704.5616 [MJ/s]
B70 = 6.924 [MJ/s] B71 = 9.676 [MJ/s]
Bch,03 = 47.4641 [MJ/s] Bch,07 = 4613 [MJ/s]
Bch,08 = 4613 [MJ/s] Bch,09 = 3910 [MJ/s]
Bch,10 = 3910 [MJ/s] Bch,11 = 3868 [MJ/s]
Bch,12 = 3868 [MJ/s] Bch,13 = 3868 [MJ/s]
Bch,14 = 700.7 [MJ/s] Bch,17 = 742.5 [MJ/s]
Bch,50 = 12.65 [MJ/s] Bch,51 = 29.22 [MJ/s]
Bch,52 = 12.65 [MJ/s] Bch,53 = 41.88 [MJ/s]
Bch,54 = 41.88 [MJ/s] Bch,55 = 41.88 [MJ/s]
Bch,56 = 41.88 [MJ/s] Bch,57 = 742.5 [MJ/s]
Bch,58 = 742.5 [MJ/s] Bch,59 = 742.5 [MJ/s]
Bch,60 = 742.5 [MJ/s] Bch,61 = 742.5 [MJ/s]
Bch,61A = 695.1 [MJ/s] Bch,62 = 695.1 [MJ/s]
Bch,out,Oil = 3868.282 [MJ/s] Bch,wat = 0.05 [MJ/s]
BOut,Oil = 3868.5176 [MJ/s] Bout,W at = 2.462 [MJ/s]
Bph,03 = 0.3443 [MJ/s] Bph,07 = 5.908 [MJ/s]
Bph,08 = 6.188 [MJ/s] Bph,09 = 0.5299 [MJ/s]
Bph,10 = 0.9718 [MJ/s] Bph,11 = 0.7855 [MJ/s]
Bph,12 = 0.7936 [MJ/s] Bph,13 = 0.4114 [MJ/s]
Bph,14 = 4.938 [MJ/s] Bph,17 = 5.229 [MJ/s]
Bph,50 = 0.00267 [MJ/s] Bph,51 = 0.1078 [MJ/s]
Bph,52 = 0.0733 [MJ/s] Bph,53 = 0.1733 [MJ/s]
Bph,54 = 0.1463 [MJ/s] Bph,55 = 0.3482 [MJ/s]
Bph,56 = 0.2919 [MJ/s] Bph,57 = 7.526 [MJ/s]



133

Bph,58 = 6.829 [MJ/s] Bph,59 = 8.944 [MJ/s]
Bph,60 = 8.483 [MJ/s] Bph,61 = 10.6 [MJ/s]
Bph,61A = 9.92 [MJ/s] Bph,62 = 9.489 [MJ/s]
Bph,out,Oil = 0.2358 [MJ/s] CO = 0.07378
?PHE02,cool = 50 [kPa]
?PHE04,hot = 50 [kPa] ?PP 04 = 19900 [kPa]
Diff = 20.09 ?2nd = 0.9901
?Bray = 0.2849 ?C01 = 0.9
?C03 = 0.65 ?C04 = 0.65
?P = 0.75 ?T 01 = 0.9
E01 = 2.904 [kJ/s] E02 = 20698 [kJ/s]
E03 = 45745 [kJ/s] E03A = 66443 [kJ/s]
E04 = 64946 [kJ/s] E05 = 31281 [kJ/s]
E06 = 28010 [kJ/s] E07 = 4592011 [kJ/s]
E08 = 4.595 × 106 [kJ/s] E09 = 3.915 × 106 [kJ/s]
E10 = 3.918 × 106 [kJ/s] E11 = 3.878 × 106 [kJ/s]
E12 = 3.878 × 106 [kJ/s] E13 = 3.875 × 106 [kJ/s]
E14 = 673225 [kJ/s] E17 = 713423 [kJ/s]
E19 = 6833 [kJ/s] E20 = 6838 [kJ/s]
E21 = 844 [kJ/s] E22 = 844.8 [kJ/s]
E23 = 4115 [kJ/s] E50 = 12170 [kJ/s]
E51 = 28105 [kJ/s] E52 = 12261 [kJ/s]
E53 = 40366 [kJ/s] E54 = 40198 [kJ/s]
E55 = 40466 [kJ/s] E56 = 40198 [kJ/s]
E57 = 716516 [kJ/s] E58 = 712733 [kJ/s]
E59 = 715640 [kJ/s] E60 = 712733 [kJ/s]
E61 = 715640 [kJ/s] E61A = 669895 [kJ/s]
E62 = 667174 [kJ/s] ED,03A = 0.07633 [MJ/s]
ED,17 = 0.001194 [MJ/s] ED,53 = 0.007765 [MJ/s]
ED,61A = 0.3331 [MJ/s] ED,AC03A = 0.02705 [MJ/s]
ED,AC03B = 0.05634 [MJ/s] ED,AC04A = 0.6977 [MJ/s]
ED,AC04B = 0.461 [MJ/s] ED,AC04C = 0.4315 [MJ/s]
ED,C01 = 0.9827 [MJ/s] ED,C03A = 0.02017 [MJ/s]
ED,C03B = 0.06605 [MJ/s] ED,C04A = 0.7954 [MJ/s]
ED,C04B = 0.7924 [MJ/s] ED,C04C = 0.7924 [MJ/s]
ED,Comb = 15.83 [MJ/s] ED,Gas = 4.149 [MJ/s]
ED,HE01 = 0 [MJ/s] ED,HE02 = 0.7978 [MJ/s]
ED,HE03 = 0.1024 [MJ/s] ED,HE04 = 0.7566 [MJ/s]
ED,HE,OIL = 0.1757 [MJ/s] ED,HE,W at = 0.1335 [MJ/s]
ED,HT F = 0.0002865 [MJ/s] ED,Mix,Comb = 14.41 [MJ/s]
ED,Oil = 1.44 [MJ/s] ED,P 01 = 0.002198 [MJ/s]



134

ED,P 02 = 0.002085 [MJ/s] ED,P ow = 36.44 [MJ/s]
ED,Sea = 0.933 [MJ/s] ED,T 01 = 1.466 [MJ/s]
ED,V 01 = 0.3275 [MJ/s] ED,V 02 = 0.07591 [MJ/s]
ED,W at = 2.598 [MJ/s] ef = 45528 [kJ/s]
EOut,Oil = 3873079 [kJ/s] EOut,W at = 5518 [kJ/s]
HeatRate = 12637 HO = 0.2521
H00 = 2.904 [kJ/s] H01 = 2.904 [kJ/s]
H02 = 20698 [kJ/s] H03 = ?4439 [kJ/s]
H03A = 16260 [kJ/s] H04 = 14.79 [kJ/s]
H05 = ?18.87 [kJ/s] H06 = ?22.14 [MJ/s]
H06A = ?42.47 [MJ/s] H07 = ?56746 [kJ/s]
h07,gas = ?4374 [kJ/kg] h07,Oil = 54.12 [kJ/kg]
h07,wat = 231.5 [kJ/kg] H08 = ?53987 [kJ/s]
h08,gas = ?4359 [kJ/kg] h08,Oil = 67.27 [kJ/kg]
h08,wat = 261.5 [kJ/kg] H09 = 1980 [kJ/s]
H10 = 5251 [kJ/s] H12 = 9230 [kJ/s]
H13 = 6471 [kJ/s] H14 = ?67578 [kJ/s]
H17 = ?71658 [kJ/s] H20 = 11444 [kJ/s]
H21 = 844 [kJ/s] H23 = 4115 [kJ/s]
H51 = ?2793 [kJ/s] H52 = ?1119 [kJ/s]
H53 = ?3912 [kJ/s] H54 = ?4080 [kJ/s]
H55 = ?3812 [kJ/s] H56 = ?4080 [kJ/s]
H57 = ?68565 [kJ/s] H58 = ?72348 [kJ/s]
H59 = ?69441 [kJ/s] H60 = ?72348 [kJ/s]
H61 = ?69441 [kJ/s] H61A = ?65002 [kJ/s]
H62 = ?67724 [kJ/s] Hout,Oil = 4797 [kJ/s]
Hout,W at = 10124 [kJ/s] LHV gas = 43353 [kJ/kg]
LHV Oil = 42380 [kJ/kg] MmEx = 28.56
MmF uel = 21.21 m01 = 57.6 [kg/s]
m02 = 57.6 [kg/s] m03 = 1.05 [kg/s]
m03A = 58.65 [kg/s] m04 = 58.65 [kg/s]
m05 = 58.65 [kg/s] m06 = 58.65 [kg/s]
m07 = 151.6 [kg/s] m08 = 151.6 [kg/s]
m09 = 92.2 [kg/s] m10 = 92.2 [kg/s]
m11 = 91.28 [kg/s] m12 = 91.28 [kg/s]
m13 = 91.28 [kg/s] m14 = 15.5 [kg/s]
m15 = 0.9266 [kg/s] m17 = 16.43 [kg/s]
m19 = 43.93 [kg/s] m20 = 43.93 [kg/s]
m21 = 7.5 [kg/s] m22 = 7.5 [kg/s]
m23 = 7.5 [kg/s] m50 = 0.28 [kg/s]
m51 = 0.6466 [kg/s] m52 = 0.28 [kg/s]



135

m53 = 0.9266 [kg/s] m54 = 0.9266 [kg/s]
m55 = 0.9266 [kg/s] m56 = 0.9266 [kg/s]
m57 = 16.43 [kg/s] m58 = 16.43 [kg/s]
m59 = 16.43 [kg/s] m60 = 16.43 [kg/s]
m61 = 16.43 [kg/s] m61A = 15.38 [kg/s]
m62 = 15.38 [kg/s] m70 = 138.5 [kg/s]
m71 = 138.5 [kg/s] mgas = 16.43 [kg/s]
moil = 91.28 [kg/s] mwat = 43.93 [kg/s]
NO = 3.74 PinchHE03 = 10[C]
PinchHE04 = 15[C] P00 = 101.3 [kPa]
P01 = 101.3 [kPa] P02 = 1317 [kPa]
P04 = 1317 [kPa] P05 = 141.2 [kPa]
P07 = 1500 [kPa] P08 = 1500 [kPa]
P09 = 389.8 [kPa] P10 = 389.8 [kPa]
P11 = 101.3 [kPa] P12 = 175 [kPa]
P13 = 175 [kPa] P14 = 1500 [kPa]
P17 = 1500 [kPa] P19 = 101.3 [kPa]
P20 = 250 [kPa] P21 = 900 [kPa]
P22 = 1000 [kPa] P23 = 950 [kPa]
P50 = 101.3 [kPa] P52 = 389.8 [kPa]
P53 = 389.8 [kPa] P54 = 389.8 [kPa]
P55 = 1500 [kPa] P56 = 1500 [kPa]
P57 = 3557 [kPa] P58 = 3557 [kPa]
P59 = 8434 [kPa] P60 = 8434 [kPa]
P61 = 20000 [kPa] P61A = 20000 [kPa]
P62 = 20000 [kPa] P70 = 100 [kPa]
P71 = 20000 [kPa] Qv07 = 12800

[
m3/day

]
Qv11 = 9001

[
m3/day

]
Qv14 = 1.415

[
Mm3/day

]
Qv15 = 0.0846

[
Mm3/day

]
Qv17 = 1.5

[
Mm3/day

]
Qv19 = 3799

[
m3/day

]
Qv20 = 0.04397

[
m3/s

]
Qv21 = 0.008261

[
m3/s

]
Qv50 = 0.02556

[
m3/s

]
Qv51 = 0.05904

[
m3/s

]
Qv62,s = 17.74

[
m3/s

]
Qv70 = 12000

[
m3/day

]
Qvin = 0.1481

[
m3/s

]
QAC03A = 168.2 [kJ/s] QAC03B = 268 [kJ/s]
QAC04A = 3783 [kJ/s] QAC04B = 2907 [kJ/s]
QAC04C = 2722 [kJ/s] QAv,Ex = 23.6 [MJ/s]
QC03 = 436.1 [kJ/s] QC04 = 9412 [kJ/s]
QHE02 = 3.271 [MJ/s] QHE03 = 2.759 [MJ/s]
QHE04 = 3.271 [MJ/s] QHE,Oil = 1.674 [MJ/s]
QHE,W at = 1.32 [MJ/s] QLoss,Comb = 1.465 [MJ/s]
?Oil = 876.2

[
kg/m3

]
rPC03A = 3.848



136

rPC03B = 3.848 rPC04A = 2.371
rPC04B = 2.371 rPC04C = 2.371
rP,C01 = 13 SGOil = 0.8762
T00 = 25 [C] T01 = 25 [C]
T02 = 371.8 [C] T03 = 124 [C]
T03A = 361.3 [C] T04 = 996.8 [C]
T05 = 516.5 [C] T06 = 467.5 [C]
T07 = 55 [C] T08 = 62.19 [C]
T09 = 62.19 [C] T10 = 81 [C]
T11 = 81 [C] T12 = 81 [C]
T13 = 65 [C] T14 = 62.15 [C]
T15 = 81 [C] T17 = 61 [C]
T19 = 62.19 [C] T20 = 62.19 [C]
T21 = 96 [C] T22 = 96 [C]
T23 = 300 [C] T50 = 81 [C]
T51 = 81 [C] T52 = 219.6 [C]
T53 = 126 [C] T54 = 40 [C]
T55 = 172 [C] T56 = 40 [C]
T57 = 147.2 [C] T58 = 40 [C]
T59 = 124 [C] T60 = 40 [C]
T61 = 124 [C] T61A = 124 [C]
T62 = 40 [C] T70 = 25 [C]
T71 = 25 [C] TAD = 1016.8 [C]
Tmin,Ex = 150 [C] Tout,AC = 40 [C]
Tout,Gas = 40 [C] Tout,Oil = 55 [C]
Tout,W at = 55 [C] WisoP 01 = 6.538 [kJ/s]
WisoP 02 = 7.678 [kJ/s] WisoP 03 = 0.8261 [kJ/s]
WisoP 04 = 2764 [kJ/s] WC01 = 20.6956 [MJ/s]
WC03 = 0.3588 [MJ/s] WC03A = 0.0908 [MJ/s]
WC03B = 0.268 [MJ/s] WC04 = 8.908 [MJ/s]
WC04A = 3.093 [MJ/s] WC04B = 2.907 [MJ/s]
WC04C = 2.907 [MJ/s] WNet = 12.97 [MJ/s]
WP 01 = 8.718 [kJ/s] WP 02 = 10.24 [kJ/s]
WP 03 = 1.101 [kJ/s] WP 04 = 3.685 [MJ/s]
WT 01 = 33.6656 [MJ/s] xg07 = 0.6019
xo07 = 0.1083 xw07 = 0.2897



137

C.4.1 Mass and energy balances

Following tables summarize the mass and energy balances ob-
tained from data calculated by the program. In addition, the calculated
values were put together with those obtained from Hysys for results
comparison.

Table 29 – Mass balances per system in EES model, kg/h.

System

Inlets Outlets

Separation plant
07 545899 Oil 328596
05 211141 17 59145
56 3336 50 1008

51 2328
Wat 158157
06 211141

Subtotals 760375 760375

Gas turbines
01 207360 05 211141
03 3781

Subtotals 211141 211141

Gas boost
50 1008 56 3336
51 2328

Subtotals 3336 3336

Gas injection
17 59145 62 55365

03 3781

Subtotals 59145 59145

Seawater injection
70 498600 71 498600

Subtotals 498600 498600



138

Table 30 – Mass balances per system in Hysys model, kg/h.

System

Inlets Outlets

Separation plant
FLUID 540922 OIL 324558
A07a 109816 B11 54216
A07b 109816 B13 2910
B18 4108 B15 1625
B26 571 B20a 2054
B27 696 B20b 2054
B29 595 A09 219633

WATER 159476

Subtotals 766525 766526

Gas turbines
B20a 2054 A07a 109816
B20b 2054 A07b 109816
AIR 107773
AIRb 107773

Subtotals 219654 219633

Gas boost
B11 54216 B26 571
B12 2910 B29 595
B14 1625 B17 57585

Subtotals 58751 58751

Gas injection
B17 57585 GAS 52716

B18 4108
B27 696
G03 66

Subtotals 57585 57586

Seawater injection
H01 498993 H02 498993

Subtotals 498993 498993



139

Table 31 – Power demand distribution according to EES and Hysys
models, kW.

System Equipment Value

Separation plant Hysys EES Hysys EES

P-B01 P02 25.48 10.24
P-B02 P01 0.32 8.72
P-E01 P03 14.47 1.10
E-B05 NI 111.38 0

Subtotal 151.65 20.06

Gas boost system C-C01 C03A 71 90.8
C-C02 C03B 246 268

Subtotal 317 359

Gas injection C-D01 C04A 2685 3093
C-D02 C04B 2509 2907
C-D03 C04C 2324 2907
C-D04 NI 2014 0

Subtotal 9531 8908

Seawater injection P-H01 P04 4569 3685
Subtotal 4569 3685

Total 14569 12972

NI- Not included.



140

Table 32 – Heat rejection distribution according to EES and Hysys
models, kW.

System Equipment Value T,?C

Hysys EES Hysys EES

Separation E-B03 HE Oil 1819 1674 65
E-B04 HE Wat 1210 1320 61

Subtotal 3029 2994

Gas turbines E-E01’* Exh. Gas 21570 23601 471
R-A01 Comb. 543 1465 1046
R-A01b NI 543 0 1046

Subtotal 22656 25066

Gas boosting E-C01 AC03A 393 168 108
E-C02 AC03B 301 268 149

Subtotal 694 436

Gas injection F-D01 AC04A 3983 3783 126
F-D02 AC04B 3116 2907 111
F-D03 AC04C 3426 2722 109
F-D04 NI 2882 0 105

Subtotal 13407 9412

Total 39786 37909

*Considering a min. allowed temp. of 150 ?C for exhaust gases.

NI- Not included.



APPENDIX D -- Exergy balances per equipment





143

D.1 EXERGY BALANCES

Table 33 presents the formulation of the exergy balances carried
out for each equipment conforming the plant.

Table 33 – Exergy balances per equipment.

Equipment Figure Formulation

Three
phase
separator

BD = B01 ? (B02 + B03
+B04)

Air cooler BL=B01-B02

Combustor

BL =
(
1 ? T0

T?

)
Q

BD = B01 ? (B02 + B03
+BL)

Compressor BD = B01 ? B02 + W

Cooler BL = B01 ? B02

Expander BD = B01 ? (B02 + W)

Heat ex-
changer

BD = B01 ? B02 + B03
?B04



144

Table 33 – Exergy balances per equipment (cont.).

Equipment Figure Formulation

Heater
(electric)

BD = B01 + W ? B02

Mixer BD = B01 + B02 ? B03

Pump BD = B01 + W ? B02

Recycle BD = 0

Separator BD = B01 ? (B02 + B03)

Tee BD = B01 ? (B02 + B03)

Valve BD = B01 ? B02



145

D.2 RESULTS

Tables 34 through 38 present the detailed exergy balances for
both cases (Hysys and EES).

Table 34 – Exergy losses per system, kW.

System Stream Value

Hysys EES Hysys EES

Separation plant
HE-B03 HE Oil 197 176
HE-B04 HE Wat 124 133
A09 06 14152 17291
WATER Wat 2496 2462

Subtotal 16968 20063

Gas turbines
A07a 05 8241 19287
A07b NI 8241
HR-A01a Comb. 379.1 1006
HR-a01b NI 379.1

Subtotal 17240 20293

Gas boost
HE-C01 AC03A 49 27
HE-C02 AC03B 56 56
B26 NI 2673

Subtotal 2777 83

Gas injection
HF-D01 AC04A 655 698
HF-D02 AC04B 458 461
HF-D03 AC04C 482 432
HF-D04 NI 387
B27 NI 268

Subtotal 2249 1590

Recirculations
A07a 8241 19287
A07b 8241
B26 2673
B27 268

Total 19812 22743

NI- Not included.



146

Table 35 – Exergy destruction rate per equipment, kW.

System/Equp. Type Value T0Sgen

Separation plant

Hysys EES Hysys EES Hysys

M-B01A NI Mixer 7.0 2.7
M-B03 NI Mixer 0.0 0.0
V-B01 V01 3 Ph. Sep. 0.0 327.52 0.0
V-B02 V02 3 Ph. Sep. 12.1 75.91 11.2
L-B01 NI Valve 166.5 166.5
L-B02 NI Valve 32.8 32.8
L-B03 NI Valve 0.2 0.2
L-E01 NI Valve 0.0 0.0
L-B04 NI Valve 57.2 57.2
L-B00 NI Valve 1425.5 1425.5
L-B05 NI Valve 34.7 34.7
E-B01 HE03 Heat Ex. 170.8 102.37 170.8
E-E01 HE02 Heat Ex. 545.8 797.84 545.8
E-B02 HE04 Heat Ex. 1301.8 756.61 1301.8
P-B01 P02 Pump 2.6 2.09 2.6
P-E01 P03 Pump 1.7 1.7
P-B02 P01 Pump 0.0 2.20 0.0
V-B03 NI Separator 3.7 3.6
R-E01 NI Recycle 0.0 0.0
R-B01 NI Recycle -0.1 0.0
R-B02 NI Recycle -0.6 0.0
R-B03 NI Recycle 0.0 0.0
R-B04 NI Recycle 0.0 0.1
E-B05 NI Heater 118.3 118.3
Y-B01 NI Tee 0.0 0.0

Subtotal 3879.9 2064.5

Gas turbines

T-A02 T01 Expander 162.0 1465.53 162.0
T-A01 NI Expander 121.1 121.1
T-A03 NI Expander 239.1 239.1
C-A02 C01 Comp. 478.8 982.68 478.8
C-A01 NI Comp. 474.4 474.4
R-A01 Comb. Gibbs R. 8003.4 14821.02 8383.6

NI–Not included.



147

Table 35 – Exergy destruction rate per equipment (Cont.), kW.

System/Equp. Type Value T0Sgen

Hysys EES Hysys EES Hysys

M-A01 3A Mixer 400.4 76.33 400.4

L-A01 NR Valve 18.6 18.6

Total per turbine 9897.6 17345.6
Subtotal 19795.1 17345.6

Gas boost system

M-C02 17 Mixer 26.4 1.19 26.4
M-C01 53 Mixer 6.2 7.76 6.2
C-C01 C03A Comp. 17.8 20.17 17.8
C-C02 C03B Comp. 63.3 66.05 63.3
V-C01 NI Separator 0.9 0.9
V-C02 NI Separator 0.0 0.0
R-C01 NI Recycle 0.0 0.0
L-C01 NI Valve 195.0 195.0
Y-C01 NI Tee 0.0 0.0

Subtotal 309.6 95.2

Gas injection system

C-D01 C04A Comp. 721.2 795.41 721.2
C-D02 C04B Comp. 700.4 792.36 700.4
C-D03 C04C Comp. 648.8 792.36 648.8
C-D04 NI Comp. 566.8 566.8
V-D01 NI Separator 0.1 0.1
V-D02 NI Separator 0.1 0.1
V-D03 NI Separator 0.0 0.0
V-D04 NI Separator 6.6 6.6
R-D01 NI Recycle 0.0 0.0
R-D02 NI Recycle -15.1 0.7
R-D03 NI Recycle -0.1 0.0
Y-D02 NI Tee 0.0 0.0
Y-D01 61A Tee 0.0 333.13 0.0
L-D02 NI Valve 766.0 766.0
L-D01 NI Valve 197.8 197.8

Subtotal 3592.6 2713.3

NI–Not included.



148

Table 35 – Exergy destruction rate per equipment (Cont.), kW.

System/Equp. Type Value T0Sgen

Hysys EES Hysys EES Hysys

Seawater injection system

P-H01 P04 Pump 503.1 933.44 503.1
Y-H01 NI Tee 0.0 0.0
L-H01 NI Valve 799.4 799.4
M-H01 NI Mixer 11.4 11.4
R-H01 NI Recycle 0.0 0.0

Subtotal 1313.8 933.4

Total 28891 23152

NI–Not included.



149

Table 36 – Exergy balances per system in EES model, kW.

System Inlets Outlets

Separation plant 07 4618923.61 Oil 3868517.64
05 19286.91 17 747765.57
56 42170.93 50 12657.48
Work 20.06 51 29332.04

Losses 20062.8
Destr. 2064.5

Subtotals 4680401 4680400

Gas turbines 01 2800.14 05 19286.91
03 47808.39 Work 12970

Losses 1006
Destr. 17346

Subtotals 50609 50609

Gas boosting 50 12657.48 56 42170.93
51 29332.04 Losses 83
Work 359 Dest. 95.2

Subtotals 42348 42349

Gas injection 17 747765.57 62 704561.58
Work 8908 03 47808.39

Losses 1590
Destr. 2713.3

Subtotals 756674 756674

Seawater injection 70 6923.87 71 9675.62
Work 3685 Dest. 933.4

Subtotals 10609 10609



150

Table 37 – Exergy balances per system in Hysys model, kW.

System Inlets Outlets

Separation plant FLUID 4742058 OIL 4023631
A07a 8241 B11 673297
A07b 8241 B13 31901
B18 51667 B15 19258
B26 2673 B20a 25830
B27 268 B20b 25830
B29 7292 Losses 16968
Work 152 Destr. 3879.9

Subtotals 4820591 4820595

Gas turbines B20a 25830 WT-A03 7285
B20b 25830 WT-A03b 7285
AIR 108 Losses 17240
AIRb 108 Destr. 19795.1

Subtotals 51875 51604

Gas boost system B11 673297 B16 714395
B13 31901 B29 7292
B15 19258 Losses 2777
Work 317 Destr. 309.6

Subtotals 724773 724773

Gas injection system B17 714395 GAS 666416
Work 9531 B18 51667

Losses 2249
Destr. 3593

Subtotals 723926 723925

Seawater injection system H01 6924 H02 10179
Work 4569 Destr. 1313.8

Subtotals 11493 11493



151

Table 38 – General exergy balance, kW.

Streams

Inlets Hysys EES Hysys EES

FLUID 07 4742058 4618923.61
AIR 01 108 2800
AIRb NI 108 0.00
H01 70 6924 6923.87

Subtotals 4749197 4628648

Outlets Hysys EES Hysys EES

OIL Oil 4023631 3868518
GAS 62 666416 704562
H02 71 10179 9675.62
Losses Losses 19812 22743
Destr. Destr. 28891.1 23152.0

Subtotals 4748930 4628650



152



APPENDIX E -- Oil characterization results





155

This appendix presents the results concerning the oil character-
ization using the procedure described in Sec. 3.1, which are included
within the Hysys calculation subroutines. These results are obtained
from a minimum set of standardized data commonly encountered in
the industry. As mentioned in Aspentech (2011), the more information
provided, the greater the accuracy of the characterization. However,
the lack of information is common when modeling this type of pro-
cess. Given that the properties and composition of crude change over
time and from a reservoir to another, the characterization of the crude
shown here corresponds to a typical fluid (as shown in Tab. 8) and does
not pretend to model an actual fluid in detail. Moreover, the scope of
present work is rather focused on the energy efficiency of the processes
than on the crude characterization.

Figures 53 through 56 present the calculated properties for the
pseudocomponents generated in order to model the crude, which corre-
sponds to as a mixture of 34 pseudocomponents, 7 pure hydrocarbons,
CO2, Nitrogen, Oxygen and water. In addition, Tab. 39 shows the
composition of the oily phase of the crude, which reports an average
molecular weight of 250.7 kg/kmol.

Figure 53 – TBP curve and normal boiling point (NBP) of each pseu-
docomponent.



156

Table 39 – Crude composition (oily phase).

Hypo name mass frac.

NBP[0]121* 0.0061
NBP[0]134* 0.0108
NBP[0]148* 0.0139
NBP[0]162* 0.0180
NBP[0]177* 0.0213
NBP[0]191* 0.0244
NBP[0]205* 0.0272
NBP[0]219* 0.0297
NBP[0]234* 0.0320
NBP[0]248* 0.0340
NBP[0]262* 0.0357
NBP[0]277* 0.0371
NBP[0]291* 0.0382
NBP[0]305* 0.0390
NBP[0]320* 0.0396
NBP[0]334* 0.0399
NBP[0]348* 0.0399
NBP[0]362* 0.0397
NBP[0]377* 0.0393
NBP[0]391* 0.0387
NBP[0]404* 0.0293
NBP[0]420* 0.0209
NBP[0]442* 0.0659
NBP[0]468* 0.0681
NBP[0]495* 0.0620
NBP[0]522* 0.0555
NBP[0]555* 0.0940



157

Figure 54 – Some physical properties and lower heating value (LHV)
of each pseudocomponent.



158

Figure 55 – Elemental composition of each pseudocomponent.

Figure 56 – Specific heat of crude (oily phase).


</field>
	</doc>
</add>