<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.12094</field>
		<field name="filename">17624_S1679-62252010000100019.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Neotropical Ichthyology, 8(1):163-170, 2010
Copyright © 2010 Sociedade Brasileira de Ictiologia

163

Influence of the riparian zone phytophysiognomies on the longitudinal
distribution of fishes: evidence from a Brazilian savanna stream

Fabrício Barreto Teresa and Renato de Mei Romero

The structure and composition of a fish community in a tributary stream of the Aquidauana River, located in the plateau region
of the Paraguay River basin, central west Brazil are described, with special attention to the differential effects of the
phytophysiognomies of the Cerrado (a tropical savanna), which are predominant in riparian zones all along their longitudinal
gradient. A total of 1,166 individuals belonging to 44 species were captured. Similarity analyses of composition and abundance
showed two groups: upstream reaches (R1 and R2) and downstream reaches (R3, R4 and R5), which presented 85.8% of the
average dissimilarity. Although physical habitat and physicochemical descriptors varied along the longitudinal gradient of the
Correntes stream, shoreline vegetation was the most important environmental feature predicting fish structure and composition.
The Mantel test revealed a correlation between shoreline vegetation structure and fish composition and quantitative structure
of the fish community (R &gt; 0.65; p &amp;lt;0.04). This relationship is driven by the prevalence of species occupying microhabitats
associated with shoreline vegetation in contact with water in upstream reaches. Structural differences in shoreline vegetation
along the longitudinal gradient correspond to the phytophysiognomic dichotomy observed in the Correntes stream, where
riparian vegetation is made up of wet grassland upstream and of gallery forest downstream; this reinforces the importance of
the phytophysiognomic heterogeneity of the Cerrado in maintaining ichthyofauna diversity.

São descritas a estrutura e composição da comunidade de peixes em um riacho afluente do rio Aquidauana, localizado na região
planáltica da bacia do rio Paraguai, centro-oeste do Brasil, com atenção especial aos efeitos diferenciais das fitofisionomias de
Cerrado predominantes nas zonas ripárias ao longo do seu gradiente longitudinal. Foram capturados 1.166 indivíduos
pertencentes a 44 espécies. As análises de similaridade com a composição e abundância evidenciaram dois grupos: os trechos
a montante (R1 e R2) e trechos a jusante (R3, R4 e R5), os quais apresentaram 85,8% de dissimilaridade média. Embora os
descritores fisico-químicos e do habitat físico tenham variado ao longo do gradiente longitudinal do córrego Correntes, a
vegetação marginal foi o componente ambiental mais importante predizendo a estrutura e composição da ictiofauna. O teste de
Mantel revelou correlação entre a estrutura da vegetação marginal com a composição e estrutura quantitativa da comunidade
de peixes (R &gt; 0.65; p &amp;lt;0.04). Essa relação é representada pela prevalência de espécies que exploram micro-habitats associados
à vegetação marginal em contato com a água nos trechos a montante. As diferenças na estrutura da vegetação marginal ao
longo do gradiente longitudinal correspondem à dicotomia fitofisionômica observada no córrego Correntes, cuja vegetação
marginal é constituída de campos úmidos à montante e por fisionomias florestais nos trechos à jusante, reforçando a importância
da heterogeneidade fitofisionomica do Cerrado brasileiro para a manutenção da diversidade ictiofaunística.

Key words: Paraguay basin, Cerrado, Longitudinal gradient, River continuum concept, Riparian forest.

UNESP, Universidade Estadual Paulista, Instituto de Biociências, Letras e Ciências Exatas - IBILCE, Laboratório de Ictiologia, Departa-
mento de Zoologia e Botânica. Rua Cristóvão Colombo, 2265, 15.054-000 São José do Rio Preto, SP, Brazil. fabricioteresa@yahoo.com.br,
romerobio@yahoo.com.br

Introduction

The upper Paraguay River basin is one of the most important
basins in the Neotropics, occupying an area of approximately
363,442 km² in Brazilian territory. It can be divided into two
distinct regions: a floodplain called the Pantanal which is one
of largest wetland areas in the world and a plateau around the
Pantanal, including areas with an altitude of over 200 m. These
two regions are distinguished by geologic and geomorphologic

characteristics, but they are interdependent in ecological terms
since headwaters of the most important rivers that supply the
Pantanal are situated in the plateau region, providing high
hydrologic connectivity (Willink et al., 2000).

The plateau region is biologically distinct from the
floodplain (Chernoff &amp;amp; Willink, 2000), and its ichthyofauna,
as well as the factors that modulate it, is poorly known when
compared to the accumulated scientific knowledge about the
Pantanal region (Catella et al., 1996; Súarez et al., 2004; Britski



Influence of the riparian zone phytophysiognomies on the longitudinal distribution of fishes164

et al., 2007). Knowledge is especially scarce for small fishes
from streams, which make up the greatest proportion of fish
species richness of the Neotropics (Castro, 1999).

Most of the Paraguay basin plateau streams flow into the
Brazilian Cerrado (savanna) biome, which is a world biodiversity
hotspot due to its richness, high degree of endemism and
anthropogenic threat (Ratter et al., 1997; Myers et al., 2001).
Vegetation in these areas is very heterogeneous, and riparian
vegetation is one example of this variation, showing
phytophysiognomies ranging from grassland to closed canopy
(Ratter et al., 1997; Ribeiro &amp;amp; Walter, 1998). Considering the
strong predictive power of riparian vegetation in structuring
stream fish communities (Wichert &amp;amp; Rapport, 1998; Growns et
al., 2003), it is plausible that the spatial distribution of fish
species can be affected by alterations in the longitudinal
variation of riparian vegetation structure in Cerrado streams.

The purpose of this study was to describe fish community
structure and composition in a stream located in the plateau
region of the Paraguay basin, central west Brazil, with special
attention to the differential effects of the predominant Cerrado
phytophysiognomy in riparian zones. In this stream, shoreline
vegetation of the upstream reaches is formed by wet grassland,
a phytophysiognomy characterized by the dominance of
herbaceous species, while in downstream reaches gallery
forest predominates.

Material and Methods

This study was carried out in the Correntes stream, a
tributary on the left bank of the Aquidauana River (Fig. 1),
located in Dois Irmãos do Buriti municipality, Mato Grosso
do Sul State, central west Brazil, Paraguay basin. This stream
is roughly 18.5 km in length and its catchment encompasses
approximately 11,690 ha, where cattle pastures and eucalyptus
plantations predominate. The region is located in the São
Bento formation, represented by the Botucatu group. As to
geomorphology, it belongs to the Maracaju plateau, a region
characterized by plains topography and wide hills. The climate
is wet mesothermal with a rainy summer (October to March)
and a dry winter (April to September); annual precipitation
ranges from 1,300 to 1,400 mm.

Five 100-m reaches were selected (R1-R5) along the
longitudinal gradient of the Correntes stream (Table 1). The
distance between each reach was 2.5 km, except between R4
and R5, where the distance was 5.2 km (Fig. 1). One sampling
of the ichthyofauna was conducted in both the wet (February
2008) and dry seasons (September 2008). Fish were collected
by use of a hand seine (2.5 m in width x 1.5 m in height, 3 mm
mesh) and a dip net (0.9 m in width x 0.45 m in height, 3 mm
mesh) during a period of 60 min. Fish were fixed in 10% formalin
and afterward transferred to 70% EtOH. Voucher specimens
were deposited in the fish collection at the Departamento de
Zoologia e Botânica da Universidade Estadual Paulista
(DZSJRP), São José do Rio Preto, São Paulo State, Brazil.

Eighteen habitat structure descriptors related to in-stream
and shoreline physical structures were estimated visually

along each reach in the wet and dry periods. These descriptors
were divided into three categories related to shoreline
vegetation structure, substrate composition and hydrological
measurements. Descriptors related to shoreline vegetation
comprise characteristics of shoreline vegetation in contact
with the water as follows: proportion of shoreline occupied
by grass, thin roots, large roots, bryophytes, pteridophytes,
tree trunks, and bush leaves. Substrate composition was
evaluated by estimating the proportion of bottom occupied by
clay, sand, gravel, rock, algae, roots, litter, aquatic macrophytes
and logs and branches. Hydrological descriptors included
depth and width measurements obtained by means of transect
measured along each reach. Additionally, a physicochemical
analysis including measurement of dissolved oxygen,
conductivity, pH, turbidity and temperature (all measured using
electronic equipment, Horiba®, model U-10) was carried out.
These analyses were only performed in the dry period due to
operational problems with the equipment in the wet period.

Species diversity was calculated using the Shannon-
Wiener index (H’) as described by Magurran (2004), and
species dominance was obtained using the Berger-Parker
dominance index (where abundance of the dominant species
is divided by the total abundance of the species, multiplied
by 100). The spatial-temporal ordination of the reaches was
evaluated by non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS)
analysis, considering ichthyofauna composition and the
quantitative structure of the community. This analysis
resulted in stress values of 0.08 and 0.05, respectively,
indicating good ordination and reliability of resulting
interpretation (Clarke &amp;amp; Warwick, 2001). To complement the

Fig. 1. Map showing localization of the sampled reaches of
Correntes stream in the plateau region of the Paraguay basin,
Mato Grosso do Sul State, Brazil.



F. B. Teresa &amp;amp; R. de M. Romero 165

ordination analysis, a two-way analysis of similarity (routine
ANOSIM) was used to verify differences in the fish
composition and quantitative structure of communities
between rainy and dry seasons and between groupings
determined by ordination analysis (NMDS). In order to
investigate if spatial-temporal variation in the environmental
descriptors had a pattern similar to fish abundance data, the
same analysis was performed for shoreline vegetation
structure, substrate composition and hydrological
measurements. Additionally, a similarity percentage analysis
(routine SIMPER) was applied to determine which species
mainly explained differences in community composition
between groupings established by NMDS.

The relative importance of environmental descriptors
(shoreline vegetation, substrate and hydrological
measurements) structuring ichthyofauna in the Correntes
stream was evaluated by 2Stage analysis. This analysis
indicates which categories of the environmental descriptors
are more correlated to biotic similarity matrices, calculating
the rank correlation between all pairs of matrices. Afterward,
the significance of the correlation between biotic and abiotic
matrices was tested using the Mantel test in the Past software,
version 1.68 (Hammer et al., 2001). In this case, data were
pooled from the wet and dry seasons by summing species
abundance (biotic data) and by means (abiotic data), except
for physicochemical data which were obtained just in the dry
period. In this case, abiotic data was correlated with biotic
ones of the same period. Data were transformed according to
the arcsin procedure for proportions (shoreline and substrate
descriptors), log (x+1) procedure for hydrological
measurements (Zar, 1999) and fourth root for abundance matrix.
Similarity matrices were constructed using the Euclidean
distance similarity measure for abiotic data (Clarke &amp;amp;
Ainsworth, 1993), Jaccard similarity coefficient for
ichthyofauna composition and Bray-Curtis similarity
coefficient for quantitative structure of the communities. All
analyses (except the Mantel test) were performed using Primer
6 (2006) software.

Results

Spatial variability on the environmental descriptors was
greater than temporal variability (Table 2). Reaches 1, 2 and 3
were narrower and deeper than downstream reaches (Table
2). Grass and bush leaves were the most representative
shoreline vegetation in contact with water in reaches 1 and 2,
whereas in the downstream reaches, tree trunks and roots
were the vegetation most representative (Table 2). Substrate

was uniform along the longitudinal gradient of Correntes
stream with a predominance of sand in all reaches (Table 2). A
total of 1,166 individuals were sampled, belonging to six orders,
18 families and 44 species (Table 3). Characiformes and
Siluriformes represented 85.3% of the species recorded and
approximately 97.2% of total abundance. The most abundant
species were Odontostilbe pequira (24.3%), Jupiaba
acanthogaster (14.0%), Bryconamericus exodon (9.0%),
Characidium aff. zebra (7.9%), Moenkhausia bonita (6.4%),
Hemiloricaria lanceolata (4.6%), Hypostomus sp. (4.6%) and
Astyanax abramis (4.6%) (Table 3). Five species (11.4%) were
recorded in all reaches in at least one sampling: Astyanax
abramis, Bryconamericus exodon, Jupiaba acanthogaster,
Hypostomus sp. and Hemiloricaria lanceolata.

Total abundance obtained in the rainy season was greater
than in the dry, except for reach 2 (Table 3). Reach 5 exhibited
the greatest species richness, followed by reaches 1 and 4
which had greater species diversity but less dominance. Reach
2 had low species richness and diversity and high Jupiaba
acanthogaster dominance. Reach 3 had the lowest species
richness of all and low dominance. Although having the
greatest species richness, reach 5 had low diversity and higher
dominance due to the high relative abundance of
Odontostilbe pequira.

The ordination generated by NMDS, considering the fish
composition and quantitative structure of the communities,
revealed two subsets formed by upstream reaches (sites 1
and 2) and downstream reaches (sites 3, 4 and 5),
notwithstanding seasonality (Fig. 2). This was confirmed by
two-way ANOSIM which indicated significant differences of
ichthyofauna composition and quantitative structure between
upstream and downstream reaches (R = 1.00; p = 0.01 for
both), but not between rainy and dry seasons (p &gt; 0.40).

The SIMPER procedure revealed that the two sub-sets
indicated in the NMDS, i.e., the upstream reaches (R1 and R2)
and the downstream reaches (R3, R4 and R5), had an average
dissimilarity of 85.8%. This pattern was principally obtained
because of the differential contribution of Jupiaba
acanthogaster, Odontostilbe pequira, Moenkhausia bonita,
Characidium aff. zebra, Hemiloricaria lanceolata and
Bryconamericus exodon along the longitudinal gradient of
the Correntes stream (Table 4).

In a similar way, the shoreline vegetation structure
differed significantly between upstream and downstream
reaches (R = 0.79; p = 0.01), but not between wet and dry
periods (R = 0.06; p = 0.37). Substrate composition and
hydrological descriptors did not differ significantly between
upstream and downstream reaches (p &gt; 0.46) not between

Table 1. Location and general characteristics of reaches (R1-R5) of the Correntes stream, central west Brazil. *sensu Ribeiro &amp;amp;
Walter (1998).

Descriptors Reach 1 Reach 2 Reach 3 Reach 4 Reach 5 

Coordinates 20º32’44.8”S 55º21’56.1”W 
20º31’45.3”S 
55º22’53.1”W 

20º30’47.4”S 
55º23’47.3”W 

20º29’41.6”S 
55º24’46.6”W 

20º27’20.4”S 
55º25’16.8”W 

Altitude (m) 240 209 183 176 165 
Riparian phytophysiognomies* wet grassland wet grassland gallery forest gallery forest gallery forest 
Main mesohabitats run and pool run and pool run and pool run and pool run 

 



Influence of the riparian zone phytophysiognomies on the longitudinal distribution of fishes166

seasons (p &gt; 0.30). Shoreline vegetation structure was more
related to fish composition and quantitative structure of
community (2Stage analysis: R = 0.63 and 0.62, respectively)
than substrate composition and hydrological measurements
(0.28 &gt; R &gt; -0.32). This was confirmed by Mantel tests which
revealed a significant correlation of fish composition and
quantitative structure of the fish communities with the
shoreline vegetation (R &gt; 0.65; p &amp;lt;0.04), but not with substrate
composition, width and depth and physicochemical
measurements (p &gt; 0.12). Qualitatively, it was shown that
Gymnotiformes species such as Apteronotus albifrons,
Brachyhypopomus sp., Eigenmannia trilineata and
Gymnotus sp. and the loricariids Farlowella paraguayensis,
Hemiloricaria lanceolata and Rineloricaria cacerensis were
always captured associated with thin roots, shrub leaves and
grass in contact with the water.

Discussion

The two most abundant species, Odontostilbe pequira
and Jupiaba acanthogaster, were also the ones that most
contributed to the dissimilarity between up- and downstream
reaches in the Correntes stream. Jupiaba acanthogaster was
more restricted to upstream reaches, while Odontostilbe
pequira was exclusive to downstream reaches and was
predominant in R5. Marginal areas with moderate water flow
seem to favor O. pequira in this reach. The occurrence of
Jupiaba acanthogaster in upstream reaches of the Correntes
stream is compatible with findings of their preferential
occurrence in headwater streams of the Serra da Bodoquena
(L. Casatti &amp;amp; R. M. Romero, pers. comm.).

The greater species abundance recorded during the rainy

season can be explained by the increased volume of the
habitat, which provides a higher availability of microhabitats
and increases the amount of allochthonous material in the
stream, increasing the availability of food and substrates that
can be used as shelter and as reproductive sites (Schlosser,
1982; Angermeier &amp;amp; Karr, 1983; Casatti, 2005). Moreover, the
rainy season is also the reproduction period for many tropical
species when there is an increase in abundance, especially of
young in the streams (Casatti, 2005; Súarez et al., 2007). Reach
2 with its lower abundance in the rainy season may be due to
a sampling artifact, since there are limitations to the collecting
methodology used in deeper localities, as is the case with
this reach in rainy periods. Despite potential limitation of the
sampling techniques used in this study (Wiley &amp;amp; Tsai, 1983;
Mercado-Silva &amp;amp; Escandón-Sandoval, 2008), there was no
evidence of differential catchability between reaches along
the longitudinal gradient of the Correntes stream, except
between dry and wet period in reach 2. In this case, abundance
rather than richness seems to have been underestimated, but
this did not affect the results because relations obtained from
fish composition and quantitative structure of communities
were congruent in all analyses.

Despite the tendency for an increased abundance during
the rainy season, similarity analyses results indicate that such
differences were not enough to alter the structure of the
communities. Studying the fish communities in headwater
streams of Paraguay and Paraná basins, Valério et al. (2007)
found little seasonal influence on the organization of
communities, a pattern comparable to that seen in this study.
The increase in richness and diversity along the longitudinal
gradient predicted by the River Continuum Concept (Vannote
et al., 1980) has been confirmed in rivers and streams in

Table 2. Values of physicochemical (absolute) and physical habitat (proportion) descriptors of reaches (R1-R5) of the Correntes
stream in the wet (W) and dry period (D), central west Brazil. ND = no data available.

Reach 1 Reach 2 Reach 3 Reach 4 Reach 5 Category Descriptor 
W D W D W D W D W D 

Dissolved oxygen(mg.l-1) ND 6.40 ND 7.89 ND 8.03 ND 8.51 ND 8.52 
Conductivity (mS.cm-1) ND 0.054 ND 0.017 ND 0.049 ND 0.048 ND 0.049 
pH ND 6.58 ND 6.83 ND 6.70 ND 6.25 ND 7.18 
Turbidity (NTU) ND 14 ND 07 ND 10 ND 25 ND 28 

Physicochemical 

Water temperature (oC) ND 24.6 ND 27.4 ND 24.2 ND 21.3 ND 23.2 
           Mean depth (m) 0.68 0.54 0.85 0.70 0.82 0.65 0.45 0.35 0.26 0.20 Hydrological Mean width (m) 2.14 2.04 1.65 1.52 2.4 2.32 3.95 3.87 6.62 6.50 
           Grass (%) 0.44 0.35 0.43 0.30 - - 0.01 - - - 

Thin roots (%) 0.07 0.25 0.13 0.20 0.33 0.75 0.14 0.40 0.24 0.25 
Large roots (%) - 0.25 - 0.10 0.33 0.25 0.21 0.15 - - 
Bryophytes (%) - - - - 0.33 - 0.25 0.15 - - 
Pteridophytes (%) 0.07 0.10 0.26 0.15 - - 0.21 - - - 
Tree trunks (%) - - 0.02 - - - 0.14 0.15 0.33 0.35 

Shoreline vegetation 

Bush leaves (%) 0.36 - 0.17 0.25 - - - 0.05 - - 
           Sand (%) 0.67 0.85 1.00 0.90 0.70 0.50 0.90 0.85 0.75 0.75 

Clay (%) - - - - - 0.05 - 0.05 - - 
Gravel (%) 0.17 0.05 - - 0.10 0.10 0.05 - - - 
Rock (%) 0.17 - - - - - 0.05 - 0.04 0.05 
Adhered algae (%) - - - - - - - - 0.06 0.05 
Roots (%) - - - - - 0.25 - - - - 
Litter (%) - - - - - 0.05 - 0.05 - - 
Aquatic macrophytes (%) - 0.10 - - - - - - - - 

Substrate 

Logs and branches (%) - - - 0.10 0.20 0.05 - 0.05 0.16 0.15 

 



F. B. Teresa &amp;amp; R. de M. Romero 167

Table 3. Species abundance during the wet (W) and dry period (D) and ichthyofauna descriptors of the five reaches of the
Correntes stream, central west Brazil.



Influence of the riparian zone phytophysiognomies on the longitudinal distribution of fishes168

different zoogeographic regions (Sheldon, 1968; Evans &amp;amp;
Noble, 1979; Garutti, 1988; Oberdorff et al., 1993; Casatti, 2005;
Petry &amp;amp; Schulz, 2006). In the Correntes stream, this pattern
was especially evident from the intermediate reach (R3) to the
extreme downstream reach (R5) (14 to 25 species), apparently
following the increase in habitat volume (Angermeier &amp;amp;
Schlosser, 1989; Casatti, 2005). Moreover, fish migration from
bigger rivers to tributaries is also a factor that contributes
toward an increase in species richness in reaches of the
stream near the mainstem (Gorman, 1986; Fernandes et al.,
2004). Therefore, the proximity of R5 to the Aquidauana River
(less than 600 m) could also have contributed to the
maintenance of richer communities in the downstream reaches.

Surprisingly, headwater reaches, normally with smaller
species richness (Whiteside &amp;amp; McNatt, 1972; Garutti, 1988;
Casatti, 2005), had high species richness and diversity in the
Correntes stream. This happens when the headwaters have
singular characteristics such as a high structural heterogeneity,
making the occurrence of richer communities feasible
(McNeely, 1986; Ferreira &amp;amp; Casatti, 2006). In fact, upstream
reaches of the Correntes stream maintain high structural
diversity, especially the abundance of shoreline vegetation
in contact with the water; notably grasses, bushes and roots.
The high structural diversity of the banks was a marked
characteristic of upstream reaches, allowing the occurrence
of diverse species, notably fishes of the orders Gymnotiformes
and Siluriformes, which were abundant at these sites. These

results reinforce the predictive role of the structural
composition of the habitat for the structuring of fish communities
(Gorman &amp;amp; Karr, 1978; Schneider &amp;amp; Winemiller, 2008).

The addition of species was the most important process in
the downstream reaches (R3 to R5), which is generally the result
of increased habitat volume and complexity along the
longitudinal gradient of the streams, providing favorable
conditions for the occurrence of a greater number of species
(Sheldon, 1968; Angermeier &amp;amp; Schlosser, 1989). Nevertheless,
the high species richness in upstream reaches, among which
12 were exclusive, and its high dissimilarity in relation to
downstream reaches, evidenced by NMDS and SIMPER, also
suggests species substitution as an important process in the
structuring of fish communities in the Correntes stream. Species
substitution is predominant when environmental changes along
the longitudinal gradient are sudden, causing physical or
biological impediments to ichthyofauna longitudinal
colonization (Burton &amp;amp; Odum, 1945; Tramer &amp;amp; Rogers, 1973).
In fact, the structural composition of habitats in upstream areas
is quite distinct from that of downstream reaches, apparently
limiting the occurrence of some species while favoring others.

Although physical habitat and physicochemical descriptors
varied along the longitudinal gradient of the Correntes stream,
the shoreline vegetation was the most important environmental
feature predicting fish structure and composition as evidenced
by 2Stage analysis and Mantel tests. Structural differences
between upstream and downstream reaches correspond to the
phytophysiognomy dichotomy observed in the Correntes
stream whose shoreline vegetation consists of wet grassland
upstream and gallery forest downstream. Wet grasslands are
characterized by the dominance of herbaceous and shrubby
vegetation adapted to hydromorphic soil (Ribeiro &amp;amp; Water,
1998). In upstream reaches, the small size of the abundantly
present shoreline vegetation on the low banks favors their
contact with the stream water. Foliage leaning over the channel
and roots extending internally increase the spatial
heterogeneity of in-stream habitats, creating specific
microhabitats (Collier et al., 1999; Rocha et al., 2009) usually
explored by species with specialized needs. In fact, some species
such as Apteronotus albifrons, Brachyhypopomus sp.,
Eigenmannia trilineata and Gymnotus sp. were captured
exclusively in upstream reaches (Table 3) and always associated
with shoreline vegetation in contact with the water. This is
probably associated with preferential use of submerged
vegetation by Gymnotiformes species for diurnal shelter and
feeding (Ferreira &amp;amp; Casatti, 2006; Ferreira, 2007; Rocha et al.,
2009). Two other species, Farlowella paraguayensis and
Hemiloricaria lanceolata, also occurred associated with
marginal areas with dense vegetation and were important for
the dissimilarity between upstream and downstream reaches
according to the similarity percentage analysis. These data are
in agreement with the Mantel test result which indicated an
association between shoreline vegetation in contact with water
and the composition and quantitative structure of the fish
community. On the other hand, most of the species associated
with downstream areas that contributed toward dissimilarity

Fig. 2. Two-dimension ordinations based on Jaccard similarity
coefficient (a) and on Bray-Curtis (b), considering the ten
samples from the wet and dry seasons from the Correntes
stream, central west Brazil.



F. B. Teresa &amp;amp; R. de M. Romero 169

between upstream and downstream reaches were water column
swimmers such as Bryconamericus exodon and Astyanax
abramis. Their preference for downstream reaches was
probably related to the increased habitat volume.

The Correntes stream ichthyofauna is structured into two
biologically distinct zones, with upstream reaches having
particular structural and biological conditions. This reinforces
the importance of preserving headwaters to maintain regional
biodiversity (Paller, 1994). The composition of ichthyocenosis
and structure differences along the longitudinal gradient are
influenced by differential contributions of
phytophysiognomies in determining specific structural
patterns on stream banks. This provides support for the
generalization that phytophysiognomic diversity is
fundamental for the maintenance of biodiversity in the Brazilian
Cerrado (Mares et al., 1986; Ratter et al., 1997; Oliveira &amp;amp;
Marquis, 2002; Almeida &amp;amp; Louzada, 2009).

Acknowledgements

This study is part of the Reflorestar Legal project, a
partnership comprising MMX Metálicos Corumbá Ltda and
Fundação Neotrópica do Brasil. The authors thank the
following: MMX Metálicos Corumbá Ltda. - Unidade Florestal
and the Fundação Neotrópica do Brasil for financial and
logistic support; Vivian R. B. Maria for the in loco floral
analysis; Francisco Langeani for helping with fish
identification; José L.Veronezzi-Junior for helping with the
fish collecting; Lilian Casatti and Fernando R. Carvalho for
critical reading of and suggestions to the early version of the
manuscript; and two anonymous reviewers for helpful
suggestions and comments that improved the manuscript.
FBT and RMR are recipients of a doctoral fellowship from
Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo
(FAPESP: 2008/03583-9, 2007/05400-6, respectively).

Literature Cited

Almeida, S. S. P. &amp;amp; J. N. C. Louzada. 2009. Estrutura da comuni-
dade de Scarabaeinae (Scarabaeidae: Coleoptera) em
fitofisionomias do Cerrado e sua importância para a conserva-

ção. Neotropical Entomology, 38(1): 32-43.
Angermeier, P. L. &amp;amp; J. R. Karr. 1983. Fish communities along

environmental gradients in a system of tropical streams.
Environmental Biology of Fishes, 9: 117-135.

Angermeier, P. L. &amp;amp; I. J. Schlosser. 1989. Species-area relationship
for stream fishes. Ecology, 70(5): 1450-1462.

Britski, H. A., K. Z. S. Silimon &amp;amp; B. S. Lopes. 2007. Peixes do
Pantanal: manual de identificação. Brasília, Embrapa, 184p.

Burton, G. W. &amp;amp; E. P. Odum. 1945. The distribution of stream fish in
the vicinity of Mountain Lake, Virginia. Ecology, 26(2): 182-194.

Casatti, L. 2005. Fish assemblage structure in a first order stream,
southeastern Brazil: longitudinal distribution, seasonality, and
microhabitat diversity. Biota Neotropica, 5(1): 1-9.

Castro, R. M. C. 1999. Evolução da ictiofauna de riachos sul-ame-
ricanos: padrões gerais e possíveis processos causais. Oecologia
Brasiliensis, 6: 139-155.

Catella, A. C. &amp;amp; M. Petrere-Jr. 1996. Feeding patterns in a fish
community of Baía da Onça, a floodplain lake of the Aquidauana
river, Pantanal, Brazil. Fisheries Management and Ecology, 3:
229-237.

Chernoff, B. &amp;amp; P. W. Willink. 2000. Ecological and geographical
structure in assemblages of freshwater fishes in the Pantanal,
Mato Grosso do Sul, Brasil. Pp. 183-201. In: Willink, P. W., B.
Chernoff, L. E. Alonso, J. R. Montambault &amp;amp; R. Lourival (Eds.).
A Biological Assessment of the Aquatic Ecosystems of the Pan-
tanal, Mato Grosso do Sul, Brazil. Washington, Bulletin of
Biological Assessment 18, Conservation International, 307p.

Clarke, K. R. &amp;amp; R. M. Warwick. 2001. Change in marine
communities: an approach to statistical analysis and
interpretation. Plymouth, Plymouth Marine Laboratory, 144p.

Collier, K. J., P. D. Champion &amp;amp; G. F. Crocker. 1999. Patch-and
reach-scale dynamics of a macrophyte-invertebrate system in a
New Zealand lowland stream. Hydrobiologia, 392: 89-97.

Evans, J. W. &amp;amp; R. L. Noble. 1979. The longitudinal distribution of
fishes in an east Texas stream. American Midland Naturalist,
101(2): 333-343.

Fernandes, C. C., J. Podos &amp;amp; J. G. Lundberg. 2004. Amazonian
ecology: tributaries enhance the diversity of electric fishes.
Science, 305: 1960-1962.

Ferreira, K. M. 2007. Biology and ecomorphology of stream fishes
from the rio Mogi-Guaçu basin, Southeastern Brazil. Neotropical
Ichthyology, 5(3): 311-326.

Ferreira, C. P. &amp;amp; L. Casatti. 2006. Influência da estrutura do hábitat
sobre a ictiofauna de um riacho em uma micro-bacia de pastagem,
São Paulo, Brasil. Revista Brasileira de Zoologia, 23(3): 642-651.

Table 4. Species contribution to dissimilarity between the upstream reaches (R1 and R2) and downstream reaches (R3, R4 and
R5) of the Correntes stream, central west Brazil. a = Contribution of each species to the mean dissimilarity between groups. b =
Mean dissimilarity between groups ± standard deviation. c = Contribution percentage of each species (&gt; 3.0%) to the dissimilarity
between groups.

Mean abundancea Species 
Upstream Downstream 

Mean dissimilarityb Contribution%c 

Odontostilbe pequira 0.0 47.2 16.48 ± 1.19 19.21 
Jupiaba acanthogaster 35.5 3.5 15.50 ± 2.36 18.07 
Moenkhausia bonita 17.2 1.0 7.16 ± 0.59 8.35 
Characidium aff. zebra 2.7 13.7 6.10 ± 0.96 7.11 
Hemiloricaria lanceolata 11.7 1.12 5.22 ± 1.14 6.08 
Bryconamericus exodon 2.0 16.2 5.14 ± 1.03 5.99 
Xenurobrycon macropus 0.0 6.5 3.33 ± 0.91 3.88 
Farlowella paraguayensis 8.5 1.33 3.30 ± 1.52 3.84 
Astyanax abramis 0.5 8.67 3.19 ± 0.91 3.72 

 



Influence of the riparian zone phytophysiognomies on the longitudinal distribution of fishes170

Garutti, V. 1988. Distribuição longitudinal da ictiofauna de um
Córrego na região noroeste do Estado de São Paulo, Bacia do rio
Paraná. Revista Brasileira de Biologia, 48: 747-759.

Gorman, O. T. 1986. Assemblage organization of stream fishes: the
effect of rivers on adventitious streams. The American
Naturalist, 128(4): 611-616.

Gorman, O. T. &amp;amp; J. R. Karr. 1978. Habitat structure and stream fish
communities. Ecology, 59: 507-515.

Growns, I., P. C. Gehrke, K. L. Astlea &amp;amp; D. A. Pollard. 2003. A
comparison of fish assemblages associated with different riparian
vegetation types in the Hawkesbury-Nepean River system.
Fisheries Management and Ecology, 10: 209-220.

Hammer, Ø., D. A. T. Harper &amp;amp; P. D. Ryan. 2001. PAST:
paleontological statistics software package for education and
data analysis. Palaeontologia Electronica, 4(1): 1-9.

Magurran, A. E. 2004. Measuring Biological Diversity. United
Kingdom, Blackwell Publishing, 256p.

Mares, M. A., K. A. Ernest &amp;amp; D. D. Gettinger. 1986. Small mammal
community structure and composition in the Cerrado Province
of central Brazil. Journal of Tropical Ecology, 2: 289-300.

McNeely, D. L. 1986. Longitudinal patterns in the fish assemblages
of an Ozark stream. Southwestern Naturalist, 31: 375-380.

Mercado-Silva, N. &amp;amp; D. S. Escandón-Sandoval. 2008. A comparison
of seining and electrofishing for fish community bioassessment
in a Mexican Atlantic slope montane river. North American
Journal of Fisheries Management, 28: 1725-1732.

Myers, N., R. Mittermeier, C. Mittermeier, G. Fonseca &amp;amp; J. Kent.
2000. Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities. Nature,
403(6772): 853-858.

Oberdorff, T., E. Guilbert &amp;amp; J. C. Lucchetta. 1993. Patterns of fish
species richness in the Seine River basin, France. Hydrobiologia,
259: 157-167.

Oliveira, P. S. &amp;amp; R. J. Marquis. 2002. The cerrados of Brazil: ecology
and natural history of a Neotropical savanna. Irvington,
Columbia University Press, 398p.

Paller, M. H. 1994. Relationships between fish assemblage structure
and stream order in South Carolina coastal plain streams.
Transactions of the American Fisheries Society, 123: 150-161.

Petry, A. C. &amp;amp; U. H. Schulz. 2006. Longitudinal changes and indicator
species of the fish fauna in the subtropical Sinos river, Brazil.
Journal of Fish Biology, 69: 272-290.

Ratter, J. A., J. F. Ribeiro &amp;amp; S. Bridgewater. 1997. The Brazilian
cerrado vegetation and threats to its biodiversity. Annals of
Botany, 80: 223-230.

Ribeiro, J. F. &amp;amp; B. M. T. Walter. 1998. Fitofisionomias do Bioma
Cerrado. Pp. 89-166. In: Sano, S. M. &amp;amp; S. P. Almeida (Eds.).
Cerrado: ambiente e flora. Planaltina, Embrapa/CPAC, 556p.

Rocha, F. C., L. Casatti, F. R. Carvalho &amp;amp; A. M. Silva. 2009. Fish
assemblages in stream stretches occupied by cattail (Typhaceae,
Angiospermae) stands in Southeast Brazil. Neotropical
Ichthyology, 7(2): 241-250.

Schlosser, I. J. 1982. Fish Community structure and function along
two habitat gradients in a headwater stream. Ecological
Monographs, 52(4): 395-414.

Schneider, K. N. &amp;amp; K. O. Winemiller. 2008. Structural complexity
of woody debris patches influences fish and macroinvertebrate
species richness in a temperate floodplain-river system.
Hydrobiologia, 610: 235-244.

Sheldon, A. L. 1968. Species diversity and longitudinal succession
in stream fishes. Ecology, 49(2): 194-198.

Súarez, Y. R., M. Petrere-Jr. &amp;amp; A. C. Catella. 2004. Factors regulating
diversity and abundance of fish communities in Pantanal

lagoons, Brazil. Fisheries Management and Ecology, 11: 45-50.
Súarez, Y. R., S. B. Valério, K. K. Tondado, A. C. Florentino, T. R.

A. Felipe, L. Q. L. Ximenes &amp;amp; L. S. Lourenço. 2007. Fish
species diversity in headwaters streams of Paraguay and Paraná
basins. Brazilian Archives of Biology and Technology, 50(6):
1033-1042.

Tramer, E. J. &amp;amp; P. M. Rogers. 1973. Diversity and longitudinal
zonation in fish populations of two streams entering a
metropolitan area. American Midland Naturalist, 90(2): 366-374.

Valério, S. B., Y. R. Súarez, T. R. A. Felipe, K. K. Tondato &amp;amp; L. Q.
L. Ximenes. 2007. Organization patterns of headwater-stream
fish communities in the Upper Paraguay-Paraná basins.
Hydrobiologia, 583:241-250.

Vannote, R. L.,G. W. Minshall, K. W. Cummins, J. R. Sedel &amp;amp; C. E.
Cushing. 1980. The river continuum concept. Canadian Journal
of Fisheries and Aquatic Science, 37: 130-137.

Whiteside, B. G. &amp;amp; R. M. McNatt. 1972. Fish species diversity in
relation to stream order and physicochemical conditions in the
Plum creek drainage basin. American Midland Naturalist, 88(1):
90-101.

Wichert, G. A. &amp;amp; D. J. Rapport. 1998. Fish community structure as
a measure of degradation and rehabilitation of riparian systems
in an agricultural drainage basin. Environmental Management,
22(3): 425-443.

Wiley, M. L. &amp;amp; C. F. Tsai. 1983. The relative efficiencies of
electrofishing vs. seines in Piedmont streams of Maryland. North
American Journal of Fisheries Management, 3: 243-253.

Willink, P. W., O. Froehlich, A. Machado-Alisson, N. Menezes, O.
Oyakawa, A. Catella, B. Chernoff, F. C. T. Lima, M. Toledo-
Piza, H. Hortega, A. M. Zanata &amp;amp; R. Barriga. 2000. Fishes of
the Rio Negro, Negrinho, Taboco, Aquidauana, Taquari and
Miranda, Pantanal, Brasil: diversity, distribution, critical habitats
and value. Pp. 63-81. In: Willink, P. W., B. Chernoff, L. E.
Alonso, J. R. Montambault &amp;amp; R. Lourival (Eds.). A Biological
Assessment of the Aquatic Ecosystems of the Pantanal, Mato
Grosso do Sul, Brazil. Washington, Bulletin of Biological
Assessment 18, Conservation International, 307p.

Accepted December 22, 2009
Published March 31, 2010


&lt;&lt;
  /ASCII85EncodePages false
  /AllowTransparency false
  /AutoPositionEPSFiles true
  /AutoRotatePages /All
  /Binding /Left
  /CalGrayProfile (Dot Gain 20%)
  /CalRGBProfile (sRGB IEC61966-2.1)
  /CalCMYKProfile (U.S. Web Coated \050SWOP\051 v2)
  /sRGBProfile (sRGB IEC61966-2.1)
  /CannotEmbedFontPolicy /Warning
  /CompatibilityLevel 1.4
  /CompressObjects /Tags
  /CompressPages true
  /ConvertImagesToIndexed true
  /PassThroughJPEGImages true
  /CreateJDFFile false
  /CreateJobTicket false
  /DefaultRenderingIntent /Default
  /DetectBlends true
  /ColorConversionStrategy /LeaveColorUnchanged
  /DoThumbnails false
  /EmbedAllFonts true
  /EmbedJobOptions true
  /DSCReportingLevel 0
  /EmitDSCWarnings false
  /EndPage -1
  /ImageMemory 1048576
  /LockDistillerParams false
  /MaxSubsetPct 100
  /Optimize true
  /OPM 1
  /ParseDSCComments true
  /ParseDSCCommentsForDocInfo true
  /PreserveCopyPage true
  /PreserveEPSInfo true
  /PreserveHalftoneInfo false
  /PreserveOPIComments false
  /PreserveOverprintSettings true
  /StartPage 1
  /SubsetFonts true
  /TransferFunctionInfo /Apply
  /UCRandBGInfo /Preserve
  /UsePrologue false
  /ColorSettingsFile ()
  /AlwaysEmbed [ true
  ]
  /NeverEmbed [ true
  ]
  /AntiAliasColorImages false
  /DownsampleColorImages true
  /ColorImageDownsampleType /Bicubic
  /ColorImageResolution 600
  /ColorImageDepth -1
  /ColorImageDownsampleThreshold 1.50000
  /EncodeColorImages true
  /ColorImageFilter /DCTEncode
  /AutoFilterColorImages true
  /ColorImageAutoFilterStrategy /JPEG
  /ColorACSImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /QFactor 0.15
    /HSamples [1 1 1 1] /VSamples [1 1 1 1]
  &gt;&gt;
  /ColorImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /QFactor 0.15
    /HSamples [1 1 1 1] /VSamples [1 1 1 1]
  &gt;&gt;
  /JPEG2000ColorACSImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /TileWidth 256
    /TileHeight 256
    /Quality 30
  &gt;&gt;
  /JPEG2000ColorImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /TileWidth 256
    /TileHeight 256
    /Quality 30
  &gt;&gt;
  /AntiAliasGrayImages false
  /DownsampleGrayImages true
  /GrayImageDownsampleType /Bicubic
  /GrayImageResolution 600
  /GrayImageDepth -1
  /GrayImageDownsampleThreshold 1.50000
  /EncodeGrayImages true
  /GrayImageFilter /DCTEncode
  /AutoFilterGrayImages true
  /GrayImageAutoFilterStrategy /JPEG
  /GrayACSImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /QFactor 0.15
    /HSamples [1 1 1 1] /VSamples [1 1 1 1]
  &gt;&gt;
  /GrayImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /QFactor 0.15
    /HSamples [1 1 1 1] /VSamples [1 1 1 1]
  &gt;&gt;
  /JPEG2000GrayACSImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /TileWidth 256
    /TileHeight 256
    /Quality 30
  &gt;&gt;
  /JPEG2000GrayImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /TileWidth 256
    /TileHeight 256
    /Quality 30
  &gt;&gt;
  /AntiAliasMonoImages false
  /DownsampleMonoImages true
  /MonoImageDownsampleType /Bicubic
  /MonoImageResolution 1200
  /MonoImageDepth -1
  /MonoImageDownsampleThreshold 1.50000
  /EncodeMonoImages true
  /MonoImageFilter /CCITTFaxEncode
  /MonoImageDict&amp;lt;&lt;
    /K -1
  &gt;&gt;
  /AllowPSXObjects false
  /PDFX1aCheck false
  /PDFX3Check false
  /PDFXCompliantPDFOnly false
  /PDFXNoTrimBoxError true
  /PDFXTrimBoxToMediaBoxOffset [
    0.00000
    0.00000
    0.00000
    0.00000
  ]
  /PDFXSetBleedBoxToMediaBox true
  /PDFXBleedBoxToTrimBoxOffset [
    0.00000
    0.00000
    0.00000
    0.00000
  ]
  /PDFXOutputIntentProfile (None)
  /PDFXOutputCondition ()
  /PDFXRegistryName (http://www.color.org)
  /PDFXTrapped /Unknown

  /Description&amp;lt;&lt;
    /FRA&amp;lt;FEFF004f007000740069006f006e00730020007000650072006d0065007400740061006e007400200064006500200063007200e900650072002000640065007300200064006f00630075006d0065006e00740073002000500044004600200064006f007400e900730020006400270075006e00650020007200e90073006f006c007500740069006f006e002000e9006c0065007600e9006500200070006f0075007200200075006e00650020007100750061006c0069007400e90020006400270069006d007000720065007300730069006f006e00200061006d00e9006c0069006f007200e90065002e00200049006c002000650073007400200070006f0073007300690062006c0065002000640027006f00750076007200690072002000630065007300200064006f00630075006d0065006e007400730020005000440046002000640061006e00730020004100630072006f0062006100740020006500740020005200650061006400650072002c002000760065007200730069006f006e002000200035002e00300020006f007500200075006c007400e9007200690065007500720065002e&gt;
    /ENU (Use these settings to create PDF documents with higher image resolution for improved printing quality. The PDF documents can be opened with Acrobat and Reader 5.0 and later.)
    /JPN&amp;lt;FEFF3053306e8a2d5b9a306f30019ad889e350cf5ea6753b50cf3092542b308000200050004400460020658766f830924f5c62103059308b3068304d306b4f7f75283057307e30593002537052376642306e753b8cea3092670059279650306b4fdd306430533068304c3067304d307e305930023053306e8a2d5b9a30674f5c62103057305f00200050004400460020658766f8306f0020004100630072006f0062006100740020304a30883073002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000204ee5964d30678868793a3067304d307e30593002&gt;
    /DEU&amp;lt;FEFF00560065007200770065006e00640065006e0020005300690065002000640069006500730065002000450069006e007300740065006c006c0075006e00670065006e0020007a0075006d002000450072007300740065006c006c0065006e00200076006f006e0020005000440046002d0044006f006b0075006d0065006e00740065006e0020006d00690074002000650069006e006500720020006800f60068006500720065006e002000420069006c0064006100750066006c00f600730075006e0067002c00200075006d002000650069006e0065002000760065007200620065007300730065007200740065002000420069006c0064007100750061006c0069007400e400740020007a0075002000650072007a00690065006c0065006e002e00200044006900650020005000440046002d0044006f006b0075006d0065006e007400650020006b00f6006e006e0065006e0020006d006900740020004100630072006f0062006100740020006f0064006500720020006d00690074002000640065006d002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000200075006e00640020006800f600680065007200200067006500f600660066006e00650074002000770065007200640065006e002e&gt;
    /DAN&amp;lt;FEFF004200720075006700200064006900730073006500200069006e0064007300740069006c006c0069006e006700650072002000740069006c0020006100740020006f0070007200650074007400650020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e0074006500720020006d006500640020006800f8006a006500720065002000620069006c006c00650064006f0070006c00f80073006e0069006e006700200066006f00720020006100740020006600e50020006200650064007200650020007500640073006b00720069006600740073006b00760061006c0069007400650074002e0020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e0074006500720020006b0061006e002000e50062006e006500730020006d006500640020004100630072006f0062006100740020006f0067002000520065006100640065007200200035002e00300020006f00670020006e0079006500720065002e&gt;
    /NLD&amp;lt;FEFF004700650062007200750069006b002000640065007a006500200069006e007300740065006c006c0069006e00670065006e0020006f006d0020005000440046002d0064006f00630075006d0065006e00740065006e0020007400650020006d0061006b0065006e0020006d00650074002000650065006e00200068006f0067006500720065002000610066006200650065006c00640069006e00670073007200650073006f006c007500740069006500200076006f006f0072002000650065006e0020006200650074006500720065002000610066006400720075006b006b00770061006c00690074006500690074002e0020004400650020005000440046002d0064006f00630075006d0065006e00740065006e0020006b0075006e006e0065006e00200077006f007200640065006e002000670065006f00700065006e00640020006d006500740020004100630072006f00620061007400200065006e002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000200065006e00200068006f006700650072002e&gt;
    /ESP&amp;lt;FEFF0055007300650020006500730074006100730020006f007000630069006f006e006500730020007000610072006100200063007200650061007200200064006f00630075006d0065006e0074006f0073002000500044004600200063006f006e0020006d00610079006f00720020007200650073006f006c00750063006900f3006e00200064006500200069006d006100670065006e00200070006100720061002000610075006d0065006e0074006100720020006c0061002000630061006c006900640061006400200061006c00200069006d007000720069006d00690072002e0020004c006f007300200064006f00630075006d0065006e0074006f00730020005000440046002000730065002000700075006500640065006e00200061006200720069007200200063006f006e0020004100630072006f00620061007400200079002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000200079002000760065007200730069006f006e0065007300200070006f00730074006500720069006f007200650073002e&gt;
    /SUO&amp;lt;FEFF004e00e4006900640065006e002000610073006500740075007300740065006e0020006100760075006c006c006100200076006f0069006400610061006e0020006c0075006f006400610020005000440046002d0061007300690061006b00690072006a006f006a0061002c0020006a006f006900640065006e002000740075006c006f0073007400750073006c00610061007400750020006f006e0020006b006f0072006b006500610020006a00610020006b007500760061006e0020007400610072006b006b007500750073002000730075007500720069002e0020005000440046002d0061007300690061006b00690072006a0061007400200076006f0069006400610061006e0020006100760061007400610020004100630072006f006200610074002d0020006a00610020004100630072006f006200610074002000520065006100640065007200200035002e00300020002d006f0068006a0065006c006d0061006c006c0061002000740061006900200075007500640065006d006d0061006c006c0061002000760065007200730069006f006c006c0061002e&gt;
    /ITA&amp;lt;FEFF00550073006100720065002000710075006500730074006500200069006d0070006f007300740061007a0069006f006e00690020007000650072002000630072006500610072006500200064006f00630075006d0065006e00740069002000500044004600200063006f006e00200075006e00610020007200690073006f006c0075007a0069006f006e00650020006d0061006700670069006f00720065002000700065007200200075006e00610020007100750061006c0069007400e00020006400690020007300740061006d007000610020006d00690067006c0069006f00720065002e0020004900200064006f00630075006d0065006e00740069002000500044004600200070006f00730073006f006e006f0020006500730073006500720065002000610070006500720074006900200063006f006e0020004100630072006f00620061007400200065002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000200065002000760065007200730069006f006e006900200073007500630063006500730073006900760065002e&gt;
    /NOR&amp;lt;FEFF004200720075006b00200064006900730073006500200069006e006e007300740069006c006c0069006e00670065006e0065002000740069006c002000e50020006f00700070007200650074007400650020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e0074006500720020006d006500640020006800f80079006500720065002000620069006c00640065006f00700070006c00f80073006e0069006e006700200066006f00720020006200650064007200650020007500740073006b00720069006600740073006b00760061006c0069007400650074002e0020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e00740065006e00650020006b0061006e002000e50070006e006500730020006d006500640020004100630072006f0062006100740020006f0067002000520065006100640065007200200035002e00300020006f0067002000730065006e006500720065002e&gt;
    /SVE&amp;lt;FEFF0041006e007600e4006e00640020006400650020006800e4007200200069006e0073007400e4006c006c006e0069006e006700610072006e00610020006e00e40072002000640075002000760069006c006c00200073006b0061007000610020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e00740020006d006500640020006800f6006700720065002000620069006c0064007500700070006c00f60073006e0069006e00670020006f006300680020006400e40072006d006500640020006600e50020006200e400740074007200650020007500740073006b00720069006600740073006b00760061006c0069007400650074002e0020005000440046002d0064006f006b0075006d0065006e00740065006e0020006b0061006e002000f600700070006e006100730020006d006500640020004100630072006f0062006100740020006f00630068002000520065006100640065007200200035002e003000200065006c006c00650072002000730065006e006100720065002e&gt;
    /KOR&amp;lt;FEFFd5a5c0c1b41c0020c778c1c40020d488c9c8c7440020c5bbae300020c704d5740020ace0d574c0c1b3c4c7580020c774bbf8c9c0b97c0020c0acc6a9d558c5ec00200050004400460020bb38c11cb97c0020b9ccb4e4b824ba740020c7740020c124c815c7440020c0acc6a9d558c2edc2dcc624002e0020c7740020c124c815c7440020c0acc6a9d558c5ec0020b9ccb4e000200050004400460020bb38c11cb2940020004100630072006f0062006100740020bc0f002000520065006100640065007200200035002e00300020c774c0c1c5d0c11c0020c5f40020c2180020c788c2b5b2c8b2e4002e&gt;
    /CHS&amp;lt;FEFF4f7f75288fd94e9b8bbe7f6e521b5efa76840020005000440046002065876863ff0c5c065305542b66f49ad8768456fe50cf52068fa87387ff0c4ee563d09ad8625353708d2891cf30028be5002000500044004600206587686353ef4ee54f7f752800200020004100630072006f00620061007400204e0e002000520065006100640065007200200035002e00300020548c66f49ad87248672c62535f003002&gt;
    /CHT&amp;lt;FEFF4f7f752890194e9b8a2d5b9a5efa7acb76840020005000440046002065874ef65305542b8f039ad876845f7150cf89e367905ea6ff0c4fbf65bc63d066075217537054c18cea3002005000440046002065874ef653ef4ee54f7f75280020004100630072006f0062006100740020548c002000520065006100640065007200200035002e0030002053ca66f465b07248672c4f86958b555f3002&gt;
    /PTB&amp;lt;FEFF005500740069006c0069007a006500200065007300740061007300200063006f006e00660069006700750072006100e700f5006500730020007000610072006100200063007200690061007200200064006f00630075006d0065006e0074006f0073002000500044004600200063006f006d00200075006d00610020007200650073006f006c007500e700e3006f00200064006500200069006d006100670065006d0020007300750070006500720069006f0072002000700061007200610020006f006200740065007200200075006d00610020007100750061006c0069006400610064006500200064006500200069006d0070007200650073007300e3006f0020006d0065006c0068006f0072002e0020004f007300200064006f00630075006d0065006e0074006f0073002000500044004600200070006f00640065006d0020007300650072002000610062006500720074006f007300200063006f006d0020006f0020004100630072006f006200610074002c002000520065006100640065007200200035002e0030002000650020007300750070006500720069006f0072002e&gt;
  &gt;&gt;
&gt;&gt; setdistillerparams
&lt;&lt;
  /HWResolution [2400 2400]
  /PageSize [612.000 792.000]
&gt;&gt; setpagedevice



</field>
	</doc>
</add>