<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.11331</field>
		<field name="filename">16607_Missawa_SilviaKazue_D.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">


FICHA CATALOGRÁFICA ELABORADA PELA 
BIBLIOTECA DO INSTITUTO DE BIOLOGIA – UNICAMP 

      

                 
                  

Título em inglês: Genetic modification of industrial Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain to improve 
ethanol production and conditional flocculation.
Palavras-chave em inglês: Fermentation; Saccharomyces cerevisiae; Alcohol; Molecular 
genetics; Industrial strain. 
Área de concentração: Genética de Microorganismos.  
Titulação: Doutora em Genética e Biologia Molecular.  
Banca examinadora: Gonçalo Amarante Guimarães Pereira, Jörg Kobarg, Flávio Henrique da 
Silva, Jorge Maurício Costa Mondego, André Ricardo Alcarde. 
Data da defesa: 30/07/2009. 
Programa de Pós-Graduação: Genética e Biologia Molecular.

                   Missawa, Silvia Kazue 
M691m            Modificação de linhagens industriais de Saccharomyces 

cerevisiae para o aumento da produtividade de álcool e 
floculação condicional / Silvia Kazue Missawa. – Campinas, 
SP: [s.n.], 2009. 

     Orientadores: Gonçalo Amarante Guimarães Pereira, 
Anderson Ferreira da Cunha. 
     Tese (doutorado) – Universidade Estadual de                   
Campinas, Instituto de Biologia. 

     1.  Fermentação.   2.  Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  3.  
Álcool.   4.  Genética molecular.   5.  Linhagem industrial.   I. 
Pereira, Gonçalo Amarante Guimarães.   II.  Cunha, 
Anderson Ferreira da.   III.  Universidade Estadual de 
Campinas. Instituto de Biologia.   IV.  Título. 

(rcdt/ib)

silviakm
Typewriter
ii





 iv

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
"Você nunca será a pessoa que pode ser se pressão, 
tensão e disciplina forem tiradas da sua vida"  
(James G. Bilkey) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

Dedico aos meus pais  
e meu irmão 



 v

AGRADECIMENTOS 
 

 Ao meu orientador Gonçalo, pela oportunidade, confiança e apoio durante todo o meu 

doutorado; 

 Ao meu co-orientador Anderson, por me ensinar as técnicas básicas de biologia 

molecular. E por toda a ajuda nos experimentos, discussão de resultados, paciência e amizade; 

 À Eliane, pela amizade, paciência e disposição, sempre pronta a nos ajudar; 

 Ao Dr. Juan Lucas Argueso, pesquisador da Duke University Medical Center, USA. Pelas 

importantes sugestões e auxílio; 

 Ao Luiz Humberto Gomes, o Beto, do laboratório de Genética de Leveduras da Esalq – 

USP (Piracicaba), pelas dicas e ajuda essencial nos ensaios fermentativos; 

 A todos os amigos que fiz durante todo o período do meu Doutorado no LGE. Às amigas 

que me acompanharam desde o começo: Carla e Ana Paula. A todo pessoal do LGE, pela ajuda e 

amizade construída no laboratório; 

 Às minhas amigas de graduação, Patrícia, Maria Paula, Lye, com que sempre divido os 

momentos bons e ruins; 

 À minha família, sempre me apoiando em todos os momentos da minha vida; 

 À Pós Graduação do Instituto de Biologia da Unicamp; 

À Fundação de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP) pelo apoio 

financeiro. 

  



  SUMÁRIO 
 

RESUMO ............................................................................................................................... 1 

ABSTRACT .......................................................................................................................... 2 

REVISÃO BIBLIOGRÁFICA ............................................................................................ 3 
1.  AQUECIMENTO GLOBAL E FONTES ALTERNATIVAS DE ENERGIA.............................. 3 
2.  PRODUÇÃO DE ETANOL NO BRASIL ........................................................................... 7 
3.  PROCESSO FERMENTATIVO ........................................................................................ 9 
4.  A LEVEDURA ............................................................................................................. 11 
5.  PROCESSO DE FLOCULAÇÃO .................................................................................... 14 
6.  ATIVIDADE MITOCONDRIAL .................................................................................... 21 

JUSTIFICATIVA ............................................................................................................... 23 

OBJETIVOS ....................................................................................................................... 24 

CAPITULO 1 ...................................................................................................................... 25 

CAPITULO 2 ...................................................................................................................... 35 

CAPITULO 3 ...................................................................................................................... 54 

CONCLUSÕES FINAIS .................................................................................................... 70 

ANEXO I ............................................................................................................................. 78 

ANEXO II .......................................................................................................................... 104 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 1

RESUMO 

A crescente necessidade da substituição de fontes de energia derivadas do petróleo 

por fontes renováveis de energia impulsionou pesquisas em todo o mundo. O etanol se 

enquadra fortemente como candidato para substituir combustíveis como, por exemplo, a 

gasolina. A produção de etanol brasileiro ocorre pela fermentação de açucares proveniente 

do caldo de cana, realizada por leveduras, fundamentalmente da espécie Saccharomyces 

cerevisiae. No processo fermentativo para a produção de etanol combustível no Brasil, a 

separação das leveduras após o esgotamento do açúcar é realizado por centrífugas de alta 

capacidade, o que torna o sistema complexo e dispendioso. Neste trabalho, linhagens de 

leveduras de laboratório e industriais foram transformadas por engenharia genética de 

modo que as leveduras reconhecessem o esgotamento da glicose do meio separando-se 

naturalmente e rapidamente. Para isso, plasmídeos e posteriormente, cassetes integrativos, 

foram construídos utilizando-se promotores, sensíveis a presença de glicose no meio, 

regulando a expressão de genes da floculação. Estes promovem a formação de agregados 

celulares que se separam do meio por decantação. Além disso, está relatado na literatura 

que mutantes respiratórios produzem uma maior quantidade de etanol. Então foi feita a 

deleção, em leveduras industriais, do gene PET191, cujo produto participa na montagem do 

citocromo c, que por sua vez é essencial para o funcionamento da cadeia respiratória nestes 

microorganismos. As leveduras deletadas apresentaram um aumento no rendimento da 

produção de etanol; na linhagem industrial JAY292, esse aumento foi de 4%. Isto pode 

refletir ao final de um ano, um aumento de 980 milhões de litros. Os resultados obtidos 

contribuem para o desenvolvimento tecnológico e industrial desta área estratégica para o 

país. 

 



 2

ABSTRACT 

The increased need for replacing energy sources from fossil oil to renewable sources 

has prompted research initiatives throughout the world. Bioethanol is a highly competitive 

candidate to replace fuels such as gasoline. The production of Brazilian ethanol occurs by 

the fermentation of sugars from sugar cane juice by the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. 

The industrial fermentation process used to produce ethanol fuel in Brazil includes a 

separation step by high-capacity centrifugation of the yeast cells after the exhaustion of the 

sugar, which makes the system complex and costly. In this work, laboratory and industrial 

yeast strains were transformed by genetic engineering techniques so that they are able to 

recognize the depletion of glucose from the medium and quickly separate by sedimentation, 

without the need of centrifugation. In order to reach this goal, plasmids and integrative 

cassettes were constructed using promoters sensitive to the presence of glucose in the 

environment regulating the expression of the genes that control flocculation. This genetic 

device promotes the formation of cellular aggregates that are separated from the medium by 

sedimentation only when glucose is depleted. Furthermore, it is reported in the literature 

that respiratory mutants produce a higher quantity of ethanol. Consequently, the PET191 

gene was deleted in an industrial yeast strain; the gene product pet191 participates in the 

assembly of cytochome c, which is an essential component of the respiratory chain in these 

microorganisms. The deleted industrial strain JAY292 showed an increased production of 

ethanol by 4%. This percentage can be translated in an increase of more than 980 million 

liters of ethanol produced per year. These results are of great technological and industrial 

importance, and may contribute to the development of this strategic area for the country. 

 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 3

REVISÃO BIBLIOGRÁFICA 
 

1. Aquecimento global e fontes alternativas de energia 
O aquecimento global é o aumento da temperatura média da superfície terrestre 

provocado principalmente pelo efeito estufa. Desde o início do século 19, a temperatura 

aumentou cerca de 0,4 a 0,8 ºC. A estimativa, que preocupa cientistas de todo o mundo, é 

que até 2100 a temperatura tenha um aumento de 1,4 a 5,8 ºC, (Mastrandrea &amp;amp; Stephen, 

2005).  

Os maiores responsáveis pelo aumento do efeito estufa na Terra são as atividades 

humanas, principalmente o desmatamento e a queima de combustíveis fósseis (provocada 

por veículos automotores e indústrias). O excesso de gases que são liberados na atmosfera, 

principalmente o dióxido de carbono (CO2), potencializam a ação do efeito estufa. Uma 

opção para minimizar isso é a substituição de combustíveis fósseis por outras fontes de 

energia (Goldemberg et al., 2008). 

A busca por energia alternativa renovável e menos poluente, visando substituir 

combustíveis derivados do petróleo, tem sido tema de discussões e pesquisas em todo o 

mundo (Farrell et al., 2006).  

Em 1997, durante uma reunião realizada no Japão, com a presença de delegações de 

mais de 160 países, foi estabelecido um acordo, conhecido como Protocolo de Kyoto. O 

objetivo foi a restrição da emissão de CO2 e outros 5 gases responsáveis pelo efeito estufa.  

A meta estabelecida é a redução, até 2012, a níveis 5% inferiores aos de 1990, 

principalmente pela substituição de combustíveis fósseis por fontes alternativas de energia 

(Mastrandrea &amp;amp; Stephen, 2005).  

Uma nova reunião será realizada em Copenhagen no final de 2009, a Conferência 

das Nações Unidas sobre Mudanças Climáticas (COP15). O governo dinamarquês tem uma 

proposta ambiciosa de estabelecer um acordo global incorporando todos os países do 

mundo. Serão estabelecidas as metas de redução de emissões de gases para as próximas 

décadas, reforçando as estabelecidas no protocolo de Kyoto e ainda lembrando o fato de 

que combustíveis fósseis não são apenas poluentes, mas fontes que de esgotam a cada ano 



 4

(http://en.cop15.dk/about+cop15). Estima-se que o petróleo se esgote nos próximos 50 

anos, o gás natural em 65 anos e o carvão em 200 anos (Branduardi et al., 2008). 

Nos últimos anos, aumentaram os investimentos das nações em pesquisas e no 

desenvolvimento de novas tecnologias para a obtenção de fontes alternativas e renováveis 

de energia, como por exemplo: bioetanol, biodiesel, 1-butanol, biogás. Além disso, 

microorganismos estão sendo estudados, de forma que eles utilizem a biomassa para 

sintetizar compostos que substituam produtos derivados de petróleo (Figura 1) (Rojo, 

2008). 

 

Referência: Adaptado de Rojo (2008). 

FIGURA 1: Biocombustíveis gerados por microorganismos. A queima de combustíveis fósseis 
libera CO2 na atmosfera, contribuindo para o aumento da concentração desse gás gerando o 
aquecimento global (linhas pontilhadas). Parte desse gás pode ser fixada pelas plantas ou por 
microorganismos fotossintéticos (linhas tracejadas). Alguns microorganismos utilizam o CO2 ou 
biomassa como fonte de carbono produzindo componentes que podem ser utilizados como 
combustível (linhas contínuas).  

 

O desenvolvimento de biocombustíveis derivados de biomassa requer integração de 

conhecimentos de biologia, química e engenharia. E o mais importante para a indústria é 

que esses novos combustíveis apresentem características como: (1) ser relativamente barato 

- a molécula deve ter alta razão energia/massa; (2) ser altamente combustível, mas não 

explosivo; (3) ser estável sob longos períodos de armazenamento e (4) ser líquido e 

transportável (Wackett, 2008). 



 5

Atualmente, o biocombustível mais utilizado e produzido em grande escala é o 

etanol. O uso do etanol como combustível no lugar de derivados do petróleo diminui 

significativamente a taxa de emissão de monóxido de carbono (CO), hidrocarbonetos e 

enxofre na atmosfera, sendo, portanto menos tóxico (Goldemberg, 2008). 

O Brasil é o segundo maior produtor mundial de etanol, sendo superado apenas 

pelos EUA, e juntos representam aproximadamente 90% da produção mundial 

(http://www.ethanolrfa.org/industry/statistics/).  

O etanol brasileiro é produzido pela fermentação dos açucares presentes na cana-de-

açúcar enquanto que o americano é produzido pela fermentação de açucares (amido - 

previamente hidrolisado enzimaticamente) do milho. Há claras vantagens na produção de 

etanol a partir do caldo de cana, como pode ser visto na tabela 1. 

 

TABELA 1: Comparação da produção de etanol no Brasil e nos EUA (Sanchez &amp;amp; Cardona, 2008). 

 Brasil EUA 
Matéria Prima Cana-de-açúcar Milho 

Produtividade (ton/ha) 70 - 123 6 - 10 
Custo da matéria prima 

(US$/Kg) 
0,010 0,076 

Rendimento etanol (L/ton) 70 370 
Rendimento anual etanol 

(L/ha ano) 
5345 - 9381 6600 

Balanço Energético (razão 
saída/entrada de energia) 

8,0 1,34 - 1,53 

Custos de produção*  14,48 39,47 
Subsidio governo* 0 7,93 

Venda subprodutos* 0 6,71 
Custo líquido da produção* 14,48 24,83 
* Referência: (Goldemberg, 2008). Valores (€/1000L).  

 

O rendimento de etanol (L/ton) proveniente do milho é maior do que a cana-de-

açúcar pelo fato de que há uma grande quantidade de açucares fermentáveis (glicose) que é 

liberada do material com amido original. Entretanto, a competitividade do etanol de cana 

do Brasil pode ser demonstrada pelo balanço energético que é aproximadamente 6 vezes 



 6

maior que no etanol de milho. O balanço energético é definido como a razão entre a energia 

contida em um determinado volume de etanol dividido pela energia fóssil gasta para sua 

produção (uso de fertilizantes, pesticidas, óleo diesel gasto na colheita mecanizada e o 

transporte de matéria-prima para os locais de processamento). Além disso, o custo de 

produção de etanol no Brasil é 2,7 vezes menor que nos EUA (Tabela1) (Goldemberg, 

2008; Sanchez &amp;amp; Cardona, 2008).  

O Brasil é um dos maiores produtores de cana-de-açúcar e álcool do mundo, e esse 

setor canavieiro, além de estar se transformando no negócio mais produtivo da 

agroindústria brasileira, é responsável por mais de 1 milhão de trabalhos diretos (Pessoa-Jr 

et al., 2005). O pioneirismo no setor alcooleiro se iniciou em meados da década de 70, após 

o primeiro choque do petróleo com a implantação do Proálcool, programa de incentivo a 

produção de álcool visando o atendimento das necessidades do mercado interno e externo e 

da política de combustíveis automotivos (Goldemberg et al., 2008). 

Atualmente há em operação no Brasil cerca de 330 usinas, processando 425 milhões 

de toneladas de cana-de-açúcar por ano, sendo que aproximadamente metade é utilizada 

para a produção de açúcar e metade para a produção de etanol. A área utilizada para o 

cultivo de cana ocupa menos de 10% da área cultivável do país. O Programa do etanol no 

Brasil está muito bem estabelecido e tem substituído 1,5% da gasolina utilizada no mundo. 

A estimativa é que nos próximos 15 - 20 anos seja possível substituir mais de 10% da 

gasolina mundial (Goldemberg, 2008). 

Apesar da supremacia brasileira no mercado de álcool, algumas deficiências 

precisam ser superadas, como a falta de investimentos em ciência e tecnologia e infra-

estrutura. Esses investimentos são importantes para conseguir manter a qualidade e os 

custos competitivos (Salomão &amp;amp; Onaga, 2006). Além disso, a biorefinaria (local do 

processamento de biomassa), não é local para a fabricação de apenas um ou dois produtos, 

mas uma ampla gama de produtos de maior valor agregado. E isso ainda é deficiente na 

indústria canavieira (Cortez et al., 2008). 

Recentemente, o governo americano decidiu investir na expansão da produção de 

etanol no mundo sendo o Brasil o principal foco neste acordo. Expectativas são de que a 



 7

produção nacional de etanol aumente de 17,4 bilhões de litros produzidos em 2006 para 

35,4 bilhões de litros até 2012 (Jank, 2007). 

 

2. Produção de etanol no Brasil 
A obtenção do etanol se dá principalmente pela via fermentativa (Wheals et al., 

1999), sendo que este é um processo utilizado há séculos para a produção de bebidas, tais 

como vinhos e cervejas (Stratford, 1996b). O que torna a fermentação a forma mais 

importante de obtenção de etanol é a grande quantidade de matérias-primas naturais 

existentes em todo o país, sendo que a cana de açúcar é, sem dúvida, a mais importante 

(Lima et al., 1975).  

Para uma produção industrial de etanol viável, o processo de fermentação deve ser 

extremamente robusto e pouco afetado por pequenas alterações da matéria prima, além da 

minimização dos custos que podem ser obtidos pela (Goldemberg et al., 2008): 

- obtenção do máximo rendimento de etanol; 

- minimização na síntese de outros produtos (glicerol, ácido láctico); 

- minimização do tempo de fermentação; 

- baixa contaminação bacteriana (ações preventivas, como por exemplo, tratamento ácido 

do fermento);  

- manutenção da alta viabilidade do fermento (70% - 80%); 

- minimização de produtos químicos (ácidos, antibióticos, antiespumante); 

- minimização dos gastos com manutenção (limpeza, vazamentos); 

- minimização de gastos de energia e água; 

- automatização das operações manuais (temperatura, brix, pH). 

O processo fermentativo de produção industrial de etanol brasileiro (Figura 2) 

ocorre em dornas nas quais são adicionadas a mistura de mosto (caldo de cana-de-açúcar ou 

melaço de cana diluído ou a mistura dos dois) e as leveduras. Após o término da 

fermentação, todo o conteúdo é transferido para centrífugas. O vinho, fermentado de cana 

sem as leveduras, segue para as torres de destilação, onde se recupera o etanol e o leite de 

levedura, nome dado ao caldo de leveduras que sai da centrifugação, passa por um 



 8

tratamento com ácido sulfúrico e retorna novamente à dorna, na qual será adicionada uma 

nova carga de mosto para um novo ciclo fermentativo (Wheals et al., 1999; Meleiro &amp;amp; 

Maciel, 2000). Cerca de 90% das leveduras são reaproveitadas de uma fermentação para 

outra e esse processo de reciclo permanece durante todo o período da safra que compreende 

200 a 250 dias, ocorrendo entre dois a três ciclos fermentativos por dia (Meleiro &amp;amp; Maciel, 

2000; Basso et al., 2008). Além disso, todo o resíduo gerado na usina é reaproveitado. As 

leveduras, por exemplo, são utilizadas como ração animal após o período da safra; e o 

bagaço da cana-de-açúcar é queimado para geração de energia, que é suficiente para suprir 

as necessidades de toda usina, e o excedente é encaminhado para ser vendido. 

 

 
 
FIGURA 2: Esquema do processo, tipo batelada, de produção de etanol no Brasil. Importante 
destacar também, o reciclo das leveduras que ocorre durante toda a safra de cana-de-açúcar e o 
reaproveitamento do bagaço para a produção de energia.  

 

Na produção de bebidas, como por exemplo, o vinho, os açúcares fermentados são a 

frutose e a glicose, obtida do suco de uva (mosto). Este suco é transferido para tanques de 

fermentação onde recebem as leveduras. Depois de estabelecido o término da fermentação, 

não há etapa de centrifugação. É necessário esperar que a levedura decante naturalmente e 

posteriormente ela é retirada do tanque podendo ser utilizada na produção de ração animal 



 9

ou adubo. Tempos muito longos de decantação levam ao rompimento das paredes celulares 

das leveduras que ainda estiverem em suspensão, liberando compostos secundários no 

meio, alterando o sabor e a qualidade do vinho. Separada a borra, o vinho é enviado para o 

processo de clarificação através de uma série de filtrações, sendo posteriormente 

engarrafado e envelhecido (Martinelli, 1983). 

Na produção de etanol e bebidas fermentadas (vinhos e cervejas), um fenômeno 

conhecido como floculação das leveduras desempenha um importante papel, pois acelera a 

separação das leveduras do meio fermentado. Esse é um processo de formação de 

agregados multicelulares, reversível (os agregados não são permanentes) e dependente de 

cálcio. Os agregados celulares formados podem se separar do meio de cultura por 

sedimentação, quando elas vão para o fundo da dorna, ou flotação, quando o agregado 

acumula ar levando as células à superfície (Stratford, 1996b; Stan &amp;amp; Despa, 2000).  

 

3. Processo fermentativo 
Os microorganismos mais comumente usados na fermentação alcoólica são as 

leveduras, fundamentalmente a espécie Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  

Bioquimicamente, a fermentação é a oxidação incompleta do açúcar, gerando como 

subproduto um composto orgânico oxidável. Considerando-se o processamento da cana 

pela levedura, inicialmente a sacarose, que é o seu açúcar de reserva, sofre hidrólise pela 

enzima invertase (SUC2) sendo convertida em glicose e frutose. Ambas entram na via 

glicolítica e, através de uma seqüência de reações, são convertidas a piruvato. Este 

primeiramente é descarboxilado pela enzima piruvato descarboxilase (PDC1, 5, 6), 

formando acetaldeído e liberando CO2. Posteriormente o acetaldeído é reduzido a etanol, 

sendo essa reação catalisada pela álcool desidrogenase 1 (ADH1). O esgotamento da 

glicose ativa, nas leveduras, a transcrição do gene da álcool desidrogenase 2 (ADH2). A 

enzima Adh2 oxida o etanol a acetaldeído, o qual posteriormente é convertido a acetato, 

passando então para as etapas posteriores do ciclo de Krebs (Devlin, 1997) (Figura 3).  

 



 10

 

FIGURA 3: Esquema das reações de fermentação e respiração. As setas pontilhadas 
indicam a via que é ativada quando a glicose é totalmente consumida (oxidação etanol). PDC1, 5, 6: 
piruvato descarboxilase; PDA1, PDB1, PDX1, LPD1, LAT1: enzimas que fazem parte do complexo 
da piruvato desidrogenase; ALD6: aldeído desidrogenase; ACS1: acetil CoA sintetase; ADH1: álcool 
desidrogenase 1; ADH2: álcool desidrogenase 2. 

 
O ADH2 é um gene muito bem estudado, cujo promotor é reprimido centenas de 

vezes na presença de glicose e é dereprimido na ausência de glicose (Price et al., 1990). O 

gene ADR1 foi originalmente identificado em S. cerevisiae como regulador positivo do 

gene ADH2 e apresenta sua transcrição inibida na presença de glicose (Ciriacy, 1979; Denis 

&amp;amp; Young, 1983). A ausência ou a baixa ligação desse ativador transcricional (Adr1) ao 

promotor do gene ADH2 faz com que a expressão deste seja mínima. Quando a glicose se 

esgota, o nível de Adr1 aumenta, se ligando ao promotor do gene ADH2, iniciando a 

transcrição (Lee &amp;amp; DaSilva, 2005). 

As leveduras quando são inoculadas em meio rico em açúcar, preferencialmente, 

seguem a via fermentativa produzindo etanol. Quando os açúcares fermentáveis se 

esgotam, as leveduras começam a consumir o etanol como fonte de carbono para o 

crescimento aeróbico. Essa mudança de crescimento anaeróbico para respiração aeróbica 

devido ao esgotamento da glicose, referida como diauxic shift (Figura 4), é correlacionada 

com alterações na expressão de genes envolvidos em processos celulares fundamentais 



 11

como metabolismo de carbono, síntese de proteínas e armazenamento de carboidratos 

(DeRisi et al., 1997). 

O diauxic shift é um ponto importante que deve ser considerado durante o processo 

fermentativo industrial. Após o término da fermentação (esgotamento da glicose), o ideal 

seria que o fermento (leveduras) seja separado imediatamente do meio para evitar que as 

células comecem a consumir o etanol, o que acarretaria em perdas de rendimento. 

 
Referência: (Otterstedt et al., 2004) 

FIGURA 4: Gráfico mostrando a curva de consumo de glicose (linha com círculos) e etanol 
produzido (linha com os triângulos) pelas leveduras. Em 15 horas é ponto em que ocorre o Diauxic 
Shift, ou seja, a transição fermentação/respiração. Depois desse tempo o etanol começa a ser 
consumido.  
 

4. A levedura 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae é um fungo leveduriforme, unicelular, tipicamente 

esférico ou oval, não filamentoso, pertencente ao filo Ascomycota. Possui reprodução 

assexuada, por brotamento, e reprodução sexuada (Tortora et al., 2002). Na reprodução 

sexuada, o cruzamento ocorre somente entre indivíduos de tipos sexuais diferentes (mating 

type a ou ?) (Figura 5). 

S. cerevisiae foi o primeiro organismo eucarionte a ter o seu genoma totalmente 

seqüenciado (Goffeau et al., 1996). Possui inúmeros bancos de dados onde é possível obter 

informações sobre seus genes e produtos (www.yeastgenome.org). É considerado o 

organismo modelo entre os eucariotos por apresentar mecanismos celulares altamente 

conservados. Por esse motivo há uma série de estudos sobre processos biológicos como 

envelhecimento e ciclo celular, estudos de doenças humanas como o câncer, e é usada 

como ferramenta em estudo de drogas, príons, pesquisa básica e aplicada de vírus e 

ecotoxicologia (Nevoigt, 2008). É popularmente conhecida na indústria alimentícia e de 



 12

bebidas, sendo classificada como GRAS (Generally Regarded as Safe) pela FDA (U.S. 

Food and Drug Administration).  

 

 

FIGURA 5: Esquema das formas de reprodução das leveduras. A forma assexuada (na haplofase), 
em que uma levedura dá origem a outra por brotamento (mitose). E a reprodução sexuada, na qual 
um esporo a cruza com um esporo ?, formando um diplóide. A esporulação desse diplóide origina 
uma tétrade que dá origem a 4 esporos.  
 

O grande sucesso da S. cerevisiae na indústria de biotecnologia é devido à alta 

capacidade de produzir etanol e dióxido de carbono a partir de açucares. Possui importantes 

características, como: tolerância a baixos valores de pH e alta concentração de açúcar e 

etanol, propriedades como alta competitividade perante contaminação (bacteriana ou por 

outras leveduras) na fermentação industrial e alta resistência a inibidores presentes na 

biomassa hidrolisada e capacidade de crescer anaerobicamente (Branduardi et al., 2008; 

Nevoigt, 2008). 

Apesar dos grandes avanços tecnológicos e do vasto conhecimento a respeito do 

potencial produtivo das leveduras, há ainda muitos aspectos desconhecidos, principalmente 



 13

quando se trata da genética e bioquímica das leveduras utilizadas nas usinas para 

fermentação alcoólica (Basso et al., 2008). 

Estudos mais recentes são relativos a análise genômica comparativa. As cepas mais 

estudadas são linhagens industriais fermentadoras principalmente para a produção de vinho 

(Borneman et al., 2008; Carreto et al., 2008). Muito pouco se conhece sobre as linhagens 

produtoras de etanol, especialmente quando se trata de caracterização fenotípica e 

genotípica e expressão gênica. Estas linhagens precisam ser exploradas e estudadas mais 

detalhadamente para o entendimento de características e fenômenos que podem ser 

essenciais para o uso biotecnológico. 

Foi verificado em algumas usinas brasileiras, que as “leveduras de pão” (baker’s 

yeast) que eram inoculadas para iniciar o processo fermentativo, desapareciam do processo, 

sendo substituídas por outras leveduras durante o período da safra. Isso ocorria devido às 

condições estressantes e competitivas presentes na fermentação industrial: alta 

concentração de etanol, alta temperatura, estresse osmótico devido a presença de açucares e 

sais, acidez e contaminação bacteriana que favoreciam o desenvolvimento de cepas mais 

resistentes, que no caso vinham junto com a cana-de-açúcar do campo (Basso et al., 2008). 

Por isso, leveduras isoladas do próprio processo fermentativo são hoje utilizadas nas 

usinas brasileiras. A linhagem mais conhecidas e utilizada em aproximadamente 30% das 

usinas brasileiras é a Pedra 2 (PE-2), que leva esse nome pois foi isolada da Usina da Pedra. 

Estudos demonstraram que ela permanece na dorna durante todo o período da safra. Além 

disso, a linhagem PE-2 apresenta características fundamentais para aperfeiçoar o processo 

fermentativo, como permanecer em suspensão, não apresentando características floculantes 

e não produzindo espuma (Figura 6) (Basso et al., 2008). 



 14

 

Referência: (Basso et al, 2008) 

FIGURA 6: Meio industrial (caldo de cana) fermentado por: (a) uma linhagem de levedura 
selecionada, PE-2; (b) uma linhagem que produz espuma; e (C) uma linhagem que produz espuma e 
ainda flocula. A presença de células floculadas resulta no baixo rendimento fermentativo. 
 

Modificações genéticas são bastante comuns em leveduras, principalmente nas 

linhagens de laboratório, que são de fácil manipulação e com marcas auxotróficas. 

Entretanto, para se melhorar o processo fermentativo, as alterações genéticas devem ser 

feitas em linhagens industriais, que permaneçam e dominem as dornas.  

O conhecimento dos fatores responsáveis pela alta eficiência fermentativa e 

robustez das leveduras industriais é essencial para se estabelecer uma estratégia para 

melhorar ainda mais estas linhagens. 

 

5. Processo de floculação 
A floculação é uma das características mais intrigantes e importantes 

industrialmente manifestadas pelas leveduras. O fenômeno é dependente da linhagem, 

dificultando o controle do processo (Verstrepen et al., 2003). Esse fenômeno causa grandes 

prejuízos nas usinas produtoras de etanol brasileiras, uma vez que a floculação se inicia 

repentinamente durante o processo, sem uma causa aparente conhecida. A floculação 

aumenta o tempo de fermentação, pois diminui a área de contato célula-meio, além disso, o 

processo para promover a desfloculação é difícil, sendo que muitas vezes as usinas são 

obrigadas a trocar o fermento. 



 15

Os fenótipos de adesão dependem de uma família de proteínas de superfície celular, 

também chamada de adesinas ou floculinas que são codificados pelos genes FLO na S. 

cerevisiae (Verstrepen &amp;amp; Klis, 2006). As proteínas dessa família consistem de 3 domínios 

(Figura 7). O domínio N-terminal (A) estaria relacionado com a afinidade dessa proteína à 

superfície; o domínio central (B) é uma região que apresenta um tamanho variável, é rico 

em resíduos de serina e treonina e contém muitas repetições em tandem; e o domínio 

carboxi-teminal (C) que é o local onde se liga covalentemente, a âncora glicosil 

fosfatidilinositol (GPI), responsável por prender a proteína à membrana. Esta ligação com o 

GPI ocorre durante as modificações pós-traducional (Verstrepen et al., 2004). 

 
Referência: (Verstrepen et al., 2004) 

FIGURA 7: Domínios presentes na adesina ou floculina. (A) Domínio N-terminal que está 
relacionado com a adesão. (B) Domínio central, região rica em serina/treonina que é codificada por 
sequencias de nucleotídeos repetitivos. (C) Domínio carboxi-terminal, contém uma região de 
ligação covalente ao GPI (mostrado em vermelho). 
 

As proteínas Flo conferem adesão por dois mecanismos distintos. A primeira é a 

adesão célula-superfície, que se acredita depender de interações hidrofóbicas entre certos 

domínios na adesina e a superfície de ligação. O gene FLO11 é o único da família que não 

é responsável pelo fenômeno da floculação em si, mas pelo crescimento invasivo, formação 

de pseudohifas, e aderência à superfície. (Van Mulders et al., 2009).  

O segundo mecanismo é a adesão célula-célula ou também chamado de floculação. 

Esse é um mecanismo físico, reversível, dependente de íons cálcio e foi primeiramente 

denominado Lectin-like theory of floculation (Miki et al., 1982). As proteínas de membrana 

das leveduras floculantes funcionam como lectinas e se ligam a carboidratos na parede 

celular das células vizinhas (Eddy &amp;amp; Rudin, 1958). As células floculantes possuem em sua 

membrana celular floculinas (lectinas) e carboidratos, enquanto que as células não 

floculantes possuem apenas carboidratos (Stratford, 1996a). Além do mecanismo físico de 



 16

interação entre as células de levedura, a floculação é influenciada por fatores genéticos de 

cada linhagem e por fatores externos, como por exemplo, concentração de íons cálcio, 

etanol, nutrientes, pH, temperatura (Touhami et al., 2003; Verstrepen et al., 2003). 

A floculação em S. cerevisiae é controlada geneticamente e vários genes foram 

relatados como sendo dominantes e responsáveis por este fenômeno. Entre eles estão: 

FLO1, FLO5, FLO9 e FLO10 (Johnston &amp;amp; Reader, 1983; Teunissen &amp;amp; Steensma, 1995).  

O genoma de S. cerevisiae mostrou que dos 5 genes FLO relacionados com a  

família das adesinas (FLO1, FLO5, FLO9, FLO10, FLO11) apenas 4 deles (FLO1, FLO5, 

FLO9, FLO10) estão localizados adjacentes ao telômero (Figura 8) (Verstrepen et al., 

2004). Os genes FLO subteloméricos, na linhagem de laboratório (S288c) de S. cerevisiae, 

são transcricionalmente silenciados, mas suas funções podem ser avaliadas substituindo o 

promotor nativo por um promotor induzível, como por exemplo, promotor de GAL1 

(induzido por galactose) (Guo et al., 2000).  

 

 

Referência: (Verstrepen et al., 2004) 
FIGURA 8: Localização cromossômica dos genes e pseudogenes da adesina na linhagem S288c de 
S. cerevisiae. Os números á esquerda indicam os cromossomos das leveduras, os pontos em 
vermelho são os centrômeros e ? indica o local dos pseudogenes FLO. O gene FLO11 é o único 
que não é nem centromérico, nem telomérico.  



 17

Com a clonagem do gene FLO1 (Watari et al., 1989) e do gene FLO5 (Bidard et al., 

1994) ficou evidenciado uma semelhança muito grande entre eles. O gene FLO1, localizado 

no cromossomo I, possui o produto de seu gene 96% similar ao produto do gene FLO5 

(cromossomo VIII) e 94% similar ao produto do gene FLO9 (cromossomo I). Já o produto 

do gene FLO10 (cromossomo XI) apresenta 58% de similaridade com o gene FLO1. 

Apesar dessa baixa similaridade, quando se alinhou a região N-terminal da proteína 

referente ao gene FLO10 com as proteínas dos genes FLO1, FLO5 e FLO9 obtiveram-se 

uma similaridade de 82%. Essa informação foi importante para classificá-lo como um gene 

de floculação (Figura 9) (Teunissen &amp;amp; Steensma, 1995).  

 

Referência: (Van Mulders et al., 2009) 

FIGURA 9: Alinhamento múltiplo da sequência de aminoácidos da região N-terminal das adesinas 
envolvidas no reconhecimento de açucares. Os resíduos de aminoácidos não conservados estão 
sombreados de cinza. Os aminoácidos marcados com um (X) contribuem para o reconhecimento de 
açucares (Kobayashi et al., 1998).  
  

Todos os quatro genes dominantes responsáveis pelo efeito da floculação, FLO1, 

FLO5, FLO9 e FLO10, possuem repetições intragênicas em tandem (Figura 10) contendo 

mais que 40 nucleotídeos. Experimentos realizados com alelos do gene FLO1 que possuem 

regiões repetitivas de diferentes tamanhos mostraram que quanto maior o alelo, mais forte é 

adesão entre as células, evidenciando que a intensidade de floculação possa estar 

intimamente relacionada com o tamanho (quantidade de repetições) destas regiões 

(Verstrepen et al., 2005; Rando &amp;amp; Verstrepen, 2007). 

 

 



 18

 

Referência: (Verstrepen et al., 2004) 

FIGURA 10: Motivos repetitivos de nucleotídeos nos genes FLO. A figura mostra os 5 genes FLO 
indicando apenas as sequências similares. Os quadrados mostram os motivos de sequência de DNA 
altamente conservados. Os quadros marcados com (X) representam motivos conservados em 
aminoácidos que não são conservados em sequência de DNA. Os “motif 4” e “motif 6” indicam as 
repetições intragênicas em tandem, que é maior no gene FLO1. 
 

Leveduras patogênicas como Candida albicans, possuem genes de adesinas com 

repetições intragênicas em tandem (igualmente aos genes da floculação). Esses genes 

podem sofrer eventos de recombinação em determinadas situações de estresses, formando 

novas adesinas. Dessa forma a levedura pode ter uma grande plasticidade de fenótipos se 

adaptando rapidamente a novos ambientes. Tanto os genes da adesina como os da 

floculação estão posicionados na região subtelomérica do cromossomo. Essa posição 

isolada permite que ocorram eventos de recombinação sem que outros genes sejam 

afetados. Não se sabe se esse mecanismo de indução de variabilidade ocorra em S. 

cerevisiae com os genes da floculação da mesma forma que ocorre com os genes da 

adesina. Mas a instabilidade do fenômeno da floculação tem sido um grande problema para 

a indústria (Verstrepen &amp;amp; Klis, 2006). 

O gene FLO10 possui uma característica muito interessante que o diferencia dos 

outros genes da floculação. Os agregados de células formados pela expressão desse gene 

são inibidos pela presença de glicose, sacarose e maltose, enquanto que agregados 

formados pela expressão do gene FLO1 são inibidos somente por manose (Guo et al., 

2000). Estudos realizados super expressando o gene FLO10 mostram que ele apresenta uma 

forte floculação bem semelhante ao produto do gene FLO1 (Guo et al., 2000). A regulação 

da expressão do gene FLO10, assim como do gene FLO11 são influenciadas por fatores 

genéticos e epigenéticos (Halme et al., 2004). 

Além dos genes responsáveis pela síntese da floculina, há outros genes como o gene 

FLO8, que juntamente com TUP1 e CYC8/SSN6, participam da regulação transcricional de 



 19

FLO1 (Kobayashi et al., 1996). Em um estudo mais recente, foi verificado que o gene 

MSS11, que anteriormente era conhecido participando da regulação da degradação do 

amido, da formação de pseudohifas e do crescimento invasivo haplóide, também age como 

um forte indutor da floculação (Bester et al., 2006). Outro gene, o GTS-1, foi caracterizado 

como um coativador trascricional. O produto da super expressão desse gene se liga ao 

repressor transcricional Sfl1p induzindo a expressão do gene FLO1 e conseqüentemente 

promovendo a floculação na linhagem de laboratório testada. Isso foi verificado em 

linhagens mutantes para o gene FLO8 (Shen et al., 2006). 

O controle da expressão dos genes de floculação, principalmente para os processos 

industriais de fermentação, pode trazer grandes benefícios (Domingues et al., 2000). Um 

modelo muito interessante para a obtenção desta característica seria através da inserção de 

um promotor, ou parte dele, que atuasse no sentido de permitir a transcrição da proteína 

responsável pela floculação apenas no final da fermentação. 

Os primeiros estudos que tentaram alterar e controlar a floculação em leveduras 

através de modificação genética foram descritos por Barney et al. (Barney et al., 1980), que 

introduziu um fragmento do DNA cromossomal derivado de uma linhagem floculante, que 

incluía os genes ADE1 e FLO1, em uma linhagem não floculante. Os mutantes se 

mostraram floculantes constitutivos, sendo assim indesejáveis aos propósitos da indústria. 

O mesmo resultado foi obtido por Ishida-Fujii (Ishida-Fujii et al., 1998) usando um 

plasmídeo em que o gene FLO1 estava sob o controle do promotor constitutivo da álcool 

desidrogenase 1 (ADH1). Em outro trabalho, o gene FLO1 foi colocado sob o controle do 

promotor HSP30. Este é um promotor heat shock que é ativado em condições de estresse, o 

que acontece no final da fermentação devido a alta concentração de etanol e limitação de 

nutrientes (Verstrepen et al., 2001).  

A utilização do promotor do gene ADH2 regulando o gene da floculação em 

linhagens leveduras de laboratório se mostrou muito promissor, floculando apenas quando a 

glicose havia se esgotado do meio, ao final da fermentação, tornando-se floculantes 

condicionais. A mesma construção foi utilizada para transformar uma linhagem industrial 

(Cunha et al., 2006). O processo foi patenteado (INPI n0 0001122) e despertou grande 

atenção da comunidade especializada, de empresas de fermentação e biotecnologia e da 

imprensa de uma forma geral. 



 20

Em um estudo mais recente, promotores nativos dos genes FLO1, FLO5 e FLO11 

foram substituídos por promotores do gene ADH2 e HSP30 (Govender et al., 2008). Com 

estes experimentos, leveduras não floculantes tiveram sua sedimentação controlada 

expressando o gene apenas no final da fermentação. Porém estes experimentos foram feitos 

apenas em laboratório, onde as condições são controladas, e com cepas de levedura 

“domesticadas”. Nas dornas de fermentação, as condições são altamente estressantes (por 

exemplo, presença de contaminantes, variações bruscas de temperatura e pH, altas 

concentrações de etanol, entre outras), e o entendimento sobre a resposta das células a este 

tipo de ambiente ainda é limitado (Gibson et al., 2007). Os genes de resposta a estresse 

podem também ser ativados em outras fases da fermentação e não somente no final. Isto 

pode ser visto em um trabalho de expressão gênica realizado durante o processo 

fermentativo de produção de vinho. Diversos genes foram analisados, entre eles o gene de 

heat shock HSP30, que se encontra ativado durante todo o processo fermentativo (Varela et 

al., 2005).  

A construção de uma linhagem de levedura que seja floculante para a produção de 

etanol combustível também foi realizada por um grupo de pesquisa chinês (Wang et al., 

2007). Apesar de a linhagem transformante apresentar as características como, 

produtividade de etanol, similares à linhagem selvagem, e ainda apresentar uma floculação 

forte e estável, o início da floculação era anterior ao esgotamento da glicose no meio de 

cultura. 

Além da possibilidade de regulação dos genes da floculação, outros fatores podem 

ser interessantes para melhorar uma linhagem. Alper (Alper et al., 2006) encontrou em 

bibliotecas de linhagens de laboratório de S. cerevisiae expostas a agentes mutagênicos, 

uma levedura que além de ser tolerante, produzia uma quantidade maior de etanol. Alper 

verificou que uma alteração de três bases (promovendo a substituição de três aminoácidos), 

sem a alteração da funcionalidade do gene SPT15, que codifica a proteína que se liga ao 

TATA-box, eram responsáveis por essas características. A mutagênese foi responsável pela 

substituição de fenilalanina por serina (Phe177Ser), tirosina por histidina (Tyr195His) e lisina 

por arginina (Lys218Arg). Em outro experimento, foi demonstrado que a interrupção da via 

do glicerol, pela delação dos genes GPD1 e GPD2, também promoveu um maior 

rendimento na produção de etanol. Foi observado um aumento, relativo à quantidade de 



 21

substrato consumido, de 6,83% e 7,41%, respectivamente, comparado com o selvagem 

(Guo et al., 2009). 

  

6. Atividade Mitocondrial 
A atividade mitocondrial é essencial em diversas funções nas células de leveduras. 

A perda do DNA mitocondrial (petite citoplasmático) provoca sérias alterações na 

superfície celular, como a redução na absorção de açúcares, alteração na floculação 

(Calleja, 1973; Iung et al., 1999) ou aglutinação e alteração nas proteínas da membrana 

plasmática reduzindo a tolerância ao etanol (Wilkie &amp;amp; Evans, 1982). 

Células tratadas com drogas que inibem a função mitocondrial (Slonimski et al., 

1968; Egilsson et al., 1979) ou com deleções dos genes OLI1 (codifica subunidade 9 da 

ATP sintase) ou OXI2 (COX3 – subunidade 3 da citocromo oxidase) (Hinrichs et al., 1988) 

têm sua capacidade de floculação, crescimento e tolerância ao etanol reduzida ou anulada.  

A comparação de células de S. cerevisiae deficiente-respiratório e competente-

respiratório mostrou que a disfunção mitocondrial promove a ativação de um conjunto de 

genes associados com atividade peroxissomal e vias de restauração metabólica atenuando 

perdas do ciclo do ácido tricarboxílico (Epstein et al., 2001). 

A deleção de um gene específico, PET191, do DNA genômico gera um mutante de 

S. cerevisiae 100% deficiente respiratório denominado petite nuclear. Tal gene codifica a 

proteína responsável pela montagem do citocromo C na cadeia respiratória e foi verificado 

que seu mutante tem a capacidade de fermentação aumentada, produzindo 43% mais etanol 

que a linhagem parental, mostrando-se ainda tolerantes à presença de etanol e não 

apresentando comprometimento na taxa de crescimento (Hutter &amp;amp; Oliver, 1998). É 

importante salientar que neste experimento foi feito com linhagem de laboratório (FY23) e 

utilizando meio sintético. A deleção desse mesmo gene (PET191) em linhagens industriais, 

produtoras de vinho, promoveu um aumento de 9% na produção de etanol quando 

comparada com a linhagem selvagem (Panoutsopoulou et al., 2001).  

Petites citoplasmáticos ou mitocondriais, produzidos com o tratamento das células 

com brometo de etídio (agente mutagênico), em ensaios utilizando linhagens de vinícolas, 

produziram mais etanol quando comparada com a linhagem parental (Ooi &amp;amp; Lankford, 

2009). Entretanto, petites citoplasmáticos sofrem diminuição na sua taxa de crescimento e 



 22

tendem a ser mais vulneráveis às condições adversas das dornas como a baixa tolerância ao 

etanol (Wilkie &amp;amp; Evans, 1982), tornando a linhagem imprópria para a utilização na 

indústria.  

  



 23

JUSTIFICATIVA 
 

Apesar de todos estes estudos, existem ainda uma ampla área a serem explorados 

com relação às linhagens industriais Com o maior conhecimento a respeito das 

características destas leveduras, novos estudos poderão ser feitos e que permitirão o 

melhoramento do processo aumentando a capacidade industrial de produção de etanol. 

Nesse trabalho, iniciamos o processo de manipulação de linhagens industriais com o 

objetivo de transferir essa tecnologia para escala industrial. Analisamos a possibilidade de 

regular a expressão do gene da floculação de leveduras, tornando-as condicionais aos níveis 

de glicose do meio e avaliamos a produção de leveduras industriais deletadas para o gene 

PET191 objetivando aumentar a produção de etanol. Os resultados deste trabalho 

apresentam perspectivas biotecnológicas e que poderão contribuir nesta área estratégica 

para o Brasil.  

 



 24

OBJETIVOS  
 

 Os objetivos desse trabalho visam o estudo e modificações genéticas da levedura 

Saccharomyces cerevisiae para: 

 

 - Melhoramento do processo fermentativo 

# Obtenção de floculantes condicionais – Avaliar linhagens transformadas 

com genes da floculação regulados por promotores sensíveis a níveis de glicose, 

possibilitando eliminar a etapa de centrifugação do processo. 

 

 - Melhoramento do desempenho celular 

 #  Caracterização molecular de uma linhagem industrial. 

 # Obtenção de petites (deficientes respiratório) buscando aumentar o 

rendimento na produção de etanol. 

 

 

 



 25

CAPITULO 1 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
  
 
 

 

CONTROL BY SUGAR OF SACCHAROMYCES CEREVISIAE FLOCCULATION 

FOR INDUSTRIAL ETHANOL PRODUCTION 

Anderson F. Cunha, Silvia K. Missawa, Luiz H. Gomes, Sérgio F. Reis, Gonçalo A. G. Pereira 

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006): 280–287 

 

 

 

 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 26

 A idéia inicial do trabalho que originou esse artigo foi, através de modificações 

genéticas na levedura Saccharomyces cerevisiae, melhorar ou simplificar o processo 

fermentativo nas usinas brasileiras produtoras de etanol e/ou cachaça. 

Foi verificado em artigos científicos a existência de genes da floculação, sendo que 

a ativação dessas proteínas promovem a separação das células do meio. A possibilidade se 

controlar a expressão desse gene poderia revolucionar o setor com a eliminação da etapa de 

centrifugação do processo fermentativo. O momento desejado para a ativação do gene seria 

quanto a fermentação acabasse, ou seja, com o esgotamento da glicose do meio.  

Sendo assim, o trabalho foi iniciado utilizado como regulador para o gene da 

floculação o promotor do gene MOX (codifica a metanol oxidase) de Hansenula 

polymorpha. O estudo desse promotor foi tema do doutorado do Prof. Dr. Gonçalo 

(orientador desse trabalho), demonstrando que ele é devidamente expresso em S. cerevisiae, 

uma levedura que não metaboliza metanol. Além disso, este estudo demonstrou que a 

expressão do gene MOX é mediada por ADR1.  

 A utilização do promotor do gene MOX se mostrou promissor, mas apresentou 

alguns problemas, entre eles, o fato de se introduzir uma sequência exógena na levedura S. 

cerevisiae, gerando um transgênico. Sendo assim, procuramos na própria S. cerevisiae, um 

promotor que fosse regulado pelo gene ADR1. O promotor do gene ADH2 se enquadrou 

perfeitamente nesse requisito. 

Os principais resultados então presente neste artigo que foi publicado na FEMS 

Yeast Research no início do meu doutorado. Participei de alguns experimentos para a 

conclusão do artigo.  
Além disso, o processo tecnológico foi submetido à patente (INPI nº 0001122). Esse 

trabalho também recebeu a menção honrosa no XXVI Prêmio Governador do Estado de 

São Paulo e foi tema de extenso artigo na revista Scientific American Brasil. 

 Segue abaixo o manuscrito. 

 



Control bysugarofSaccharomyces cerevisiae£occulationfor
industrial ethanol production
Anderson F. Cunha1, Silvia K. Missawa1, Luiz H. Gomes2, Se?rgio F. Reis3 &amp;amp; Gonc?alo A. G. Pereira1

1Laborato?rio de Geno?mica e Expressa?o, Departamento de Gene?tica e Evoluc?a?o Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Sa?o Paulo,

Brazil; 2Laborato?rio de Gene?tica de Leveduras, Universidade de Sa?o Paulo, Sa?o Paulo, Brazil; and 3Departamento de Parasitologia, Instituto de Biologia,

Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Sa?o Paulo, Brazil

Correspondence: Gonc?alo Amarante

Guimara?es Pereira, Laborato?rio de Geno?mica

e Expressa?o, Departamento de Gene?tica e

Evoluc?a?o, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade

Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP),

Campinas, Sa?o Paulo, Brazil. Tel.: 155 19

3788 6237; fax: 155 19 3788 6235; e-mail:

goncalo@unicamp.br

Received 20 April 2005; revised 4 August 2005;

accepted 25 October 2005.

First published online 10 January 2006.

doi:10.1111/j.1567-1364.2006.00038.x

Editor: Monique Bolotin-Fukuhara

Keywords

FLO5; flocculation; Saccharomyces cerevisiae;

ethanol production; fermentation;

biotechnology.

Abstract

The goal of this study was to develop conditional flocculant yeasts for use in the

alcohol fermentation industry. Promoters were constructed to completely repress

gene transcription in the presence of sugar and to support strong expression after

the exhaustion of this compound. A fusion of regulatory regions of the ADH2

promoter with the FLO5 core promoter was constructed to regulate the FLO5 gene.

This construct was inserted into multicopy plasmids and transformed into

laboratory strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, whereby the transformed cells were

selected by sedimentation from the bulk medium after sugar exhaustion, without

decreasing ethanol production. The ADH2-FLO5 region was converted into an

integrative cassette to disrupt the CAN1 gene in industrial yeast strains. Trans-

formed cells became resistant to canavanine and demonstrated conditional

flocculation. Although ethanol production was significantly decreased in the

industrial transformants, this development reveals a promising technology for the

substitution of centrifugation in industrial ethanol production.

Introduction

Brazil is the largest sugarcane producer in the world,

followed by India and Australia. In 2003, 25 million tons

of sugar were produced, together with 15 billion litres

of ethanol (www.portalunica.com.br/referencia/estatisticas.

jsp), which was mostly utilized for fuel and industrial

applications. The ethanol industry in Brazil typically uses

the batch process (Wheals et al., 1999); yeast is separated

from the medium by centrifugation, which is the most

expensive and complex step in ethanol production (Watari

et al., 1990). Centrifuge operation starts when fermentation

stops, and this point is monitored by the evaluation of the

sugar concentration (Brix) in the medium. For the produc-

tion of beverages, such as beer, wine and sugar cane ‘spirits’

(Brazilian ‘cachac?a’), cell separation is normally obtained by

natural cell sedimentation (Schwan et al., 2001).

Yeast sedimentation can be accelerated by a process called

flocculation, a reversible asexual process in which cells

adhere to each other, resulting in the development of

aggregates (Stratford, 1989; Bony et al., 1997). In Sacchar-

omyces cerevisiae, the phenomenon involves a calcium-

dependent protein–sugar interaction between specific lec-

tin-like surface proteins, called flocculins, and the cell wall

mannan of adjacent cells (Stratford, 1989; Teunissen et al.,

1993). The best-known flocculin gene is FLO1, a dominant

gene situated on the right arm of chromosome I (Teunissen

et al., 1993), and the locus is also occupied by the alleles

FLO2 and FLO4 (Stewart &amp;amp; Russell, 1977; Sieiro et al., 1997).

Other important FLO genes are FLO5, which is a FLO1

paralogue located on chromosome VIII (Teunissen &amp;amp;

Steensma, 1995), FLO9 and FLO10 (Teunissen &amp;amp; Steensma,

1995; Guo et al., 2000). Interestingly, in the yeast Kluyver-

omyces marxianus, flocculation has been associated with the

overexpression of an isoform of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate

dehydrogenase (Almeida et al., 2003).

Some processes have tried to replace centrifugation by the

natural ability of certain yeast strains to flocculate (Wieczor-

ek &amp;amp; Michalski, 1994; Abate et al., 1996; Paiva et al., 1996;

Kondo et al., 2002), or by the introduction of flocculation

genes into nonflocculant strains (Barney et al., 1980; Watari

et al., 1994; Ishida-Fujii et al., 1998). In the study by Watari

et al. (1994), the resulting yeasts flocculated constitutively,

reducing the performance of the process, although the

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

ecamargo
Typewriter
27



ethanol concentration at the end of the fermentation was

similar to that realized with nonflocculant cells. These

authors suggested that the process could be improved by

the use of more appropriate promoters. Ishida-Fujii et al.

(1998) observed that the fermentation ability of the trans-

formed strain was almost the same as that of the parent

strain, except for the fermentation rate. However, the

experiment was performed under constant agitation, which

may mask the disadvantage of flocculation during natural

fermentation.

Constitutive flocculation seems to produce sluggish fer-

mentation (Verstrepen et al., 2003), the cause of which is still

unknown. Nevertheless, constitutive flocculation has been

successfully employed to increase the cell density of yeast in

the fermentation of cheese whey permeate, a by-product of

dairy industries, which presents rather high pollutant char-

acteristics and is produced in large amounts (Domingues

et al., 2001). Similarly, Remize et al. (1998) employed floccu-

lant yeasts, obtained by transformation of nonflocculant

strains with the FLO1 gene under the control of the ADH1

promoter, for the enrichment of fructose from Jerusalem

artichoke tuber extracts, hydrolysed by H2SO4. In this case,

yeast sedimentation, controlled by air input, facilitated an

incomplete fermentation process, generating a fructose-rich

extract; ethanol and yeast biomass were valuable by-products.

At an industrial scale, systems using flocculating yeast

cells have been employed only in the later phase of primary

beer fermentation to separate biomass from the fermented

broth (Domingues et al., 2001). In this case, the process

employs natural yeast strains presenting the NewFlo pheno-

type, in which the flocculins are inhibited by sugars, allow-

ing sedimentation at the end of fermentation (Stratford &amp;amp;

Assinder, 1991).

For biotechnology, the possibility of inducing controlled

flocculation in a naturally nonflocculant strain provides

great potential for improving brewing, wine-making, baking

and ethanol-producing yeast (Dequin, 2001). A recent report

placed the FLO1 gene under the transcriptional control of the

late-fermentation HSP30 promoter (Verstrepen et al., 2001).

The transformed yeast cells showed strong flocculation at the

end of fermentation, indicating that flocculation could be

controlled by genetic modification.

Saccharomyces cerevisiae preferentially utilizes glucose via

fermentation to produce ethanol. When glucose is available,

regulatory systems repress the expression of the genes

involved in respiration and in the utilization of other carbon

sources, in a phenomenon called carbon catabolite repres-

sion (Gancedo, 1998). After glucose exhaustion, a number

of genes are activated, completely changing the cell tran-

scriptome (DeRisi et al., 1997; Ferea et al., 1999). Interest-

ingly, the molecular mechanisms involved in glucose

repression are widely conserved. For example, the regulation

of the gene encoding the peroxisomal methanol oxidase

(MOX) from Hansenula polymorpha has been demonstrated

to be conserved in S. cerevisiae, a species that does not

metabolize methanol (Pereira &amp;amp; Hollenberg, 1996).

In this study, a nonflocculant laboratory strain of S.

cerevisiae was transformed with a FLO5 gene under the

control of glucose-repressible promoters, resulting in strains

that aggregated only when the sugar was completely ex-

hausted. The same process was successfully used to trans-

form industrial yeasts. The results show the potential of this

promising new technology to replace centrifugation in

industrial ethanol production.

Materials and methods

Strains,media and glucose measurement

The Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains used in this study were

W303-1a (MATa ade2-1 trp1-1 can1-100 leu2-3, 112 his3-11

ura3) and Fleischmann (commercial yeast used in bakeries).

Cells were grown at 30 1C on YEP medium (1% yeast
extract, 2% Bacto-peptone), with 2% glucose (YPD), or SD

medium containing 0.67% Yeast Nitrogen Base without

amino acids and 2% glucose supplemented with 20 mg L?1

histidine, 30 mg L?1 leucine, 20 mg L?1 tryptophan (for
laboratory yeasts transformed with pYADE4) or 20 mg L?1

uracil (for laboratory yeasts transformed with YEp plas-

mids), and 60 mg L?1 L-canavanine (Sigma, St Louis, MO)
(for industrial yeasts). Agar at 2% was used for solid media

(Ausubel et al., 1998). The concentration of glucose was

enzymatically determined using the glucose oxidase/perox-

idase-4-aminophenazone-phenol system (Trinder, 1969).

Plasmids and DNA manipulation

Plasmids YEp352-FLO5, donated by Bidard [Laboratoire de

Microbiologie et Technologie des Fermentations, Institut

des Produits de la Vigne (IPV), INRA, Montpellier, France]

(Bidard et al., 1994), pYADE4 (Brunelli &amp;amp; Pall, 1993) and

pUC18MOX-BB (Pereira &amp;amp; Hollenberg, 1996) were used for

the construction of recombinant plasmids. Plasmid and

genomic DNA preparation, gel electrophoresis and purifica-

tion, as well as yeast and bacterial transformation, were all

performed using standard methods, as described elsewhere

(Ausubel et al., 1998).

RNA isolationandanalysis

Total yeast RNA was extracted by the hot acid phenol

method, and Northern blotting was performed as described

previously (Ausubel et al., 1998). For probe preparation, a

1900 bp HincII fragment containing the region from 1633

to 12547 of the FLO5 coding sequence was isolated from the

YEp352-FLO5 plasmid (Bidard et al., 1994) and radioac-

tively labelled by random primers using a (Bidard et al.,

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287 c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

281Control by sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation

ecamargo
Typewriter
28



1994) P-dATP (Ausubel et al., 1998). Probed membranes

were exposed to Kodak film (X-OMAT). Ribosomal RNA

stained with ethidium bromide, which showed a fairly

constant abundance under different growth conditions and

amongst the constructed strains, was used to calibrate the

amount of total RNA loaded onto the gels per sample.

Construction oftheCAN&lt;ADH2/FLO5 cassette

To construct the CANADH2/FLO5 cassette to transform

industrial yeast, a PCR was performed using the primers

CANFLO5R (50CATAGGTGATGAAGATGAAGGAGAAG-
TACAGAACGTTAAATAATTGCCAGCAATAAGG30) and
CANADH2F (50AACTTTGTCACCACCAGTAGATGTCT-
CCATGTAAGAAAGGGGCAAAACGTAGGGGC30). The re-
action was performed in a final volume of 50 mL using the
following amplification mixture: 40 ng mL?1 of pYADE4-
FLO5 plasmid as DNA template, 5 mL of 10 ? reaction
buffer (50 mM of KCl; 10 mM of Tris-HCl, pH 9; 0.1%

Triton X-100), 2 mL of 50 mM MgSO4, 12 mL of 1.25 mM of
each dNTP (dATP, dCTP, dGTP and dTTP), 15 pmol each of

the two amplification primers and 1 mL of Platinum Taq
DNA Polymerase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA; 5 U mL?1). The
cycling parameters were as follows: 94 1C for 2 min, followed
by 35 cycles at 94 1C for 15 s and 68 1C for 5 min.

Ethanol quantification

Ethanol production was evaluated for five fermentations

and three repetitions per assay with cells growing in

YEP18% sucrose. The alcohol concentration was measured

after distillation by densitometry.

Results

Induction offlocculation based on plasmids

To place the expression of the gene FLO5 under glucose

repression, a regulatory region of the MOX promoter,

named MOX-B (Pereira &amp;amp; Hollenberg, 1996), was inserted

in duplicate, upstream of the putative FLO5 promoter

present in YEp352-FLO5 (Bidard et al., 1994), creating

YEp-BB-FLO5 (Fig. 1). The laboratory strain W303-1a was

transformed with YEp-BB-FLO5, YEp352 (negative control)

and YEp352-FLO5 (positive control). The transformants

were inoculated into 20 mL test tubes containing 5 mL of

YPD with 2% glucose and incubated with vigorous agitation

for 14 h. These cultures were used to inoculate 500 mL flasks

containing 50 mL of the same medium (OD600 = 0.1). After

12 h, no flocculation could be observed in the negative

control or in the transformant bearing the YEp352-MOX-

BB-FLO5 plasmid. Conversely, the transformants carrying

YEp352-FLO5 flocculated continuously. After 20 h, the cells

carrying the YEp352-MOX-BB-FLO5 plasmid clearly started

to flocculate. The flasks were then taken from the shaker and

the cells precipitated instantly, in contrast with the cells of

the negative control (Fig. 2).

To investigate the pattern of plasmid-based FLO5 expres-

sion, total RNA of these cultures was taken after 12, 14, 16,

18, 20 and 22 h, and Northern blotting experiments were

Sacl Sacl Smal

Smal

TATA box

TATA box

TATA box

YEp352-FLO5

YEp352-MOXBB-FLO5

pUC18-MOX-BB

LIGATION

MOX-BB

MOX-BB

MOX-BB

ampR FLO5 ORF

FLO5 ORF

FLO5 promoter

FLO5 promoter

URA

URA

FLO5 ORFFLO5 promoterURA

HincIl

Sacl SaclHincIl

Fig. 1. Construction of YEp-BB-FLO5. The pUC18MOX-BB plasmid was digested by SacI and HincII and the resulting fragment (MOX-BB) was cloned in

the YEp352-FLO5 plasmid, previously digested with SmaI and SacI. This construct was used for yeast transformation to place the FLO5 putative

promoter and gene under the transcriptional control of the MOX promoter regulatory region (MOX-BB).

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

282 A.F. Cunha et al.

ecamargo
Typewriter
29



performed. The results showed a clear correlation between

flocculation and FLO5 expression (Fig. 3). In the strain

transformed with the YEp-352-BB-FLO5 construct, the

expression of FLO5 was observed only after 20 h (Fig. 3),

2 h after the exhaustion of glucose in the medium.

Control ofFLO5expression by theADH2promoter

MOX-B is not a Saccharomyces cerevisiae native sequence

and its future use in industrial processes could raise regula-

tory concerns. To overcome this problem, we tried the same

strategy by replacing MOX-BB with the ADH2 promoter, an

S. cerevisiae native sequence that, similar to MOX-B, is

regulated by Adr1p (Pereira &amp;amp; Hollenberg, 1996).

To test the expression pattern of this promoter, the green

fluorescent protein (GFP) reporter gene was placed under its

control (plasmid pYADE4). The results showed that,

although GFP expression was higher after glucose exhaus-

tion, the promoter was not silent at higher glucose concen-

tration, presenting a significant basal expression (result not

shown). Thus, instead of using the complete ADH2 promo-

ter, the regulatory sequences of this region encompassing the

poly-T region, UAS1 and UAS2 (Yu et al., 1989), were fused

to the FLO5 core promoter (Fig. 4).

Yeasttransformationand inspection ofFLO5
expression during fermentation

Strain W303-1a was transformed with the plasmid pYADE4-

FLO5. After 18 h, the cells carrying the plasmid clearly

started to flocculate (data not shown). The results of a

Northern blot analysis showed a direct correlation between

the exhaustion of glucose and the initiation of FLO5

expression (Fig. 5a).

The next step was to evaluate whether ethanol production

would be affected by flocculation. Figure 5b shows that the

ethanol production after the end of fermentation (22 h) was

practically the same in both transformed and untrans-

formed strains.

Modification of industrialyeast

In Brazil, each ethanol industry utilizes a specific strain,

adapted to the local conditions. Therefore, in order to

become a widely accepted technology, the constructs de-

scribed above should be adapted to transform, in an

integrative manner, industrial strains that are normally

diploid and have no nutritional markers. To do this, we

used the strategy of integrating the expression cassette in the

middle of the CAN1 gene, which encodes an arginine

permease (Wach et al., 1994; Camargo, 2000). Positive

integration events led to the inactivation of CAN1 and,

thereby, the cells became resistant to canavanine, an anti-

biotic analogous to arginine. A diagram of this construct is

summarized in Fig. 6a. Basically, the cassette ADH2-FLO5

from plasmid pYADE4-FLO5 was amplified using primers

that contained additional sequences of the CAN1 gene. The

PCR products were then utilized to transform the commer-

cial Fleischmann strain. Transformants were selected by

their ability to grow in the presence of canavanine. The

CAN1 deletion and the integration of the cassette were

confirmed by PCR (Fig. 6b).

Transformed cells were tested for flocculation and alcohol

production. The transformed strain was grown in YPD with

YEp-352 
MOX-

BB-FLO5NC FLO5

YEp-352 
MOX-

BB-FLO5NC

(a) (b)

FLO5

Fig. 2. FLO5 expression under the control of the MOX-BB region. The

laboratory strain W303-1a was transformed with YEp352 (negative con-

trol, NC), YEp352-FLO5 (positive control, PC) and YEp352-BB-FLO5. The

figure shows the flocculation patterns of the yeast strains transformed with

YEp352-BB-FLO5, which present a nonflocculant growth in a medium still

containing glucose (a) and rapidly aggregate after glucose depletion (b).

Time (h)

YEp352

YEp352
FLO5

YEp352
BB - FLO5

Glucose
Conentration (%) 1 0.6 0.3 0 0 0

12

* * * * * *

* *

14 16 18 20 22
FLO 5

rRNA

FLO 5

rRNA

FLO 5

rRNA

Fig. 3. FLO5 expression during fermentation. Northern blot analysis of

RNA isolated from yeast transformed with YEp352 (negative control),

YEp352-FLO5 (positive control) and YEp352-BB-FLO5 during the times

(h) indicated in the figure. The glucose concentration was evaluated

during fermentation. Asterisk indicates yeast flocculation.

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287 c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

283Control by sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation

ecamargo
Typewriter
30



2% glucose and fermented in the same medium, but with

20% glucose, until this sugar was exhausted, approximately

15 h. The results showed a strong flocculation in the

transformed strain after this time in comparison with the

nontransformed strain (Fig. 7a). However, the ethanol

production by the transformed strain was reduced by

approximately 38% (Fig. 7b).

Discussion

The goal of this study was to develop a genetic system to

produce yeast cells capable of sensing the glucose concentra-

tion in the medium and flocculating after glucose exhaus-

tion. The resulting industrial processes using these strains

could then eliminate centrifugation in the case of ethanol

production, or shorten the period of cell sedimentation for

spirits or wine production. In the latter case, the decrease in

the sedimentation time could reduce the breakage of cells,

which is responsible for off-flavours that lower the quality of

the products.

We started by transforming the laboratory strain, W303-

1a, with the FLO5 gene containing 156 bp upstream of the

ATG, thus achieving constitutive expression of the gene,

which led to constitutive flocculation. To control the expres-

sion of this gene, a regulatory region of the MOX gene,

controlled by the transcriptional activator Adr1p (Pereira &amp;amp;

Hollenberg, 1996), was inserted as a doublet upstream of the

FLO5 promoter. This construct facilitated the control of

flocculation, rendering the FLO5 promoter and flocculation

Smal Clal Clal

ClalBlunt

(Sphl )

Smal Clal

TATA box

TATA box

TATA box

YEp352-FLO5

YEp352-FLO5

LIGATION

pYADE4

pYADE4

pYADE4

FLO5 ORFFLO5 promoter

FLO5 ORF

FLO5
promoter

ADH2
promoter

ADH2 promoter

T4 DNA
polymerase
treatment

FLO5 ORFTRP

TRP

TATA
box

ADH2
promoter

TRPFLO5 promoter

URA

Fig. 4. Construction of pYADE4-FLO5. The YEp352-FLO5 plasmid was digested with SmaI and ClaI to excise the FLO5 ORF together with its putative

promoter (sequence from ? 1 to ? 156). This sequence was then cloned into pYADE4 at the ClaI and SphI sites, which were later converted into a blunt-
end site by T4 DNA polymerase treatment. This plasmid was used to transform the laboratory strain W303-1a.

Time (h)(a)

(b)

pYADE4
FLO5

FLO5

rRNA

Glucose
Concentration (%)

12 14 16 18 20 22

1

5.00

4.00

3.00

2.00

1.00

0.00
Wild Transformed

W3031a

E
th

a
n
o
l c

o
n
ce

n
tr

a
tio

n
 (

%
)

0.7 0.2 0 0 0

* * *

Fig. 5. FLO5 expression under the control of the ADH2 promoter during

fermentation, and evaluation of ethanol production. (a) Northern blot

analysis of RNA isolated from yeast transformed with pYADE4-FLO5

during the times (h) indicated in the figure. The glucose concentration

was evaluated during fermentation. Asterisk indicates yeast flocculation.

(b) No differences in ethanol production were detected between the

transformed and wild-type yeasts.

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

284 A.F. Cunha et al.

ecamargo
Typewriter
31



subject to glucose repression. This prototype was patented

in 2000 by the National Institute of Intellectual Property-

Brazil under the patent number 0001122.

However, this regulatory region comes from another

yeast species, Hansenula polymorpha, and potential indus-

trial Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains bearing this region

would be considered genetically modified organisms requir-

ing more strict regulatory rules. Moreover, flocculation was

observed to occur only 2 h after glucose exhaustion.

In view of this, it was decided to test native promoters to

improve the process and overcome the regulatory concerns.

Initially, the ADH2 promoter, which is also controlled by

Adr1p (Yu et al., 1989), was tested. However, initial trials

using the GFP reporter gene showed that the transcription

in the presence of glucose was not completely abolished

(data not shown). To avoid this problem, we used the native

FLO5 core promoter fused to only the regulatory regions of

ADH2. With this modification, we effectively eliminated

transcription in the presence of glucose and co-ordinated

FLO5 expression precisely with the depletion of glucose.

Therefore, this seems to be the ideal promoter to satisfy our

goals.

Other authors have reported the conversion of nonfloc-

culant yeast strains into flocculant strains (Barney et al.,

1980; Watari et al., 1990, 1994; Ishida-Fujii et al., 1998). In

particular, Verstrepen et al. (2001) have successfully pro-

duced conditional flocculant laboratory strains using the

late-fermentation HSP30 promoter to control FLO1 expres-

sion. However, the HSP30 promoter can be activated by a

series of other stress factors in addition to ethanol concen-

tration, such as temperature or pH (Seymour &amp;amp; Piper, 1999;

Varela et al., 2005). Thus, in the case of the ethanol industry,

in which the cells are under tremendous stresses of tempera-

ture, pH and competition with bacteria and other yeasts,

stress-sensitive promoters can present transcription escapes

before the end of fermentation. In this sense, the exhaustion

of sugar seems to be a much more appropriate environ-

mental signal.

Fleischmann(a) (b)

Wild Transformed

Wild

E
th

a
n
o
l c

o
n
ce

n
tr

a
tio

n
 (

%
)

0

2

4

6

8

10

12

Transformed

Fig. 7. Flocculation and ethanol production of the transformed Fleisch-

mann strain. (a) Difference in flocculation between cultures of wild-

type Fleischmann and transformed Fleischmann after 15 h of fermenta-

tion in medium containing 1% yeast extract, 2% Bacto-peptone and

20% glucose. (b) Evaluation of ethanol production by the transformed

strain shows a decrease of approximately 38% when compared with

the wild-type. The fermentation was performed in medium containing

20% glucose. The cells for this assay were grown in 2% glucose.

pYADE4-FLO5
ADH2

Promoter

ADH2
Promoter

TATA

TATA CAN1"

M(a) (b) 1 2

CAN1'

CAN1
(Genomic Locus)

+ 205 + 1467

FLO5

CAN-FLO5 primer

CAN-ADH2 primer

Fig. 6. Construction of CAN::ADH2/FLO5 cassette and confirmation of cassette integration in the CAN1 locus. (a) The ADH2-FLO5 cassette from

plasmid pYADE4-FLO5 was amplified using primers with additional sequences of the CAN1 gene. The amplified cassette was used for industrial yeast

transformation (Fleischmann) and replaced the wild-type CAN1 by a construct in which the putative FLO5 promoter and gene were under the

transcriptional control of the ADH2 promoter region. (b) The CAN1 deletion and the integration of the cassette were confirmed by PCR. The

amplification of the construct ADH2-FLO5 (5246 bp) was observed only in the transformed yeast (column 2).

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287 c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

285Control by sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation

ecamargo
Typewriter
32



One important point to be considered is that large-scale

industrial ethanol fermentation is performed under nonster-

ile conditions. Therefore, there is no guarantee that the yeast

strain inoculated at the beginning of a continuous fermenta-

tion cycle will remain until the end of the process, which

normally takes several months. To address this point, we

followed the fate of an inoculated strain in a standard alcohol

industrial plant. Using microsatellite PCR, we detected that

the cells of the inoculated strains were completely replaced by

a wild-type strain 30 days after inoculation (result not

shown). Similar results have been observed by other authors

(Sabate et al., 1998; Wheals et al., 1999; Howell et al., 2004).

Therefore, for industrial applications, a system must be

developed which is able to convert specific yeast strains,

which predominate at each industrial plant, to conditional

flocculant strains. For this, we integrated the flocculation

cassette into the CAN1 locus (Camargo, 2000). This system

has the advantage of avoiding the use of positive antibiotic

genes, such as for kanamycin or gentamicin resistance

(Wach et al., 1994; Longtine et al., 1998; Goldstein et al.,

1999), which would be very harmful as the excess yeast cells

are normally used for animal feed after the end of the

fermentation cycle. Therefore, strains bearing such genes

would not be approved for industrial applications.

In the initial experiments, we were able to select canava-

nine-resistant cells, in which the cassette was effectively

integrated in the cells and which presented flocculation after

the exhaustion of sugar from the growth medium. However,

in contrast with the observations with the laboratory strain,

the industrial strain presented a significant decrease in

ethanol production in comparison with nontransformed

cells. We are currently investigating the causes of this decrease,

testing new constructions combining different promoters and

FLO genes and evaluating other industrial yeast strains.

In summary, this study shows the first results of the

development of industrial yeast strains capable of floccula-

tion co-ordinated with sugar consumption, allowing the

separation of cells at the end of fermentation in a natural

manner, without the need for mechanical processing.

Acknowledgements

This work was supported by grants from GENESEARCH

Biotech and Fundo de Apoio ao Ensino e Pesquisa –

Universidade Estadual de Campinas. Anderson Cunha

was supported by a Coordenac?a?o de Aperfeic?oamento de

Pessoal de N??vel Superior fellowship. We thank Eduardo

F. Formighieri for image processing.

References

Abate C, Callieri D, Rodriguez E &amp;amp; Garro O (1996) Ethanol

production by a mixed culture of flocculent strains of

Zymomonas mobilis and Saccharomyces sp. Appl Microbiol

Biotechnol 45: 580–583.

Almeida C, Queiro?s O, Wheals A, Teixeira J &amp;amp; Moradas-Ferreira P

(2003) Acquisition of flocculation phenotype by

Kluyveromyces marxianus when overexpressing GAP1 gene

encoding an isoform of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate

dehydrogenase. J Microbiol Methods 55: 433–440.

Ausubel FM, Brent R, Kingston RE, Moore DD, Seidman JG,

Smith AJ &amp;amp; Struhl K (1998) Current Protocols in Molecular

Biology. Wiley, New York.

Barney MC, Jansen GP &amp;amp; Helber GR (1980) Use of genetic

transformation for the introduction of flocculence into yeast.

J Am Soc Brewing Chemists 38: 71–74.

Bidard F, Blondin B, Dequin S, Vezinhet F &amp;amp; Barre P (1994)

Cloning and analysis of a FLO5 flocculation gene from

S. cerevisiae. Curr Genet 25: 196–201.

Bony M, Thines-Sempoux D, Barre P &amp;amp; Blondin B (1997)

Localization and cell surface anchoring of the Saccharomyces

cerevisiae flocculation protein Flo1p. J Bacteriol 179:

4929–4936.

Brunelli JP &amp;amp; Pall ML (1993) A series of yeast shuttle vectors for

expression of cDNAs and other DNA sequences. Yeast 9:

1299–1308.

Camargo ME (2000) Sistema para transformac?a?o de leveduras

industriais e detecc?a?o de atividade recombinoge?nica. Thesis/

Instituto de Cie?ncias Biolo?gicas, Universidade de Sa?o Paulo,

Sa?o Paulo.

DeRisi JL, Iyer VR &amp;amp; Brown PO (1997) Exploring the metabolic

and genetic control of gene expression on a genomic scale.

Science 278: 680–686.

Dequin S (2001) The potential of genetic engineering for

improving brewing, wine-making and baking yeasts. Appl

Microbiol Biotechnol 56: 577–588.

Domingues L, Lima N &amp;amp; Teixeira JA (2001) Alcohol production

from cheese whey permeate using genetically modified

flocculent yeast cells. Biotechnol Bioeng 72: 507–514.

Ferea TL, Botstein D, Brown PO &amp;amp; Rosenzweig RF (1999)

Systematic changes in gene expression patterns following

adaptive evolution in yeast. Proc Natl Acad Sci 96: 9721–9726.

Gancedo JM (1998) Yeast carbon catabolite repression. Microbiol

Mol Biol Rev 62: 334–361.

Goldstein AL, Pan X &amp;amp; McCusker JH (1999) Heterologous

URA3MX cassettes for gene replacement in Saccharomyces

cerevisiae. Yeast 15: 507–511.

Guo B, Styles CA, Feng Q &amp;amp; Fink GR (2000) A Saccharomyces

gene family involved in invasive growth, cell–cell adhesion,

and mating. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97: 12158–12163.

Howell KS, Bartowsky EJ, Fleet GH &amp;amp; Henschke PA (2004)

Microsatellite PCR profiling of Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains

during wine fermentation. Lett Appl Microbiol 38: 315–320.

Ishida-Fujii K, Goto S, Sugiyama H, Takagi Y, Saiki T &amp;amp; Takagi M

(1998) Breeding of flocculent industrial alcohol yeast strains

by self-cloning of the flocculation gene FLO1 and repeated-

batch fermentation by transformants. J Gen Appl Microbiol 44:

347–353.

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

286 A.F. Cunha et al.

ecamargo
Typewriter
33



Kondo A, Shigechi H, Abe M, et al. (2002) High-level ethanol

production from starch by a flocculent Saccharomyces

cerevisiae strain displaying cell-surface glucoamylase. Appl

Microbiol Biotechnol 58: 291–296.

Longtine MS, McKenzie A III &amp;amp; Demarini DJ (1998) Additional

modules for versatile and economical PCR-based gene

deletion and modification in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast

14: 953–961.

Paiva TC, Sato S, Visconti AE &amp;amp; Castro LA (1996) Continuous

alcoholic fermentation process in a tower reactor with

recycling of flocculating yeast. Appl Biochem Biotechnol 57–58:

535–541.

Pereira GG &amp;amp; Hollenberg CP (1996) Conserved regulation of the

Hansenula polymorpha MOX promoter in Saccharomyces

cerevisiae reveals insights in the transcriptional activation by

Adr1p. Eur J Biochem 238: 181–191.

Remize F, Schorr-Galindo S, Guiraud JP, Dequin S &amp;amp; Blondin B

(1998) Construction of a flocculating yeast for fructose

production from inulin. Biotechnol Lett 20: 313–318.

Sabate J, Cano J, Querol A &amp;amp; Guillamo?n JM (1998) Diversity of

Saccharomyces strains in wine fermentations: analysis for two

consecutive years. Lett Appl Microbiol 26: 452–455.

Schwan RF, Mendonc?a AT, da Silva JJ Jr, Rodrigues V &amp;amp; Wheals

AE (2001) Microbiology and physiology of cachac?a

(aguardente) fermentations. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek 79:

89–96.

Seymour IJ &amp;amp; Piper PW (1999) Stress induction of HSP30, the

plasma membrane heat shock protein gene of Saccharomyces

cerevisiae, appears not to use known stress-regulated

transcription factors. Microbiology 145: 231–239.

Sieiro C, Reboredo NM, Blanco P &amp;amp; Villa TG (1997) Cloning of a

new FLO gene from the flocculating Saccharomyces cerevisiae

IM1-8b strain. FEMS Microbiol Lett 146: 109–115.

Stewart GG &amp;amp; Russell I (1977) The identification,

characterization, and mapping of a gene for flocculation in

Saccharomyces sp. Can J Microbiol 23: 441–447.

Stratford M (1989) Evidence for two mechanisms of flocculation

in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 5: S441–S445.

Stratford M &amp;amp; Assinder S (1991) Yeast flocculation: flo1 and

NewFlo phenotypes and receptor structure. Yeast 7: 559–574.

Teunissen AW, Holub E, van der Hucht J, van den Berg JA &amp;amp;

Steensma HY (1993) Sequence of the open reading frame

of the FLO1 gene from Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 9:

423–427.

Teunissen AW &amp;amp; Steensma HY (1995) Review: the dominant

flocculation genes of Saccharomyces cerevisiae constitute a new

subtelomeric gene family. Yeast 11: 1001–1013.

Trinder P (1969) Determination of blood glucose using an

oxidase-peroxidase system with a non-carcinogenic

chromogen. J Clin Pathol 22: 158–161.

Varela C, Cardenas J, Melo F &amp;amp; Agosin E (2005) Quantitative

analysis of wine yeast gene expression profiles under

winemaking conditions. Yeast 22: 369–383.

Verstrepen KJ, Derdelinckx G, Delvaux FR, et al. (2001) Late

fermentation expression of FLO1 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.

J Am Soc Brewing Chemists 59: 69–76.

Verstrepen KJ, Derdelinckx G, Verachtert H &amp;amp; Delvaux FR (2003)

Yeast flocculation: what brewers should know. Appl Microbiol

Biotechnol 61: 197–205.

Wach A, Brachat A, Pohlmann R &amp;amp; Philippsen P (1994) New

heterologous modules for classical or PCR-based gene

disruptions in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 10: 1793–1808.

Watari J, Kudo M, Nishikawa N &amp;amp; Kamimura M (1990)

Construction of flocculant yeast cells (Saccharomyces

cerevisiae) by mating or protoplast fusion using a yeast cell

containing the flocculation gene FLO5. Agric Biol Chem 54:

1677–1681.

Watari J, Nomura M, Sahara H, Koshino S &amp;amp; Keranen S (1994)

Construction of flocculant brewers yeast by chromosomal

integration of the yeast flocculation gene FLO1. J Inst Brewing

100: 73–77.

Wheals AE, Basso LC, Alves DMG &amp;amp; Amorim HV (1999) Fuel

ethanol after 25 years. Trends Biotechnol 17: 482–487.

Wieczorek A &amp;amp; Michalski H (1994) Continuous ethanol

production by flocculating yeast in the fluidized bed

bioreactor. FEMS Microbiol Rev 14: 69–74.

Yu J, Donoviel MS &amp;amp; Young ET (1989) Adjacent upstream

activation sequence elements synergistically regulate

transcription of ADH2 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Mol Cell

Biol 9: 34–42.

FEMS Yeast Res 6 (2006) 280–287 c? 2006 Federation of European Microbiological Societies
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd. All rights reserved

287Control by sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation

ecamargo
Typewriter
34



 35

CAPITULO 2 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

REGULAÇÃO CONDICIONAL DO GENE DA FLOCULAÇÃO FLO10 
 
 
 



 36

INTRODUÇÃO 
 

Os resultados obtidos com a regulação do gene FLO5 mostraram a possibilidade da 

“criação” de uma levedura inteligente. Porém, o gene FLO5 apresenta uma desvantagem, as 

células não desfloculam após a adição de um novo mosto. Isso causaria um problema na 

indústria, pois não seria possível a reutilização das leveduras. 

 Segundo a literatura, os agregados de células formada pela expressão do gene FLO5 

são inibidos apenas por manose, entretanto, foi relatado que agregados de células formados 

pela expressão de um outro gene da floculação, FLO10, são inibidos pela presença de 

glicose, sacarose e maltose (Guo et al., 2000). Essa informação é importante e motivou a 

continuidade da idéia de produzir linhagens floculantes condicionais, pois haveria grandes 

possibilidades de que as células desfloculassem imediatamente ao serem colocadas nas 

dornas de fermentação com um novo mosto rico em glicose e sacarose.  

 O objetivo desta etapa foi usar a mesma estratégia descrita no capítulo anterior para 

controlar a expressão do gene FLO10, em linhagens de laboratório, avaliando sua expressão 

gênica durante a fermentação e também construindo um cassete integrativo para 

transformação de linhagens industriais que são utilizadas na produção de etanol 

combustível.  

 

METODOLOGIA 
 
 I - Linhagens utilizadas 
 

Linhagens da levedura Saccharomyces cerevisiae: 

• W303-1a: Mat a ade2 can1-100 his3-11, 15 leu2-13, 112 trp1-1 ura3-1; 

• FY23: Linhagem padrão S288c: Mat a, ura3-52, leu2D1, trp1D63; 

• JAY270: isolado da linhagem industrial Pedra 2, sem marca auxotrófica; 

• JAY291: Mat a, haplóide de um esporo proveniente da JAY270; 

• JAY292: Mat alfa, haplóide de um esporo proveniente da JAY270. 

 

Linhagem da bactéria Escherichia coli empregada para a clonagem e multiplicação 

dos plasmídeos: 



 37

• DH10b: F- mcrA (mrr-hsdRMS-mcrBC) 80lacZ M15 lacX74 recA1 

endA1 ara 139 (ara, leu)7697 galU galK - rpsL (StrR) nupG; 

 

II - Meios de cultura 

Para crescimento de leveduras: 

• YEPD: meio completo composto por 1% de extrato de levedura, 2% de 

peptona e 2% de glicose. Para meio sólido adicionar 2% de ágar; 

Para a seleção dos transformantes integrativos o meio foi complementado com o 

antibiótico geneticina (G418) a uma concentração de 200 mg/L e sorbitol na concentração 

de 1 M. 

• YNB: meio mínimo composto por 0,67% YNB e 3% de glicose, sendo 

necessário suplementar com aminoácidos para a seleção de transformantes. Os aminoácidos 

triptofano, histidina e leucina são preparados à parte em uma solução estoque com 

concentração de 100X e a uracila, 50X. É adicionada também uma mistura de aminoácidos 

(drop out) ao meio (Ausubel et al., 1998); 

Para crescimento de bactérias: 

• LB: meio composto por 1% triptona, 0,5% extrato de levedura e 0,5% 

cloreto de sódio (NaCl) complementado com os antibióticos apropriados para seleção de 

transformantes (ampicilina 100 ?g/ml). 

Para a preparação dos meios sólidos foram adicionados 2% de ágar. 

 

III – Plasmídeos 

• pYADE4 – plasmídeo de expressão em levedura, contendo o promotor do 

gene da álcool desidrogenase 2 (ADH2) a frente de um sítio de clonagem múltipla (Brunelli 

&amp;amp; Pall, 1993); 

• pYADE4-FLO5 – plasmídeo que contém o gene FLO5 sob controle do 

promotor ADH2 (Cunha et al., 2006); 

• YEp352-FLO10 – plasmídeo YEp352 contendo o gene FLO10. Contém 

marca de seleção URA3 (uracila) e AmpR (resistência a ampicilina). 



 38

IV – Extração de DNA genômico de levedura  

Para a extração do DNA genômico, as leveduras foram crescidas em meio YEPD 

durante 16 horas a 30 ºC sob agitação de 300 rpm. As células foram separadas do meio de 

cultura e extração foi feita utilizando um tampão de quebra com bolinhas de vidro (glass 

beads) e uma solução de fenol/clorofórmio/álcool isoamílico. Essa mistura foi “vortexada” 

e centrifugada. O DNA foi precipitado com 1/10 de NaAc (3 M, pH 5,3) e 2 x volume de 

etanol 100% (Ausubel et al., 1998). 

 

V – Amplificação e clonagem do gene FLO10 

O gene FLO10 foi amplificado por PCR diretamente do DNA genômico de 

Saccharomyces cerevisiae usando primers específicos:  

(1) FLO10BamF: 5´ CGCGGA TCCATGCCTGTGGCTGCTCG 3´ (62ºC) 

(2) FLO10SalR: 5´ ACGCGTCGACCTATTAAACGATTGCCAG 3´ (62ºC) 

(3) FLO10PROMSAMAI: 5´ TCCCCCGGGGGAGGTTGTTTGGTATGTATC 3´ (50ºC) 

(4) FLO10BMHI: 5´ CGCGGATCCGCGTTAAACGATTGCCAGTAATAG 3´ (50ºC) 

(5) FLO10SMAIprcurto: 5´ TCCCCCGGGGGATTCTGTTGTAACGAATGATTC 3´ (52ºC) 

(6) FLO10_117pr_sma: 5’ TCCCCCGGGGGACATGTTCGAGTGCG 3’(52ºC) 

A seqüência sublinhada indica os sítios de restrição das enzimas para posterior 

digestão, e a temperatura que se encontra entre parênteses indica a temperatura de 

anelamento para a PCR. 

A PCR foi feita da seguinte forma: 3 µl de tampão (10 X), 2,5 µl MgSO4 (50 mM), 

1,5 µl de cada primer (15 pmol), 8 µl de dNTPs (1,25 mM) e 1,5 U de taq de alta fidelidade 

(Invitrogen) para um volume final de 30 µl. O programa utilizado foi: um ciclo inicial de 

desnaturação a 94 ºC por 2 minutos, seguido por 40 ciclos de 94 ºC por 30 segundos, 

temperatura anelamento por 30 segundos, 68 ºC por 2 minutos e uma extensão final de 68 

ºC por 7 minutos. 

Os fragmentos amplificados foram clonados no vetor pGEM-T Easy (Promega), 

seguindo as especificações do kit. 

 



 39

VI – Reação de sequenciamento 

As reações de sequenciamento dos produtos de PCR clonados foram realizadas em 

volume final de 10 ?l, sendo: 1,0 ?l de Bigdye terminator Mix (Applied Biosystems), 5 

pmol/?l de primer M13. Foi utilizado 400 ng de plasmídeo, que era o molde que estava 

clonado em pGEM-T. Completando-se o volume final com H2O milliQ. Os ciclos de 

sequenciamento foram: um ciclo inicial de desnaturação a 95 ºC por 2 minutos, seguido por 

50 ciclos de 95 ºC por 20 segundos, 57 ºC por 20 segundos e 60 ºC por 4 minutos. A 

precipitação das amostras seguiu a orientação do fabricante, usando-se o Sequenciador 

Applied Biosystems 377-96. 

 

VII - Construção dos plasmídeos 

A técnica de purificação e isolamento de DNA do gel de agarose foi feita utilizando-

se o kit da Qiagen (Qiaex II Gel Extraction Kit) ou kit da Invitrogen (PureLink). Todas as 

outras técnicas, como a extração de DNA plasmidial (mini preparação), o uso de enzimas 

de restrição e ligação foram realizadas de acordo com os protocolos básicos (Ausubel et al., 

1998). 

 

VIII – Preparação de células (bactérias e leveduras) competentes e 

transformação 

Todas essas técnicas seguiram os protocolos descritos em Ausubel (Ausubel et al., 

1998).  

Para o preparo das bactérias competentes, é necessário o acompanhamento do 

crescimento celular em 1 L de meio LB até a OD600 = 0,6 (fase exponencial de 

crescimento). Nesse momento o crescimento celular é parado colocando as células em 

banho de gelo. São feitas 3 lavagens sucessivas com glicerol gelado (10%) para retirar todo 

resíduo de meio de cultura. As células são ressuspendidas em 2 mL de glicerol (10%), 

aliquotadas e armazenadas em freezer -80 ºC para uso posterior. 

No preparo de leveduras competentes, as células são crescidas até OD600 = 1,3. São 

feitas sucessivas lavagens em Sorbitol (1 M) para retirar resíduos de meio. No final, as 

células são ressuspendidas em 200 µL de sorbitol e aliquotadas para uso. Nesse caso as 



 40

células foram utilizadas imediatamente após o preparo. O armazenamento, nesse caso, 

diminui o rendimento da transformação. 

A transformação, tanto de leveduras e bactérias foi realizada pelo método de 

eletroporação.  

 

 IX - Extração e análise de RNA 

O RNA total foi extraído pelo método do fenol ácido quente e o Northern blotting 

foi feito segundo protocolos básicos (Ausubel et al., 1998).  

Na extração de RNA, as células coletadas durante os experimentos foram tratadas 

com fenol ácido, tampão e aquecidas a 65 ºC por 1 hora. As etapas adicionais de extração 

foram feitas novamente com fenol ácido e clorofórmio. O RNA foi precipitado com NaAc 

(3 M, pH 5,3) e etanol 100% gelado. 

Para os experimentos de Northern blotting: Foi feita eletroforese do RNA extraído 

em gel de agarose denaturante para que as fitas de RNA permanecessem simples e não se 

ligassem entre si. O RNA presente no gel foi transferido para uma membrana Hybond-N+ 

(Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) e posteriormente hibridado com uma sonda específica 

marcada radioativamente. Esse material foi exposto em um filme e revelado.  

 

X – Determinação da concentração de glicose 

A quantificação da concentração de glicose foi feita com um kit colorimétrico 

enzimático da Laborlab. Os resultados foram expressos em porcentagem de glicose.  

Os cálculos seguem abaixo: 

                  F = 100mg/dL                        % de glicose = D . F. diluição 
                              P                                                                1000 
 Sendo que: F = constante dependente do padrão 
       P = OD505 do reagente padrão 
             D = OD505 da amostra desconhecida 

 

 

 



 41

 RESULTADOS E DISCUSSÃO 

 

 Clonagem do gene FLO10 variando tamanho do promotor e construção do 

plasmídeo expressão  

O gene FLO10 é um gene pouco estudado e por isso não havia na literatura 

nenhuma informação sobre a sua região promotora. Para verificar se o tamanho da região 

promotora teria interferência na regulação, o promotor de FLO10 foi sendo reduzido 

através da amplificação utilizando primers cada vez mais internos e utilizado na sua forma 

nativa ou fusionado com o a região regulatória do promotor do gene ADH2. 

O gene FLO10 foi amplificado por PCR com 4 variações no tamanho do promotor, 

utilizando os  pares de primers descritos abaixo. Destacado entre parênteses estão os nomes 

dados a cada um dos fragmentos: 

   - FLO10BamF e FLO10SalR: amplifica somente a parte codante do gene, ou seja, a partir 

do ATG gerando um fragmento de 3510 pb (FLO10). Nesse caso, o gene é fusionado com o 

promotor completo do gene ADH2; 

   - FLO10PROMOSMAI e FLO10BMHI: amplifica um fragmento de 3834 pb (FLO10pr), 

sendo que os 324 pb iniciais são referentes ao promotor do gene FLO10; 

   - FLO10SMAIprcurto e FLO10BMH: amplifica um fragmento de 3717 pb 

(FLO10pr_curto), sendo 207 pb referente ao promotor do gene FLO10; 

   - FLO10_117pr_Sma e FLO10BMH: amplifica um fragmento de 3627 pb 

(FLO10_117pr) com o promotor contendo 117 pb. 

Os fragmentos amplificados foram clonados no vetor pGEM-T easy (Promega). Em 

todos os casos a clonagem foi confirmada pelo padrão de bandas por digestão, PCR com 

primers específicos e sequenciamento. A figura 11 mostra a amplificação do gene FLO10 e 

a confirmação da construção pGEM-FLO10. Nesse caso, a digestão com a enzima SalI  

gera fragmentos de 3,5 kb e 3,0 kb; com BamHI/SalI, 3,5 kb e 3,0 kb, e com ScaI/SalI, 2,0 

kb, 1,8 kb, 1,5 kb e 1,1 kb.  

Como descrito em materiais e métodos, os primers utilizados para amplificação do 

gene FLO10 foram desenhados com a seqüência de determinadas enzimas de restrição, que 

foram utilizadas, posteriormente, para retirar o gene do vetor de clonagem pGEM.  

 



 42

 
FIGURA 11. (A) Amplificação por PCR do gene FLO10. (B) Digestão do pGEM-FLO10 com as 
enzimas (1) SalI, (2) BamHI/SalI e (3) ScaI/SalI. M: marcador de peso molecular ? hind.  

 

Para a construção dos plasmídeos de expressão, o  pGEM com os genes clonados 

foram digeridos com enzimas de restrição. A banda correspondente ao gene FLO10 foi 

purificada (Kit PureLink - Invitrogen) e ligada ao plasmídeo pYADE4 (que contém o 

promotor do gene ADH2), previamente linearizado também por tratamento com enzimas, 

de acordo com tabela 2: 

 

TABELA 2: Plasmídeos com os genes clonados, as enzimas utilizadas para liberar o gene, as 
bandas obtidas após a digestão, a banda isolada e as enzimas utilizadas para digerir o vetor de 
expressão. 

Plasmídeo Enzimas para 
digerir pGEM 

Bandas 
Obtidas 

Banda Isolada e 
Purificada 

Enzima para 
digestão 
PYADE4 

pGEM-FLO10 BamHI e SalI 3,0 e 3,5 Kb 3,5 Kb BamHI e SalI 
pGEM-FLO10pr SmaI e BamHI 3,0 e 3,8 Kb 3,8 Kb SphI e BamHI 

pGEM-
FLO10pr_curto 

SmaI e BamHI 3,0 e 3,7 Kb 3,7 Kb SphI e BamHI 

pGEM-
FLO10pr_117 

SmaI e BamHI 3,0 e 3,6Kb 3,6 Kb SphI e BamHI 

 

O plasmídeo pYADE4 para ser ligado a gene FLO10 sem o promotor foi linearizado 

com BamHI e SalI, ou seja, deixando o promotor do gene ADH2 inteiro. Para a reação de 

ligação usou-se a enzima T4 ligase (Invitrogen), e a concentração molar do inserto utilizado 

foi 5 vezes maior que a do plasmídeo. 

Para a construção do gene FLO10 sob o controle da parte regulatória do promotor 

do gene ADH2, o plasmídeo pYADE4 foi linearizado com a enzima SphI, gerando 

extremidades coesivas, cortando o plasmídeo na região do promotor do gene ADH2. Esse 



 43

material foi tratado com a enzima T4 DNA polimerase, deixando com que as extremidades 

se tornem abruptas. Em seguida foi feita uma nova digestão com a enzima BamHI. Esta 

digestão remove o TATA box do promotor do gene ADH2, mantendo no plasmídeo apenas 

a região regulatória (Beier et al., 1985; Cunha et al., 2006). Posteriormente o gene FLO10 

com o promotor foi ligado ao plasmídeo PYADE4 utilizando a enzima T4 ligase 

(Invitrogen). O esquema das construções está mostrado na figura 12. 

 
 

 
FIGURA 12. Esquema da construção dos plasmídeos pYADE4-FLO10, pYADE4-FLO10pr, 
pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto e pYADE4-FLO10pr_117. Os plasmídeos (pGEM) foram digeridos com 
as enzimas restrição, liberando um fragmento de aproximadamente 3,7 Kb, que foi ligado ao 
plasmídeo pYADE4 linearizado previamente digerido. 

 

A confirmação da construção correta dos plasmídeos de expressão foi feita por 

digestão com as enzimas de restrição (Figura 13) e por PCR com os primers específicos 

(Figura 14). 

 



 44

 
FIGURA 13. (A) Foto do gel de agarose com a digestão do plasmídeo pYADE4-FLO10pr com as 
enzimas: (1) EcoRV , produzindo bandas de 6,9 Kb, 2,5 Kb e  145 pb (banda não visível); (2) 
BamHI, linearizando o plasmídeo (9,6 Kb). (B) Digestão com EcoRI para confirmar a construção 
dos plasmídeos pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto (1-3) e pYADE4-FLO10pr_117 (4-6). O padrão de banda 
esperado é de ~1,4 kb e ~8,2 kb. M = marcador de peso molecular o ?hind (Invitrogen).  
 

 
FIGURA 14: Produto da reação de PCR para confirmar a construção utilizando-se os primers 
ADH2F/FLO10BMHI. Foi obtido o padrão de bandas esperado (4,0Kb). As amostras referentes aos 
plasmídeos pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto (1-3) e pYADE4-FLO10pr_117 (4-6). 
 

Transformação de leveduras de laboratório e testes de floculação 

A linhagem de laboratório W303-1a foi transformada por eletroporação com os 

plasmídeos: pYADE4 (controle negativo), pYADE4-FLO10, pYADE4-FLO10pr, 

pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto, pYADE4-FLO10pr_117. 

As amostras de células foram coletadas periodicamente até o esgotamento da 

glicose para posterior extração de RNA, foram feitas medidas de densidade óptica (OD), 

concentração de glicose, presença ou ausência de floculação (observação visual). 

 Para os experimentos de Northern Blot foi necessária a construção de uma sonda. O 

fragmento da sonda, contendo 1,3 kb, referente ao gene FLO10 foi isolado da digestão do 

plasmídeo pYADE4-FLO10 com as enzimas EcoRI e XhoI (Figura 15) e foi marcado 

radioativamente usando ?[32]P-dATP (Ausubel et al., 1998).  



 45

 

 
FIGURA 15: Esquema da região de onde a sonda do gene FLO10 (1,3 Kb) foi retirada após a 
digestão do plasmídeo pYADE4-FLO10 com as enzimas EcoRV e XhoI  e foto do gel de agarose 
contendo a banda isolada. 
 

O primeiro resultado de Northern blot com linhagens transformada com o 

plasmídeo pYFLO10 (FLO10 clonado a partir do ATG) mostra que o promotor do gene 

ADH2 não ativa somente quando a glicose se esgota, mas há uma expressão basal mesmo 

com quantidades elevadas de glicose (Figura 16). Esse mesmo fenômeno foi observado 

com o gene GFP3 (green fluorescent protein) na construção pYADE4-GFP3 realizado pelo 

Prof. Luiz Humberto do Laboratório de Genética da ESALQ, Piracicaba (comunicação 

pessoal). 

 

 
 

FIGURA 16. Experimento de Northern blotting mostrando a expressão basal do gene FLO10 
durante ensaio de fermentação. Nas linhagens transformadas com o plasmídeo PYADE4 não se 
observa a expressão do gene, como esperado. 
 

Com a expressão basal do gene, partimos para as outras construções, então 

linhagens de laboratório (W303-1a) foram transformadas com o plasmídeo pYFLO10pr, na 



 46

qual apenas a região regulatória do promotor do gene ADH2 foi fusionada com o promotor 

básico do gene FLO10.  

O experimento de Northern continuou apresentando expressão basal do gene. As 

células crescidas em meio completo (YEPD) começaram a flocular podendo ser 

identificadas visualmente após o esgotamento da glicose. A intensidade da floculação 

aumentava um pouco a medida que a glicose estava sendo consumida, mas isso pode ser 

decorrente também do aumento da massa celular. Já as células crescidas em meio YNB-

Trp- não flocularam em nenhum momento, nem após o esgotamento da glicose (Figura 17).  

 

 
FIGURA 17: Experimento de Northern blotting de linhagens transformadas com o plasmídeo 
pYADE4-FLO10pr crescidas em meio YEPD e YNB-Trp-. (C+) controle positivo, gene FLO10 
amplificado por PCR; (C-) controle negativo, RNA de leveduras transformadas com o plasmídeo 
pYADE4. 

 

 As células crescidas em meio YNB-Trp- apresentaram uma intensidade de expressão 

do gene menor do que as linhagens crescidas em YEPD (Figura 17). Govender (Govender 

et al., 2008) observou também que transformantes para o gene FLO1 e FLO5 crescidos em 

meio mínimo apresentam capacidade de floculação diminuída. Nesse caso, o RNAm para 

pode estar sendo expresso, mas a proteína pode não estar ativa. Pelo fato do meio de cultura 

ser pobre, algum elemento essencial para ativar a proteína, como por exemplo, o cálcio, 

pode funcionar como um fator limitante. 



 47

As células floculadas resultante da expressão do gene FLO10 foram lavadas com 

uma solução de EDTA (quelante de íons) e observou-se a desfloculação de todas as células, 

ou seja, ficaram todas em suspensão. Isso indica que a floculação é dependente de íons Ca++ 

como no gene FLO1.  

Para verificar se o tamanho do promotor teria influencia na expressão gênica, as 

leveduras foram transformadas com os plasmídeos pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto, pYADE4-

FLO10pr_117. Os dados de tempo de fermentação, OD, concentração de glicose e 

floculação se encontram na tabela 3. Foram feitos com os 3 plasmídeos construídos pY-

FLO10pr, pY-FLO10pr_curto, pY-FLO10pr_117, e também com um controle negativo, 

pYADE4, e positivo, YEPFLO10pr. 

Como observados no experimento de Northern (Figura 18), as leveduras 

transformadas com os três plasmídeos construídos apresentaram floculação basal durante 

todo o processo fermentativo. A intensidade da expressão gênica aumenta 

significativamente à medida que a glicose vai sendo consumida, principalmente no último 

ponto de coleta (10hs), quando já não há mais glicose presente no meio de cultura.  

 É interessante observar que as leveduras transformadas com o plasmídeo pYADE4-

FLO10pr_117 apresentaram o mesmo padrão de expressão gênica das transformadas com 

as demais construções, ou seja, a expressão se mostrou basal aumentando nas etapas finais 

da fermentação (Figura 18 C). Mas quando se observaram as células, elas não apresentaram 

característica floculante. Visualmente, o fenótipo dessas leveduras era muito semelhantes 

ao fenótipo das leveduras transformadas com o plasmídeo pYADE4 (controle negativo), 

com as células todas em suspensão. Nessa construção, o tamanho do promotor do gene 

FLO10 apresenta 117pb (que contém a região de TATA box) e o restante do promotor 

referente à região regulatória se encontra no pedaço do promotor do gene ADH2. O RNA 

mensageiro referente ao gene FLO10 está sendo transcrito, como pode ser visto no 

experimento de Northern, mas a proteína provavelmente não está sendo traduzida 

corretamente ou após a tradução ela não esteja sendo ativada. Outra hipótese seria que 

nessa construção as enzimas responsáveis pela transcrição tenham encontrado outra região 

iniciadora para a proteína, mudando o frame, transcrevendo outra sequência. 

 

 



 48

TABELA 3. Testes de floculação com as leveduras da linhagem W303-1a transformadas com os 
diferentes plasmídeos e crescidas em meio completo YEPD. 

Plasmídeo Tempo (hrs) OD 
[ ] Glicose 

(%) Floculação* Observação 

 0 2,7 1,4 0  
  2 4,3 1,3 0 Plasmídeo 

pYADE4 4 5,7 1,0 0 sem o gene  
 6 7,0 0,7 0 da  
  8 8,1 0,2 0 floculação 
  10 8,3 0,04 0 (C-) 
       
 0 2,7 1,3 1  
 2 4,1 1,3 1 Gene  

YEPFLO10p 4 5,5 1,1 1 FLO10 
  6 6,7 0,8 1 constitutivo 
 8 7,9 0,2 1 (C+) 
  10 8,3 0,04 1  
       
 0 2,4 1,3 1  

  2 3,8 1,3 1 Promotor 
 pYFLO10pr 4 5,4 1,1 1 do gene 

 6 6,3 0,8 1 FLO10 
 8 7,9 0,3 1 com 324pb 
  10 8,2 0,04 2  
      
 0 2,7 1,3 1  
 2 4,2 1,2 1 Promotor 

pYFLO10pr_ 4 5,4 1,0 1 do gene 
curto 6 6,5 0,8 1 FLO10 

 8 8,0 0,2 1 com 207pb 
 10 8,1 0,03 2  
      
 0 2,7 1,3 0  
 2 4,0 1,3 0 Promotor 

pYFLO10pr_ 4 5,9 1,1 0 do gene 
117 6 6,4 0,8 0 FLO10 

 8 8,1 0,3 0 com 117pb 
  10 8,3 0,04 0  

* A intensidade da floculação: (0) ausência de floculação; (1) Floculação fraca; (2) Floculação intensa. 



 49

  
FIGURA 18. Experimentos de Northern blotting da linhagem W303-1a transformada com o 
plasmídeo (A) pYADE4-FLO10pr, (B) pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto e (C) pYADE4-FLO10pr_117. 
Linhagens transformadas com pYADE4 representam o controle negativo, e as transformadas com 
YEPFLO10pr, controle positivo. 
 

 Em nenhuma das outras duas construções (pYADE4-FLO10pr e pYADE4-

FLO10pr_curto) foi obtida uma regulação controlada pelos níveis de glicose no meio como 

era esperado. Observando na figura 18 A e B, nos experimentos de Northern, os transcritos 

obtidos apresentam o tamanho um pouco menor do que o controle (Yep-FLO10pr – flocula 

o tempo todo). Isso indica que pode estar havendo uma regulação pós-transcricional ou que 

o promotor do gene FLO10 tenha algum elemento que esteja impedindo o controle exato da 

floculação no momento que a glicose se esgote. 

 

 

 



 50

Construção dos cassetes integrativos e integração no genoma  

A partir dos plasmídeos pYADE4-FLO10pr, pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto e pYADE4-

FLO10pr_117, foram construídos cassetes integrativos, transformando linhagens industriais 

(que efetivamente realizam a fermentação nas usinas) e avaliando o comportamento da 

expressão do gene FLO10.  

O plasmídeo pYADE4, que é utilizado para expressão de genes em leveduras, 

possui uma região de 2 ?m, que confere a habilidade desse plasmídeo de se replicar com 

autonomia dentro da célula de levedura (Griffiths et al., 1993). Para a construção dos 

cassetes integrativos, a região de 2 ?m foi substituída pelo gene KAN (Figura 19), que 

confere resistência ao antibiótico G418.  

A retirada da região de 2 ?m foi necessária para garantir que o plasmídeo não 

continuasse funcional no caso de sua recircularização. Houve também a necessidade de 

inserir o gene KAN para selecionar as linhagens industriais transformadas, pois elas não 

possuem marcas auxotróficas como as linhagens de laboratório. 

Para que ocorresse a recombinação homóloga, o plasmídeo foi linearizado com a 

enzima BsgI. Esta corta a região central do gene triptofano. É nesse gene que o cassete irá 

se integrar no genoma da levedura.  

As leveduras têm a capacidade de reconhecer sequências homólogas de DNA livres 

dentro da célula e promover a recombinação homóloga. Esse é um fenômeno muito comum 

entre as leveduras.  

 
FIGURA 19: Esquema padrão do plasmídeo integrativo contendo o gene FLO10 sob regulação do 
promotor do gene ADH2 e com parte da região de 2 ?m substituída pelo gene KAN. O plasmídeo foi 
linearizado com a enzima BsgI para transformar leveduras.  



 51

 Quando se insere o fragmento de DNA linearizado dentro da célula, as 

extremidades desse fragmento, que apresentam a sequência do gene triptofano, se pareiam 

com esse mesmo gene presente no genoma da levedura no cromossomo VI onde ocorre a 

recombinação homóloga. Nesse caso, como mostrado no esquema da figura 20, observa-se 

que após a integração do cassete, o gene TRP1 não é deletado ou, ele ficará duplicado 

sendo que as duas cópias permanecem funcionais. Além disso, as leveduras ficam 

resistentes à ampicilina e à geneticina (G418), genes presentes no cassete. 

 

 
FIGURA 20: Esquema da integração do cassete no genoma da levedura. Observa-se a duplicação 
do gene triptofano.  

 

As transformações com os cassetes integrativos (pYADE4-FLO10pr_Kan, 

pYADE4-FLO10pr_curto_Kan e pYADE4-FLO10pr_117_Kan) nas linhagens FY23 

(laboratório), JAY270, JAY291 e JAY292 foram feitas por eletroporação.  

Após a eletroporação, as leveduras foram ressuspendidas em meio YEPD com 

sorbitol e deixadas crescer durante toda a noite para serem plaqueadas em meio seletivo 

(YEPD + G418). O sorbitol ajuda na estabilização da membrana que sofreu uma 

desestabilização após a eletroporação. Antes de se plaquear é necessário esse tempo para 

que as células possam se multiplicar e aumentar a probabilidade de que ocorra a 

recombinação homóloga. 



 52

Após 3 dias na estufa a 30ºC, observou-se crescimento de colônias em todas as 

linhagens transformadas. Confirmou-se a integração do cassete, na região do gene 

triptofano, por PCR. 

Algumas colônias selecionadas foram crescidas em meio YEPD e crescidas até o 

total esgotamento da glicose. A tabela 4 mostra os resultados preliminares encontrados 

nestas linhagens. Foi feita apenas uma triagem inicial para verificar se todas as colônias 

expressavam o fenótipo da floculação. 

A maioria das colônias obtidas não flocularam mesmo apresentando resistência ao 

antibiótico G418. Isso pode ter acontecido devido a algum erro na recombinação que 

eliminou a funcionalidade do gene da floculação. A construção pYADE4-FLO10pr_117 

não consegue expressar o fenótipo floculante. 

 

Tabela 4: Linhagens de leveduras transformadas com os respectivos cassetes integrativos e 
observações da capacidade floculante das colônias obtidas. 

Linhagem Plasmídeo *Colonia 1 *Colonia 2 *Colonia 3 
JAY270 Kan-FLO10pr + - 0 

 Kan-FLO10pr_curto - 0 0 
 Kan-FLO10pr_117 - - 0 

JAY291 Kan-FLO10pr - - 0 
 Kan-FLO10pr_117 - - 0 

JAY292 Kan-FLO10pr + - 0 
 Kan-FLO10pr_curto + + + 
 Kan-FLO10pr_117 - - 0 

FY23 Kan-FLO10pr + - 0 
 Kan-FLO10pr_curto - - 0 
 Kan-FLO10pr_117 - - - 

*intensidade de floculação de cada colonia selecionada. (-) ausência de floculação, (+) floculação 
fraca, não separa completamente do meio, (0) Colônia inexistente. 
 
 Os resultados de integração do cassete no genoma da levedura ainda não são 

conclusivos. Uma nova estratégia de integração de cassetes no genoma da levedura 

industrial está em andamento. A “domesticação” de linhagens industriais é o trabalho do 

mestrando Felipe Galzerani, que se baseia na técnica do Delitto Perfetto, na qual 

modificações genéticas são feitas de forma que, ao final de todo processo de transformação, 

não permaneça nenhuma marca auxótrofica ou marca de seleção. Isso é muito importante, 

pois diferentemente da técnica utilizada aqui, que insere o gene KAN, deixando na levedura 



 53

a marca de resistência ao antibiotico G418, é possível se obter uma levedura “limpa”, 

evitando toda a polêmica e discussão sobre organismos transgênicos. 

 Depois de se obter tranformantes a partir dessa nova técnica de integração será feito 

um acompanhamento mais detalhado durante a fermentação até o esgotamento da glicose. 

 Há ainda a necessidade de se investigar o motivo da expressão basal de todas as 

construções do gene FLO10. Nas linhagens de laboratório, apesar de ter apresentado 

expressão basal nos experimentos de Northen, a expressão aumenta após o esgotamento da 

glicose  e é possível se observar o aumento da floculação.  

Uma outra possibilidade seria a busca de um outro promotor que seja expresso 

somente ao final da fermentação. Essa informação poderá ser obtida  no trabalho do 

doutorando Osmar Netto, que está avaliando a expressão gênica de linhagens industriais 

durante o processo fermentativo na condições reais de dornas. Essa expressão gênica será 

comparada com linhagens de laboratório, investigando também diferenças que possam dar 

indícios da maior robustez e eficiência da linhagem industrial.  

 A possibilidade de se controlar a floculação e a desfloculação é de grande 

importância biotecnológica. Novos promotores serão testados, para se tentar melhorar o 

controle da expressão do gene da floculação.  

  

CONCLUSÃO 

 O gene FLO10, nos experimentos de Northen, mostrou uma expressão basal desde o 

início da fermentação, entretanto essa expressão é aumentada após o esgotamento da 

glicose.   

 Não foi observado o fenômeno da desfloculação.  



 54

CAPITULO 3 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

 

AUMENTO DA PRODUÇÃO DE ETANOL EM LINHAGENS DE LEVEDURAS 

INDUSTRIAIS BRASILEIRAS 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



 55

INTRODUÇÃO 

 

 As pesquisas para o melhoramento genético de linhagens de leveduras industriais 

brasileiras ainda são bem escassas. As linhagens que efetivamente realizam fermentação 

nas usinas têm características de alta eficiência e robustez. Alterações que promovam o 

melhoramento da linhagem baseado no aumento na produtividade ou diminuição de 

problemas como, formação de espuma ou floculação, são de extremo interesse para os 

usineiros.  

Estudos com linhagens de Saccharomyces cerevisiae mostraram que mutantes 

respiratórios apresentam um aumento na produtividade de etanol comparada com leveduras 

que respiram (Hutter &amp;amp; Oliver, 1998; Panoutsopoulou et al., 2001). A deleção de um gene 

específico, PET191, responsável por uma das etapas da montagem do citocromo C, produz 

um mutante 100% deficiente respiratório, neste caso, um mutante nuclear. Foi verificado 

que esse mutante promove um aumento de 43% e 9% na produção de etanol em linhagens 

de laboratório e industriais de vinho, respectivamente. 

 Outro tipo de deficiente respiratório, o mutante citoplasmático, não possui genoma 

mitocondrial funcional. Esse mutante é obtido pelo tratamento das células com brometo de 

etídeo. O grande problema desse mutante é que o genoma mitocondrial, que está 

degradado, possui genes importantes para a linhagem como, por exemplo, tolerância ao 

etanol. 

O objetivo dessa parte do trabalho é a utilização de linhagens industriais brasileiras 

(haplóides derivados da linhagem PE-2) para a produção de deficientes respiratórios 

(petites nucleares e mitocondriais) e a análise do rendimento fermentativo comparando-se 

com as linhagens selvagens.  

Os resultados mostram uma tendência de aumento da quantidade de etanol pelas 

linhagens petites quando comparadas com as controle.  

 

MATERIAL E MÉTODOS 

 

Linhagens de levedura e meios de cultura 



 56

As linhagens de Saccharomyces cerevisiae utilizadas neste trabalho estão listadas na 

tabela 5. As células foram incubadas a 30 ºC para crescimento em meio completo YEPD 

(1% extrato de levedura, 2% peptona, 2% glicose). Para o meio seletivo, foi adicionado 200 

mg/L geneticina (G418). Os petites mitocondriais (?0) foram selecionados em meio YPG 

(1% extrato de levedura, 2% peptona, 2% glicerol). Os ensaios fermentativos foram feitos 

com extrato de cana-de-açúcar esterilizado, meio utilizado nas indústrias Brasileiras de 

etanol. 

 
TABELA 5. Linhagens de Saccharomyces cerevisiae usadas neste trabalho. 

Linhagem Genótipo Referência 
FY23 Linhagem padrão S288c: Mat a, ura3-52, 

leu2D1, trp1D63 
(Winston et al., 

1995) 
PE-2 Linhagem industrial brasileira LNF-Latino 

Americana 
JAY270 Colônia isolada da PE-2 Argueso et al., 2009 

(AnexoI) JAY291 Esporo da JAY270, Mat a, haplóide 
JAY292 Esporo da JAY270, Mat alpha, haplóide 

 

Produção de mutantes respiratórios (100% deficiente respiratório) 

Mutante nuclear (estratégia 1): O cassete para deletar o gene PET191 foi 

amplificado por PCR utilizando como DNA molde o plasmídeo pFA6aKanMX4 

(plasmídeo contendo o gene de resistência à ampicilina e o gene KAN que confere 

resistência ao antibiótico G418) com os seguintes primers: 
DsPET191-2 (rev) 
5’ TATTTATGTATATATTTACAGGCCAATTTTCATAAATTCGACAGCAGTATAGCGACCAG 3’ 
 
DsPET191-1 (fw) 
5’ ACAAATAAATTTGCAGTGCGTTTGTAGATATCAAAGAGCTTGCCTCGTCCCCGCCGGGT 3’ 
 
 A região não sublinhada é a que apresenta homologia com o DNA molde e a região 

sublinhada é homóloga ao começo a ao fim do gene PET191, local onde ocorrerá a 

recombinação homóloga. Essa PCR amplifica um fragmento de 1472 pb (Figura 16). 

 As condições da PCR foram: 5 µl de tampão (10 X), 1,5 µl MgCl2 (50 mM), 1,25 µl 

de cada primer (15 pmol), 9 µl de dNTPs (1,25 mM) e 2,5 U de Taq DNA polimerase 

(Invitrogen) para um volume final de 50 µl. O programa utilizado foi: um ciclo inicial de 

desnaturação a 94 ºC por 3 minutos, seguido por 35 ciclos de 94 ºC por 30 segundos, 60 ºC 



 57

por 30 segundos e 72 ºC por 1 minuto e 30 segundos, além da extensão final de 72 ºC por 4 

minutos. 

Mutante nuclear (estratégia 2): A produção desses petites foi realizada deletando 

um gene específico, o gene PET191, através do método do double-joint PCR (Yu et al., 

2004). Com essa metodologia, é possível aumentar a região de homologia facilitando a 

recombinação na região em que se pretende deletar o gene. Para isso, 3 etapas de PCR são 

necessárias para a construção do cassete integrativo. A figura 21 mostra os diversos passos 

envolvidos nesta técnica. Os primers utilizados foram: KAN-F_dj: 5’ 

CGTTAGAACGCGGCTACAAT 3’, KAN-R_dj: 5’ GCCGATTCATTAATG 

CAGGT 3’, 5’PET-F: 5’ AGGCAGTTTACTGGCGTGTC 3’, 5’PET-R-KAN: 5’ 

TGTATTAATTGTAGCCGCGTTCTAACGTGCTACCCCTCAGACAGCTT 3’, 3’PET-

F-KAN: 5’ CAGGTTAACCTGCATTAATGAATCGGCAGGGCGATGCAAT 

AAAAGTG 3’, 3’PET-R: 5’ ACGTTGCAGAGCGGTCTTAC 3’, PET-KAN_nst-F: 5’ 

CGACCGCAGTACAGTCTGAT 3’, PET-KAN_nst-R 5’ GCGATTGTAGGTTGC 

TAAAG 3’.  

Na primeira etapa (I), três PCRs independentes são feitas. Uma amplifica o gene de 

resistência (1), no caso, o gene KAN; a outra amplifica a região 5’ do gene que se pretende 

deletar (2); e a última amplifica a região 3’ do gene que se quer deletar (3). Estas duas 

últimas PCRs, são feitas com primers contendo uma cauda homóloga ao gene KAN. 

 Na segunda etapa, os três produtos da primeira etapa (1, 2 e 3) são adicionados em 

uma mesma reação de PCR. Os fragmentos 2 e 3 serão os “primers”, estendendo os 

fragmentos.  

Para finalizar, a terceira etapa consiste em utilizar primers internos (nested) para 

selecionar apenas os fragmentos completos, contendo o gene KAN flanqueado com a região 

de homologia ao gene PET191. Os parâmetros de todas as reações de PCR foram as 

mesmas descritas no trabalho original (Yu et al., 2004).  

Ambos os cassetes construídos foram utilizados para transformar leveduras por 

eletroporação. 

Para verificar se o cassete (PET-KAN-PET) se recombinou, integrando-se 

corretamente no cromossomo da levedura, foram desenhados os seguintes primers que 

flanqueiam o gene PET191: 



 58

- JAO262 - 5’ CTTAGGCAGTTTACTGGCGTG 3’ 

- JAO263 - 5’ AAGCACGTTAACTCCCAGATC 3’ 

As condições utilizadas foram: 1 µl de tampão (10 X), 0,7 µl MgCl2 (50 mM), 0,5 µl 

de cada primer (15 pmol), 2 µl de dNTPs (1,25 mM) e 0,5 U de Taq DNA polimerase 

(Invitrogen) para um volume final de 10 µl. O programa utilizado foi: um ciclo inicial de 

desnaturação a 94 ºC por 2 minutos, seguido por 35 ciclos de 94 ºC por 30 segundos, 51 ºC 

por 30 segundos e 72 ºC por 1 minuto e 30 segundos, além da extensão final de 72 ºC por 5 

minutos. 

 

 
FIGURA 21. Metodologia double-joint PCR usado para construir os cassetes integrativos. Três 
etapas de PCR são necessárias para fazer o cassete. (I) Uma PCR para amplificar o gene marcador 
(KAN) e outros dois para amplificar a região do DNA genômico na região 3’ e 5’ do gene que se 
pretende deletar usando primers com cauda homologa ao gene KAN. (II) O produto das três PCRs 
anteriores são adicionadas numa nova reação para a segunda etapa. (III) Última PCR com primers 
internos. 

 



 59

Mutante citoplasmático ou mitocondrial (?0): A deleção completa de todo 

mtDNA gera esse tipo de mutante. As células, nesse caso, são tratadas com brometo de 

etídio, degradando todo o DNA mitocondrial. As leveduras foram incubadas em 10 µg/ml 

de brometo de etídio por aproximadamente 8 horas (Fox et al., 1991). Posteriormente, as 

células foram plaqueadas em meio completo (YEPD). Algumas colônias foram colocadas 

em meio YPG para verificar a deficiência respiratória já que as células petites são incapazes 

de crescer e utilizar glicerol como fonte de carbono. 

Para confirmar se todos os mutantes produzidos realmente eram 100% deficientes 

respiratórios, foi utilizado um reagente, o TTC (cloridrato de 2.3.5 trifeniltetrazolio). O 

TTC é um sal incolor que forma um precipitado vermelho quando é reduzido. As amostras 

celulares são espalhadas sobre a superfície de meio sólido na placa (YEPD com ágar) e 

incubados por 2 dias a 30 °C sob condições aeróbicas. Depois desse tempo, a placa com as 

colônias crescidas são cobertas com 20 mL de solução TTC à 50 °C (ágar 0,75%; glicose 

0,5%; TCC 0,05%) e incubadas por 3 horas a temperatura ambiente. Colônias que 

apresentarem coloração rosa têm a capacidade de respirar, enquanto as colônias brancas são 

deficientes respiratórios (Allen, 1994). 

  

Ensaios fermentativos 

Os ensaios fermentativos foram compostos por 4 fermentações consecutivas e em 

triplicata. Cada amostra foi montada com um volume final de 40 ml, utilizando 10% de 

massa fresca (úmida) de fermento, ou seja, 4 g de massa fresca e 36 ml de meio de 

fermentação. O meio utilizado foi caldo de cana esterilizado. A fermentação teve duração 

de 15 horas a uma temperatura de 30 oC e sem agitação. O pH foi acertado para 4,0. A 

quantidade inicial de açucares redutores total (ART%) foi iniciada com aproximadamente 

18%.  

Para se saber a quantidade máxima teórica de etanol que pode ser obtida a partir da 

glicose inicial, faz-se o calculo baseado na equação:  

 

C6H1206 ? 2C2H5OH + 2CO2 

    180               92             88         (massa molecular) 

 



 60

O valor de 180 equivale 100% da glicose que pode ser convertida em etanol. Desses 

180, apenas 92 podem ser efetivamente convertido em etanol, ou seja, 51,111...%= 

0,51111. Esta é a taxa de conversão utilizada nos cálculos de rendimento teórico máximo. 

Para o cálculo, multiplica-se o valor de ART% (que nesse caso é de 18,0%) pela taxa de 

conversão (0,5111). Resultando no valor de 9,20. 

Para a análise dos resultados e construção dos gráficos, os dados da concentração de 

etanol foram normalizados em função da quantidade máxima teórica que pode ser 

convertido em etanol e que está diretamente ligado a quantidade inicial de Açucares 

Redutores Totais (ART%). 

A medida de ART% foi feita segundo a metodologia de Somogyi-Nelson (Nelson, 

1944; Somogyi, 1945). Foram preparados os reativos de Somogyi, o reativo de Nelson e 

uma solução padrão de glicose. À cada amostra foi adicionada 1 mL de reativo de Somogyi 

e colocado em banho-maria por 10 min. Depois de frio, adicionou-se 1 mL do reativo de 

Nelson. As amostras foram medidas em espectrofotômetro a 540 nm. 

A medida de álcool foi feita por destilação e densitometria. O produto fermentado 

foi destilado e posteriormente foi medido em um densímetro. 

 

RESULTADOS E DISCUSSÃO 

 

Há ainda poucos estudos visando melhorar linhagens industriais, seja por genética 

clássica ou engenharia genética, principalmente, as linhagens brasileiras produtoras de 

etanol. A grande parte dos estudos está focada no melhoramento da cana-de-açúcar e no 

processo durante a fermentação. As leveduras, que efetivamente convertem a sacarose em 

etanol, têm recebido pouca atenção. Existe, portanto, uma ampla área a ser estudada e 

explorada, para poder aumentar ainda mais a produção de etanol e para a síntese de novos 

compostos. 

 Principalmente no Brasil, cada usina possui uma linhagem específica que 

predomina durante toda a safra. Estas leveduras foram isoladas do próprio processo 

fermentativo e são multiplicadas todo ano para iniciarem o processo (Basso et al., 2008). 

Para a realização de modificações genéticas é importante considerar a permanência das 



 61

linhagens nas dornas para que as leveduras possam expressar as características desejáveis e 

sobreviver ao estresse da fermentação. 

Foram usadas para a realização desses experimentos, linhagens industriais haplóides 

derivadas da PE-2. Essa escolha foi feita, pois elas possuem as mesmas características, 

como a alta produtividade de etanol, observadas na linhagem diplóide (JAY270 – PE-2) 

(Argueso et al., 2009 – artigo aceito para publicação Anexo I). A linhagem industrial 

haplóide pode ter a capacidade de exibir a mesma habilidade de competir e sobreviver nas 

condições fermentativas das indústrias. 

 

Levedura petite  

Para deletar o gene PET191, gerando um petite nuclear (100% deficiente 

respiratório - ?pet191), e verificar se a ausência funcional desse gene realmente aumenta a 

produção de etanol, foram desenhados os primers DsPET191-2 (rev) e DsPET191-1 (fw). 

Eles amplificam o gene KAN do plasmídeo pFA6aKanMX4 tendo as extremidades 

homólogas ao gene PET191 do genoma da levedura (Figura 22). 

 

 
FIGURA 22: Esquema da construção do cassete integrativo por PCR a partir do plasmídeo 
pfa6aKanMX4. Os primers apresentam uma cauda homóloga ao gene PET191. No final, o cassete 
apresenta o gene KAN flanqueado por seqüências da região onde se deseja que ocorra a 
recombinação homóloga. 

 

As linhagens FY23, JAY270, JAY291 e JAY292 foram transformadas com esse 

cassete e após plaquear em meio seletivo (YEPD + sorbitol + G418) observou-se uma 

grande quantidade de pequenas colônias. O aspecto aparentava crescimento residual de 

leveduras, mesmo assim, algumas colônias foram selecionadas para verificar se o gene 

PET191 havia sido deletado. Isso foi feito por PCR com primers adjacentes ao gene 

PET191, o JAO262/JAO263. 



 62

Se houver integração, o fragmento amplificado seria de 2,4 Kb. Se a recombinação 

não tiver ocorrido na região correta a PCR amplificaria somente o gene PET191, gerando 

um fragmento de 1,4 Kb. O resultado da PCR mostrou o cassete PET-KAN-PET não 

integrou no genoma da levedura. O padrão de bandas encontrado na linhagem transformada 

foi o mesmo da linhagem não transformada. 

Um dos motivos pode ter sido porque a região de homologia do cassete com a 

região do genoma é de apenas 37 bases. Essa quantidade de bases é o mínimo que se deve 

ter para que a recombinação ocorra, mas a eficiência aumentaria muito com o aumento de 

bases homólogas.  

Esta estratégia foi baseada em Wach (Wach et al., 1994). Segundo este artigo, é 

possível obter transformantes por recombinação com um mínimo de 35 pb de homologia 

com a região que se pretende substituir. Entretanto, esta metodologia não se mostrou 

eficiente para transformação de linhagens industriais. Para se obter sucesso na 

transformação e recombinação foi necessária a construção de um cassete com uma maior 

região de homologia. As dificuldades encontradas em se transformar linhagens industriais 

não são conhecidas. Elas devem ter algumas características peculiares que dificultam o 

processo de transformação e integração quando comparada com as linhagens de laboratório. 

Para isso uma nova metodologia foi escolhida, a do double-joint PCR. 

Nesse caso, o cassete foi construído com uma região de homologia de 143 bp na 

região 5’ do gene PET191’e de 245 bp na região 3’ do gene PET191. Depois da 

transformação por eletroporação, diversas colônias apresentaram crescimento no meio com 

o antibiótico G418 e foram separadas para confirmação da integração por PCR. Como 

mostra a figura 23, as colônias 2, 3 e 4 confirmaram a inserção e foram usadas nos 

experimentos posteriores, enquanto as colônias 5 e 6 não apresentaram deleção do gene 

PET191. 

 

 



 63

 
FIGURA 23. PCR de confirmação da integração do cassete e conseqüente deleção do gene 
PET191. (1) marcador peso molecular, ?hind; (2 a 4) banda de 2,4 Kb indicando a inserção do gene 
KAN substituindo o gene PET191; e (5 e 6) banda de 1,4 Kb, indicando apenas o tamanho do gene 
PET191. 

 

Para a obtenção do outro tipo de deficiente respiratório, também 100% deficiente, 

(petite mitocondrial ou citoplasmático - ?0), as células foram crescidas e posteriormente 

tratadas com brometo de etídio. As colônias selecionadas são incapazes de crescer usando 

glicerol como fonte de carbono, não apresentando crescimento em meio YPG. Esse tipo de 

petite tem a taxa de crescimento menor quando comparada com as células normais, se 

apresentado como pequenas colônias quando plaqueadas.  

Todos os mutantes respiratórios produzidos, tanto nucleares (testado previamente 

também por PCR) quanto o mitocondrial, foram confirmados pela técnica de cobertura por 

TTC. A figura 24 mostra duas linhagens testadas, FY23 e JAY292. As colônias 1 e 5 são os 

controles (células normais) e a coloração rosa confirma a capacidade de respirar. As demais 

colônias sem coloração são deficientes respiratórios: petites nucleares (2, 6) e petites 

mitocondriais (3, 4, 7, 8).   

 

 

 
FIGURA 24. Técnica de cobertura com TTC. As colônias rosa têm a capacidade de respirar e as 
brancas são deficientes respiratórias. (1) JAY292; (2) JAY292?pet191; (3) JAY292-EtBr-a; (4) 
JAY292-EtBr-b; (5) FY23; (6) FY23?pet191; (7) FY23-EtBr-a; (8) FY23-EtBr-b.  
 



 64

 As linhagens transformadas e os mutantes produzidos foram utilizados para a 

realização dos ensaios fermentativos. 

 

Ensaios Fermentativos 

 Foram feitas 4 fermentações consecutivas, reutilizando as mesmas células, em caldo 

de cana esterilizado (a porcentagem de açucares redutores totais foi diluído para 

aproximadamente 18%), simulando as mesmas condições das usinas.  

 O mutante petite mitocondrial (?0) tem a taxa de crescimento menor (dados não 

mostrados) e isso pode também ser visualizado na placa, pois suas colônias apresentam 

tamanho bem inferior às colônias de células normais, devido a esse fato elas são chamadas 

de petites. O petite nuclear (?pet191), interessantemente, nas linhagens FY23 e JAY292 

não apresentaram diferenças muito significativas na taxa de crescimento, quando 

comparada com as células normais (Figura 25). Esse mesmo fato foi observado por Hutter 

&amp;amp; Oliver (Hutter &amp;amp; Oliver, 1998). Apenas os mutantes da linhagem JAY291 apresentaram 

uma taxa de crescimento menor. Possivelmente esta última, por ser um haplóide derivado 

da esporulação da JAY270, apresenta algumas características diferentes do outro haplóide 

(JAY292), que acaba ficando mais acentuado após a deleção do gene PET191. 

  

 
FIGURA 25. Curva de crescimento das linhagens FY23, JAY291 e JAY292 com seus respectivos 
mutantes (?pet191).  
 

Foi comparada a produção de etanol entre as células normais e os dois tipos de 

mutantes produzidos. 

Os gráficos da figura 26 mostram os resultados das 4 bateladas consecutivas. A 

primeira batelada de todos os ensaios apresenta uma menor produção de etanol devido a 



 65

adaptação das leveduras ao meio de fermentação. Pois inicialmente o aumento da massa 

celular do inoculo foi preparado em meio YEPD.  

 Na fermentação feita com linhagens de laboratório é possível observar os melhores 

resultados (Figura 26). Células tratadas com brometo de etídio, FY23EtBr, já iniciaram a 

fermentação com alta produtividade. O petite nuclear, FY23?pet191, e as células normais, 

iniciam a fermentação com uma produção reduzida e depois de alguns ciclos a 

produtividade se estabiliza. Na última batelada houve uma diminuição da produção de 

etanol pelo mutante tratado com brometo. Mas isso provavelmente foi decorrente de 

oscilações normais presentes no processo de fermentação. O controle FY23 naturalmente é 

uma linhagem ruim para a fermentação.  

Essa diferença na produtividade entre células normais e petites é mais evidente, pois 

a linhagem FY23 apresenta sempre uma baixa taxa de produção de etanol. Isto pode ser 

visualizada quando se analisam os dados de todas as fermentações juntas (Figura 27). O 

aumento da produtividade em FY23?pet191 e FY23EtBr foi de 7,4% e 11,8% 

respectivamente, comparado com as células normais FY23. 

As duas linhagens haplóides petites JAY291 e JAY292 apresentam a mesma 

tendência durante os ensaios fermentativos. Na primeira batelada que seria o período de 

adaptação ao meio, é mais rápido ou é menos afetado pelas linhagens petite, especialmente 

o petite mitocondrial. Já na segunda batelada, os dois petites se destacam mais 

acentuadamente, principalmente na linhagem JAY292. Após a terceira batelada há uma 

tendência de se igualar a produtividade entre os mutantes e o controle.  



 66

 
FIGURA 26. Fermentação com caldo de cana. Os gráficos representam 4 bateladas de fermentação 
com o reciclo de células e cada barra representa a média das triplicatas. A porcentagem de etanol 
produzido mostrado no gráfico foi normalizada com o valor máximo teórico, que depende da 
quantidade inicial de glicose. 



 67

As linhagens haplóides industriais (JAY291 e JAY292) se mostram bons 

fermentadores da mesma foram que o diplóide que os originou e por isso o aumento na 

produtividade de etanol pelos dois tipos de mutantes é menor do que as observadas nas 

linhagens de laboratório. O haplóide, JAY292, tem uma maior capacidade fermentativa, 

produzindo 4,0% e 5,2% mais etanol em JAY292?pet191 e JAY292EtBr, respectivamente, 

comparado com células normais. O outro haplóide, JAY291, teve um aumento de 1,5% e 

4% pelos mutantes, JAY291?pet191 e JAY291EtBr, respectivamente (Figura 27 e tabela 

5). 

 

 
FIGURA 27. Total de etanol produzido durante o todo o período do experimento. O gráfico mostra 
a média de todas as repetições e de todas as bateladas. Na tabela, é mostrada a produção total e o 
aumento de produção pelos mutantes. A porcentagem de aumento é referente à respectiva linhagem 
controle. 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 



 68

TABELA 5. Rendimento total e o aumento de produção de etanol pelos mutantes. A porcentagem 
de aumento é referente à respectiva linhagem controle. 

Linhagem Rendimento (%) % de aumento 
FY23 78,24 - 

FY23?pet191 84,00 7,36 
FY23EtBr 87,46 11,78 
JAY291 81,31 - 

JAY291?pet191 82,52 1,49 
JAY291EtBr 84,66 4,12 

JAY292 82,04 - 
JAY292?pet191 85,31 3,99 

JAY292EtBr 86,27 5,15 
  

 A perda funcional do DNA mitocondrial (petite citoplasmático) torna as células 

incapazes de crescer por meio da respiração, mas isso pode ser suprido pois as leveduras 

podem crescer utilizando fontes de carbono fermentáveis, e as células não estão sujeitas ao 

efeito Pasteur (inibição da glicólise pela fosforilação oxidativa ou a inibição da fermentação 

pela adição de oxigênio) (Slonimski et al., 1968).  Apesar disso, a ausência do DNA 

mitocondrial pode provocar muitas alterações deletérias nas características da superfície da 

célula, como a redução na captação dos açucares, alteração da floculação e aglutinação, 

diminuição da tolerância ao etanol por afetar as proteínas da membrana plasmática (Wilkie 

&amp;amp; Evans, 1982). Os petites citoplasmáticos provavelmente não sobreviveriam às condições 

das dornas de fermentação, devido às condições altamente estressantes. 

A vantagem do petite nuclear (?pet191) é que os genes presentes na mitocôndria 

continuam intactos e todas as outras funções da mitocôndria permanecem funcionais 

aumentando a probabilidade das células colonizarem as dornas de fermentação. Além disso, 

a deleção do gene PET191 não promove alteração na taxa de crescimento. O fato de a 

linhagem possuir uma taxa de crescimento semelhante ao selvagem é uma vantagem, pois 

não altera o tempo para a produção do inoculo. Um atraso na taxa de crescimento implica 

em um maior tempo na produção do inoculo e conseqüentemente um gasto maior pra usina. 

E ainda, devido a essa deficiência respiratória, o petite não é capaz de metabolizar o etanol 

como substrato secundário, permitindo assim manter todo o etanol produzido. 

 

 

 



 69

CONCLUSÃO 

 Linhagens de laboratório e industriais petites apresentaram um aumento de 

rendimento na produção de etanol. 

 As linhagens industriais modificadas com as características desejáveis têm a 

possibilidade de dominar o processo durante todo o período da safra. As leveduras 

industriais sem o gene PET191, tiveram um aumento de 4% na produção, baseando-se na 

linhagem JAY292. No Brasil, onde a produção anual é cerca de 24,5 bilhões de litros de 

etanol, este aumento de porcentagem representaria um aumento de 980 milhões de litros 

por ano, que é muito significativo. 

 Novos experimentos serão feitos para comprovar o efeito provocado pela deleção 

do gene PET191. Um deles é a cinética da produção de etanol durante a fermentação. 

Provavelmente os mutantes para o gene PET191 conseguiriam atingir o máximo de etanol 

produzido mais rápido que as linhagens que respiram. Isso diminuiria ainda mais o tempo 

necessário para que a fermentação ocorra. 

 

 

 



 70

CONCLUSÕES FINAIS 
 

 A melhoria do processo fermentativo pode ser obtida com o controle da expressão 

do gene da floculação. A regulação condicional do gene FLO5 foi obtida com sucesso, 

entretanto a impossibilidade de desfloculação inviabiliza a utilização deste gene no 

processo industrial. Além disso, a linhagem industrial transformada com a construção do 

gene FLO5 teve uma diminuição do rendimento fermentativo. Isso pode ter ocorrido, pois a 

integração da construção se deu no local do gene da arginina permease. Este gene não é 

essencial para a levedura, mas a redução ou interrupção na captação de arginina pode ter 

afetado a eficiência da linhagem na produção de etanol. 

 A utilização de outro gene da floculação, FLO10, também regulado 

condicionalmente, se mostrava promissor pois a proteína resultante deste gene seria 

inativado naturalmente pela glicose. Infelizmente, os resultados obtidos não foram os 

esperados. O gene FLO10  apresentou uma expressão basal durante toda a fermentação e os 

agregados produzidos não desfloculavam após nova adição de glicose. 

 Apesar disso, há a possibilidade de se utilizar linhagens floculantes na produção de 

cachaça e vinho, sem a necessidade de desfloculação, pois não há reuso de leveduras. 

 Durante o período do doutorado foi feito um trabalho em parceria com o 

pesquisador, Dr. Juan Argueso, com o objetivo de se estudar uma linhagem industrial, 

compreendendo sua fisiologia e genética. O resultado desse estudo gerou um artigo que foi 

aceito (agosto 2009) para publicação pela Genome Research (AnexoII). Foram encontrados 

vários fatores que podem estar relacionados com o melhor desempenho das leveduras 

industriais nas dornas. Este artigo começa a desvendar os “segredos do sucesso” das 

linhagens selvagens industriais brasileiras, abrindo oportunidades para futuras 

manipulações desses organismos.  

 A última etapa da tese, foi a deleção do gene PET191, que resultou em um aumento 

na produção de etanol nas linhagens de laboratório e industriais. A possibilidade da 

domesticação e manipulação de leveduras industriais visando uma maior produtividade do 

processo motiva a continuidade das pesquisas em busca de novos desafios. 



 71

REFERÊNCIAS BIBLIOGRÁFICAS 

Allen, F. (1994). The Microbrewery Laboratory Manual - Part III: Wild Yeats Detection 
and Remediation, BrewingTechniques. Vol. 2, No 6. 

Alper, H.; Moxley, J.; Nevoigt, E.; Fink, G. R.; Stephanopoulos, G. (2006). "Engineering 
yeast transcription machinery for improved ethanol tolerance and production." 
Science 314(5805): 1565-8. 

Ausubel, F. M.; Brent, R.; Kingston, R. E.; Moore, D. D.; Seidman, J. G.; Smith, A. J.; 
Struhl, K. (1998). Current Protocols in Molecular Biology. New York - USA, John 
Wiley &amp;amp; Sons Inc. 

Barney, M. C.; Jansen, G. P.; Helber, G. R. (1980). "Use of genetic transformation for the 
introduction of flocculence into yeast." J Am Soc Brew Chem 38: 71-74. 

Basso, L. C.; de Amorim, H. V.; de Oliveira, A. J.; Lopes, M. L. (2008). "Yeast selection 
for fuel ethanol production in Brazil." FEMS Yeast Res 8(7): 1155-63. 

Beier, D. R.; Sledziewski, A.; Young, E. T. (1985). "Deletion analysis identifies a region, 
upstream of the ADH2 gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae, which is required for 
ADR1-mediated derepression." Mol Cell Biol 5(7): 1743-9. 

Bester, M. C.; Pretorius, I. S.; Bauer, F. F. (2006). "The regulation of Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae FLO gene expression and Ca2+ -dependent flocculation by Flo8p and 
Mss11p." Curr Genet 49(6): 375-83. 

Bidard, F.; Blondin, B.; Dequin, S.; Vezinhet, F.; Barre, P. (1994). "Cloning and analysis of 
a FLO5 flocculation gene from Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Curr Genet 25(3): 196-
201. 

Borneman, A. R.; Forgan, A. H.; Pretorius, I. S.; Chambers, P. J. (2008). "Comparative 
genome analysis of a Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine strain." FEMS Yeast Res 8(7): 
1185-95. 

Branduardi, P.; Smeraldi, C.; Porro, D. (2008). "Metabolically engineered yeasts: 'potential' 
industrial applications." J Mol Microbiol Biotechnol 15(1): 31-40. 

Brunelli, J. P.; Pall, M. L. (1993). "A series of yeast shuttle vectors for expression of 
cDNAs and other DNA sequences." Yeast 9(12): 1299-308. 

Calleja, G. B. (1973). "Role of mitochondria in the sex-directed flocculation of a fission 
yeast." Arch Biochem Biophys 154(1): 382-6. 

Carreto, L.; Eiriz, M. F.; Gomes, A. C.; Pereira, P. M.; Schuller, D.; Santos, M. A. (2008). 
"Comparative genomics of wild type yeast strains unveils important genome 
diversity." BMC Genomics 9: 524. 



 72

Ciriacy, M. (1979). "Isolation and characterization of further cis- and trans-acting 
regulatory elements involved in the synthesis of glucose-repressible alcohol 
dehydrogenase (ADHII) in Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Mol Gen Genet 176(3): 
427-31. 

Cortez, L. A. B.; Lora, E. E. S.; Gómez, E. O. (2008). Biomassa para Energia, Editora 
Unicamp. 

Cunha, A. F.; Missawa, S. K.; Gomes, L. H.; Reis, S. F.; Pereira, G. A. (2006). "Control by 
sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation for industrial ethanol production." 
FEMS Yeast Res 6(2): 280-7. 

Denis, C. L.; Young, E. T. (1983). "Isolation and characterization of the positive regulatory 
gene ADR1 from Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Mol Cell Biol 3(3): 360-70. 

DeRisi, J. L.; Iyer, V. R.; Brown, P. O. (1997). "Exploring the metabolic and genetic 
control of gene expression on a genomic scale." Science 278(5338): 680-6. 

Devlin, T. M. (1997). Textbook of Biochemistry with clinical correlations, Wiley-Liss. 

Domingues, L.; Vicente, A. A.; Lima, N.; Teixeira, J. A. (2000). "Applications of yeast 
flocculation in biotechnological processes." Biotechnol Bioprocess Eng 5: 288-305. 

Eddy, A. A.; Rudin, A. D. (1958). "Part of the yeast surface apparently involved in 
flocculation." J. Inst. Brew.(64): 19-21. 

Egilsson, V.; Evans, I. H.; Wilkie, D. (1979). "Toxic and mutagenic effects of carcinogens 
on the mitochondria of Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Mol. Gen. Genet.(174): 39-46. 

Epstein, C. B.; Waddle, J. A.; Hale, W. t.; Dave, V.; Thornton, J.; Macatee, T. L.; Garner, 
H. R.; Butow, R. A. (2001). "Genome-wide responses to mitochondrial 
dysfunction." Mol Biol Cell 12(2): 297-308. 

Farrell, A. E.; Plevin, R. J.; Turner, B. T.; Jones, A. D.; O'Hare, M.; Kammen, D. M. 
(2006). "Ethanol can contribute to energy and environmental goals." Science 
311(5760): 506-8. 

Fox, T. D.; Folley, L. S.; Mulero, J. J.; McMullin, T. W.; Thorsness, P. E.; Hedin, L. O.; 
Costanzo, M. C. (1991). "Analysis and manipulation of yeast mitochondrial genes." 
Methods Enzymol 194: 149-65. 

Gibson, B. R.; Lawrence, S. J.; Leclaire, J. P.; Powell, C. D.; Smart, K. A. (2007). "Yeast 
responses to stresses associated with industrial brewery handling." FEMS Microbiol 
Rev 31(5): 535-69. 

Goffeau, A.; Barrell, B. G.; Bussey, H.; Davis, R. W.; Dujon, B.; Feldmann, H.; Galibert, 
F.; Hoheisel, J. D.; Jacq, C.; Johnston, M.; Louis, E. J.; Mewes, H. W.; Murakami, 



 73

Y.; Philippsen, P.; Tettelin, H.; Oliver, S. G. (1996). "Life with 6000 genes." 
Science 274(5287): 546, 563-7. 

Goldemberg, J. (2008). "The Brazilian biofuels industry." Biotechnol Biofuels 1(1): 6. 

Goldemberg, J.; Nigro, F. E. B.; Coelho, S. T. (2008). Bioenergia no Estado de São Paulo: 
situação atual, perspectivas, barreiras e propostas. São Paulo, Imprensa Oficial do 
Estado de São Paulo. 

Govender, P.; Domingo, J. L.; Bester, M. C.; Pretorius, I. S.; Bauer, F. F. (2008). 
"Controlled expression of the dominant flocculation genes FLO1, FLO5, and 
FLO11 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Appl Environ Microbiol 74(19): 6041-52. 

Griffiths, A. J. F.; Miller, J. H.; Suzuki, D. T.; Lewontin, R. C.; Gelbart, W. M. (1993). An 
Introduction to Genetics Analysis. New York, W. H. Freeman and Company. 

Guo, B.; Styles, C. A.; Feng, Q.; Fink, G. R. (2000). "A Saccharomyces gene family 
involved in invasive growth, cell-cell adhesion, and mating." Proc Natl Acad Sci U 
S A 97(22): 12158-63. 

Guo, Z. P.; Zhang, L.; Ding, Z. Y.; Wang, Z. X.; Shi, G. Y. (2009). "Interruption of 
glycerol pathway in industrial alcoholic yeasts to improve the ethanol production." 
Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 82(2): 287-92. 

Halme, A.; Bumgarner, S.; Styles, C.; Fink, G. R. (2004). "Genetic and epigenetic 
regulation of the FLO gene family generates cell-surface variation in yeast." Cell 
116(3): 405-15. 

Hinrichs, J.; Stahl, U.; Esser, K. (1988). "Flocculation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae and 
mitochondrial DNA structure." Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol 29: 48-54. 

Hutter, A.; Oliver, S. G. (1998). "Ethanol production using nuclear petite yeast mutants." 
Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol 49(5): 511-516. 

Ishida-Fujii, K.; Goto, S.; Sugiyama, H.; Takagi, Y.; Saiki, T.; Takagi, M. (1998). 
"Breeding of flocculent industrial alcohol yeast strains by self-cloning of the 
flocculation gene FLO1 and repeated-batch fermentation by transformants." J Gen 
Appl Microbiol 44(5): 347-353. 

Iung, A. R.; Coulon, J.; Kis, F.; Ekome, J. n. N.; Vallner, J.; Bonaly, R. (1999). 
"Mitochondrial function in cell wall glycoprotein synthesis in Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae NCYC 625 (Wild type) and [rho0] mutants." Applied and Enviromental 
Microbiology 65(12): 5398-5402. 

Jank, M. S. (2007). Da Alca para o álcool. O Estado de São Paulo. São Paulo: J3. 



 74

Johnston, J. R.; Reader, H. P. (1983). Genetic control of flocculation. Yeast genetics: 
Fundamental and applied aspects. J. F. T. Spencer, Spencer, D.M. and Smith, 
A.R.W. New York, Springer-Verlag: 205-224. 

Kobayashi, O.; Hayashi, N.; Kuroki, R.; Sone, H. (1998). "Region of FLO1 proteins 
responsible for sugar recognition." J Bacteriol 180(24): 6503-10. 

Kobayashi, O.; Suda, H.; Ohtani, T.; Sone, H. (1996). "Molecular cloning and analysis of 
the dominant flocculation gene FLO8 from Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Mol Gen 
Genet 251(6): 707-15. 

Lee, K. M.; DaSilva, N. A. (2005). "Evaluation of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae ADH2 
promoter for protein synthesis." Yeast 22(6): 431-40. 

Lima, U. A.; Aquarone E.; Borzani, W. (1975). Tecnologia das fermentações. 1: 48-59. 

Martinelli, A. (1983). Tecnologia de vinhos e vinagres de frutas. 

Mastrandrea, M. D.; Stephen, H. S. (2005). Global Warming, World Book Online 
Reference Center. 2009. 
http://www.worldbookonline.com/wb/Article?id=ar226310. 

Meleiro, L. A. C.; Maciel, R. (2000). "State and parameter estimation based on a nonlinear 
filter applied to an industrial process control of ethanol production." Braz J Chem 
Eng 17(4-7): 991-1001. 

Miki, B. L.; Poon, N. H.; James, A. P.; Seligy, V. L. (1982). "Possible mechanism for 
flocculation interactions governed by gene FLO1 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae." J 
Bacteriol 150(2): 878-89. 

Nelson, N. (1944). "A fotometric adaptaion of Somogyi method for the determination of 
glucose." J.Biol.Chen. 153: 375 - 380. 

Nevoigt, E. (2008). "Progress in metabolic engineering of Saccharomyces cerevisiae." 
Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 72(3): 379-412. 

Ooi, B. G.; Lankford, K. R. (2009). "Strategy for adapting wine yeasts for bioethanol 
production." Int J Mol Sci 10(1): 387-4. 

Otterstedt, K.; Larsson, C.; Bill, R. M.; Stahlberg, A.; Boles, E.; Hohmann, S.; Gustafsson, 
L. (2004). "Switching the mode of metabolism in the yeast Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae." EMBO Rep 5(5): 532-7. 

Panoutsopoulou, K.; Hutter, A.; Jones, P.; Gardner, D. C. J.; Oliver, S. G. (2001). 
"Improvement of Ethanol Production by an Industrial Yeast Strain via Multiple 
Gene Deletions." J Inst Brew 107(1): 49-53. 



 75

Pessoa-Jr, A.; Roberto, I. C.; Menossi, M.; dos Santos, R. R.; Filho, S. O.; Penna, T. C. 
(2005). "Perspectives on bioenergy and biotechnology in Brazil." Appl Biochem 
Biotechnol 121-124: 59-70. 

Price, V. L.; Taylor, W. E.; Clevenger, W.; Worthington, M.; Young, E. T. (1990). 
"Expression of heterologous proteins in Saccharomyces cerevisiae using the ADH2 
promoter." Methods Enzymol 185: 308-18. 

Rando, O. J.; Verstrepen, K. J. (2007). "Timescales of genetic and epigenetic inheritance." 
Cell 128(4): 655-68. 

Rojo, F. (2008). "Biofuels from microbes: a comprehensive view." Microbial 
Biotechnology 1(3): 208-210. 

Salomão, A.; Onaga, M. (2006). Etanol o mundo quer. O Brasil tem. Revista Exame. 0870. 

Sanchez, O. J.; Cardona, C. A. (2008). "Trends in biotechnological production of fuel 
ethanol from different feedstocks." Bioresour Technol 99(13): 5270-95. 

Shen, H.; Iha, H.; Yaguchi, S.; Tsurugi, K. (2006). "The mechanism by which 
overexpression of Gts1p induces flocculation in a FLO8-inactive strain of the yeast 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae." FEMS Yeast Res 6(6): 914-23. 

Slonimski, P. P.; Perrodin, G.; Croft, J. H. (1968). "Ethidium bromide induced mutation of 
yeast mitochondria: complete transformation of the cells into respiratory deficient 
non-chromosomal petites." Biochem Biophys Res Commun 30: 232-239. 

Somogyi, M. (1945). "A new reagent for determination sugars." A New Sugar Reagent 
May: 61 - 68. 

Stan, S.; Despa, F. (2000). "On the doublet formation in the flocculation process of the 
yeast cells." Biosystems 57(3): 139-45. 

Stratford, M. (1996a). "Induction of flocculation in brewing yeasts by change in pH value." 
FEMS Microbiol Lett 136(1): 13-8. 

Stratford, M. (1996b). "Yeast flocculation: reestruturing the theories in line with recent 
research." Cerevisia 21(1): 38-45. 

Teunissen, A. W.; Steensma, H. Y. (1995). "Review: the dominant flocculation genes of 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae constitute a new subtelomeric gene family." Yeast 
11(11): 1001-13. 

Tortora, G. J.; Funke, B. R.; Case, C. L. (2002). Microbiology - An Introduction, Benjamin 
Cummings. 



 76

Touhami, A.; Hoffmann, B.; Vasella, A.; Denis, F. A.; Dufrêne, Y. F. (2003). "Aggregation 
of yeast cells: direct measurement of discrete lectin-carbohydrate interactions." 
Microbiology 149: 2873-2878. 

Van Mulders, S. E.; Christianen, E.; Saerens, S. M.; Daenen, L.; Verbelen, P. J.; Willaert, 
R.; Verstrepen, K. J.; Delvaux, F. R. (2009). "Phenotypic diversity of Flo protein 
family-mediated adhesion in Saccharomyces cerevisiae." FEMS Yeast Res 9(2): 
178-90. 

Varela, C.; Cardenas, J.; Melo, F.; Agosin, E. (2005). "Quantitative analysis of wine yeast 
gene expression profiles under winemaking conditions." Yeast 22(5): 369-83. 

Verstrepen, K. J.; Derdelinckx, G.; Delvaux, F. R.; Winderickx, J.; Thevelein, J. M.; Bauer, 
F. F.; Pretorius, I. S. (2001). "Late fermentation expression of FLO1 in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Journal of the American Society of Brewing Chemists 
59(2): 69-76. 

Verstrepen, K. J.; Derdelinckx, G.; Verachtert, H.; Delvaux, F. R. (2003). "Yeast 
flocculation: what brewers should know." Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 61(3): 197-
205. 

Verstrepen, K. J.; Jansen, A.; Lewitter, F.; Fink, G. R. (2005). "Intragenic tandem repeats 
generate functional variability." Nat Genet 37(9): 986-90. 

Verstrepen, K. J.; Klis, F. M. (2006). "Flocculation, adhesion and biofilm formation in 
yeasts." Mol Microbiol 60(1): 5-15. 

Verstrepen, K. J.; Reynolds, T. B.; Fink, G. R. (2004). "Origins of variation in the fungal 
cell surface." Nat Rev Microbiol 2(7): 533-40. 

Wach, A.; Brachat, A.; Pohlmann, R.; Philippsen, P. (1994). "New heterologous modules 
for classical or PCR-based gene disruptions in Saccharomyces cerevisiae." Yeast 
10(13): 1793-808. 

Wackett, L. P. (2008). "Biomass to fuels via microbial transformations." Curr Opin Chem 
Biol 12(2): 187-93. 

Wang, F. Z.; Shen, W.; Rao, Z. M.; Fang, H. Y.; Zhan, X. B.; Zhuge, J. (2007). 
"Construction of a flocculating yeast for fuel ethanol production." Biotechnol Lett. 

Watari, J.; Kudo, M.; Ogawa, M.; Nishikawa, N.; Kamimura, M. (1989). "Molecular 
cloning of a flocculation gene in Sacharomyces cerevisiae." Agric Biol Chem 53: 
901-903. 

Wheals, A. E.; Basso, L. C.; Alves, D. M.; Amorim, H. V. (1999). "Fuel ethanol after 25 
years." Trends Biotechnol 17(12): 482-7. 



 77

Wilkie, D.; Evans, I. (1982). "Mitochondria and the yeast cell surface: implications for 
carcinogenesis." Trends Biochem Sci 7(4): 147 - 151. 

Winston, F.; Dollard, C.; Ricupero-Hovasse, S. L. (1995). "Construction of a set of 
convenient Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains that are isogenic to S288C." Yeast 
11(1): 53-5. 

Yu, J. H.; Hamari, Z.; Han, K. H.; Seo, J. A.; Reyes-Dominguez, Y.; Scazzocchio, C. 
(2004). "Double-joint PCR: a PCR-based molecular tool for gene manipulations in 
filamentous fungi." Fungal Genet Biol 41(11): 973-81. 

 

 

 

 

 

 



 78

ANEXO I 

 

 

 

 

 

 

INDUSTRIAL ASPECTS OF BIOETHANOL 

SECTION 2 
BIOTECHNOLOGY AND ENGINEERING SCIENCE INTEGRATION FOR 

CHEMICAL AND FUEL INDUSTRIES 
 

CHAPTER 4 
INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE 
PRODUCTION OF BIOETHANOL IN BRAZIL: THE EXAMPLE OF 

CONDITIONAL FLOCCULATION 
 

ANDERSON F. CUNHA, SILVIA K. MISSAWA AND GONÇALO A. G. PEREIRA 



INDUSTRIAL
PERSPECTIVES

FOR BIOETHANOL

ecamargo
Typewriter
79



DIRETORIA EXECUTIVA

Mauricio Prates de Campos Filho
Diretor Executivo

Nelson Antonio Pereira Camacho
Diretor para Assuntos Administrativos e Financeiros

Saul Gonçalves d’Ávila
Diretor para Assuntos Científicos e Tecnológicos

ecamargo
Typewriter
80



Edited by
Telma Teixeira Franco

INDUSTRIAL
PERSPECTIVES

FOR BIOETHANOL
Eduardo P. Carvalho   Isaias C. Macedo   José Luiz Olivério

Pedro Wongtschowski   Francisco I. Pellegrini   Flávio C. Cavalcanti
Anderson F. Cunha   Silvia K. Missawa   Gonçalo A. G. Pereira

Silvio R. Andrietta   Maria da Graça Stupiello Andrietta
Adrie J. J. Straathof   Çagri Efe   Luuk A. M. van der Wielen

Peter M. M. Nossin   Telma T. Franco   Carlos Eduardo Vaz Rossell
H. J. Veringa   P. Alderliesten

Coleção UN I E M P Inovação

ecamargo
Typewriter
81



Av. Paulista, 2.200 - 16o andar
Tel. (11) 2178-0466
Fax. (11) 3283-3386

uniemp@uniemp.org.br
www.uniemp.org.br

01310-300   São Paulo - SP

Produzido no Brasil
2006

ISBN 85-98951-06-4

INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

ecamargo
Typewriter
82



LIST OF CONTENTS

Preface
Telma T. Franco

9

Section 1
Industrial Perspectives for Bioethanol:

a Brazilian approach
11

Chapter 1
Ethanol from Sugar Cane in Brazil:

the Industrial Technology Perspectives
Eduardo P. Carvalho and Isaias C. Macedo

13

Chapter 2
Technological evolution of the Brazilian

sugar and alcohol sector:
Dedini’s contribution

José Luiz Olivério
19

Chapter 3
Insertion of bioethanol into a new paradigm

for the Brazilian chemical industry
Pedro Wongtschowski, Francisco I. Pellegrini

and Flávio C. Cavalcanti
33

ecamargo
Typewriter
83



Section 2
BioTechnology and Engineering Science integration

for Chemical and Fuel Industries
57

Chapter 4
Industrial Potential of Yeast Biotechnology
in the Production of Bioethanol in Brazil:
the Example of Conditional Flocculation
Anderson F. Cunha, Silvia K. Missawa

and Gonçalo A. G. Pereira
59

Chapter 5
Optimization and Limits of Ethanol Production

Silvio R. Andrietta
and Maria da Graça Stupiello Andrietta

77

Chapter 6
Innovation and sustainability through

industrial biotechnology
Adrie J. J. Straathof, Çagri Efe,

Luuk A. M. van der Wielen,
Peter M. M. Nossin and Telma T. Franco

91

Chapter 7
Advances of the Brazilian production of chemicals

and other products from biomass
Telma T. Franco

107

Section 3
Role of Bioethanol in the Energy Landscape

121

ecamargo
Typewriter
84



Chapter 8
Conversion of lignocellulose biomass (bagasse and straw)

from the sugar-alcohol industry into bioethanol
Carlos Eduardo Vaz Rossell

123

Chapter 9
Advanced techniques for generation of energy

from biomass and waste
H. J. Veringa and P. Alderliesten

143

ecamargo
Typewriter
85



Industrial Potential of Yeast Biotechnology
in the Production of Bioethanol in Brazil:
the Example of Conditional Flocculation

Anderson Ferreira da Cunha
Silvia Kazue Missawa

Gonçalo Amarante Guimarães Pereira

Introduction

The existence of life on earth as we know it is due fundamentally
to the reduction of CO2 levels primarily existing in the atmosphere, mainly
through the fixation of this compound into carbon chains. These long-
term processes combine with geologic events, although they are basically
biological activities.

Man as a species has developed in this rather milder atmosphere,
although his social and economic progress, in the last hundred years,
has reversed the direction of carbon fixation and is now jeopardizing
biological maintenance of the atmosphere. Since the introduction of fossil
fuels (gasoline, diesel, etc.) utilization, we have systematically released
gigantic amounts of carbonic gas back to the atmosphere effectively
reversing millions of years of carbon fixation. This means that our social
progress is taking us back to our biological environmental starting point,
which will certainly have major consequences.

In recent years a number of research studies, as well as scientific
and social organizations, have pointed to this problem, although without
much success. The largest producers of CO2 even admit that this process
is occurring, but up to now, they have only considered it as something
that will occur in the remote future. Within this context, weather changes

ecamargo
Typewriter
86



60 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

that have occurred in the past few years, particularly floods and the
record number of hurricanes, have brought to light an unmistakable
demonstration that the consequences of fossil fuels are already here.
Therefore, there is no more time to wait, alternative and renewable energy
sources must be found.

The history of economic events show that during great crises, great
opportunities arise and the ability to capitalize during these times is
key to economic success. In the specific scenario of the fuel crisis a
huge opportunity has been created for countries that have ample land,
sun and water. This is undoubtedly the case of Brazil.

Although most of the developed world has reached a situation that
is considered critical, with dependence on imported petroleum and alar-
ming and overwhelming natural phenomena linked to climate changes,
Brazil started take positive step to reduce this situation about 30 years
ago, for economical reasons. With the oil shortage that occurred in 1973
and 1979, oil prices rose from US$ 4.00 to US$ 40.00 per barrel.  Between
1973 and 1974, fuel costs jumped from US$ 600 million to over US$ 2
billion. This gigantic impact on the balance of payments showed the
strategic vulnerability of Brazil, which at the time was importing nearly
80% of the oil consumed by the Country, and therefore was highly sus-
ceptible to an energy collapse.

In 1975, Brazil launched Proalcool, the Brazilian Program for
Alcohol Fuel. Sugarcane alcohol soon provided an ideal alternative fuel
for gasoline. In order to make this program feasible, the Brazilian govern-
ment offered a financial plan that was supported by the World Bank,
which made it possible to increase the areas planted to sugarcane, build
new plants and develop and enlarge boiler shop industries (source:
UNICA, the Sao Paulo State Sugarcane Agribusiness Union –
www.unica.com.br).

Once available, this so-called green fuel was harnessed in two forms.
Initially, it was mixed with gasoline as anhydrous alcohol. This process
has increased the amount of alcohol in gasoline over time, i.e. the
gasoline distributed in Sao Paulo city changed from a 20% v/v mixture
in 1977 to 22% in 1980, which has been adopted all over the country
(Demetrius 1990). Also during this period the first cars that exclusively

ecamargo
Typewriter
87



61INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

utilized hydrated alcohol were introduced, unfortunately, these vehicles
used poorly adapted gasoline motors and were not well received. Only
during the 1980s, after the second oil shortage did automobile manu-
facturers launched new models that were especially manufactured to
work with alcohol. Also during this time alcohol prices were kept favo-
rable to gasoline, through governmental subsidies. The success of these
automobiles exceeded all predictions. In 1984, alcohol-powered cars re-
presented 94.4% of the assembly line production in Brazil, which accoun-
ted for 19 out of 20 cars.

However, this huge increase in demand was not maintained and com-
bined with increases in the Brazilian production of crude oil and the reduc-
tion in the world price of this commodity, there was limited interest in
maintaining the alcohol subsidies. Moreover, ethanol producers started
an irrational process of increasing prices, which led to a shortage of the
product, resulting in a lack of confidence in the consumer market. As a
combined consequence, the production of alcohol-powered cars fell from
88.4% in 1988 to 61% in 1989, to 19.9% in 1990 and finally to 0.3% in 1996.

However, in spite of the program’s limit adoption, the government
viewed this as strategically important to the country and kept alcohol
production at high levels. In 1991 a new federal law mandated the addi-
tion of 22% anhydrous alcohol to gasoline, which helped to promote the
production of ethanol for fuel purposes. Associated with this strategy,
environmental factors in cities like Sao Paulo, where air pollution had
reached alarming levels, could also be improved by the addition of alcohol
to gasoline.

More recently, the alcohol program has once again returned to the
spotlight, at first because a consistent and apparently irreversible in-
crease in the international crude oil prices and due to the development
of the so-called FLEX engines that are capable of burning hydrated
alcohol/gasoline mixture at any proportion. Cars with these new motors
have given Brazilian consumers a choice in which fuel to use and thus
a relevant power to resist increases in gasoline prices.

Thus, given the global demand for alternative fuels, Brazil now pre-
sents itself as the country capable of leading the world. Brazil has a huge
production capacity and has developed new technologies for production,

ecamargo
Typewriter
88



62 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

distribution and utilization of ethanol, as well as demonstrating increa-
sed implementation of these technologies. For example, the sugar mill
extract process has increased the amount of sugar that can be processed
from sugarcane. The sugar extraction index, that was 89%, at the be-
ginning of the Proalcool program, has reached 97% today. In parallel,
the sugarcane residues (bagasse) burning technology to produce energy
has been widely adopted, thus making approximately 95% of the sugar
mills self-sufficient in terms of electricity (van Haandel 2005), and in
some case providing excess electric that is redirected into the national
electrical networks.

However, there are still technological advances that remain to be
developed in order to maximize the inherently biological processes. In
the case of sugarcane, over the last few years an intensive research
effort has been developed to improve the plant. Genomics have been
used to in an attempt to understand the biochemical processes connected
to the plant’s physiology, and these have lead to potential features of
agronomic importance (Vettore et al. 2003; Vincentz et al. 2004). This
advancement has led to the recent creation of companies focused on the
use of biotechnology in the development of new cultivated varieties, as
in the case of Canavialis (www.canavialis.com.br). Curiously, this has
not happened in the case of Saccharomyces cerevisiea. Even though this
yeast is an essential part in fermentation, very little research has been
done to improve its efficiency and specificity. This lack of research pre-
sents huge opportunities for biotechnological improves. This issue will
be discussed in detail in the following items.

The Biochemistry of Ethanol Production

The ethanol production process in Brazil occurs almost exclusively
by fermentation of sugarcane juice by yeasts, mainly the Saccharomyces
cerevisiae species, an organism that, given its technological importance,
is widely used as an experimental model to understand eukaryotic cells
(Goffeau et al. 1996).

Biochemically, alcohol fermentation is the degradation of hexoses
into ethanol with the  production of 2 ATP molecules in the process. In

ecamargo
Typewriter
89



63INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

the case of sugarcane juice, the fermentation process metabolizes the
disaccharide sucrose that is formed by one molecule of fructose and one
molecule of glucose. The first step is the hydrolysis of sucrose by inver-
tase enzyme that is encoded by the SUC2 gene. Both glucose and fructose
enter the glycolytic pathway and are converted into pyruvate via a se-
quence of reactions (Figure 1).  Pyruvate is then decarboxylated to form
acetaldehyde and this releases CO2 and causes intense bubbling when
the cells are grown in liquid medium. Later, the acetaldehyde molecule
is reduced to ethanol, and this reaction is catalyzed by the enzyme alcohol
dehydrogenase 1 (ADH1). The glucose depletion results in the end of
the fermentation phase.  During this period the yeast cells vigorously
multiply, which is characterized by an exponential growth phase. From
the depletion point on the yeasts seem to enter a stationary phase, but
they actually continue to grow for a long period, and actually consume
the ethanol previously produced through respiration. This change from
fermentation metabolism into respiratory metabolism is called diauxic
shift, which involves intense genetic reprogramming (De Risi et al. 1997;
Lashkari et al. 1997), and is based on an increase in the transcription of
certain genes and repression of others.

To better understand these processes it is important to briefly men-
tion how these genes are organized and how they work. Basically, the
genes that encode proteins are organized into two independent regions,
namely, a promoter region and a coding region.  The promoter region is
responsible for the transcription regulation that defines when a gene
should be switched on or off. When the gene is switched on, in a portion
close to the coding region, a messenger RNA (mRNA) starts to form and
copies the information from the coding region, which will be translated
later into a protein by ribosomes. It is fundamental to note that these
regions of the gene act independently and may be interchangeable
through genetic engineering, for example, leading to the formation of
new genes with unique expression patterns (Lewin 1990).

In particular, the growth in a medium containing glucose leads to
the repression of a series of genes involved with respiration and the use
of alternative sources of carbon. The SUC2 gene is repressed under these
conditions, thus preventing the release of further amounts of glucose

ecamargo
Typewriter
90



64 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

and fructose stored in the sucrose molecule (Gancedo 1998). The ADH1
gene, on the other hand, is induced by this sugar.

The end of fermentation activates a set of genes required for respi-
ration and leads to intense multiplication of mitochondria (Mahler et
al. 1975; Ulery et al. 1994). In particular, the absence of glucose in the
medium activates the transcription of ADH2 (alcohol dehydrogenase 2)
gene (Ciriacy 1979). The enzyme produced by the expression of this gene
oxidizes ethanol to acetaldehyde via the reverse of the ADH1 pathway;
acetaldehyde is then converted into acetate, which participates in the
later stages of the Krebs cycle that is the major aerobic respiration cycle
(Devlin 1997) (Figure 1).

Figure 1. Schematic diagram of the fermentation and respiration reactions.  The dotted
arrows indicate the pathway that is activated after glucose depletion (ethanol oxidation).
PDC1, 5, 6: pyruvate decarboxylase; PDA1, PDB1, PDX1, LPD1, LAT1: enzymes form
the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex; ALD6: aldehyde dehydrogenase; ACS1: acetyl-
CoA synthetase; ADH1: alcohol dehydrogenase 1; ADH2: alcohol dehydrogenase 2.

ecamargo
Typewriter
91



65INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

Industrial Production of Ethanol

An interesting question is: why do yeasts produce ethanol? This
would seem to be a waste if we consider it from the energetic perspective;
respiration produces a much higher amount of energy compared to fer-
mentation. However, from the strategic perspective, this seems to have
been an effective evolutionary pathway. After all, only a few organisms
are able to live in high concentrations of ethanol, a compound that is
largely used as an antisepsis. While the yeast developed the ability to
produce high concentrations of ethanol, the species also developed a
system to resist this compound. Therefore, during theproduction of etha-
nol, the yeast can reduce significantly the competition from other orga-
nisms for the existing substrates and afterwards can consume the ethanol
that was produced; while waiting for new stocks of sugar to be made
available. If we look at the natural environments, this seems to be the
logical strategy used by yeasts in fruits like grapes. As fruits fall from
the vine, an environment is created that is similar to a fermentation
vat, where ethanol is rapidly produced in large amounts. When new
fruits fall from the vine this provides new stocks of sugar, and the entire
cycle begins again. This parallel shows that the industrial fermentation
of alcohol is just a scaled increase of a natural phenomenon. This process
is not a human invention, but rather a human discovery.

Industrially, the production of alcohol follows basically two pro-
cesses: fed-batch and continuous fermentation, with the first being the
most used. In the fed-batch process, fermentation occurs in independent
vats, beginning with low concentrations of yeast cells and high concen-
trations of substrate. The whole mixture of must (mixture of sugarcane
juice and molasses), nutrients and yeast is added to the vat and after
approximately 8 hours, once the fermentation has ended, the entire
contents are removed and centrifuged. The “wine” – a name used in the
sugar mills industry to indicate the fermented sugarcane juice without
the yeast – is conveyed to the distillation towers, while the yeast milk,
that is, the yeast broth obtained by centrifugation, is subjected to a
decontamination treatment in the treatment vat consisting of a lowering
of the pH with concentrated sulfuric acid. The yeast is then returned to

ecamargo
Typewriter
92



66 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

the vat and a new load of must is added, to start a new fermentation cycle
(Wheals et al. 1999) (Figure 2).

Figure 2. The fed-batch process of ethanol production. The whole mixture of must,
nutrients and yeast is added to the vat and, once the fermentation has ended, the
whole contents are removed and centrifuged. The wine is distilled and the yeast milk is
returned to the vat, where a new load of must is added, starting a new fermentation
cycle.

To start the fermentation, the original yeast used by sugar mills is
usually multiplied under sterile conditions up to 50 liters and sent to a
pilot stage until it reaches the volume required to start the production.
This volume varies according to the size of the mill and can reach a
value of up to 600,000 liters (Zarpelon and Andrietta 1992, Wheals et
al. 1999).

An important observation that was only recently ascertained was
that, although the yeast is inoculated at high levels, in some sugar
mills it is rapidly replaced with wild yeast strains within a few fermen-

ecamargo
Typewriter
93



67INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

tation cycles and is then maintained until the end of the cropping season
(da Silva Filho et al. 2005). In many cases this replacement is not even
noted and there is no decrease in the productivity of the mill, possibly
because the invading yeasts are better adapted to the conditions of the
mill. Recently we have detected this fact in a large sugar mill in the
Campinas region that for many years had been inoculating a strain to
start the crop, and after a few weeks this strain was replaced with a
wild strain that increased the process. This fact demonstrates clearly
the low importance given to the fermentation agent, which is considered
an abiotic factor. These factors may actually open up new opportunities
for the development of new technological advances for improving the
yeast strains used.

The Yeast

This microorganism has been used in the production of bread and
beverages for centuries. Since the nineteenth century it became an im-
portant experimental model, to the extent that it was the first eukaryotic
organism to have its genome fully sequenced (Goffeau et al. 1996; Go-
ffeau 1998), which tremendously simplified investigations to understand
its metabolism. Moreover, Saccharomyces cerevisiae is an organism that
can be easily genetically manipulated, which has led to a systematic de-
letion of all of its genes, either individually or in combination, in order
to analyze their functions and determine how their products interact
(Dujon 1998; Hauser et al. 1998). Full information is available for real
time searches at the site www.yeastgenome.org.

The effective production of ethanol requires that yeasts included in
the process have some essential characteristics such as: (1) ability to
ferment rapidly and, effectively produce ethanol; (2) a high tolerance to
ethanol; (3) a high osmotolerance (ability to ferment concentrated so-
lutions of carbohydrates such as, for example, sugar molasses used in
many sugar mills to produce ethanol); (4) genetic stability; (5) cellular
viability and tolerance toward repeated fermentation cycles; (6) tolerance
to temperature variations; (7) a high competitive capacity.  There are
several yeast species capable of producing ethanol on a large scale;

ecamargo
Typewriter
94



68 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

however, over 97% of processes involve the use of the species Saccha-
romyces cerevisiae (Stewart et al. 1987).

Therefore based on the knowledge we have of this organism, it is
possible to manipulate it genetically to adequate it even further to the
fermentation process.  Several methods that have been used in the past
have been to employed classical methods such as: cross hybridizations,
selection and isolation of new strains.

The advent of molecular biology and the development of genetic
engineering techniques made it possible to manipulate genes to increase
the possibility of changing undesired characteristics or adding new desira-
ble ones. Through transformation of an organism with modified genes,
it is now possible to make the organism express certain characteristics
that are not identified in natural populations. This means that it could
be possible to build strains with specific functions, for industrial uses.

Yeast flocculation and its use in alcohol fermentation processes

A phenomenon that plays an important role in industrial production
is yeast flocculation, that can be defined as the ability of certain strains
to aggregate and form multicell masses that will separate by
sedimentation or flotation (Stratford 1996; Stan and Despa 2000). This
feature has been employed successfully in the beer industry to facilitate
the removal of cells once the fermentation has ended (Stratford 1996).
This precedent makes us think about it could possibly be used in a similar
fashion in the ethanol production industry, since it would eliminate the
need for centrifugation, an expensive and complicated step in the process.

In fact, this idea has led to the development of industrial procedures
of alcohol production based on flocculating yeasts (Domingues et al. 2000,
Domingues et al. 2001, Kondo et al. 2002). However, it was shown that
continuous flocculation has a series of disadvantages and can lead to a
reduction in the overall production of ethanol, as well as to in-process
problems such as duct clogging (Stratford 1992, Verstrepen et al. 2003).

The physical and genetic mechanism of flocculation has been widely
studied in recent years (Verstrepen et al. 2003). It involves primarily the
interaction of surface proteins of a certain lecithin-like, sugar-binding

ecamargo
Typewriter
95



69INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

cell, with exposed sugar residues on surrounding cells. Thus, a cell pro-
ducing a flocculation protein is capable of interacting with cells that do
not produce the protein, and interact with the exposed sugars of those
cells (Stratford and Carter 1993) (Figure 3).

Figure 3. Schematic diagram of flocculation mechanism showing that all cells have
sugar residues on their cell walls and that, after glucose (C6H12O6) depletion, flocculin
– the flocculation-related protein – is formed.

Several genes have been genetically identified as being responsible
for flocculation. Such genes express proteins called flocculins. The control
mechanism for flocculins and proteins encoded them is different and
has been intensely studied (Cormack 2004; Halme et al. 2004). The option
used by industry has been to control flocculation by using engineering
solutions. However, it seems that there is a huge potential for using
biotechnological techniques to develop strains more adequate to the
industrial process.

Based on this, we developed the following scenario: the ideal yeast
should be perfectly soluble in the medium while this medium would
include a fermentation substrate, i.e. sugar. The cells would be able to
efficiently exploit this substrate because they would multiply and reach
the maximum total contact surface. However, once the sugar was deple-
ted, ideally we should have the opposite response, that is, the cells would
aggregate and be deposited on the bottom of the vat. This would prevent
ethanol consumption and the cells could be separate naturally, thus
eliminating the need for centrifugation.

To determine if this idea was viable we used laboratory strains of
S. cerevisiae, which are easily manipulated. At the same time we created
a hybrid gene containing the promoter region of the ADH2 gene asso-

ecamargo
Typewriter
96



70 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

ciated with the coding region of the FLO5 flocculation gene. From this
point on we had a desired effect. As mentioned before, the ADH2 gene
promoter is repressed by glucose, and induced when this sugar is depleted
from the medium. This mechanism selectively insures that the cells will
continue to produce ethanol while preventing its oxidization to acetal-
dehyde when there is a flow in the opposite direction (Figure 1). At this
point the flocculin encoded by the FLO5 gene is produced, and mobilized
to the cell surface thus leading to a synchronized sedimentation (Figure
4). Starting with this simple system we were able to achieve a situation
where we could sense the sugar levels in the medium, quench the fermen-
tation at the appropriate moment and removing the yeast cells at that
point. In a broader sense, we developed intelligent yeast – or, at least,
smart yeast.

Figure 4. Expression of FLO5 gene under the control of the ADH2 gene promoter regu-
latory region.
1- Wild strain; 2- Wild strain with the flocculation gene controlled by glucose levels; 3-
Wild strain with constitutively activated flocculation gene. A. Culture medium with
glucose; B. Culture medium after glucose depletion. As shown in the figure, the strain
whose flocculation gene is controlled by glucose levels is deposited after carbohydrate
depletion.

ecamargo
Typewriter
97



71INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

This prototype worked perfectly in the laboratory, was patented
(INPI # 0001122), and was awarded a Honorable Mention in the 2000
issue of the National Contest of Brazilian Inventions. It was the only
laureate invention in the biotechnology area.

However, we know that a huge challenge is in front of us. As
mentioned before, in the fermentation vats there is strong competition
among microorganisms, and only the best-adapted strains reside in the
process. Thus, our invention has no potential to produce a default strain
that could be largely employed. On the contrary, we must be capable of
identifying specific strains from the different sugar mills and modify
them genetically so that they acquire the ability to flocculate according
to the schematic diagram shown above. Recently we achieved this in the
first industrial strains (Cunha et al. 2006) by integrating the flocculation
cassette into the arginine permease gene present in all isolates of the
species. This makes cells resistant to a drug called canavanine, allowing
the selection of the transforming agents. However, the production of
alcohol using these transforming agents is still unsatisfactory, and is
the object of intense investigation.

Additionally, our laboratory team is committed to developing strains
that are more resistant to ethanol and less capable of consume this
compound. Theoretically, this can be achieved by deleting a few already-
identified genes. This is an ongoing study and preliminary results are
not yet ready to be disclosed at this time. With these first steps accom-
plished we are hopeful that it is possible to achieve higher concentrations
of ethanol in the fermentation stage.

Conclusion

Based on all current information, it appears that the demand for
ethanol is no longer a national issue, but a global concern. This change
in scale suggests that future ethanol programs will need to have a lot more
stability than previous programs in order to meet future requirements.
Thus, the search for an increase in ethanol production and in the efficacy
of the process will dramatically increase and will be an opportunity for
Brazil to develop high tech solutions on its own. Innovative improve-

ecamargo
Typewriter
98



72 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

ments have already been made to fermentation engineering and the
automotive industry, particularly with the launching of FLEX fuel cars.
However, major advances in the biological process of fermentation, or
more specifically in the genetics of the yeast S. cerevisiae have yet to be
accomplished. This report presents the development of conditional floccu-
lating yeasts that have the potential of eliminating the need for centri-
fugation from the industrial fermentation process. When this system is
available on the industrial scale, the possibility of having small alcohol/
sugar mills spread all over the country using the fed-batch production
process, will be feasible since the costly centrifugation step will be repla-
ced with genetically modified “smart yeast”.

Anderson Ferreira da Cunha, Silvia Kazue Missawa
and Gonçalo Amarante Guimarães Pereira

Institute of Biology, Department of Genetics and Evolution
State University of Campinas - UNICAMP

Campinas, SP – Brazil

ecamargo
Typewriter
99



73INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

References

Ciriacy M (1979).  Isolation and characterization of further cis- and
trans-acting regulatory elements involved in the synthesis of glucose-
repressible alcohol dehydrogenase (ADHII) in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.
Mol Gen Genet 176(3): 427-31.

Cormack B (2004).  Can you adhere me now? Good.  Cell 116(3):
353-4.

Cunha AF, Missawa SK, Gomes LH, Reis SF, Pereira GA (2006).
Control by sugar of Saccharomyces cerevisiae flocculation for industrial
ethanol production. FEMS Yeast Res 6(2): 280-7.

da Silva-Filho EA, Brito dos Santos SK, Resende Ado M, de Morais
JO, de Morais MA, Jr., Ardaillon Simoes D (2005). Yeast population
dynamics of industrial fuel-ethanol fermentation process assessed by
PCR-fingerprinting.  Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek 88(1): 13-23.

Demetrius FJ (1990). Brazil’s national alcohol program: technology
and development in authoritarian regime. New York.

DeRisi JL, Iyer VR and Brown PO (1997).  Exploring the metabolic
and genetic control of gene expression on a genomic scale. Science
278(5338): 680-6.

Devlin TM (1997). Textbook of Biochemistry with clinical corre-
lations, Wiley-Liss.

Domingues L, Lima N, Teixeira JA (2001).  Alcohol production from
cheese whey permeate using genetically modified flocculent yeast cells.
Biotechnol Bioeng 72(5): 507-14.

Domingues L, Vicente AA, Lima N, Teixeira JA (2000).  Applications
of yeast flocculation in biotechnological processes.  Biotechnol Bioprocess
Eng 5: 288-305.

Dujon B (1998).  European Functional Analysis Network (EUROFAN)
and the functional analysis of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome.
Electrophoresis 19(4): 617-24.

Gancedo JM (1998).  Yeast carbon catabolite repression.  Microbiol
Mol Biol Rev 62(2): 334-61.

Goffeau A (1998).  [The yeast genome]. Pathol Biol (Paris) 46(2):
96-7.

ecamargo
Typewriter
100



74 INDUSTRIAL PERSPECTIVES FOR BIOETHANOL

Goffeau A, Barrell BG, Bussey H, Davis RW, Dujon B, Feldmann H,
Galibert F, Hoheisel JD, Jacq C, Johnston M, Louis EJ, Mewes HW, Mura-
kami Y, Philippsen P, Tettelin H, Oliver SG (1996).  Life with 6000 genes.
Science 274(5287): 546, 563-7.

Halme A, Bumgarner S, Styles C, Fink GR (2004). Genetic and
epigenetic regulation of the FLO gene family generates cell-surface varia-
tion in yeast. Cell 116(3): 405-15.

Hauser NC, Vingron M, Scheideler M, Krems B, Hellmuth K, Entian
KD, Hoheisel JD (1998).  Transcriptional profiling on all open reading
frames of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 14(13): 1209-21.

Kondo A, Shigechi H, Abe M, Uyama K, Matsumoto T, Takahashi S,
Ueda M, Tanaka A, Kishimoto M, Fukuda H (2002). High-level ethanol
production from starch by a flocculent Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain
displaying cell-surface glucoamylase.  Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 58(3):
291-6.

Lashkari DA, DeRisi JL, McCusker JH, Namath AF, Gentile C, Hwang
SY, Brown PO, Davis RW (1997). Yeast microarrays for genome wide
parallel genetic and gene expression analysis.  Proc Natl Acad Sci USA
94(24): 13057-62.

Lewin B (1990).  Commitment and activation at pol II promoters: a
tail of protein-protein interactions.  Cell 61(7): 1161-4.

Mahler HR, Assimos K, Lin CC (1975).  Derepression in Saccharo-
myces cerevisiae can be dissociated from cellular proliferation and deoxy-
ribonucleic acid synthesis. J Bacteriol 123(2): 637-41.

Stan S, Despa F (2000).  On the doublet formation in the flocculation
process of the yeast cells. Biosystems 57(3): 139-45.

Stewart GG, Russel I, Klein RD, Hiebsch RR (1987). Biological Re-
search on Industrial Yeasts.

Stratford M (1992). Yeast flocculation: a new perspective. Adv Microb
Physiol 33: 2-71.

Stratford M (1996).  Induction of flocculation in brewing yeasts by
change in pH value. FEMS Microbiology Letters 136: 13-18.

Stratford M (1996).  Yeast flocculation: restructuring the theories
in line with recent research. Cerevisia 21(1): 38-45.

ecamargo
Typewriter
101



75INDUSTRIAL POTENTIAL OF YEAST BIOTECHNOLOGY IN THE PRODUCTION...

Stratford M, Carter AT (1993).  Yeast flocculation: lectin synthesis
and activation. Yeast 9(4): 371-8.

Ulery TL, Jang SH, Jaehning JA (1994).  Glucose repression of yeast
mitochondrial transcription: kinetics of derepression and role of nuclear
genes. Mol Cell Biol 14(2): 1160-70.

van Haandel AC (2005).  Integrated energy production and reduction
of the environmental impact at alcohol distillery plants.  Water Sci
Technol 52(1-2): 49-57.

Verstrepen KJ, Derdelinckx G, Verachtert H, Delvaux FR (2003).  Yeast
flocculation: what brewers should know.  Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 61(3):
197-205.

Vettore AL, da Silva FR, Kemper EL, Souza GM, da Silva AM, Ferro
MI, Henrique-Silva F, Giglioti EA, Lemos MV, Coutinho LL, Nobrega MP,
Carrer H, Franca SC, Bacci Junior M, Goldman MH, Gomes SL, Nunes LR,
Camargo LE, Siqueira WJ, Van Sluys MA, Thiemann OH, Kuramae EE,
Santelli RV, Marino CL, Targon ML, Ferro JA, Silveira HC, Marini DC,
Lemos EG, Monteiro-Vitorello CB, Tambor JH, Carraro DM, Roberto PG,
Martins VG, Goldman GH, de Oliveira RC, Truffi D, Colombo CA, Rossi
M, de Araujo PG, Sculaccio SA, Angella A, Lima MM, de Rosa Junior VE,
Siviero F, Coscrato VE, Machado MA, Grivet L, Di Mauro SM, Nobrega
FG, Menck CF, Braga MD, Telles GP, Cara FA, Pedrosa G, Meidanis J, Arruda
P (2003).  Analysis and functional annotation of an expressed sequence
tag collection for tropical crop sugarcane. Genome Res 13(12): 2725-35.

Vincentz M, Cara FA, Okura VK, da Silva FR, Pedrosa GL, Hemerly
AS, Capella AN, Marins M, Ferreira PC, Franca SC, Grivet L, Vettore AL,
Kemper EL, Burnquist WL, Targon ML, Siqueira WJ, Kuramae EE, Marino
CL, Camargo LE, Carrer H, Coutinho LL, Furlan LR, Lemos MV, Nunes
LR, Gomes SL, Santelli RV, Goldman MH, Bacci M, Jr., Giglioti EA,
Thiemann OH, Silva FH, Van Sluys MA, Nobrega FG, Arruda P, Menck CF
(2004). Evaluation of monocot and eudicot divergence using the
sugarcane transcriptome. Plant Physiol 134(3): 951-9.

Wheals AE, Basso LC, Alves DM, Amorim HV (1999).  Fuel ethanol
after 25 years. Trends Biotechnol 17(12): 482-7.

Zarpelon F, Andrietta SR (1992). Fermentação contínua para obten-
ção de álcool. STAB (March-April): 23-28.

ecamargo
Typewriter
102



 103

 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



 104

ANEXO II 

 

 

 

 

 

 

GENOME STRUCTURE OF A SACCHAROMYCES CEREVISIAE STRAIN 
WIDELY USED IN BIOETHANOL PRODUCTION. 

 
JUAN LUCAS ARGUESO, MARCELO F. CARAZZOLLE,  

PIOTR A. MIECZKOWSKI, FABIANA M. DUARTE, OSMAR V. C. NETTO,  
SILVIA K. MISSAWA, FELIPE GALZERANI, GUSTAVO G. L. COSTA, RAMON 

O. VIDAL, MELLINE F. NORONHA, MARGARET DOMINSKA, MARIA G. S. 
ANDRIETTA, SÍLVIO R. ANDRIETTA, ANDERSON F. CUNHA, LUIZ H. 

GOMES, FLAVIO C. A. TAVARES, ANDRÉ R. ALCARDE,  
FRED S. DIETRICH, THOMAS D. PETES, AND GONÇALO A. G. PEREIRA 

ARTIGO ACEITO PARA PUBLICAÇÃO NA GENOME RESEARCH 

 

 

 

 

 



Genome structure of a Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain widely used in bioethanol production. 

Juan Lucas Argueso 1,9,10, Marcelo F. Carazzolle 3,9, Piotr A. Mieczkowski 6,9, Fabiana M. Duarte 3, Osmar V. C. 

Netto 3, Silvia K. Missawa 3, Felipe Galzerani 3, Gustavo G. L. Costa 3, Ramon O. Vidal 3, Melline F. Noronha 3,

Margaret Dominska 1, Maria G. S. Andrietta 4, Sílvio R. Andrietta 4, Anderson F. Cunha 5, Luiz H. Gomes 7, Flavio 

C. A. Tavares 7, André R. Alcarde 8; Fred S. Dietrich 1,2, John H. McCusker 1, Thomas D. Petes 1, and Gonçalo A. 

G. Pereira 3,10

1 Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology; and 2 Institute for Genome Sciences and Policy, Duke 

University Medical Center, Durham-NC, USA. 
3 Laboratório de Genômica e Expressão, Departamento de Genética e Evolução, Instituto de Biologia; and 4

Laboratório de Biotecnologia e Bioprocessos, Centro Pluridisciplinar de Pesquisas Químicas e Biológicas, 

Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas-SP, Brazil. 
5 Departamento de Genética e Evolução, CCBS, Universidade Federal de São Carlos, São Carlos-SP, Brazil. 
6 Department of Genetics, School of Medicine, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill-NC, USA. 
7 Departmento de Genética; and 8 Departamento de Agroindústria, Alimentos e Nutrição, Escola Superior de 

Agricultura “Luiz de Queiroz”, Universidade de São Paulo, Piracicaba-SP, Brazil. 

9 These authors contributed equally to this work. 
10 Corresponding authors. 

Corresponding authors: 

Juan Lucas Argueso, PhD 

Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Duke University Medical Center,  

371 CARL Building, Box 3054, Durham-NC, 27710, USA. 

Phone: 1-919-684-5814; Fax: 1-919-684-6033; email: lucas.argueso@duke.edu 

Gonçalo A. G. Pereira, PhD 

Laboratório de Genômica e Expressão, Departamento de Genética e Evolução, Instituto de Biologia, 

Universidade Estadual de Campinas, CP 6109, Campinas-SP, 13083-970, Brazil. 

Phone: 55-19-3521-6237; Fax: 55-19-3521-6235; email: goncalo@unicamp.br 

ecamargo
Typewriter
105



ABSTRACT 

 In the search for renewable sources of energy, bioethanol stands out as a benchmark biofuel because 

its production is based on a proven technological platform.  Bioethanol is produced mainly from the fermentation 

of carbohydrates derived from agricultural feedstocks by the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  One of the most 

widely adopted strains is PE-2, a heterothallic diploid naturally adapted to the sugar cane fermentation process 

used in Brazil.  Here we report the molecular genetic analysis of a PE-2 derived diploid (JAY270), and the 

complete genome sequence of a haploid derivative (JAY291).  The JAY270 genome is highly heterozygous (~2 

SNPs per kilobase), and has several structural polymorphisms between homologous chromosomes.  These 

chromosomal rearrangements are confined to the peripheral regions of the chromosomes, and appear to reflect 

ectopic homologous recombination between repetitive DNA sequences.  Despite the complex karyotype of 

JAY270, this diploid, when sporulated, had a high frequency of viable spores (93%).  Crosses of haploids 

derived from JAY270 to a haploid of the unrelated laboratory strain S288c also resulted in diploids that had good 

spore viability (75-95%).  Thus, the rearrangements that exist near the ends of chromosomes do not impair 

meiosis and spore viability, as they do not span regions that contain essential genes.  This observation is 

consistent with a model in which the peripheral regions of chromosomes represent plastic domains of the 

genome that are free to recombine ectopically and experiment with alternative structures.  We also explore 

features of the JAY270 and JAY291 genomes that help explain their high adaptation to industrial environments, 

exhibiting desirable phenotypes such as high cell mass production and fermentation kinetics, high temperature 

growth and oxidative stress tolerance.  The genomic manipulation of such strains could enable the creation a 

new generation of industrial organisms, ideally suited for use as delivery vehicles for future bioenergy 

technologies. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
106



INTRODUCTION 

 As concerns mount over the alarming effects of climate change and of the continued volatility in 

petroleum markets, nations throughout the world are increasingly adopting policies to promote the use of 

renewable and domestic sources of energy (Robertson et al. 2008).  Among the most viable alternatives, 

bioethanol stands out as a benchmark biofuel because its production is based on a proven technological 

platform.  Bioethanol is produced through microbial fermentation of carbohydrates derived from agricultural 

feedstocks, mainly starch and sucrose.  While the United States and Brazil are the dominant players in 

bioethanol, sharing approximately 70% of the global market, their production systems differ in many respects 

(Sanderson 2006; Goldemberg 2007).  North American bioethanol is currently produced from enzymatically-

hydrolyzed starch from grains.  Farming this type of feedstock is energy intensive, resulting in a final energy 

balance that is only marginally positive.  This process is currently regarded as a transitional technology, which in 

the coming years is expected to give way to advanced cellulosic biofuels (Gura 2009).  The Brazilian system 

uses sugar cane as feedstock, a tropical grass crop that abundantly accumulates sucrose that can be converted 

to bioethanol directly by the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae without enzymatic pre-treatment.  Among other 

advantages, sugar cane is semi-perennial and has symbiotic interactions with nitrogen-fixing microorganisms, 

allowing this system to produce an energy surplus estimated at about eight-fold (Goldemberg 2007; Robertson 

et al. 2008). 

 In the microbial fermentation process used in Brazil, the yeast inoculum is often recycled from one 

fermentation tank to the next (Wheals et al. 1999).  In many distilleries, this recycling spans the entire eight-

month sugar cane harvesting season (Basso et al. 2008), imposing both biotic and abiotic stresses on the 

fermenting yeast strain.  While yeast strains genetically bred for high-efficiency in fermentation have been 

available since the 1980’s (Tavares and Echeverrigaray 1987), they are often outcompeted in the industrial 

environment by more robust “wild” yeasts that contaminate the sugar cane stalks (Wheals et al. 1999; da Silva 

et al. 2005).  In the 1990’s, an alternative strategy was adopted: selection among the wild yeast contaminants 

for those that combined high fermentation efficiency with prolonged persistence in the system.  In recent years, 

such strains have been widely adopted by the industry.  One of the most successful examples is the PE-2 wild 

isolate (Basso et al. 2008), currently used by ~30% of Brazilian distilleries, generating about 10% of the world’s 

bioethanol supply. 

 Thirteen years ago, the S. cerevisiae laboratory strain S288c became the first eukaryote to have its 

genome completely sequenced (Goffeau et al. 1996).  Since then, other haploid strains from diverse 

backgrounds have been sequenced (RM11-1a, YJM789, M22, YPS163, and AWRI1631) (S. cerevisiae RM11-

1a Sequencing Project - http://www.broad.mit.edu/) (Wei et al. 2007; Borneman et al. 2008; Doniger et al. 2008), 

and more recently a large scale effort to determine the genome sequences of many others has been completed  

(Liti et al. 2009). 

ecamargo
Typewriter
107



 Extensive analysis has been done to examine the nucleotide sequence diversity between these strains 

(Liti et al. 2009; Schacherer et al. 2009), whereas studies of structural variation have mostly focused on 

comparisons of S. cerevisiae to other related species (Fischer et al. 2000; Goffeau 2004; Scannell et al. 2007; 

Gordon et al. 2009).  Microarray-based whole genome hybridization studies of wild, industrial, and laboratory S.

cerevisiae strains (Winzeler et al. 2003; Carreto et al. 2008; Schacherer et al. 2009; Faddah et al. 2009) have 

uncovered a recurrent pattern of copy number variation (CNV) near the ends of chromosomes, suggesting a 

role for repetitive DNA sequences in structural genome diversification.  Despite these valuable insights, two 

central questions regarding the role of chromosomal rearrangements in genome evolution in S. cerevisiae

remain unanswered:  First, it is still unclear how these rearrangements contribute to long-term fitness in natural 

environments; and second, it is not known if they are compatible with the formation of viable meiotic spores that 

would allow their sexual dissemination between natural S. cerevisiae populations. 

 In this study, we report a detailed molecular genetic characterization of a PE-2 derived diploid (JAY270), 

and the complete genome sequence of a derived haploid (JAY291).  We have found extensive structural 

differences between the genome of JAY270 and those of other sequenced S. cerevisiae strains, including 

chromosomal translocations and insertions of large blocks of DNA absent in the reference strain’s genome.  

These differences were confined to the peripheral regions of the chromosomes, while the central portions have 

remained structurally conserved.  This pattern of structural variation was fully compatible with the formation of 

viable meiotic spores, and in some cases, the chromosome rearrangements resulted in the amplification of 

genes implicated in environmental stress tolerance.  This observation supports a model in which S. cerevisiae

chromosomes are organized in two structural domains (Pryde et al. 1997).  Our data suggest a general 

chromosome organization in which the central core sectors, harboring the essential genes, are refractory to 

rearrangements, while the peripheral regions are highly plastic and are free to undergo ectopic recombination. 

RESULTS

Genetic and phenotypic characterization 

 Before initiating a detailed characterization of PE-2, we used Pulse-Field Gel Electrophoresis (PFGE) to 

show that the commercially-available stocks of this strain contain a mixture of cells that have slightly diverged 

karyotypes (Supplemental Fig. 1).  Consequently, we purified a single colony isolate with a representative 

karyotype.  This isolate, JAY270, was indistinguishable from the original PE-2 culture in phenotypic tests (Fig. 

1a, and data not shown) and was used in all subsequent experiments. 

 Upon induction of meiosis, JAY270 displayed rapid and efficient sporulation producing mostly asci with 

four ascospores.  We dissected 104 tetrads and observed four viable spores per tetrad in 88 (93.3% spore 

viability).  By PCR analysis, we found 2:2 segregation at the mating type locus (MAT; data not shown).  These 

results show that JAY270 is a diploid, does not contain recessive lethal mutations, and is not heterozygous for 

ecamargo
Typewriter
108



chromosome aberrations that span essential genes.  The haploid segregants derived from JAY270 had stable 

MATa or MAT? genotypes, indicating that the strain is naturally heterothallic.  We crossed haploid strains (both 

MATa and MAT?) derived from JAY270 to S288c-derived strains of the opposite mating type.  The hybrid 

diploids produced in these crosses sporulated normally, had high spore viability (75-95%), and exhibited 

Mendelian segregation for all auxotrophic markers from the S288c-derived parent.  These results argue that the 

chromosome structure of JAY270 is mostly collinear with that of S288c, at least in the regions required for 

viability.

 We compared JAY270 and its derivatives to S288c in several phenotypic tests.  In sugar cane extract 

fermentation assays that simulate the conditions found in the industry (Fig. 1a), JAY270 and all four spore 

clones from a JAY270 tetrad (segregants JAY289, JAY290, JAY291 and JAY292), produced roughly 50% more 

ethanol than the S288c strain.  The observation that all four spore clones were equally proficient in ethanol 

production argues that the major alleles contributing to this complex phenotype are homozygous in the JAY270 

diploid.  We also compared growth phenotypes under a variety of stress conditions.  Tolerance to ethanol, acid 

washing and short-term heat killing were not differently affected in these strains (Supplemental Fig. 2); however, 

JAY270 was much more tolerant to oxidative stress and high temperature growth than S288c (Fig 1b).  When 

grown in the presence of menadione, an inducer of reactive oxygen species, JAY270 grew normally at 

concentrations that were inhibitory to S288c.  JAY270 was also highly tolerant to temperature stress.  While 

S288c had reduced growth rates at 37C, and did not form isolated colonies at 41C, JAY270 formed larger 

colonies at 37C than it did at 30C (Supplemental Fig. 3).  At 41C, JAY270 displayed slower growth, but 

maintained full viability.  These traits are likely important for long-term viability and competitiveness in the 

industrial setting, where oxidative stress (Landolfo et al. 2008) and heat are generated during high-pitch 

fermentation (fermentation involving large inocula). 

 Finally, we examined the patterns of genetic inheritance associated with two of the most important 

industrial traits of JAY270: cell mass accumulation and kinetics of ethanol production.  To bypass the influence 

of factors specific to sugar cane extract (e.g. sucrose utilization), the fermentations were carried out in rich 

media with 10% glucose.  We mated an S288c-isogenic strain to a haploid spore derived from JAY270 

(JAY291) and generated hybrid diploids.  Two reciprocal F1 generation diploids (JAY361 and JAY365) were 

created by mating ?0 mitochondrial petites derived from either parent (Fox et al. 1991).  These two diploids were 

phenotypically indistinguishable from each other (data not shown), indicating that differences between the 

mitochondrial genomes of S288c and JAY291 do not have a major influence on the traits examined.  We then 

evaluated the JAY291 and S288c haploid parents and the F1 hybrid JAY361 in time-course fermentations.  

JAY291 displayed a higher growth rate and finished the fermentation with a cell density 34% higher than S288c; 

the JAY361 hybrid had an intermediate phenotype (Fig. 2a).  Under the conditions used in this assay all three 

strains reached the same final concentration of ethanol at the end of the fermentation (Fig. 2b), but, JAY291 and 

ecamargo
Typewriter
109



JAY361 were much more efficient, displaying higher kinetics of ethanol production and requiring ~30% less time 

than S288c to complete the fermentation.  We have not tested diploidized versions of the JAY291 and S288c 

parents in these assays, therefore we cannot firmly ascertain dominance effects associated with these traits.  

However, if ploidy is not an influencing factor, our results would suggest that the cell mass accumulation trait is 

semi-dominant, whereas the kinetics of ethanol production trait is fully dominant. 

 We sporulated and dissected asci from JAY361 to isolate F2 haploids segregating genomic segments 

from the two parent strains.  Individual clones in this progeny were then examined for final cell mass 

accumulation, and ethanol concentration after 8 hours of fermentation (the point of highest differential between 

the parents) as an indicator of ethanol production kinetics.  The phenotypic distributions for these two traits in 

the progeny were quite distinct, and gave preliminary indications of the genetic control associated with each.  

The distribution of cell mass accumulation (Fig. 2c) appeared to be bimodal, with two distinct peaks centered 

around the phenotypes of the parents and a valley which corresponded roughly to the phenotype of the F1

hybrid.  One interpretation of this pattern is that it was created by segregation of the two alleles of a single gene 

that is the major determinant of the cell mass accumulation phenotype.  In addition to this major locus, the 

segregation of other minor contributing alleles was responsible for the bell-shaped distribution around each 

peak.  The distribution of ethanol production kinetics (Fig. 2d) was more typical of a quantitative trait controlled 

by loci with roughly equal contributions to the phenotype.  From this limited initial analysis, we can estimate that 

three or four genes are responsible for the segregation pattern observed for ethanol production kinetics. 

 We also asked whether there is a correlation between cell mass accumulation and ethanol production 

kinetics.  This analysis (Fig. 2e) suggested that the two traits are largely independent of each other, and are 

presumably controlled by different genes.  The calculated broad-sense heritabilities associated with both traits 

were very high (H2 &gt; 0.90), indicating that most of the phenotypic variance observed between F2 individuals was 

due to differences in genetic composition. 

Molecular karyotype analysis 

 We compared the molecular karyotypes of JAY270 and S288c using a combination of PFGE, and 

microarray-based Comparative Genomic Hybridization (CGH-array) and Band-array (Argueso et al. 2008).  

PFGE analysis revealed clear chromosome (Chr) length polymorphisms between S288c and JAY270 (Fig. 3a).  

This analysis also showed polymorphisms between several pairs of homologs within the JAY270 diploid.  Image 

tracing of the separated chromosomes in JAY270 revealed that some chromosomes were represented by two 

bands, each present in one copy in the diploid.  For example, Chr6 is represented by short (Chr6S) and long 

(Chr6L) homologs, differing in size by about 60 kb.  Interestingly, karyotypic analysis of the meiotic haploid 

spores revealed parental-sized chromosomes in JAY289 and JAY290, and chromosomes with the sizes 

expected for reciprocal recombinants between Chr6S and Chr6L in JAY291 and JAY292 (Fig. 4a; second band 

ecamargo
Typewriter
110



from the bottom).  In addition to Chr6, at least Chr3, Chr5, Chr9, Chr11, Chr14, and either Chr7 or Chr15 had 

length polymorphisms between homologs in JAY270. 

 We examined the structural polymorphisms between the Chr6 homologs by excising their respective 

chromosomal bands from PFGE, labeling the DNA and hybridizing them to microarrays covering the entire 

S288c reference genome (Band-array; Fig. 5).  The JAY270 Chr6 homologs differed from each other and from 

Chr6 in S288c only near the chromosome ends, in regions distal to the first and last essential genes (SEC53

and RPN12).  This analysis showed that Chr6L contained a ~16 kb region on the left arm that was missing in 

Chr6S (including the AGP3 gene), and that Chr6S contained a ~12 kb translocation from the right arm of Chr1 

(including the YAR064W gene) that was missing in Chr6L.  Southern analysis (Fig. 4b-c) confirmed this 

arrangement and revealed an additional translocation involving AGP3 on one of two Chr10 homologs of 

JAY270.  Notably, the cumulative Band-array hybridization signal for Chr6L (~322 kb in size, Fig. 2a), accounted 

for only ~250 kb of sequences, suggesting the presence of about 70 kb of DNA that did not hybridize to the 

microarrays. 

 We used CGH-arrays to look for sequences that were missing or duplicated in JAY270 relative to S288c 

(CNVs; Fig 3b).  Most regions of the genome were present in equal dose between these strains.  The regions 

shown in green near the telomeres of Chr1, Chr4, Chr6, Chr10, and Chr15 were underrepresented in the 

JAY270 genome.  These could be either missing in JAY270, or represent diverged sequences that do not 

hybridize to the S288c-based microarrays.  The underrepresented regions that were not telomeric corresponded 

to regions containing tandemly repeated genes in S288c (HXT7, HXT6, HXT3 and ENA5, ENA2, ENA1 in Chr4; 

and ASP3-1 to ASP3-4 in Chr12) that likely contracted in JAY270 or expanded in S288c as a consequence of 

unequal crossing-over.  The regions shown in red represent sequences that were amplified in JAY270 relative to 

S288c.  An amplification signal detected in the central section of Chr15 corresponded to the HIS3 marker locus.  

This gene is present in JAY270, but was intentionally deleted in the derivative of S288c that was used in the 

CGH-array experiments.  Thus, we can effectively detect a single amplified gene by these methods. 

The amplification at the left end of Chr16 spans the SAM3 and SAM4 genes that are involved in 

metabolism of S-adenosylmethionine (AdoMet), a key biochemical cofactor that participates in a variety of 

metabolic pathways.  The Sam4p has been proposed to participate in the recycling of AdoMet from the inactive, 

and possibly toxic, (R,S)-AdoMet isomeric state back to the biologically essential form (S,S)-AdoMet (Vinci and 

Clarke 2007).  Based on CGH-array and Southern blot data (Fig. 3b, and data not shown), we estimate that four 

copies of these genes are present in JAY270 compared to two in the laboratory diploid strain. 

 Another interesting gene amplification resulted in two peaks at the left ends of Chr6 and Chr14.  In 

S288c these regions contain, respectively, the duplicated SNO3 and SNZ3, and SNO2 and SNZ2 genes which 

are involved in vitamin B6 metabolism, and have a role in oxidative stress tolerance (Padilla et al. 1998; 

Ehrenshaft et al. 1999; Rodriguez-Navarro et al. 2002).  To determine the extent and chromosomal distribution 

ecamargo
Typewriter
111



of the SNO/SNZ gene amplifications in JAY270, we did a Southern analysis of pulse-field gels for this region 

(Fig. 4d). We detected nine copies of the SNO/SNZ genes in JAY270, compared to four in the S288c diploid.  

Consistent with this observation, we found that expression levels of these genes were up-regulated about four-

fold in JAY270 relative to S288c (Supplemental Table 1).  These results also showed that SNO/SNZ genes were 

redistributed among the chromosomes in JAY270 with no copies on either Chr6 homolog and new copies on 

Chr9, Chr10, Chr13 or Chr16, Chr7 or Chr15, and Chr4 (Fig. 4d).  Strikingly, three of the extra copies were 

hemizygous (only one copy of a gene is present in a pair of homologous chromosomes) in the JAY270 diploid 

as could be inferred from their Mendelian segregation among the haploid spores JAY289-JAY292. 

Genome sequencing of JAY291, a haploid spore derived of JAY270 

 In addition to the molecular genetic analysis described above, we employed massively parallel DNA 

sequencing to characterize the genome of JAY270.  To avoid complications due to heterozygosity in the diploid, 

we sequenced the genome of a haploid derivative, JAY291.  Two independent DNA sequencing platforms were 

used, Roche/454 and Illumina, resulting in 162-fold coverage (Table 1).  Despite this high level of redundancy, 

because both of these methods generated relatively short sequence reads (&lt;250 bp), we were still unable to 

assemble the genome into one single contiguous sequence per chromosome.  Instead, our de novo assembly of 

the JAY291 genome resulted 452 genomic fragments (contigs; Materials and Methods).  As expected, when we 

compared these contigs to the S288c reference genome, it became clear that most interruptions occurred at 

regions of dispersed repetitive DNA sequences, mostly Ty retrotransposon insertions. As described below, we 

compared the sequences of JAY291 to those of other sequenced S. cerevisiae strains: S288c, RM11-1a, and 

YJM789 (Wei et al. 2007).  These sequence comparisons were done to characterize chromosome structure 

differences between these strains, as well as to determine the level of nucleotide sequence divergence. 

Chromosome structure polymorphisms 

 From the PFGE profiles of JAY270 and its haploid descendants (Figs. 3a and 4a) it was clear that this 

diploid has chromosomes that vary in size, not only in comparison to S288c, but also between the two 

homologs.  To investigate the nature of these rearrangements, we focused our analysis on Chr6.  In JAY270, 

the two homologs were approximately 261 kb (Chr6S) and 322 kb (Chr6L) in size.  The Chr6 of JAY291 is a 

recombinant between Chr6S and Chr6L, and is about 290 kb in size.  We assembled the complete sequence of 

Chr6 in JAY291 by searching the 452 whole genome contigs for known Chr6 sequences from the S288c, RM11-

1a and YJM789 strains; this search identified 14 candidate contigs.  We then used PCR to amplify across the 

small gaps between the contigs and to position telomeric repeats, confirming their relative order and orientation 

(data not shown).  The size of the resulting assembled sequences (including one X and one Y’ element as each 

telomere) was 290 kb, matching the observed PFGE size.  The chromosome structure and nucleotide sequence 

ecamargo
Typewriter
112



in the central portion of Chr6 were very similar to those of S288c, whereas in the regions near the telomeres the 

sequences were more diverged or completely different (Fig. 6a).  At the left end of the Chr6 alignment, we found 

two segments (9.1 and 19.3 kb) that are absent in the S288c genome.  We also aligned the JAY291 

chromosome to the Chr6 sequence from Saccharomyces paradoxus (Kellis et al. 2003), the closest known 

relative of S. cerevisiae, and observed continual synteny through most of Chr6, including the entire left arm.  

This alignment suggests that the 9.1 and 19.3 kb insertions were present in the last common ancestor of S.

cerevisiae and S. paradoxus, and that they were probably lost from the progenitor of S288c.  The only structural 

difference in the central section of Chr6 was a Ty2 retrotransposon element insertion which is present in S288c 

(YFLWTy2-1), but absent in JAY291.  Chr6 had no full-length retrotransposons in JAY270, but Ty elements 

were found in all other chromosomes (Supplemental Fig. 4). 

 Although we concentrated our sequencing efforts on the JAY291 haploid, from our analysis of the 

sequences of S288c, RM11-1a, and YJM789 and from our examination of the microarray data and Southern 

analysis (Figs. 3-5), we were able to predict the structures at the left ends of the two Chr6 homologs in the 

JAY270 diploid.  We then designed specific PCR primers to confirm our predictions (Supplemental Fig. 5).  

Repetitive DNA sequences were found at the breakpoints (shown as boxed letters in Fig. 6b) of all chromosomal 

rearrangements in this region, suggesting that they formed through ectopic homologous recombination. 

 We determined that JAY270 Chr6S has a portion of Chr1 that includes the YAR064W gene attached to 

the left end of Chr6 (Fig. 4c).  This translocation is also present in RM11-1a and YJM789, and the breakpoint is 

between YAR062W in Chr1 (boxed “A”) and YFL051C in Chr6, both are pseudogene members of the FLO gene 

family.  The YFL051C pseudogene is also the site of the 19.3 kb region which is present in JAY270 Chr6L and 

deleted in Chr6 from S288c.  While YFL051C is short and non-functional in S288c, in JAY270 Chr6L this ORF 

extends into the 19.3 kb region to form a full length FLO gene (boxed “B”).  Near the left end of this insertion 

region, there was a 4.3 kb translocated section of S288c Chr10, with breakpoints at HXT8 (boxed “C”; a hexose 

transporter gene family member) and YJL216C (boxed “D”; a gene with similarity to maltase genes).  Finally, the 

leftmost rearrangement in JAY270 Chr6L contains the 9.1 kb sequence not represented in S288c.  The 

breakpoint for this rearrangement was at the THI5 gene (boxed “E”; a member of a gene family involved in the 

thiamine biosynthesis).  In S288c, the SNO3 and SNZ3 genes are located immediately distal to THI5, whereas 

this region of Chr6L of JAY270 contains a copy of the MPR2 gene involved in tolerance to oxidative stress and 

ethanol toxicity (Du and Takagi 2007).  MPR2 is also present the RM11-1a and ?1278b strains, but strikingly, 

the genes in MPR family are found at different genomic locations in these strains: in RM11-1a, MPR2 is at the 

left end of Chr10; whereas in ?1278b, MPR2 is at the right end of Chr10 and MPR1 is at the left end of Chr14 

(Takagi et al. 2000). 

 This detailed analysis also allowed us to examine the rearrangements between the two Chr10 homologs 

in JAY270 (arbitrarily designated A and B).  The left end structure of Chr6L was essentially identical to that 

ecamargo
Typewriter
113



found in Chr10 of RM11-1a and in JAY270 Chr10A (inherited by the JAY289 and JAY292 spores).  A similar 

Chr6/Chr10 translocation with a breakpoint at YJL216C (boxed “D”) has been described recently in the M22 

vineyard strain (Doniger et al. 2008).  The Chr10 structure in YJM789 is similar to RM11-1a, M22, JAY270 

Chr10A, with the exception of the extreme left end at positions distal to THI5 (boxed “E”) where YJM789 is 

similar to S288c Chr6.  Interestingly, the YJM789 Chr10 configuration is precisely what would be predicted from 

a crossover occurring between S288c Chr6 and RM11-1a Chr10 anywhere between THI5 and YFL051C.  An 

analogous meiotic crossover event within translocated chromosomal segments has been recently observed in 

the S288c/Y101 laboratory hybrid (Faddah et al. 2009).  The second JAY270 Chr10 homolog (Chr10B; inherited 

by JAY290 and JAY291) had at its left end a ~15 kb translocated segment not found in the S288c genome.  The 

breakpoint in this chromosome is near an unannotated Ty1 delta LTR element (boxed “F”) that is located on 

S288c Chr10 between SGD coordinates 29000 and 29500 and is also present in the JAY291 Chr10 sequence.  

Finally, it is important to note that all rearrangements described above occurred at sites distal to the first 

essential genes in the Chr6 (SEC53) and Chr10 (PRP21).

Nucleotide polymorphisms 

 We compared the sequences of JAY291 to S288c, estimating the number of SNPs at 5.4 per kilobase 

(about 65000 for the entire genome).  To compare JAY291 to other S. cerevisiae strains, we analyzed a ~49 kb 

region from Chr14 that has been sequenced for several unrelated strains (Steinmetz et al. 2002) and used it to 

construct an unrooted phylogenetic tree (Fig. 7a).  This analysis indicated that JAY291 is highly diverged 

relative to S288c, YJM789, and RM11-1a and, therefore, will be useful in characterizing the rich sequence 

diversity present in S. cerevisiae.

 We also sought to estimate the degree of heterozygosity in the JAY270 diploid genome.  We performed 

a limited sequence analysis of JAY292, a haploid spore derived from the same tetrad as JAY291.  Because the 

genomic coverage in this case was relatively low (15-fold with Illumina paired-end reads), we did not attempt to 

assemble the genome de novo.  Instead, we assembled the JAY292 sequence using the JAY291 contigs as 

reference.  After filtering out repetitive elements, regions of high divergence, and regions of low quality and/or 

coverage, we estimated a density of about 1.3 SNPs/kb in the single-copy genomic regions.  Because JAY291 

and JAY292 are sibling haploid strains, about half of their genomes should be identical by descent and we found 

that about half of the genomic regions had a very low level of polymorphisms (data not shown).  We estimate, 

therefore, that the JAY270 diploid has about 2.6 SNPs/kb between allelic regions in homologous chromosomes. 

 We also examined heterozygosis restricting the analysis to the Chr6 sequences of JAY291 and 

JAY292.  Because these two haploids carry the two reciprocal products of a meiotic crossover between the two 

parental Chr6 homologs (Fig. 4a), it should be possible to directly find all Chr6 SNPs in the diploid by comparing 

the JAY291 and JAY292 sibling sequences (assuming that they formed as a result of exactly one crossover).  

ecamargo
Typewriter
114



We found 465 SNPs in the 208 kb region common to both the Chr6L and Chr6S homologs (Fig. 5).  The Chr6 

SNP density (~2.2 SNPs/kb) was consistent with our estimate for the whole genome. 

Overview of specific gene polymorphisms important for bioethanol production 

 We compared the sequences of several JAY291 genes to those of other strains to establish possible 

links between the genotype and the observed phenotypes.  High-Temperature Growth (HTG) has been 

investigated in S. cerevisiae as a model for complex quantitative inheritance (Steinmetz et al. 2002; Sinha et al. 

2008), and three major contributing loci have been identified: NCS2, MKT1, and END3.  We found that JAY291 

had all three of the alleles that are related to HTG+ (Fig. 7b).  However, HTG, as is often the case for 

quantitative traits, is known to be influenced by genetic background (Sinha et al. 2006).  We therefore tested the 

role of these polymorphisms in the JAY291 background by constructing isogenic strains carrying HTG- allele 

replacement versions of NCS2 and MKT1 from S288c, and END3 from YJM789.  We found that the allele 

replacement strains, individually, were not compromised for HTG, at least within the resolution of our co-culture 

competition assays (~5 fold; data not shown).  This result was analogous to the background-specific phenotypic 

response described by Sinha et al. (2006), and suggested that other uncharacterized alleles present in the 

JAY291 genome are contributing to its distinct HTG+ phenotype. 

 We also examined the sequence of the HO gene that encodes the endonuclease that stimulates mating 

type switching in homothallic strains (Herskowitz 1988).  The ho allele in JAY291 has three missense mutations, 

including the H475L substitution that is present in S288c and has been shown to significantly reduce HO activity 

(Meiron et al. 1995; Ekino et al. 1999).  In addition, an in-frame deletion between 8 bp direct repeats within the 

gene removed 36 amino acid residues from the DNA binding domain (residues 524-559).  These mutations 

likely eliminate the endonuclease activity of HO, explaining the heterothallic life cycle of JAY270. 

 Flocculation is a mechanism through which yeast cells aggregate to form clumps, or flocs.  While 

flocculation is a desirable trait in brewing, it is problematic in sugar cane batch fermentation because it 

significantly slows fermentation kinetics, and can cause excessive foaming and clogging of pipes.  One of the 

attractive properties of JAY270 is that it rarely flocculates and produces very little foam in fermentation tanks 

(Basso et al. 2008).  The JAY291 haploid is also non-flocculant.  We examined the sequences of genes 

encoding cell surface adhesins involved in flocculation (FLO1, FLO5, FLO11, and others) and found that they 

are present in JAY291, although, due to their internal repeat structures (Verstrepen et al. 2004), these 

sequences were sometimes split between two contigs in our assembly.  In addition, we looked at the FLO8

gene, a positive regulator of flocculation.  In S288c, FLO8 contains a nonsense mutation (flo8-1) that renders 

the cells non-flocculant  (Liu et al. 1996).  The FLO8 gene in JAY291 appears to be functional, indicating that 

the non-flocculant phenotype of JAY291 involves a block in a different step of the pathway.  Interestingly, among 

120 F2 progeny from the S288c x JAY291 cross described above (Fig. 2) we observed 19 individuals that 

ecamargo
Typewriter
115



flocculated in fermentation media and 101 that did not; roughly a 1:7 phenotypic ratio expected for a trait 

controlled by three unlinked genes (?2 = 1.22; p = 0.27).  We genotyped the flocculant progeny by PCR and 

restriction digest and observed that all 19 flocculant progeny inherited the FLO8 allele from JAY291, therefore 

confirming the requirement of a functional Flo8p for flocculation. 

 In the S288c genome, there is a Ty1 retrotransposon insertion in the HAP1 gene (Gaisne et al. 1999).  

HAP1 encodes a heme-mediated transcription factor that controls the expression of genes involved in 

fermentation (Mense and Zhang 2006), and in the biosynthesis of ergosterol which is important for ethanol 

tolerance (Inoue et al. 2000).  As in other industrial strains (Tamura et al. 2004), this interrupting Ty1 element is 

absent in JAY291.  Consistent with this result, we found that several of the Hap1p regulated genes were 

expressed at a higher level in JAY270 than in S288c (Supplemental Table 1). 

 Another gene important for industrial yeast strains is MIP1, a nuclear-encoded mitochondrial DNA 

polymerase (Foury 1989).  A polymorphism present in Mip1p (Mip1p-661A) has been shown recently to be 

responsible for the high frequency of spontaneous cytoplasmic respiratory mutations (??- petites) observed in 

S288c (Baruffini et al. 2007).  The MIP1 sequence in JAY291 contains five non-synonymous substitutions 

relative to S288c, including the Mip1p-661T variant, which is associated with a low frequency of petites.  This 

desirable trait was confirmed in semi-quantitative petite mutation assays in which JAY270 produced petite

colonies at a frequency about five fold lower than S288c (data not shown). 

 Efficient sucrose utilization is essential in sugar cane fermentation.  S. cerevisiae strains have long been 

known to vary in the number of copies of the SUC genes coding for invertase, the enzyme that breaks down 

sucrose in glucose and fructose which are then fermented to produce ethanol (Carlson and Botstein 1983).  

S288c only has one copy, SUC2, the only non-telomeric member of this gene family.  Since JAY270 thrives in 

the sugar cane extract, we expected to find several SUC copies in its genome.  Instead, the only invertase gene 

found in the genome sequence of JAY291 was SUC2.  Another gene we did not find in JAY291 was RTM1 

(Ness and Aigle 1995), involved in resistance to toxins found in molasses, a byproduct of sugar production 

sometimes used in bioethanol fermentation.  Incidentally, RTM1 is always found clustered with the telomeric 

copies of SUC genes (Ness and Aigle 1995). 

 A comprehensive list of all genes found in both JAY291 and S288c is presented in Supplemental Table 

1, including the local density of SNPs inside the coding sequences and in the upstream regulatory regions, and 

the relative level of gene expression between these strains measured with cDNA microarrays.  In addition to the 

shared genes discussed above, it is possible that the genes present in JAY291 but absent in S288c also 

contribute to the properties of JAY270.  At least sixteen such genes have been identified in the genome of 

JAY291 (Supplemental Table 1).  An attractive example of such genes are two copies of putative S-

adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferases found in the JAY291 genome (contig404-gene1 and 

contig386-gene1; their predicted protein sequences share 92% similarity).  These new genes participate in the 

ecamargo
Typewriter
116



same processes as the amplified SAM3 and SAM4 genes discussed above.  Interestingly, a protein identical to 

the one coded by contig404-gene1 has been recently identified and found to be specific to the West African 

lineage of S. cerevisiae strains (hypothetical protein 5; Liti et al. 2009). 

DISCUSSION 

Diverse genome structure of JAY270 and its implications for genome evolution 

 Our molecular analysis of the JAY270 diploid revealed that its genome is highly heterogeneous, both 

structurally and at the nucleotide level.  Thus far, the genomic analysis of S. cerevisiae had been mostly limited 

to haploids, often derived from homothallic diploid strains.  In this type of life cycle, immediately after meiosis, 

the haploid spores undergo mating type switching, followed by self mating to restore a diploid state (Herskowitz 

1988).  This cycle generates diploids that are homozygous for the entire genome, except at the MAT locus.  In 

contrast, heterothallic spores, such as those derived from JAY270, are unable to switch mating type because of 

a mutation in the HO gene.  The spores restore the diploid state by mating to spores of the opposite mating 

type, either siblings from the same ascus or by outcrossing (Knop 2006).  The heterozygous JAY270 genome 

richly illustrates how this process is effective in preserving and amplifying genetic diversity.  It is important to 

note, however, that both the homothallic and heterothallic life cycles require the production of viable haploid 

spores in meiosis, and thus both types of strains are expected to continuously remove from the gene pool 

recessive lethal mutations and chromosomal rearrangements associated with the loss of essential genes. 

 We have found that the genomes of JAY270 and S288c are collinear through most regions and hybrids 

generated by crosses between these genetic backgrounds have good spore viability.  Structural variation, 

though abundant, was limited to the end sections of chromosomes.  A similar pattern has been previously 

observed in microarray-based surveys of genome variation among different S. cerevisiae strains (Winzeler et al. 

2003; Carreto et al. 2008; Schacherer et al. 2009), which found that most polymorphisms, including SNPs and 

CNVs, were more common within 25 kb of the telomeres.  In these studies, however, the full extent of the 

structural variation in these regions could not be revealed because the microarrays used were based on the 

S288c genome, and regions of high sequence divergence or sequences that were absent in the reference strain 

could not be examined.  This gap has been recently filled by a whole genome sequencing-based survey of 

dozens of S. cerevisiae and S. paradoxus strains (Liti et al. 2009).  This study identified DNA sequences, 

including 38 genes, that are present in some of these strains but are absent in the reference S288c genome.  

Importantly, these new genes are mostly subtelomeric. 

 The peripheral regions of chromosomes in S. cerevisiae typically contain genes that participate in 

alternative carbon source and vitamin metabolisms, ion and amino acid transport, flocculation and other 

processes that are not essential for viability.  In the S288c genome, ~8% of all genes are located at sites distal 

to essential genes (Supplemental Table 1).  Some of these genes, like SNO/SNZ and SAM, are functionally 

ecamargo
Typewriter
117



clustered.  Previous studies have shown that there are very few functionally clustered genes in S. cerevisiae,

and that those which are clustered tend to be associated with specific functions that differ between strains (Hall 

and Dietrich 2007).  Analogous distributions of non-essential genes are also found in other species.  For 

example, in Plasmodium falciparum, the peripheral regions encode variable surface antigen genes (contingency 

genes) that help this parasite evade the host’s immune defenses (Freitas-Junior et al. 2000; Barry et al. 2003).  

Many of the genes found in such regions are members of multi-copy gene families that allow structural variation 

to occur through ectopic homologous recombination events similar to those detected in JAY270.  In addition to 

their repetitive nature, the telomere-proximal regions of chromosomes are often spatially co-localized at the 

nuclear envelope, forming clusters of chromatin that are believed to facilitate ectopic recombination interactions 

(Palladino et al. 1993; Gasser et al. 2004).  Pryde et al. (1997) integrated these observations to formulate a 

model in which the yeast genome is structured in chromosomal sectors that are either rigid (central core) or 

plastic (peripheries).  A schematic model of this concept as it relates to a set of S. cerevisiae haplotypes is 

shown in Fig. 8. 

 We recently demonstrated a mechanism in diploid strains that explains how repetitive elements 

participate in ectopic homologous recombination through their differential interactions with DNA double strand 

breaks (DSBs; Argueso et al. 2008).  While lesions in single-copy regions of the genome are efficiently repaired 

to restore the original structures, DSBs that occur within repetitive sequences often lead to chromosomal 

rearrangements by engaging in homologous recombination with ectopic repeats.  This experiment imposed no 

restrictions regarding the fitness effect or the haploid viability associated with the rearrangements, thus, we 

identified re-structuring events spanning the entire S. cerevisiae genome.  Because most rearrangements were 

non-reciprocal and involved regions containing essential genes, it is likely that those events would be 

deleterious in meiosis, generating inviable spores and therefore eliminating them from the population.  In 

contrast, the naturally-occurring rearrangements observed in JAY270 are not detrimental, since the 

translocations do not span genes essential for viability.  At least six chromosomes in JAY270 were polymorphic 

in length and yet the diploid had excellent spore viability.  Further, crosses between spores derived from 

JAY270 and S288c generated hybrid diploids in which structural differences were present in virtually every 

homolog pair.  Despite their heterogeneous karyotype, these hybrids produced mostly viable spores (75-95%).  

We propose that all DSBs that occur in repetitive elements of the genome are able to promote ectopic 

recombination and generate chromosomal rearrangements.  Those that span essential genes result in poor 

spore viability and are, therefore, eventually eliminated from the population, whereas those that involve the 

peripheral chromosome regions do not affect spore viability and may lead to increased fitness. 

 A distinguishing feature of the JAY270 genome architecture that may contribute to its fitness in 

competitive environments is the hemizygous distribution of useful stress tolerance genes.  It is possible that this 

configuration offers alternative mechanisms for diploid cells to adjust the copy number of these genes through 

ecamargo
Typewriter
118



mitotic crossiover, break-induced replication, or meiotic segregation followed by re-mating of sibling haploid 

spores (Paques and Haber 1999; Knop 2006; Llorente et al. 2008).  For example, these mechanisms could, in 

just a few generations, produce diploids containing 0 to 4 copies of MPR genes and 6 to 12 copies of SNO/SNZ

genes.  Notably, once the homozygous state is achieved, it may be reversed over time through outcrossing or 

ectopic homologous recombination between neighboring repeats.  This scenario may explain how the highly 

plastic genome structure at the peripheral regions of chromosomes could enable S. cerevisiae to rapidly 

respond to a changing environment. 

 Finally, it is interesting to contrast the pattern of spatially restricted chromosomal rearrangements in S.

cerevisiae to the much more radical chromosomal rearrangements recently described in the haploid asexual 

yeast pathogen Candida glabrata (Polakova et al. 2009).  These very complex genome reconfiguration events 

included chromosome fusions, large translocations, aneuploidy and even possible circularizations, that are 

completely incompatible with meiosis.  These authors proposed that C. glabrata has taken genome re-

structuring to the extreme, sacrificing its sexual life cycle to fully explore the adaptation potential provided by a 

highly unstable genome structure.  We believe that S. cerevisiae has found the middle ground by confining the 

genome rearrangements to the ends of chromosomes. 

Implications of highly adapted industrial strains to future bioenergy technologies. 

 In addition to the insights into genome evolution discussed above, the analysis of the JAY270 genome 

offers a number of opportunities for the development of a new generation of industrial yeast strains.  The finding 

that JAY270 is genetically compatible with laboratory strains indicates that the full arsenal of research tools 

developed to study yeast as a model system can be readily applied to the modification of this naturally adapted 

strain.  We envision the use of JAY270 as an ideal delivery vehicle for future renewable energy technologies.  

One of the most active fields of investigation in the effort to develop these technologies has been the search for 

strategies to efficiently break down cellulosic feedstocks and to utilize its complex derived sugars in bioethanol 

fermentation (Gura 2009).  These advances would dramatically improve the overall energy balance in 

bioethanol production.  While the early signs of success in this effort are very encouraging, it is important to 

remember that even when the solutions for this problem are found, there will be a need to efficiently deliver 

these technologies to the industrial setting.  Decades of experience in the development of industrial strains have 

convincingly demonstrated that any large-scale attempt to introduce genetically modified yeast strains in the 

bioethanol industry will be futile, unless they are based on naturally adapted strains.  Therefore, strains such as 

JAY270 are likely to play a key role in facilitating the transition from laboratory technological breakthroughs to 

industrial scale field applications. 

METHODS

ecamargo
Typewriter
119



Growth media and yeast strains.  Yeast culture, mating, sporulation, and tetrad dissection were conducted 

using standard procedures (Rose et al. 1990).  Menadione was obtained from Sigma-Aldrich.  The PE-2 stock 

used to purify JAY270 was from our own laboratory collection, which was derived from commercially available 

dry active yeast sold to bioethanol distilleries (LNF-Latino Americana).  The S288c-isogenic strain used as a 

control in the fermentation assays in Fig. 1a was the BY4741 haploid (Giaever et al. 2002).  For the initial 

genetic characterization of JAY270, the S288c-isogenic strains used were from the FY series (Winston et al. 

1995).  FY833 (Mata, ura3-52, leu2?1, trp1?63, his3?200, lys2?202) and FY834 (Mat?, ura3-52, leu2?1, trp1?

63, his3?200, lys2?202) were crossed to the JAY270-derived haploid spores JAY289 (Mata), JAY290 (Mat?),

JAY291 (Mata), and JAY292 (Mat?) to generate hybrid diploids.  FY23 (Mata, ura3-52, leu2?1, trp1?63) and 

FY86 (Mat?, ura3-52, leu2?1, his3?200) were crossed to each other to generate the JAY309 diploid used as a 

control in comparative stress tolerance assays (Fig. 1b, and Supplemental Fig. 2 and 3).  Finally, the S288c-

isogenic strains used in the quantitative genetic analysis described in Fig. 2 were S1 and S97 (Steinmetz et al. 

2002).  Genomic DNA was also prepared from RM11-1a and YJM789 strains. 

Fermentation assays.  The fermentation assays shown in Fig. 1a were carried out by inoculating 4 g of fresh 

yeast cells in 36 ml of autoclaved sugar cane extract (pH4.0, 18.2% Total Reducing Sugars - mostly sucrose).  

Fermentation cultures were incubated at 30C without agitation for exactly 15 hours.  The cells were recovered 

by centrifugation and the supernatant was distilled for the measurement of ethanol by densimetry.  Cells were 

recycled for five consecutive fermentation cycles, and four independent replicates were analyzed for each 

genotype.  In each replicate, only the data from cycles 2 to 5 were considered, since the data from the first cycle 

(adaptation round) is usually highly variable.  The final ethanol concentration measurements from cycles 2 to 5 

from all four replicates were combined to generate the average and standard error shown. 

 The fermentation assays used in the quantitative genetic analysis (Fig. 2) were carried out by 

inoculating 0.08 g of fresh yeast cells in 8 ml of media containing 0.5% yeast extract, 1% peptone, and 10% 

glucose.  Cells were pre-grown in the same media for two cycles to provide an adaptation round.  The cell mass 

concentration was normalized to 1% prior to the third cycle which was used to record cell growth and ethanol 

production kinetics.  Cultures were incubated at 30C in a slow rotating drum to avoid decantation.  Samples 

were taken at regular intervals and centrifuged in pre-weighted tubes to determine the weight of the cell pellets.  

The supernatant was frozen and later used to determine the ethanol concentration using the BioChain 

(Hayward, CA) Saccharide Removal and Ethanol Assay kits in sequence according to the manufacturer’s 

recommendations. 

Microarray and physical analysis of DNA.  CGH-array and Band-array experiments, and PFGE procedures 

were conducted as previously described (Argueso et al. 2008).  Image tracing of PFGE bands was obtained 

ecamargo
Typewriter
120



using BioRad Quantity One software.  All PCR reactions were conducted using BioRad iProof High-Fidelity DNA 

polymerase.  For the differential gene expression experiments shown in Supplemental Table 1, total RNA was 

extracted from exponentially growing cells of JAY309 and JAY270.  Three independent biological replicates 

were grown in YP 2% glucose liquid media, with 30C incubation and 200 RPM agitation.  First strand cDNA was 

synthesized and labeled with dUTP-Cy3 or dUTP-Cy5, respectively, using the Invitrogen SuperScript Direct 

labeling kit.  Labeled cDNAs were then competitively hybridized to microarrays containing all S288c ORFs.  The 

Log2 (Cy5/Cy3) signal for all three replicates and average for each microarray probe is shown.  The CGH/Band-

array, and the differential gene expression microarray data are available under GEO accession numbers 

GSE14601 and GSE17578, respectively. 

Parallel sequencing and genome assembly.  Total genomic DNA from JAY291 was isolated using Qiagen 

Maxi kit.  We performed sequencing in the Illumina Genome Analyzer II and Roche Genome Sequencer FLX 

(454) platforms (Table 1), using standard manufacturer recommended sample preparation procedures.  The 

Illumina and 454 reads were assembled into longer contigs using de novo assembler Edena  (Hernandez et al. 

2008) and Newbler (Roche), respectively.  The hybrid assembly was performed through the combination of 

3581 Illumina contigs and 1259 454 contigs resulting in 452 hybrid contigs (pipeline developed in our group; 

Zorro: A hybrid assembly pipeline for next-gen sequencing data; G. G. L. Costa, R. O. V., M. F. C., J. M. C. 

Mondego, M. J. Guiltinam, S. C. Schuster, J. E. Carlson, P. A. M., J. L. A., L. W. Meinhardt and G. A. G. P.; 

manuscript in preparation).  Briefly, the zorro pipeline consists of (1) masking repeat regions in the contigs, (2) 

overlap detection, (3) unmasking repeat regions and (4) assembly of hybrid contigs.  In phase (1), the repeat 

regions were determined based on counting occurrences of k-mers in the Roche 454 reads, the assembler then 

masks k-mers in the contigs that occur at high frequency.  The absence of repeats produces correct overlap 

detection in phase (2).  The contigs are then unmasked in phase (3), and the correct hybrid assembly can be 

obtained in (4), by merging all overlapping contigs into hybrid contigs.  The overlaps detection and consensus 

generation were performed using the minimus package (Sommer et al. 2007).  The hybrid contigs were ordered 

and oriented with Bambus program  (Pop et al. 2004) using paired-end information and manual verification 

producing 427 scaffolds.  These sequences were aligned to the reference genome (S288c) using Mummer 

package (Kurtz et al. 2004).  The genome comparisons were visualized using Artemis Comparison Tool - ACT 

(Carver et al. 2005).  ab initio and extrinsic gene predictions were obtained using Augustus (Stanke and 

Morgenstern 2005) and Exonerate (Slater and Birney 2005), respectively.  For the Augustus analysis, we used 

the training sets available for S288c, and for Exonerate we used the reference curated ORFs (SGD; 

http://www.yeastgenome.org) that were aligned into our hybrid assembly. 

 This Whole Genome Shotgun project has been deposited at DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank under the 

accession ACFL00000000.  The version described in this paper is the first version, ACFL01000000. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
121



ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 

 We are grateful to Chris Vinci, Steven Clarke, Dina Raveh, Joseph Heitman, and Eric Alani for useful 

discussions and comments on the manuscript.  We thank CENAPAD-SP (Centro Nacional de Processamento 

de Alto Desempenho de São Paulo) for data processing support.  Research in the Pereira, Tavares, Alcarde 

and Andrietta laboratories is supported by CNPq (Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e 

Tecnológico, FAPESP (Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo), and CAPES 

(Coordenadoria de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior).  Research in the Pereira laboratory is also 

supported by BRASKEM and ETH Bioenergia.  Work in the Petes laboratory is funded by NIH grants GM52319 

and GM24110. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
122



FIGURE LEGENDS 

Figure 1.  Comparative phenotypic analysis of JAY270 and S288c.

a. Sugar cane extract fermentation assays (~18% sucrose).  The ethanol concentration shown is the average 

reached in four fermentation assay repetitions, each comprised of four consecutive 15 hours of fermentation at 

30C with cell recycling (see Materials and Methods for details).  b. Reactive oxygen (menadione) and 

temperature effects on colony growth.  Ten-fold serial dilutions of saturated cultures spotted (5 ?l) in rich 

medium (YPD) containing various concentrations of menadione were incubated at the indicated temperatures, 

and scanned after the indicated incubation period.  The S288c-isogenic control strain used in (a) was the 

BY4741 haploid; and in (b) was the JAY309 diploid. 

Figure 2.  Genetic analysis of cell mass accumulation and ethanol production kinetics. 

a and b.  Kinetics of cell mass accumulation and ethanol production, respectively, during fermentation of rich 

media with 10% glucose.  The results show the average values and standard error for three biological replicates 

from each strain.  The S288c-isogenic strains used in these assays were the MAT? haploids S1 (?+) and S97 

(?0).  The JAY361 diploid was obtained by mating JAY291 and S97; this diploid inherited 100% of its 

mitochondrial genome from JAY291.  c. and d. show the distributions of cell mass accumulation after 18 hours 

and ethanol production after 8 hours (respectively) among haploid F2 spores derived from JAY361.  F2

individuals were grouped in bins according to their phenotypes, and the bars represent the number of individuals 

in each phenotypic bin.  e. Scatter plot of cell density (x axis) vs. ethanol concentration (y axis) for all F2

individuals tested in both assays (gray dots).  P1, F1 and P2 indicate the relative phenotypes of JAY291, JAY361 

and S1, respectively.  n is the number of F2 individuals in each dataset, H
2 is the broad-sense heritability 

calculated from phenotypic and environmental variances, and r2 is coefficient of correlation between the two 

traits analyzed.  Only data from non-flocculant F2 individuals was used in this analysis. 

Figure 3.  Molecular karyotype and gene copy number variation in JAY270. 

a.  PFGE and densitometric analysis of individual chromosomal bands in S288c and JAY270.  The size of the 

peaks reflects the intensity of the ethidium bromide staining for each chromosomal band as determined by 

image analysis using BioRad QuantityOne software.  The predicted chromosome sizes (in kb) are shown next to 

the corresponding chromosomal peaks were determined by comparison to the BioRad l molecular weight ladder 

(not shown).  Note the presence of different sized homologs for Chr6 and Chr11 that appear at lower relative 

intensities.  Contrast the abundance of each Chr6 homolog to the intensity of Chr3 for which both homologs are 

about the same size, and compare the abundance of each Chr11 homolog to the intensity of Chr10. 

b.  CGH-array relative gene dosage plots.  Each horizontal line corresponds to a specific S288c chromosome; 

the signal of each array probe was smoothed in CGH-miner software in a seven-probe sliding window to reduce 

ecamargo
Typewriter
123



noise (Wang et al. 2005).  Gray areas indicate regions of similar genomic dosage, while positive/red and 

negative/green peaks indicate genomic regions over- or under-represented, respectively.  The amplification 

signal on the left end of Chr1 included the SEO1 gene encoding a putative amino-acid permease; the 

amplification peak on the right end of Chr3 did not include any known genes; all other amplifications are 

discussed in the text.  None of the deletion/under-representation peaks spanned regions containing genes 

known to be essential in S288c.  The S288c-isogenic control strain used in (a) and (b) was the JAY309 diploid. 

Figure 4.  Molecular karyotype of meiotic products and segregation of chromosomal rearrangements. 

a.  Ethidium bromide staining of a PFGE including the four meiotic spore clones from a JAY270 tetrad.  The 

S288c-isogenic control strain used was the JAY309 diploid.  b, c, and d show Southern hybridizations of the 

PFGE in (a), using as probes, respectively, the AGP3, YAR064W, and SNO/SNZ sequences that were PCR-

amplified from S288c genomic DNA.  The SNO/SNZ (2-3) probe detects only the duplicated SNO2, SNZ2,

SNO3, and SNZ3 genes.  The diverged single copy genes SNO1 and SNZ1 on Chr13 are not detected.  The 

numbers to the left indicate the S288c chromosomes to which these probes hybridized.  The YAR064W gene is 

duplicated in S288c and JAY270 at the right end of Chr8. 

Figure 5. Band-array analysis of Chr6L and Chr6S homologs in JAY270. 

The curves indicate the normalized hybridization signal of specific chromosomal DNA samples (y axis) to probes 

arranged according to their chromosomal coordinates (x axis) in S288c Chr6 (a) and Chr1 (b).  The dashed 

vertical lines indicate the breakpoints where JAY270 Chr6S and Chr6L differ from each other and from the 

S288c chromosomes.  Only the data for Chr6 and Chr1 probes are shown.  No hybridization signal was 

detected for other S288c chromosomes, with the exception of the right end of Chr8 that is essentially identical to 

Chr1.  SEC53 and RPN12 indicate the most distal essential genes in S288c Chr6, and SNO3, SNZ3, AGP3 and 

YAR064W indicate the position of Southern blot probes used in Fig. 4. The signal valley in the central position of 

Chr6 corresponds to the position of the YFLWTy2-1 retrotransposable element (arrow) which is not present in 

the JAY270 Chr6 homologs.  The black circles indicate the centromere positions. 

Figure 6.  Genome rearrangements near the ends of chromosomes. 

a.  Full-length Chr6 sequences aligned with Artemis Comparative Tool software (Carver et al. 2005).  Red lines 

connect regions of sequence similarity higher than 85%, gaps in white indicate lower or absent similarity.  Green 

indicates S288c Chr6 sequences and thick areas indicate regions conserved in JAY291, whereas thin areas 

indicate non-conserved regions.  The small segment in Blue is a translocated fragment from S288c Chr10.  

Black indicates S. cerevisiae sequences not found in the S288c genome.  The gray thick line corresponds to S.

paradoxus Chr6 assembled from contigs 346, 345, 344, 434 and 433, from left to right, in this order (Kellis et al. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
124



2003).  SEC53 and RPN12 indicate the positions of the most distal essential genes in Chr6.  Black circles 

indicate the position of the centromere (CEN6) and the arrow represents the YFLWTy2-1 element.  Y’ and X 

sub-telomeric sequences are not represented in this alignment.  b. Multi-strain chromosome alignment around 

the left end of Chr6.  The horizontal lines represent the left ends of the designated chromosomes, with the 

exception of S288c Chr1 (top line) for which the inverted right end is shown.  The source strain for each 

sequence is indicated to the left in bold, other strains with similar chromosome structures are also indicated.  

The rectangles represent ORFs, and their positions above and below the central line designate the Watson and 

Crick orientations, respectively.  Chromosomal regions are color coded according to their correspondence to 

S288c Chr1 (orange), Chr6 (green) and Chr10 (blue), while regions in black correspond to sequences not found 

in the S288c genome.  The dotted line in S288c Chr6 represents a discontinuity in the alignment at the site of a 

19.3 kb insertion in JAY291.  The rectangles hatched in red between chromosomes indicate a high level of 

sequence similarity (&gt;85%; analogous to the red lines in panel a).  All sequence similarities are indicated in red 

except for the left end of YJM789 Chr10 which contains the SNO3 and SNZ3 genes and is nearly identical to the 

collinear region in S288c Chr6.  Boxed letters (A-F) indicate the specific chromosomal rearrangements 

discussed in the text, and SNO3, SNZ3, AGP3 and YAR064W indicate the positions of Southern blot probes 

used in Fig. 4.  The source sequences for this figure were the complete Chr6 sequences from S288c and 

JAY291, contigs 1.67 (Chr10) and 1.109 (Chr6) from RM11-1a, contigs 100 (Chr10) and 7 (Chr6) from YJM789, 

and contig 386 (Chr10) from JAY291.  The 10 kb scale bar indicates the size scale for panel b.

Figure 7.  Phylogenetic placement and High-Temperature Growth (HTG) alleles in JAY291.

a.  Unrooted phylogenetic tree of 15 S. cerevisiae strains based on a 49 kb region from Chr14 containing the 

three HTG QTLs (Sinha et al. 2008).  b.  HTG QTL allele distribution in various S. cerevisiae strains.  The three 

critical amino acid residues implicated in High Temperature Growth are shaded in gray, and HTG ( +, - , nd - not 

determined) phenotype is shown to the right. 

Figure 8.  Structural diversity in S. cerevisiae: rigid and plastic domains of the genome. 

The model depicts a set of homologs of a hypothetical chromosome in several unrelated S. cerevisiae strains.  

The top line (continuous gray) depicts the structural configuration of this chromosome in the first sequenced 

strain (i.e. S288c; reference), whereas the chromosomes shown below represent the rearrangements found in 

other strains.  The diverged structural configurations (colors) in the peripheral regions harbor genes that are not 

required for viability, but that may contribute to fitness in specific environments.  The entire set shares structural 

conservation in the central core region (delimited by the most distal essential genes - arrows), therefore meiotic 

crossovers between the unrelated haplotypes can generate new combinations, while remaining compatible with 

haploid viability. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
125



Table 1.  Summary of JAY291 genome sequencing and assembly parameters. 

Haplotype JAY291 

Contigs 452 

Contig size (average) 25.5 Kb 

N50a 65 Kb 

Assembly size 11.6 Mb 

Coverage depthb:

       454 single end 12x 

       Illumina single end 55x 

       Illumina paired-ends 95x 

Gene modelsc:

       Extrinsic 5864 

       Ab initio 5488

       Total gene models 5880 

a. 50% of the genome assembly is represented by contigs of N50 size and longer. 

b. Roche/454 reads were about 250 bp, Illumina single end reads were 35 bp, and paired-end reads correspond 

to two 35 bp reads physically linked by ~125 bp of undetermined sequence. 

c. Extrinsic gene models were predicted based on the established S288c ORFs; ab initio gene models were 

predicted without regard to S288c data.  5471 genes were predicted by both models; 392 and 16 genes were 

found exclusively in the extrinsic and ab initio models, respectively. 

ecamargo
Typewriter
126



REFERENCES 

Argueso, J.L., Westmoreland, J., Mieczkowski, P.A., Gawel, M., Petes, T.D., and Resnick, M.A. 2008. Double-
strand breaks associated with repetitive DNA can reshape the genome. Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A
105:11845-11850 

Barry, J.D., Ginger, M.L., Burton, P., and McCulloch, R. 2003. Why are parasite contingency genes often 
associated with telomeres? Int.J.Parasitol. 33:29-45

Baruffini, E., Lodi, T., Dallabona, C., and Foury, F. 2007. A single nucleotide polymorphism in the DNA 
polymerase gamma gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae laboratory strains is responsible for increased 
mitochondrial DNA mutability. Genetics 177:1227-1231 

Basso, L.C., de Amorim, H.V., de Oliveira, A.J., and Lopes, M.L. 2008. Yeast selection for fuel ethanol 
production in Brazil. FEMS Yeast Res. 

Borneman, A.R., Forgan, A.H., Pretorius, I.S., and Chambers, P.J. 2008. Comparative genome analysis of a 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine strain. FEMS Yeast Res. 8:1185-1195 

Carlson, M. and Botstein, D. 1983. Organization of the SUC gene family in Saccharomyces. Mol.Cell Biol.
3:351-359

Carreto, L., Eiriz, M.F., Gomes, A.C., Pereira, P.M., Schuller, D., and Santos, M.A. 2008. Comparative 
genomics of wild type yeast strains unveils important genome diversity. BMC Genomics 9:524

Carver, T.J., Rutherford, K.M., Berriman, M., Rajandream, M.A., Barrell, B.G., and Parkhill, J. 2005. ACT: the 
Artemis Comparison Tool. Bioinformatics. 21:3422-3423 

da Silva, E.A., dos Santos, S.K.B., Resende, A.D., de Morais, J.O.F., de Morais, M.A., and Simoes, D.A. 2005. 
Yeast population dynamics of industrial fuel-ethanol fermentation process assessed by PCR-
fingerprinting. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek International Journal of General and Molecular Microbiology
88:13-23

Doniger, S.W., Kim, H.S., Swain, D., Corcuera, D., Williams, M., Yang, S.P., and Fay, J.C. 2008. A catalog of 
neutral and deleterious polymorphism in yeast. PLoS.Genet. 4:e1000183 

Du, X. and Takagi, H. 2007. N-Acetyltransferase Mpr1 confers ethanol tolerance on Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
by reducing reactive oxygen species. Appl.Microbiol.Biotechnol. 75:1343-1351 

Ehrenshaft, M., Bilski, P., Li, M.Y., Chignell, C.F., and Daub, M.E. 1999. A highly conserved sequence is a novel 
gene involved in de novo vitamin B6 biosynthesis. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of 
the United States of America 96:9374-9378 

Ekino, K., Kwon, I., Goto, M., Yoshino, S., and Furukawa, K. 1999. Functional analysis of HO gene in delayed 
homothallism in Saccharomyces cerevisiae wy2. Yeast 15:451-458 

Faddah, D.A., Ganko, E.W., McCoach, C., Pickrell, J.K., Hanlon, S.E., Mann, F.G., Mieczkowska, J.O., Jones, 
C.D., Lieb, J.D., and Vision, T.J. 2009. Systematic identification of balanced transposition 
polymorphisms in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. PLoS.Genet. 5:e1000502 

Fischer, G., James, S.A., Roberts, I.N., Oliver, S.G., and Louis, E.J. 2000. Chromosomal evolution in 
Saccharomyces. Nature 405:451-454

Foury, F. 1989. Cloning and sequencing of the nuclear gene MIP1 encoding the catalytic subunit of the yeast 
mitochondrial DNA polymerase. J.Biol.Chem. 264:20552-20560 

Fox, T.D., Folley, L.S., Mulero, J.J., Mcmullin, T.W., Thorsness, P.E., Hedin, L.O., and Costanzo, M.C. 1991. 
Analysis and manipulation of yeast mitochondrial genes. Methods in Enzymology 194:149-165 

ecamargo
Typewriter
127



Freitas-Junior, L.H., Bottius, E., Pirrit, L.A., Deitsch, K.W., Scheidig, C., Guinet, F., Nehrbass, U., Wellems, T.E., 
and Scherf, A. 2000. Frequent ectopic recombination of virulence factor genes in telomeric chromosome 
clusters of P. falciparum. Nature 407:1018-1022 

Gaisne, M., Becam, A.M., Verdiere, J., and Herbert, C.J. 1999. A 'natural' mutation in Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae strains derived from S288c affects the complex regulatory gene HAP1 (CYP1). Curr.Genet.
36:195-200 

Gasser, S.M., Hediger, F., Taddei, A., Neumann, F.R., and Gartenberg, M.R. 2004. The function of telomere 
clustering in yeast: the circe effect. Cold Spring Harb.Symp.Quant.Biol. 69:327-337

Giaever, G., Chu, A.M., Ni, L., Connelly, C., Riles, L., Veronneau, S., Dow, S., Lucau-Danila, A., Anderson, K., 
Andre, B., et al. 2002. Functional profiling of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome. Nature 418:387-
391

Goffeau, A. 2004. Evolutionary genomics: seeing double. Nature 430:25-26

Goffeau, A., Barrell, B.G., Bussey, H., Davis, R.W., Dujon, B., Feldmann, H., Galibert, F., Hoheisel, J.D., Jacq, 
C., Johnston, M., et al. 1996. Life with 6000 genes. Science 274:546, 563-546, 567 

Goldemberg, J. 2007. Ethanol for a sustainable energy future. Science 315:808-810 

Gordon, J.L., Byrne, K.P., and Wolfe, K.H. 2009. Additions, losses, and rearrangements on the evolutionary 
route from a reconstructed ancestor to the modern Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome. PLoS.Genet.
5:e1000485 

Gura, T. 2009. Driving Biofuels from Field to Fuel Tank. Cell 138:9-12

Hall, C. and Dietrich, F.S. 2007. The reacquisition of biotin prototrophy in Saccharomyces cerevisiae involved 
horizontal gene transfer, gene duplication and gene clustering. Genetics 177:2293-2307 

Hernandez, D., Francois, P., Farinelli, L., Osteras, M., and Schrenzel, J. 2008. De novo bacterial genome 
sequencing: millions of very short reads assembled on a desktop computer. Genome Res. 18:802-809 

Herskowitz, I. 1988. Life cycle of the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Microbiol.Rev. 52:536-553 

Inoue, T., Iefuji, H., Fujii, T., Soga, H., and Satoh, K. 2000. Cloning and characterization of a gene 
complementing the mutation of an ethanol-sensitive mutant of sake yeast. Bioscience Biotechnology 
and Biochemistry 64:229-236 

Kellis, M., Patterson, N., Endrizzi, M., Birren, B., and Lander, E.S. 2003. Sequencing and comparison of yeast 
species to identify genes and regulatory elements. Nature 423:241-254 

Knop, M. 2006. Evolution of the hemiascomycete yeasts: on life styles and the importance of inbreeding. 
Bioessays 28:696-708 

Kurtz, S., Phillippy, A., Delcher, A.L., Smoot, M., Shumway, M., Antonescu, C., and Salzberg, S.L. 2004. 
Versatile and open software for comparing large genomes. Genome Biol. 5:R12

Landolfo, S., Politi, H., Angeozzi, D., and Mannazzu, I. 2008. ROS accumulation and oxidative damage to cell 
structures in Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine strains during fermentation of high-sugar-containing 
medium. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta-General Subjects 1780:892-898 

Liti, G., Carter, D.M., Moses, A.M., Warringer, J., Parts, L., James, S.A., Davey, R.P., Roberts, I.N., Burt, A., 
Koufopanou, V., et al. 2009. Population genomics of domestic and wild yeasts. Nature 458:337-341 

Liu, H.P., Styles, C.A., and Fink, G.R. 1996. Saccharomyces cerevisiae S288C has a mutation in FL08 a gene 
required for filamentous growth. Genetics 144:967-978 

ecamargo
Typewriter
128



Llorente, B., Smith, C.E., and Symington, L.S. 2008. Break-induced replication: what is it and what is it for? Cell
Cycle 7:859-864 

Meiron, H., Nahon, E., and Raveh, D. 1995. Identification of the heterothallic mutation in HO-endonuclease of S. 
cerevisiae using HO/ho chimeric genes. Curr.Genet. 28:367-373

Mense, S.M. and Zhang, L. 2006. Heme: a versatile signaling molecule controlling the activities of diverse 
regulators ranging from transcription factors to MAP kinases. Cell Res. 16:681-692 

Ness, F. and Aigle, M. 1995. RTM1: a member of a new family of telomeric repeated genes in yeast. Genetics
140:945-956

Padilla, P.A., Fuge, E.K., Crawford, M.E., Errett, A., and Werner-Washburne, M. 1998. The highly conserved, 
coregulated SNO and SNZ gene families in Saccharomyces cerevisiae respond to nutrient limitation. 
Journal of Bacteriology 180:5718-5726 

Palladino, F., Laroche, T., Gilson, E., Axelrod, A., Pillus, L., and Gasser, S.M. 1993. SIR3 and SIR4 proteins are 
required for the positioning and integrity of yeast telomeres. Cell 75:543-555 

Paques, F. and Haber, J.E. 1999. Multiple pathways of recombination induced by double-strand breaks in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Microbiol.Mol.Biol.Rev. 63:349-404 

Polakova, S., Blume, C., Zarate, J.A., Mentel, M., Jorck-Ramberg, D., Stenderup, J., and Piskur, J. 2009. 
Formation of new chromosomes as a virulence mechanism in yeast Candida glabrata.
Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A 106:2688-2693 

Pop, M., Kosack, D.S., and Salzberg, S.L. 2004. Hierarchical scaffolding with Bambus. Genome Res. 14:149-
159

Pryde, F.E., Gorham, H.C., and Louis, E.J. 1997. Chromosome ends: all the same under their caps. 
Curr.Opin.Genet.Dev. 7:822-828 

Robertson, G.P., Dale, V.H., Doering, O.C., Hamburg, S.P., Melillo, J.M., Wander, M.M., Parton, W.J., Adler, 
P.R., Barney, J.N., Cruse, R.M., et al. 2008. Agriculture. Sustainable biofuels redux. Science 322:49-50

Rodriguez-Navarro, S., Llorente, B., Rodriguez-Manzaneque, M.T., Ramne, A., Uber, G., Marchesan, D., Dujon, 
B., Herrero, E., Sunnerhagen, P., and Perez-Ortin, J. 2002. Functional analysis of yeast gene families 
involved in metabolism of vitamins B-1 and B-6. Yeast 19:1261-1276 

Rose, M.D., Winston, F., and Hieter, P. 1990. Methods in yeast genetics. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, 
Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 

Sanderson, K. 2006. US biofuels: a field in ferment. Nature 444:673-676 

Scannell, D.R., Butler, G., and Wolfe, K.H. 2007. Yeast genome evolution--the origin of the species. Yeast
24:929-942 

Schacherer, J., Shapiro, J.A., Ruderfer, D.M., and Kruglyak, L. 2009. Comprehensive polymorphism survey 
elucidates population structure of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Nature 458:342-345 

Sinha, H., David, L., Pascon, R.C., Clauder-Munster, S., Krishnakumar, S., Nguyen, M., Shi, G., Dean, J., 
Davis, R.W., Oefner, P.J., et al. 2008. Sequential elimination of major-effect contributors identifies 
additional quantitative trait Loci conditioning high-temperature growth in yeast. Genetics 180:1661-1670 

Sinha, H., Nicholson, B.P., Steinmetz, L.M., and McCusker, J.H. 2006. Complex genetic interactions in a 
quantitative trait locus. PLoS.Genet. 2:e13

Slater, G.S. and Birney, E. 2005. Automated generation of heuristics for biological sequence comparison. BMC
Bioinformatics. 6:31

ecamargo
Typewriter
129



Sommer, D.D., Delcher, A.L., Salzberg, S.L., and Pop, M. 2007. Minimus: a fast, lightweight genome assembler. 
BMC Bioinformatics. 8:64

Stanke, M. and Morgenstern, B. 2005. AUGUSTUS: a web server for gene prediction in eukaryotes that allows 
user-defined constraints. Nucleic Acids Res. 33:W465-W467 

Steinmetz, L.M., Sinha, H., Richards, D.R., Spiegelman, J.I., Oefner, P.J., McCusker, J.H., and Davis, R.W. 
2002. Dissecting the architecture of a quantitative trait locus in yeast. Nature 416:326-330 

Takagi, H., Shichiri, M., Takemura, M., Mohri, M., and Nakamori, S. 2000. Saccharomyces cerevisiae sigma 
1278b has novel genes of the N-acetyltransferase gene superfamily required for L-proline analogue 
resistance. J.Bacteriol. 182:4249-4256 

Tamura, K., Gu, Y., Wang, Q., Yamada, T., Ito, K., and Shimoi, H. 2004. A hap1 mutation in a laboratory strain 
of Saccharomyces cerevisiae results in decreased expression of ergosterol-related genes and cellular 
ergosterol content compared to sake yeast. J.Biosci.Bioeng. 98:159-166 

Tavares, F.C.A. and Echeverrigaray, S. 1987. Yeast Breeding for fuel production. In Biochemistry and Biology of 
Industrial Yeasts (eds. G. Stewart, I. Russell, R. Klein, R. Hiebish), pp. 59-80. CRC, Florida. 

Verstrepen, K.J., Reynolds, T.B., and Fink, G.R. 2004. Origins of variation in the fungal cell surface. 
Nat.Rev.Microbiol. 2:533-540 

Vinci, C.R. and Clarke, S.G. 2007. Recognition of age-damaged (R,S)-adenosyl-L-methionine by two 
methyltransferases in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. J.Biol.Chem. 282:8604-8612 

Wang, P., Kim, Y., Pollack, J., Narasimhan, B., and Tibshirani, R. 2005. A method for calling gains and losses in 
array CGH data. Biostatistics. 6:45-58 

Wei, W., McCusker, J.H., Hyman, R.W., Jones, T., Ning, Y., Cao, Z., Gu, Z., Bruno, D., Miranda, M., Nguyen, 
M., et al. 2007. Genome sequencing and comparative analysis of Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain 
YJM789. Proc.Natl.Acad.Sci.U.S.A 104:12825-12830 

Wheals, A.E., Basso, L.C., Alves, D.M., and Amorim, H.V. 1999. Fuel ethanol after 25 years. Trends Biotechnol.
17:482-487 

Winston, F., Dollard, C., and Ricuperohovasse, S.L. 1995. Construction of a set of convenient Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae strains that are isogenic to S288C. Yeast 11:53-55 

Winzeler, E.A., Castillo-Davis, C.I., Oshiro, G., Liang, D., Richards, D.R., Zhou, Y., and Hartl, D.L. 2003. 
Genetic diversity in yeast assessed with whole-genome oligonucleotide arrays. Genetics 163:79-89 

ecamargo
Typewriter
130



0

2

4

6

88

6

4

2

0

ethanol g / 100 ml

S
28

8c

P
E

-2

JA
Y

27
0

JA
Y

28
9

JA
Y

29
0

JA
Y

29
1

JA
Y

29
2

a

S288c

JAY270

S288c

JAY270

S288c

JAY270

0 50 75

30C
2 days

37C
2 days

41C
5 days

Menadione (?M)
b

Argueso et al Figure 1

ecamargo
Typewriter
131



0

10

20

30

40

50

0 3 6 9 12 15 18
0

2

4

6

8

0 3 6 9 12 15 18

0

5

10

15

20

0

2

4

6

8

10

2

3

4

5

6

25 30 35 40 45 50

a b
ce

ll 
de

ns
ity

 (
m

g/
m

l)

et
ha

no
l (

g/
10

0 
m

l)

hours hours

JAY291 (P1) JAY361 (F1) S288c (P2)

42
.9

44
.5

46
.1

49
.3

50
.9

52
.5

54
.1

55
.7

26
.9

28
.5

30
.1

31
.7

33
.3

34
.9

36
.5

38
.1

39
.7

41
.3

57
.3

cell density (mg/ml) after 18 hours

2.
6

2.
9

3.
2

3.
5

3.
8

4.
1

4.
4

4.
7

5.
0

5.
3

ethanol (g/100 ml) after 8 hours cell density (mg/ml)

et
ha

no
l (

g/
10

0 
m

l)

nu
m

be
r 

of
 F

2
in

di
vi

du
al

s

nu
m

be
r 

of
 F

2
in

di
vi

du
al

s
c d e

n = 101
H2 = 0.96

n = 47
H2 = 0.92

n = 47
r2 = -0.28

P2

P1

F1 P1

P2

F1
P2

P1F1

Argueso et al Figure 2

ecamargo
Typewriter
132



Argueso et al Figure 3

a

Chr1 (219)
Chr6S (261)

Chr6L (322)
Chr3 (352)

Chr9 (461)

Chr8S (571)
Chr5,8L (609)

Chr11S (687)

Chr10 (761)
Chr11L (716)

Chr2,14 (840)

Chr13,16 (963)

Chr7,15 (1112)

Chr12 (~2500)

Chr4 (~1500)

(254) Chr1
(290) Chr6

(367) Chr3

(458) Chr9

(617) Chr5,8

(698) Chr11

(771) Chr10

(835) Chr2

(971) Chr13,16

(1129) Chr7,15

(~2500) Chr12

(~1550) Chr4

(805) Chr14

S
28

8c

JA
Y

27
0

loading
well

loading
well

1

2

3

4

5

6

7

8

9

10

11

12

13

14

15

16

SNO3 SNZ3

SAM3 SAM4

b

SNO2 SNZ2

HIS3

ecamargo
Typewriter
133



Argueso et al Figure 4

a

14

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0
JA

Y
28

9
JA

Y
29

0
JA

Y
29

1
JA

Y
29

2

SNO/SNZ (2-3)

b

6

ethidium bromide

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0
JA

Y
28

9
JA

Y
29

0
JA

Y
29

1
JA

Y
29

2

8

1

AGP3 YAR064W

c

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0
JA

Y
28

9
JA

Y
29

0
JA

Y
29

1
JA

Y
29

2

d

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0
JA

Y
28

9
JA

Y
29

0
JA

Y
29

1
JA

Y
29

2

15

ecamargo
Typewriter
134



SEC53

S288c
Chr6

RPN12

a

AGP3SNO3
SNZ3

JAY270 Chr6L JAY270 Chr6S

YFL051CTHI5 HXK1

S288c
Chr1

YAR064W

b
YAR062w

Argueso et al Figure 5

ecamargo
Typewriter
135



Argueso et al Figure 6

SEC53

JAY291
Chr6

S288c
Chr6

RPN12a

S. paradoxus
Chr6

Chr6

PRP21

JAY270-Chr6S
JAY289
JAY292
RM11-1a
YJM789

SEC53

YAR064W

AGP3
Chr6

JAY270-Chr6L
JAY290
JAY291

Chr10 - S288c

A

BCDE

F

Chr10 - YJM789

Chr1 - S288c

Chr6 - S288c

JAY270-Chr10A
JAY289
JAY292
RM11-1a

Chr10

Chr10
JAY270-Chr10B
JAY290
JAY291

10 Kb

SNO3 SNZ3

MPR2

b

ecamargo
Typewriter
136



HTG
End3p-

258
Mkt1p-

30
Ncs2p-

71

-
-
-
-
-
-
-

nd

+
+
+
+
+
+
+

H
L
H
L
L
L
L
L

L
L
L
L
L
L
L

NGRM11-1a

SDS288c
SGSK1
SGW303
NGYJM1129
NGYJM627
SGYJM269
SGYJM270

SGYJM339
SGYJM421
NGYJM280
NGYJM320
NGYJM326
NGYJM789
SGJAY291

0.0005
JAY291

YJM339

YJM421

SK1

W303

S288c

YJM789
YJM280

YJM320

YJM627

YJM326

YJM1129

YJM269 YJM270
RM11-1a

0.001

a b

Argueso et al Figure 7

ecamargo
Typewriter
137



central core region
essential genes, conserved

peripheral regions
niche-specific genes, variable

Argueso et al Figure 8

ecamargo
Typewriter
138



Supplemental Figure 1. Molecular karyotype analysis of PE-2 and its derived pure strains.

a. PFGE analysis of the original PE-2 mixed cultured and of four independent clonal single colony 
isolates derived from PE-2. Note the diffuse chromosomal banding pattern in PE-2 which was 
caused by the presence of subpopulations of cells with slightly divergent karyotypes.  In contrast, 
the bands observed in the purified isolates (JAY270 to JAY274) are discrete and sharper as 
expected for clonal cell lineages, each carrying specific chromosomal variants.

S
28

8c
P

E
-2

P
E

-2
a 

(J
A

Y
27

0)
P

E
-2

b 
(J

A
Y

27
1)

P
E

-2
c 

(J
A

Y
27

2)
P

E
-2

d 
(J

A
Y

27
4)

12

4

7,15

13,16

2
14
10
11

5,8

9

3
6
1

ecamargo
Typewriter
139



Heat killing (1h):

30C

37C

42C

47C

52C

S288c JAY270

c

Ethanol (2h):

0%

8%

10%

12%

14%

S288c JAY270

a

Acid wash (2h):

0 mM

20 mM

40 mM

60 mM

80 mM

S288c JAY270

b

Supplemental Figure 2. Effect of incubation on various stressors on cell viability.

10-1 dilutions of saturated overnight cultures of an S288c-derived diploid (JAY309) and JAY270 
were incubated in the presence of various concentrations of ethanol (a), sulfuric acid (b), or at 
different temperatures (c).  After the indicated time periods, these aliquots were serially diluted in 
sterile water in 10-1 fold increments, spotted to rich medium and allowed to grow at 30C for 48 
hours to assess cell viability.

No significant differences in viability were observed between the two strains for ethanol tolerance 
up to 14% concentration (a). Under standard sugarcane extract fermentation the final ethanol 
concentration rarely exceeds 12%. 

Also, no significant differences were observed in tolerance to short-term acid wash (b), or to 
short-term heat killing (c) at high temperatures beyond those compatible with cell growth (42C, 
47C and 52C). 

ecamargo
Typewriter
140



0

500

1000

1500

2000

JAY309
30C

JAY309
37C

JAY270
30C

JAY270
37C

2000

1500

1000

0

500

S288c
30C

S288c
37C

JAY270
30C

JAY270
37C

Colony area in pixels

b

Supplemental Figure 3. Effect of incubation temperature on colony size.

a. Cropped sample Petri dish scans showing difference in colony size between S288c and 
JAY270 grown in rich medium (YEPD) for 48 hours at 30C and 37C. Scale bar is 5x1 mm.

b. Quantification of colony sizes. Cells were plated to a density of about 20 colonies per plate. 
After 48 hours of incubation, Petri dishes were scanned at 800 dpi and images were analyzed in 
Adobe Photoshop CS2 to measure the colonies. The average colony area in pixels with standard 
error are shown. In the images above, 1 mm2 equals 986 pixels. In the specific experiment shown, 
the diameter of 13 well-spaced colonies was determined.  Colonies were then sorted by size and 
two smallest and the two largest were ignored for the average area calculation to minimize the 
influence of possible petite colonies in the plate. The same trend was observed in another two 
independent experimental repetitions.

S288c JAY270

30C

37C

a

5 mm

ecamargo
Typewriter
141



b

a
365 366

S288c - 8023 bp

YJM789 - 2061 bp

RM11-1a - 1234 bp
JAY289
JAY290
JAY291
JAY292

M
.W

. m
ar

ke
rs

S
28

8c
R

M
11

-1
a

Y
JM

78
9

JA
Y

27
0

JA
Y

28
9

JA
Y

29
0

JA
Y

29
1

JA
Y

29
2

Supplemental Figure 4. PCR mapping of the YFLWTy2-1 region and Ty distribution in JAY270.

a. Screen capture of GBrowser software showing the YFLWTy2-1 region in Chr6 of S288c, 
including the MSH4 and SPB4 flanking genes. The forward PCR primer JAO365 is positioned at 
the 5’ end of MSH4, and the reverse primer JAO366 is positioned at the 3’ end of SPB4. The 
schematics below the map show the expected PCR products from this region in various S.
cerevisiae strains. S288c contains multiple Ty element insertions upstream of the tN(GUU)f tRNA
gene, including the full length YFLWTy2-1 element. YJM789 has the same LTRs as S288c, but 
lacks the Ty2 element. Finally, RM11-1a and the JAY270 ascospores contain only the 
YFLWdelta2 LTR, which likely marks the founding Ty insertion at this site.

b. Ethidium bromide stained agarose gel showing the JAO365 / JAO366 PCR products from (a). 

c. PFGE and Southern analysis of Ty1 and Ty2 retrotransposons in JAY270. S288c 
chromosomes are indicated to the left and JAY270 chromosomes to the right. The probe used 
hybridizes to both Ty1 and Ty2 elements.

c

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0

S
28

8c
JA

Y
27

0

ethidium
bromide

Ty1/Ty2
probe

12

4

7,15

13,16

2
14
10
11

5,8

9

3
6
1

12

4

7,15

13,16

2
14
10
11

5,8

9

3
6

1

8023 bp

2061 bp

1234 bp

ecamargo
Typewriter
142



Supplemental Figure 5. PCR mapping of chromosomal rearrangements at the left arm of Chr6 
and Chr10.

a. Map of PCR primer locations in the region examined. This map matches the genome 
rearrangement breakpoints in Fig. 6b, but it is not drawn to scale. The chromosomal regions and 
primers are color coded according to their correspondence to S288c’s Chr1 (orange), Chr6 
(green) and Chr10 (blue), while regions in black correspond to sequences not found in the S288c 
genome. Arrows indicate primer forward or reverse orientations.

b. Cropped ethidium bromide stained agarose gels with PCR reactions using as template genomic 
DNA from the indicated strains. The primer pair used in each reaction is shown to the left, and the 
size of the expected target product is indicated to the right. Only the region of each gel containing 
the target PCR product is shown. The expected target band was observed in all cases. 
Occasional unspecific PCR products were also present in a few of the reactions, but were 
cropped out to facilitate visualization of the results.

c. PCR primers used in mapping of chromosomal rearrangements at the left arm of Chr6 and 
Chr10, and of the YFLWTy2-1 insertion (Supplemental Fig. 4).

417 418

417 422

415 418

418415

415

423 419

423 414

414423

416

416424

414411

425 359

396 359

396 359

416

415 423 414416425 359

Chr6

Chr6

Chr10 - S288c

Chr10 - YJM789

Chr1 - S288c

Chr6 - S288c

RM11-1a
JAY289
JAY292

Chr10

Chr10 JAY291JAY290

b

S
28

8c

R
M

11
-1

a
Y

JM
78

9

JA
Y

27
0

JA
Y

28
9

JA
Y

29
0

JA
Y

29
1

JA
Y

29
2

417 422

417 418

415 418

423 419

415 416

416424

414411

425 359

396 359

a

PRIMERS
For     Rev

2.2 kb (duplicated
in Chr8 in all strains)

1.5 kb 
1.4 kb

1.2 kb

4.2 kb

2.0 kb

3.1 kb

3.4 kb

5.2 kb

5.0 kb

JAY270-Chr6S
JAY289
JAY292
RM11-1a
YJM789

JAY270-Chr6L
JAY290
JAY291

AAACTAGATAGATTAGATTCACTCJAO365

GTTTCCAGCAAAGCTATCCAAGGCJAO366

Nucleotide sequence (5’?3’)Primer

ACATCACCAAGATTAAGGCGGAGJAO425

AGAGTTCAGTTGTTGCGGACCGAGJAO424

GTCATTATCAAGATCAATGAACTGJAO423

AACTCAAGGACGAGGAGTATTCGGJAO422

CCCACGACGTGCTTACAACGCACTJAO419

TGCAATTGATGCCTACCGGAGJAO418

CATTGCTGCGATAGAATGGAGJAO417

CAGTTCATTGATCTTGATAATGACJAO416

TGTCAGTGTGCGCTTATCACGJAO415

ACAGCTGTCAAAGGCACTAGCAGGJAO414

CTTACTGATAGCGATGCCGCAGACJAO411

AGTTTATATTGTAGTGGCATGACTCJAO396

TCGCTGTCTCTTCAATGTCGACAGJAO359

c

ecamargo
Typewriter
143




	capa1
	capa2
	capa3
	Capa4
	tese1
	tese2
	tese3
	tese4
	tese5
	tese6
	tese7
	tese8
	cibio

</field>
	</doc>
</add>