<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.15905</field>
		<field name="filename">22410_000568245.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Revista Brasileira de Paleontologia 8(3):203-208, Setembro/Dezembro 2005
© 2005 by the Sociedade Brasileira de Paleontologia

203

ABSTRACT – The Itaituba Formation contains the most abundant and diverse fossiliferous deposits of the
Tapajós Group Pennsylvanian of the Amazonas Basin with a rich fauna of normal marine organisms, including
conodonts, fish remains, foraminifers, brachiopods, echinoids, gastropods, bryozoans, trilobites, corals, ostracodes,
scolecodonts, sponges. Palynomorphs are also common. Conodonts are widely distributed. Genera like
Rhachistognathus, Neognathodus, Idiognathodus and Diplognathodus are among the most important to calibrate
the age and to correlate the studied deposits. The occurrence of Diplognathodus coloradoensis, D. orphanus,
and the first appearance of D. ellesmerensis in the Itaituba Formation, Pennsylvanian of the Amazonas Basin are
reported, which suggest an Atokan age to this interval.

Key words: Conodonts, Diplognathodus, Amazonas Basin, Pennsylvanian, Itaituba Formation.

RESUMO – A Formação Itaituba possui os estratos carbonáticos mais espessos do Grupo Tapajós. Esta
formação contém os depósitos fossilíferos mais diversos e abundantes do Pensilvaniano da Bacia do Amazonas
com organismos que representam uma fauna de ambiente marinho normal, incluindo conodontes, fragmentos de
peixes, foraminíferos, braquiópodes, equinodermos, gastrópodes, briozoários, trilobitas, corais, ostracodes,
escolecodontes, esponjas e flora caracterizada por palinomorfos. Os conodontes tem sido amplamente encontra-
dos. Gêneros como Rhachistognathus, Neognathodus, Idiognathodus e Diplognathodus estão entre os mais
importantes para o refinamento das idades e a correlação dos estratos estudados. Este trabalho tem por objetivo
reportar a presença de Diplognathodus coloradoensis, D. orphanus, e a primeira ocorrência de D. ellesmerensis
na Formação Itaituba, Pensilvaniano da Bacia do Amazonas, as quais sugerem uma idade Atokana para o
intervalo estudado.

Palavras-chave: Conodontes, Diplognathodus, Bacia do Amazonas, Pensilvaniano, Formação Itaituba.

DIPLOGNATHODUS OCCURRENCE IN THE ITAITUBA FORMATION,
AMAZONAS BASIN, BRAZIL

ANA KARINA SCOMAZZON &amp;amp; VALESCA BRASIL LEMOS
IGEO, UFRGS, Av. Bento Gonçalves, 9500, 91509-900, Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil. akscomazzon@yahoo.com.br

INTRODUCTION

Conodonts have shown to be useful for correlation and
biozonation in the Pennsylvanian strata widely studied in
North America and Europe. In Brazil, conodonts have been
reported in Paleozoic basins with main attention to the
Pennsylvanian strata of Amazonas Basin, which comprises
the marine deposits of Tapajós Group - Monte Alegre, Itaituba
and Nova Olinda formations. Among these formations the
Itaituba Formation has the thick carbonate marine strata of
the Tapajós Group been the focus of this study.

Some species of the genus Diplognathodus have been
regarded as useful for stratigraphic correlation of
Pennsylvanian strata because they have shown
stratigraphically short ranges, like Diplognathodus
orphanus, typical of Atokan age. Outside North America the
distribution of this genus is still little known, whereas other
genera like Idiognathodus and Neognathodus have been
widely discussed and documented in the Carboniferous of
North America and Europe.

Diplognathodus distribution has been analyzed in the
Pennsylvanian of United States mainly by Merrill (1973), von
Bitter &amp;amp; Merrill (1990) among others, in the Midcontinent
region, Appalachian and Illinois basins, by Bender (1980) in
the Canadian Arctic, by van den Boogaard (1983) in Western
Europe and North Africa, by Wang Zhi-hao &amp;amp; Qi Yu-ping
(2002) in China, among others.

In South America, Diplognathodus has been found in
Brazil in Pennsylvanian strata of the Amazonas Basin.
Diplognathodus coloradoensis and D. orphanus were
studied by Lemos (1990) and Neis (1996) in wells collected
by PETROBRAS. Later, studying an outcrop area of
fossiliferous calcareous limestones in the southern part of
the Amazonas Basin, Scomazzon (1999) report the presence
of D. orphanus in the lower portion of the Itaituba Formation
and Nascimento et al. (2005) registered the occurrence of D.
coloradoensis in a quarry in this region, however in
stratigraphically older marine deposits, suggesting an Atokan
age to the studied interval.

This paper aim to record the Pa elements of Diplognathodus

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56203



REVISTA BRASILEIRA DE PALEONTOLOGIA, 8(3), 2005204

occurrence in calcareous marine deposits of the Itaituba
Formation, Pennsylvanian of the Amazonas Basin. We herein
present the occurrence of Pa elements of Diplognathodus
coloradoensis, D. orphanus and the first report of Pa elements
of D. ellesmerensis in the Amazonas Basin.

MATERIAL AND METHODS

The material here studied comes from four wells made by
the Brazilian oil company (PETROBRAS) in the Amazonas
Basin (Figure 1). About 15 kg of carbonates from thirty-nine
samples were collected from the wells. Processing techniques
followed the usual methodology of Austin (1987). Around
400 g of each sample were used to process the material. From
the processed material 125 Pa elements of the genus
Diplognathodus were studied (Table 1). Other elements like
M and S ones were also found in the sediment analyzed, but
they were not herein considered because it is difficult to
establish whether they belong or not to Diplognathodus
apparatus. The conodonts studied herein are deposited in
the collection of the Departamento de Paleontologia e
Estratigrafia, UFRGS under acronym MP-M.

GEOLOGICAL SETTING

The Amazonas Basin is a large intracratonic sedimentary
basin occupying 500 000 km2 within the northern Brazilian
states of Amazonas and Pará (Figure 1). Three sectors are
distinguished trending generally east – west: the north
platform, the south platform and the central basin area. The
Paleozoic sedimentary succession is limited by two
Precambrian Shields, the Guianas to the north and the Guaporé
to the south of the Amazonian Craton (Tassinari &amp;amp;
Macambira, 1999). To the east, it is separated from the Marajó
Basin by the Gurupá Arch, and to the west it is separated
from Solimões Basin by a subsurface basement-high, the N-
S trending Purus Arch. The basin holds a Proterozoic through
Recent sedimentary and sub-volcanic stratigraphic record
up to 6,000 m thick, in the central area. The Carboniferous-
Permian contribution accounts for more than half of the total
deposition (Caputo, 1984, Milani &amp;amp; Zalán, 1998).

The Pennsylvanian-Permian deposits are represented by
the Tapajós Group, which comprises the Monte Alegre,
Itaituba, Nova Olinda and Andirá Formations. The Itaituba
Formation, the focus of this paper, varies in thickness from
110 m in the southern outcrops area to 420 m in the central
part of the basin. This formation represents the establishment
of widespread marine conditions. It consists of diverse
carbonate rocks including lime mudstones, wackestones,
packstones, and oolitic and peloidal grainstones and includes
a rich faunal association with brachiopods, crinoids,
bryozoans, corals, foraminifers, trilobites, ostracodes,
gastropods, bivalves, scolecodonts, and fish teeth. Although
conodonts are low in numbers, they are more abundant and
diverse in the Itaituba Formation than the other formations
of the Tapajós Group, occurring in the three geographic areas
of the Itaituba Formation.

SYSTEMATIC PALEONTOLOGY

Diplognathodus Kozur &amp;amp; Merrill in Kozur (1975)

Type species. Spathognathodus coloradoensis Murray &amp;amp;
Chronic, 1965.
Diagnosis. A sphatognathodid consisting anteriorly of a
blade-like portion and posteriorly of an enlarged cup of
subelliptical shape, both portions separated orally by a
distinct notch. The blade–like portion is formed by laterally
compressed denticles and extends anteriorly into a single
row of more rounded denticles an undenticulated carina.

Diplognathodus coloradoensis (Murray &amp;amp; Chronic, 1965)
(Figures 2A, B)

Spathognathodus coloradoensis Murray &amp;amp; Chronic,
1965: 606-607, pl. 72: 11-13; Webster, 1969: 44, pl. 7: 7; Merrill,
1973: 304, pl. 3: 20-42.

Diplognathodus coloradoensis (Murray &amp;amp; Chronic);
Merrill, 1975: 48-50, figs. 16: 40, 17: 16; Landing &amp;amp; Wardlaw,
1981: 1257-1259, pl. 1: 4, 5, 8.

Description. In lateral view unit small, slightly arched. In oral
view blade with four to six denticles more or less uniform in
length, posterior part of the oral edge consisting of
approximately one half of the total length composed of single
spatula-like ridge (carina) which is separated from the
denticulate blade by a prominent notch. The carina is distinctly
lower than the denticulate blade. In aboral view a large and
symmetrical basal cavity, deep beneath the carina and
continuing as a groove along aboral surface of the blade.
Remarks. This species is distinguished from D. orphanus in
having a nondenticulate carina, the blade with uniform
denticles and not as high as in D. orphanus, and the
prominent notch.
Material. 39 specimens.

Diplognathodus orphanus (Merrill, 1973)
(Figures 2C, D)

Spathognathodus orphanus Merrill, 1973: 309, pl. 3: 45-56.
Diplognathodus coloradoensis (Murray &amp;amp; Chronic); Landing
&amp;amp; Wardlaw, 1981, pl. 1: 1, 6, 7, 9, 10.
Diplognathodus orphanus (Merrill, 1973); Grubbs, 1984: 69,
pl. 1: 4.
Diplognathodus coloradoensis (Murray &amp;amp; Chronic); Savage
&amp;amp; Barkeley, 1985: 1473, figs. 12: 9-16.

Description. In lateral view element slightly arched, anterior
half of the unit up to twice as high as posterior half. The
denticles of the blade are higher than those of the carina.
They are fused about 2/3 of their length. The denticles of
carina are short and fused over half their length resulting in a
row of denticles of which the free tips are as high as their
fused parts. Between the posteriormost denticle of the blade
and the anterior most denticle of the carina occurs a

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56204



205SCOMAZZON &amp;amp; LEMOS – DIPLOGNATHODUS OCCURRENCE IN THE ITAITUBA FORMATION

suppressed denticle located in front of the apex of the basal
cavity. This point is comparable to the notch of the D.
coloradoensis. The denticles of the carina are almost uniform.
They increase slightly in inclination toward the posterior end
forming a right angle to the aboral side of the unit. In oral
view the unit is almost straight. In aboral view the basal cavity
is deep, wide and subsymmetrical.
Remarks. Diplognathodus orphanus is distinguished from
D. coloradoensis by the latter having the prominent notch
and by the carina; it is coarsely denticulate in the former and

relatively to nondenticulate (spatula) in the latter.
Material. 42 specimens.

Diplognathodus ellesmerensis Bender, 1980
(Figures 2E, F)

Diplognathodus ellesmerensis Bender, 1980: 9-10, pl. 4: 5-7,
11, 15-21, 23-25.
Diplognathodus orphanus (Merrill, 1973); Grubbs, 1984: 69,
pl. 1: 3.

Figure 1. Location map of the studied wells (1- 4) in the Amazonas Basin. Stratigraphic profiles of the wells 2 and 3, showing the
sampled levels (indicated by the numbers), constituting the Diplognathodus  reference section (modified from Scomazzon, 1999).

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56205



REVISTA BRASILEIRA DE PALEONTOLOGIA, 8(3), 2005206

Figure 2. Diplognathus from Itaituba Formation, all hypotypes, in lateral view. A-B, Diplognathodus coloradoensis: A, MP-M-687; B,
MP-M-705; C-D, D. orphanus: C, MP-M-706; D, MP-M-691; E-F, D. ellesmerensis: E, MP-M-696; F, MP-M-694.

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56206



207SCOMAZZON &amp;amp; LEMOS – DIPLOGNATHODUS OCCURRENCE IN THE ITAITUBA FORMATION

Description. In lateral view the specimens are small. The blade
consists of four to five denticles increasing in length toward
the posterior end of the blade. The apex of the basal cavity is
under the notch, which has in general one small denticle. The
blade is twice as high as the posterior portion of the unit. In
some specimens the long axes of the denticles of the blade
slightly diverge giving a particular appearance to the blade.
The denticles of the carina are low, the third or rarely the
fourth denticle from the posterior end is the highest. In oral
view the specimens are straight. In aboral view a broad and
symmetrical basal cavity extends from the posterior end to
about the aboral midpoint of the blade.
Remarks. Diplognathodus ellesmerensis is distinguished
from D. orphanus by unfused denticles of the carina, the
posterior end is sharp and the posteriormost blade denticle
is prominent pointing toward the carina.
Material. 44 specimens.

DISCUSSION

The conodont fauna of the studied material comprises
Diplognathodus coloradoensis, D. orphanus, D.
ellesmerensis, Idiognathodus incurvus, Idiognathoides
sinuatus, Neognathodus bassleri, N. atokaensis, N.
medadultimus, N. roundyi and Adetognathus lautus.

The three Diplognathodus species studied were
recovered from the lower through the upper part of the Itaituba
Formation. While D. orphanus and D. ellesmerensis are more
abundant in the lower part, D. coloradoensis mainly occurs
in the upper part of the formation. The latter species is
characteristic of lower Desmoinesian, but its range is
Morrowan to lower Desmoinesian (von Bitter &amp;amp; Merrill, 1990).
D. orphanus is typical of Atokan age. This species has been
used to characterize this interval in North America by Grubbs
(1984), von Bitter &amp;amp; Merrill (1990), among others.
Diplognathodus ellesmerensis was considered characteristic
of Atokan by Bender (1980). However, van den Boogaard
(1983) and von Bitter &amp;amp; Merrill (1990) suggest that this species
may also range into the early Desmoinesian.

The occurrence of these species is extremely important
to refine the Pennsylvanian of the Amazonas Basin.
Scomazzon (1999), suggested that the Atokan-Desmoinesian
boundary is somewhere between the Itaituba and Nova
Olinda Formations. However, the present conodonts were all
considered of Atokan-early Desmoinesian age. Therefore,

the occurrence of the Atokan guide-form D. orphanus and
other short-ranging conodont species are important for the
dating of the Pennsylvanian strata.

Diplognathodus coloradoensis, D. orphanus and D.
ellesmerensis have been considered to be morphotypes of
one species by Landing &amp;amp; Wardlaw (1981) and Savage &amp;amp;
Barkeley (1985) and as separate species by van den Boogaard
(1983), van den Boogaard &amp;amp; Bless (1985), and von Bitter &amp;amp;
Merrill (1990) because of denticulate or undenticulated
spatulas. Comparing and discussing the Pa elements of the
specimens found in this study we suggest that they belong
to different Diplognathodus species because they have
distinct characteristics discussed in the systematic
paleontology. For an extensive discussion related to inter-
and intra-specific variation of Diplognathodus and its
speciation see von Bitter &amp;amp; Merrill (1990).

CONCLUSIONS

Diplognathodus coloradoensis was found in the lower,
middle and upper part of the Itaituba Formation. According
to the accepted range of this species would be possible to
suggest a Morrowan to early Desmoinesian age to this
interval; however this species is main characteristic of early
Desmoinesian. Nevertheless, the occurrence of
Diplognathodus  orphanus and Diplognathodus
ellesmerensis in the lower and upper part of the formation
help to refine the suggested age pointing to an Atokan age
to this interval.

ACKNOWLEDGMENTS

We are grateful to Nilo Matsuda (PETROBRAS) for his
help with sample collection and discussions. For allowing
access to material we are grateful to Paulus H. Van Der Ven
and Sven Wolf (PETROBRAS). We thank to Eduardo Koester
for his help with preparation of samples. We also thank the
journal editors, to H. Kozur and G. Merrill for the improvements
to this paper. The research was supported by CNPq-CTPETRO
2000-1, grant 461082/2000-4.

REFERENCES

Austin, R.L. 1987. Conodonts: investigative techniques and
applications. 1ª ed. London, British Micropaleontological
Society Series, Ellis Horwood, 562 p.

Bender, K.P. 1980. Lower and Middle Pennsylvanian conodonts
from the Canadian Artic Archipelago. Ottawa, Geological Survey
of Canada, 24 p. (Paper 79-15).

Caputo, M.V. 1984. Stratigraphy, tectonics, paleoclimatology and
paleogeography of northern basins of Brazil. University of
California, Ph.D. thesis, 582 p.

Grubbs, R.K. 1984. Conodont platform elements from the
Wapanucka and Atoka Formations (Morrowan-Atokan) of the
Mill Creek Syncline Central Arbuckle Mountains, Oklahoma.
Oklahoma Geological Survey Bulletin, 136:65-79.

Kozur, H. 1975. Beiträge zur Conodontenfauna des Perm.
Geologisch-Paläontologische Mitteilungen, 5(4):1-44.

Table 1. Conodont distribution along the four wells studied.

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56207



REVISTA BRASILEIRA DE PALEONTOLOGIA, 8(3), 2005208

Kozur, H. &amp;amp; Merrill, G.K. 1975. Genus Diplognathodus. In: Kozur,
H. Beiträge zur Conodontenfauna des Perm. Geologisch-
Paläontologische Mitteilungen, Innsbruck, p. 9-10.

Landing, E. &amp;amp; Wardlaw, B.R. 1981. Atokan conodonts from the
Pennsylvanian outlier of the Michigan Basin. Journal of
Paleontology, 55(6):1251-1269.

Lemos, V.B. 1990. Assembléia de Conodontes do Carbonífero da
Bacia do Amazonas. Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências,
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Ph.D. thesis, 259
p .

Merrill, G.K. 1973. Pennsylvanian nonplatform conodont genera,
I: Spathognathodus. Journal of Paleontology, 47(2):289-314.

Merrill, G.K. 1975. Pennsylvanian conodont biostratigraphy and
paleoecology of northwestern Illinois. Geological Society of
America, 130 p. (Microform Publication 3).

Milani, E.J. &amp;amp; Zalán, P.V. 1998. The geology of Paleozoic cratonic
basins and Mesozoic interior rifts of Brazil. (Brazilian Geology
Part I). AAPG International Conference &amp;amp; Exhibition, 184 p.

Murray, F.N. &amp;amp; Chronic, J. 1965. Pennsylvanian conodonts and
other fossils from insoluble residues of the Minturn Formation
(Desmoinesian), Colorado. Journal of Paleontology, 39(4):594-
610.

Nascimento, S.; Scomazzon, A.K.; Moutinho, L.P.; Lemos, V.B. &amp;amp;
Matsuda, N.S. 2005. Conodont biostratigraphy of the Lower
Itaituba Formation, (Atokan, Pennsylvanian), Amazonas Basin,
Brazil. Revista Brasileira de Paleontologia, 8(3):193-202.

Neis, P.A. 1996. Resultados Biocronoestratigráficos das Associa-
ções de Conodontes da Formação Itaituba, Carbonífero Supe-
rior (Pensilvaniano), da Bacia do Amazonas. Programa de Pós-

graduação em Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Gran-
de do Sul, Master Dissertation, 138 p.

Savage, N.M. &amp;amp; Barkeley, S.J. 1985. Early to Middle Pennsylvanian
conodonts from the Klawak Formation and the Ladrones
Limestone, southeastern Alaska. Journal of Paleontology,
59(6):1451-1475.

Scomazzon, A.K. 1999. Refinamento bioestratigráfico, com base
em conodontes, no Pensilvaniano da Bacia do Amazonas –
Região do Tapajós. Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências,
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Master
Dissertation,142 p.

Tassinari, C.C.G. &amp;amp; Macambira, J.B. 1999. Geochronological
provinces of the Amazonian Craton. Episodes, 22(3):174-182.

van den Boogaard, M. 1983. On some occurrence of Diplognathodus
in Carboniferous strata of Western Europe and North Africa.
Scripta Geologica, 69:19-29.

van den Boogaard, M. &amp;amp; Bless, M.J.M. 1985. Some conodont
faunas from the Aegiranum Marine Band. Proceedings of the
Koninklijke Nederlandse Akademi van Wetenschappen, Series
B, 88:133-154.

von Bitter, P.H. &amp;amp; Merrill, G.K. 1990. Effects of variation on the
speciation and phylogeny of Diplognathodus. Courier
Forschungsinstitut Senckenberg, 118:105-129.

Wang, Zhi-hao &amp;amp; Qi, Yu-Ping 2002. Report on the Pennsylvanian
conodont zonation from the Nashui section of Loudian,
Guizhou, China. Newsletter on Carboniferous Stratigraphy,
20:29-33.

Received May, 2005; accepted October, 2005.

05_Art04_Scomazzon.pmd 28/11/2005, 13:56208


</field>
	</doc>
</add>