<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.17109</field>
		<field name="filename">23861_Com96-p101.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis - Santo António de Pádua
sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 

T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS*1; P. E. FONSECA**; J. M. MUNHÁ**; C. C. G. TASSINARI*** &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO***

Keywords: Transpression, flower structure, deformation partition, antithetical kinematics, Ribeira Fold Belt.

Abstract: New structural analysis and petrological results on granulites from the central segment of Ribeira Fold Belt indicate that the
regional thrusts D1 (245-260°, 55-70° NW) was coeval with the high grade peak metamorphism at 565 – 575 Ma, post-dating earlier collision related
nappe thrusts at 630 – 610 Ma (D0). These were mostly erased by D2 thrusting and long-term dextral transpressional shearing (50-65°, 70-85°NW),
simultaneous with very slow cooling of the orogen until 480 – 520 Ma. Brittle, extensional, tectonic event D3 (290-320°, subvertical) is associated
with late granite emplacement in the area, being followed by tectonic collapse that resulted in rapid exhumation/cooling of the high grade rocks
at ~ 470 Ma. Results suggest that a &gt; 35 Ma period of nearly orthogonal shortening between the San Francisco and West Congo cratons occurred until
565 Ma with development of the D1 flower thrust system. Afterwards, when rocks could not absorb further orthogonal shortening, D2 dextral trans-
pressive regime became dominant, turning the flower structure asymmetric. Specific positioning within the flower structure and partition of deforma-
tion induced “local” antithetical sinistral kinematics within the main regional dextral regime and differential exhumation: granulites in the central axis
were rapidly exhumed, whereas along the lateral branches exhumation was much slower resulting in very slow cooling that lasted for almost 100 Ma. 

Palavras-chave: Transpressão, estrutura em flor, partição da deformação, cinemática antitética, Faixa Ribeira.

Resumo: Análise estrutural e resultados petrológicos recentes em granulitos da zona central da Faixa Ribeira indicam que a fase de deformação D1
(cavalgamentos de alta temperatura: 245-260°, 55-70° NW) foi simultânea com o pico metamórfico, atingido aos 565 – 575 Ma, após os episódios coli-
sionais com imbricação de nappes há 630 – 610 Ma (D0). Os marcadores cinemáticos de D0 e D1 foram abundantemente apagados pela fase de defor-
mação D2. Esta apresentou uma componente cavalgante e, fundamentalmente, de cisalhamento direito (50-65°, 70-85° NW), associada a transpressão
direita de longa duração, relacionada com uma prolongada taxa de arrefecimento do orógeno que durou até 480 – 520 Ma. O evento tectónico D3, frágil
e em regime extensional (290-320°, subvertical), associado a relaxamento térmico e à instalação de granitos tardios na área, foi seguido pelo colapso
orogénico, aumentando drasticamente as taxas de arrefecimento há ~ 470 Ma. 

Os resultados sugerem que terá ocorrido um período de &gt; 35 Ma de encurtamento ortogonal entre o Cratão de São Francisco e o Cratão do
Congo Ocidental, até há 565 Ma, com o desenvolvimento da estrutura em flor D1. Posteriormente, quando as rochas deixaram de suportar encurtamento,
o regime transpressivo direito D2 tornou-se predominante, tornando a estrutura em flor assimétrica. O posicionamento específico no interior da estru-
tura em flor e a existência de uma forte partição da deformação induziu cinemática antitética esquerda em alguns locais, dentro da estrutura predomi-
nantemente direita, bem como exumação diferencial: os granulitos na zona central da estrutura foram rapidamente exumados, enquanto nos ramos
laterais a exumação procedeu-se de uma forma mais lenta, resultando em taxas de arrefecimento muito baixas que duraram quase 100 Ma.

Comunicações Geológicas, 2009, t. 96, pp. 101-122

* LNEG – Laboratório Nacional de Energia e Geologia, Estrada da Portela – Zambujal – Alfragide, 2720-866 Amadora, Portugal
(1Corresponding author: telmo.santos@ineti.pt);  

** Centro/Departamento de Geologia, Universidade de Lisboa, Edifício C6, 3º, Campo Grande, 1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal. pefonseca@fc.ul.pt;  
*** Instituto de Geociências, Universidade de São Paulo, Rua do Lago, 562 – Butantã, CEP: 05508-080, São Paulo, Brazil. ccgtassi@usp.br. 

© INETI 2009. Todos os direitos reservados.

1. INTRODUCTION

Geochronological studies and structural analyses of
different sectors of Ribeira Fold Belt (RFB) made in the
past (CORDANI, 1971; CAMPOS NETO &amp;amp; FIGUEIREDO,
1995; MACHADO et al., 1996; HEILBRON &amp;amp; MACHADO,
2003; SCHMITT et al., 2004; ALKMIN et al., 2006)
allowed a better understanding of the global evolution of
this orogenic belt from collision to late-exhumation

times. However, main relationships between the thermo-
tectonic evolution of this Western Gondwana belt and the
imprinted structural features that usually characterize the
Braziliano granulites and the regional size structure
centred in the Paraíba do Sul River valley are still to
explore. In this work, we will try to integrate and summa-
rize the most recent petrological and thermochronologi-
cal data (BENTO DOS SANTOS, 2008; BENTO DOS SANTOS
et al., 2007; 2008b; FONSECA et al., 2008, TASSINARI et



102 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

al., 2006) with the field work developed during the
2004-2009 campaigns with the purpose of obtaining a
new multidisciplinary view of the thermotectonic/geody-
namic evolution of the central segment of the RFB, with
a main focus on the development of the tectonic frame-
work associated with the Além Paraíba – Santo António
de Pádua megashear. 

2. GEOLOGICAL SETTING 

The studied São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua
(SFSAP) sector, is located in the central-north RFB
(CORDANI, 1971), northern Rio de Janeiro State, SE Brazil
(Fig. 1). The RFB extends along the SE coast of Brazil,
over 1,500 km from southern Bahia State to Uruguay,
through Espírito Santo, Rio de Janeiro, Minas Gerais,
São Paulo and Paraná States (CORDANI et al., 1973). This
elongated belt is a NE-SW trending (south and central
sectors) and NNE-SSW trending (northern sector)
Neoproterozoic mobile belt (CORDANI et al., 1973) formed
in the Braziliano-Panafrican Orogeny, as outcome of the

collision between the São Francisco and West Congo
cratons (Fig. 2), from which resulted the southern part of
Western-Gondwana at around 670 – 480 Ma ago
(TROUW et al., 2000). Some authors (EBERT &amp;amp; HASUI,
1998; CAMPOS NETO, 2000) also envisage the involve-
ment of a third cratonic block (or shield), responsible for
the southern RFB structural features, that nowadays lies
beneath the Paraná sedimentary basin. 

One of the main features of this belt is that it consti-
tutes a very complex orogenic zone composed of several
geological units separated by deep dextral shears (DIAS
NETO et al., 2006). The SFSAP sector is located imme-
diately SE to one of this megashears, the Além Paraíba –
Santo António de Pádua shear (APPS) (EGYDIO-SILVA et
al., 2002), that strongly deformed the area rocks impo-
sing a NE-SW trending dextral transpressive shear defor-
mation associated with high grade metamorphism (Fig. 3). 

According to TROUW et al. (2000), RFB could be
divided in four major lithologic associations: a) reworked
Archaean to Paleoproterozoic basement rocks composed
of metavolcanic-sedimentary sequences, granodioritic
orthogneisses and intermediate granulites (HEILBRON et

Fig. 1 – Location of the studied São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector (SFSAP) in the central-north Ribeira Fold Belt, northern Rio de Janeiro
State, SE Brazil (Modified from HEILBRON &amp;amp; MACHADO, 2003). SFC – São Francisco Craton; OcD – Occidental Domain; PSK – Paraíba do
Sul Klippe; OrD – Oriental Domain; CFT – Cabo Frio Terrane. Box locates studied area.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 103

Fig. 2 – Location of the central Ribeira Fold Belt and the Além Paraíba – Pádua Shear zone in the Gondwana Supercontinent (modified from PIPER,
2000) (a) and Ribeira Fold Belt positioning in the Western Gondwana context as the result of the amalgamation between the São Francisco
(SF) and the Congo (Co) cratons (Modified from TROUW et al., 2000) (b). Further abbreviations as in TROUW et al. (2000).

al. 1998); b) a deformed meta-sedimentary sequence
composed of pelitic schists and high grade migmatitic
paragneisses with quartzite, calc-silicate and amphibolite
intercalations; c) molasic sedimentary basins and d)
widespread granitoid intrusive bodies with different

Fig. 3 – The Além Paraíba – Pádua Shear (APPS) system in the central Ribeira Fold Belt (Modified from VAUCHEZ et al., 1994). APPS main shear
is bold and marked. Box locates studied area.

tectonic settings, from pre- to post-collision stages of the
Braziliano orogenic system. 

A common lithologic feature of the RFB is the wide-
spread occurrence of Neoproterozoic charnockites. These
occur as massive metamorphic charnockites, variable



104 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

sized patches and veins of incipient charnockites and as
sin-/late intrusions of enderbites, commonly considered
as massif-type igneous charnockites (TASSINARI et al.,
2006). 

Various tectonic, interpretative kinematics and
geodynamic models have been proposed for the
tectonometamorphic evolution of the RFB (TASSINARI &amp;amp;
CAMPOS NETO, 1988; HEILBRON et al., 1993; CAMPOS
NETO &amp;amp; FIGUEIREDO, 1995; MACHADO et al., 1996;
TROUW et al., 2000; CAMPOS NETO, 2000; SCHMITT,
2001; HEILBRON &amp;amp; MACHADO 2003) and other restricted
areas (DIAS NETO et al., 2006). A dominant ensialic
evolution with important crustal reworking has been
favoured (CORDANI, 1971; CORDANI et al., 1973),
although subordinated oceanic crust subduction (and
obduction) and continental accretion have also been
considered (PEDROSA SOARES &amp;amp; WIEDEMANN-LEONAR-
DOS, 2000; PEDROSA SOARES et al., 2001). 

According to CAMPOS NETO &amp;amp; FIGUEIREDO (1995)
the RFB includes distinct microplates, which were amal-
gamated on Neoproterozoic and Eopaleozoic times,
producing the actual patchwork scenario. Within the
Serra do Mar microplate, which includes the Costeiro
Complex, the Rio Doce Orogeny was active from 590 Ma
to 570 Ma, involving calc-alkaline arc magmatism,
followed by collision (560 – 530 Ma) of the microplate
against the continent and post-collision magmatism
(520 – 480 Ma), characterized by the emplacement of
alkali-calcic plutons and dikes. 

Within the Rio de Janeiro State (central RFB), HEIL-
BRON et al. (1993) and MACHADO et al. (1996) proposed
a tectonometamorphic evolution of the Braziliano Orogeny
divided in 3 stages: a collision period (590 – 565 Ma) in
which occurred the main deformation (D1 + D2) and the
main metamorphic period (M1) with reworking and
partial melting of older continental basement rocks and
emplacement of several granitoid bodies; followed by the
post-collision period at 535 – 520 Ma, corresponding to
D3 and M2 retrograde metamorphism that developed in
response to major dextral shear zones formation. It was
then followed by a post-tectonic period of orogenic
collapse with the emplacement of late granitic plutons. In
a later work, HEILBRON &amp;amp; MACHADO (2003) divided the
central part of the RFB in four tectonic domains (klippen
thrusted against the São Francisco Craton) according to
geochronological data. These authors regarded the RFB
as including, from NW to SE, a) the Occidental Domain,
a pre-1.8 Ga passive margin succession, considered as
being the reworked margin of the São Francisco Craton

(basement); b) the Paraíba do Sul klippe, composed of
amphibolite facies orthogneisses and meta-sediments; c)
the Oriental Domain, comprising the Rio Negro
Magmatic arc (TUPINAMBÁ, 1999) and fore-arc and
back-arc meta-sedimentary sequences; and d) the Cabo
Frio Terrane, an allochthonous terrane belonging to the
West Congo Craton. A younger orogenic event, the Bœzios
orogeny (SCHMITT, 2001), was defined in the Cabo Frio
Terrane (TROUW et al., 2000) at 525 – 520 Ma. The
referred authors suggest that the second collision (Bœzios
Orogeny) exhumed the roots of the APPS producing the
late shearing with strong vertical dislocation. 

In the northern part of the RFB, also named Araçuaí
Belt, a 625 – 595 Ma calc-alkaline magmatic arc was
developed in a continental active margin; this was
followed by a collision stage (595 – 575 Ma) during
which fragmented slices of oceanic crust (dated 800 Ma,
minimum age for ocean-floor basalts) were obducted
upon the sedimentary sequences. Long-term, intensive
granitic magmatism characterized late- to post-collision
times, from 575 to 490 Ma (PEDROSA SOARES &amp;amp; WIED-
MANN-LEONARDOS, 2000; PEDROSA SOARES et al.,
2001). These authors proposed that RFB would be the
result of the development of a complete Wilson Cycle
in a confined environment, namely that the São Fran-
cisco Craton was a paleo-peninsula of the larger Congo
Craton and the north end of the RFB the product of a single
cycle of metamorphism in gulf-deposited sediments.

The former articles, with large impact in the scien-
tific community, led to the concept of a Braziliano
cycle with several orogenic events in which the older
one, in Ribeira Fold Belt, correspond to the 630 – 600 Ma
“Rio Negro Orogeny” (TUPIMAMBÁ, 1999), followed by
the 625 – 575 Ma “Araçuaí’ Orogeny” (PEDROSA SOARES
&amp;amp; WIEDMANN-LEONARDOS, 2000) and the 590 – 570 Ma
“Rio Doce Orogeny” (CAMPOS NETO &amp;amp; FIGUEIREDO,
1995), and finally by the late ~ 520 Ma “Bœzios orogeny”
(SCHMITT, 2001) in the Cabo Frio terrane. 

This work brings a new conceptual model for the
studied area, resulting from an innovative approach of
integrating the structural data with geochronologi-
cal/thermochronological data in central RFB. 

3. STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS 

This study is concentrated in the near area SE to the
Além Paraíba – Santo António de Pádua megashear,
within the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector
(over 2500 Km2 wide) of the Ribeira Fold Belt. 



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 105

From the structural/tectonic point of view, this area
underwent complex polyphase deformation shown by
three main tectonometamorphic phases that globally
correspond to three main thermochronological periods
(BENTO DOS SANTOS et al. 2007; BENTO DOS SANTOS,
2008). The earliest deformation period (D1) corresponds
to high grade thrusts (245-260°, 55-70° NW) and
stretching lineation (55-65°, 5-20°), that were mostly
erased by the major and strongest deformation phase
(D2) that corresponds to the Além Paraíba – Santo
António de Pádua polyphasic thrust and shear system
(APPS). The most impressive shear system in the region
(D2) corresponds to a dextral transpressive megashear
zone (50-65°, 70-85° NW) with a sub-horizontal stretching
lineation (5-20°, 230-235°). A dextral high grade conju-
gated system (120-140°, 80-85° SW)(D2b) related and
synchronous to D2 can commonly be observed. It is a
NNE-NE thrusting system with stretching lineation
printed along the mylonitic foliations of 70°, 230° that is
imprinted (at diverse scales including satellite views) by
the structural/geomorphologic features drawn by the
river in the Santo António de Pádua – São Fidelis sector
(Fig. 4). Finally a brittle tectonic event (corresponding to
the intrusion of the granitoids) D3, corresponds to the
reactivation (opening and thermal relaxation) of the D2b
shear system (290-320°, subvertical) (Fig. 5). Also
ubiquitously present in the studied area as part of the late

brittle regime, crosscutting all the previous structures, is
a metric scale sub-horizontal discontinuity (D3b) that
represents the tardy-tectonic rebound of the exhumation-
-caused tectonic collapse (CLIFT et al., 2004). 

The stated field observations are compatible with a
global structural framework of an asymmetrical flower
structure tilted to the São Francisco Craton but with a
larger (verging) SE branch, as the result of the collision
between the two cratons (Fig. 6). 

An important structural feature of the studied area is
that D1 + D2 deformation phases correspond to a dextral
transpressional regime developing in a non-homoge-
neous tectonic system with characteristics of deforma-
tion partition (TEYSSIER et al., 1995; TASSINARI et al.,
2004), evidenced by the cartographic presence of
secondary discrete megashear corridors (Fig. 7) occurring
parallel to the main APPS, separated by considerable
distances (5 to 10 km). 

Intense granulite facies metamorphism simultaneous
with D1 collision phase produced generalized migmati-
zation and granitization by the partial melting of
paragneisses. Outcrops in the area comprise the referred
migmatitic paragneisses (metatexites), interlayered with
marbles, calc-silicates and amphibolites; diatexitic
migmatites; massive and incipient-type charnockites
associated with their granitic to granodioritic orthogneiss
precursors and aplites; and blastomylonites that resulted
from the relatively late deformation (D2) and retrogres-
sion of the other major rock types in areas closer to the
APPS (Fig. 8 – 11). The former lithologic units are com-
monly intruded by late undeformed granites and
pegmatitic veins associated with D3. 

Metatexites show a clear separation of gneissic paleo-
some and aplitic neosome. Gneissic banding is well
developed in these rocks, as well as clear evidence of late
deformation and retrogression. Diatexites comprise large
elongated or rounded, undeformed and homogeneous
granular garnet-biotite-hornblende granitic to migmatitic
batholiths, derived by the partial melting of metatexites.
In the study area, charnockitic rocks range from ender-
bites (basic charnockites) to charnockites (s. s.), occur-
ring in elongated NE-SW trending massifs. 

The structural observations performed in the study
area allow us to state that the amphibolitic facies retro-
gression of this granulitic sector is intimately associated
with the large late dextral shearing that produced the
blastomylonitic occurrences, as well as the major rock
lineaments. However, this late deformation was not
equally distributed, as metatexites present a penetrative

Fig. 4 – Stereographic projection of stretching lineations mapped
along the mylonitic foliations of D2 APPS system showing
rare high vertical ascension in the central parts of the flower
structure and dominant almost horizontal shearing in the late-
ral branches of the flower structure. Lower hemisphere equals
area plot.



106 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

Fig. 5 – Summarized deformation phases present in the studied area: a) D1 high-temperature thrusts in metatexites; b) and c) APPS in the Três Rios
area showing book-shelf (special antithetical sinistral kinematics) and dominant dextral “thrusting clasts” textures; d) conjugated D2b of the
APPS with thrusting of a granulite onto a sheared migmatite near Cambuci; e) Late D3 pegmatite outcrop cutting the D2 amphibolites in Três
Rios; f) Late D3 pegmatite cutting metatexites.

Fig. 6 – 3D schematics of the inferred asymmetric flower structure
present in the studied area. The studied area is located in the
central (Santo António de Pádua) to the east (São Fidelis) part
of the roots of this flower structure.

Fig. 7 – Detailed example (at outcrop scale) of deformation partition
where a centimetric dextral corridor concentrates deformation.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 107

Fig. 8 –  Several field examples of the studied metatexites (a-e) and marble pockets in metatexites (f).

Fig. 9 –  Field examples of the studied diatexites showing clear homogeneous look.



108 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

deformation whereas the stiffer charnockitic and
diatexitic rocks preserved themselves as very large
boudins with deformed margins. Geomorphologically,
these granular rocks (charnockites and diatexites) are
inselbergs placed between deformation corridors that
preserved them as kilometric boudins with deformed
margins, a typical case of deformation partition in the
study area. Field cartography of the studied area further

shows that these outcrops were constrained by the main
deformation structures that produced a “boudinage”-like
mapping with the migmatites stretching lineations outlining
the main rigid bodies, especially away from the centre of the
APPS (Fig. 12). 

Another geomorphologic example of inferred defor-
mation partition is the abrupt change in the direction of
the main course of the Paraíba do Sul River that is

Fig. 10 –  Several field examples of the studied massive charnockites (a-b); orthogneisses (c); aplites (d-e); and sheared charnockites (f-h).



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 109

Fig. 11 –  Field examples of the studied blastomylonites.

Fig. 12 – Geological map of the studied SFSAP
sector that evidences mega-shear corridors
and boudin-like outcropping for charno-
ckites and diatexites in a “matrix” of
migmatites and blastomylonites. Tectonic
imbrication is visible for charnockites and
diatexites. Stereographic projections show
progressive dip decrease of the D1
stretching lineations (X1) from Santo
António de Pádua area (centre of the APPS
flower structure) to São Fidelis area (lateral
branch of the flower structure). £Sm is the
average pole for the mylonitic foliations
where stretching lineations were measured.
Lower hemisphere equals area plot.



110 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

tectonically controlled by the dextral D2b conjugated
shears that are also discrete corridors, although with a
smaller strain rate than the main APPS. 

Also seldom present in the study area is a sinistral
antithetical regime near the strong and imposing dextral
faults that globally dominate and define the tectonic D2
transpressive regime. 

Field observations and stereographic projections also
suggest that the studied area underwent strong deforma-
tion partition that placed highly deformed rocks side by
side to almost isotropic rocks (like the charnockite
massifs). Moreover, it is suggested that it was this long-
-term transpressive regime, with associated deformation

partition, that slowly exhumed the roots of this lower
crust segment (Fig. 13).

Summarizing, the study area is characterized by a
long and strong megastructure – the APPS shear system
– with a current low angle stretching lineation (10-15°)
underlined by the Paraíba do Sul River between Andrade
Pinto and Cambuci (Rio de Janeiro State). This megas-
tructure is the central axis of a complex parallel shear
system dominated by discrete structures in a globally
transpressional regime that deformed and retrograded the
high grade granulitic rocks and exhumed the various
lithologies at different rates (BENTO DOS SANTOS et al.,
2007; BENTO DOS SANTOS, 2008). 

The first collision pulse of the transpression is made
by high velocity vertical movements (D1) at the apical
zone, whereas the parallel “lateral sheets or lateral
ramps” of the inferred asymmetrical flower structure
have lower dip angles, which makes its ascension
(exhumation) to be much slower, as commonly observed
in flower structures systems (Fig. 6). 

Because the collision between the two cratons (São
Francisco and West Congo) is oblique and progressively
more tangential, a dramatically change in the exhumation
rate between the centre of the structure and the lateral
sheets occurs: while the movement is mainly collision,
with fast shortening by compression of the central part,
exhumation of the central part is faster than in the periph-
ery, and when the main shortening process ends and
transpression becomes the main deformation process
(SANDERSON &amp;amp; MARCHINI, 1984), the main vertical
ascension changes to the lateral sheets, turning the
exhumation rates from fast to slow in the central part and
inversely in the lateral sheets (Fig. 14). 

Fig. 13 – Stereographic projection with D1 high-temperature thrusts
showing clear dichotomy between the central part of the
flower structure (almost vertical thrusting) and the lateral
branches that show almost horizontal imbrication-style
shearing. Lower hemisphere equals area plot.

Fig. 14 – Geodynamic evolution of the APPS system and tectonic implications
of exhumation for the central and peripheral parts of the flower
structure during D1 and D2 deformation phases.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 111

4. PETROGRAPHY

4.1. Metatexites 

The metatexites paleosome commonly comprises a g
+ bi + pl + q + ksp + ru + mt ± ilm ± ap ± sill ± mu ± sp

(Mineral abbreviations according to POWELL &amp;amp; HOLLAND,
1999) gneissic association, whereas the neosomatic frac-
tion is a q + pl + ksp + g + bi ± sill ± ap aplite (Fig. 15). 

The anastomosing granolepidoblastic texture largely
defined by the bi + q association is commonly obliterated
by coarse grained, sometimes centimetric, sub-euhedral or

Fig. 15 – Metatexite petrography with generic mineral assemblages present in these rocks.



112 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

rounded poikiloblastic garnet, plagioclase and K-feldspar
granoblasts. These megablasts frequently have matrix
mineral inclusions, like biotite and opaque minerals, and
are usually deformed, bent, cracked and with recrystali-
zed rims, representing the metamorphic peak paragenesis
of the metatexites, possibly with small amounts of quartz
and residual biotite. Quartz is also abundant in garnet
microcraks and in contact areas between megablasts.
Symplectitic bi + q + sill growth after garnet is a
common feature of these rocks. In some cases these

migmatites are intensively sheared, originating fine
grained mylonitic banding with abundant (sometimes
centimetric) sillimanite and/or muscovite. 

4.2. Diatexites 

Homogeneous, undeformed, medium grain sized
pl + q + ksp + bi + g + amph ± ap assemblage is typical,
having rare ilmenite, muscovite and in one case small
amounts of orthopyroxene (Fig. 16). The texture is

Fig. 16 – Diatexite petrography with generic mineral assemblages present in these rocks.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 113

frequently dominated by biotite, imposing a granolepi-
doblastic texture to the rock or in some cases, granone-
matoblastic, when amphibole is dominant. Garnet is
commonly surrounded by biotite and amphibole, whether
along the rims or in small symplectites with quartz. 

4.3. Charnockites 

According to their paragenesis and occurrence they
can broadly be divided in three types: 

a) isotropic charnockites (s. s.): medium to coarse
sized granoblastic texture with megablastic (sometimes

centimetric) sub-euhedral pl + ksp (microcline) + g + opx
is common. Q + bi + ilm + mt + ap + zrc are only present
as diffuse, rarely orientated, matrix minerals. As in meta-
texites, megablasts commonly have a large amount of
mineral inclusions, as well as, deformed and cracked
rims. Bi + q symplectites are common around garnet and
pyroxene rims (Fig. 17); 

b) Margins of the charnockite massifs: charnockites
with fine grained mylonitic or cataclastic lepidoblastic
texture with bi + pl + ksp + q + opx (relict) + ap ± g ±
amph mineral assemblage. Metamorphic peak mine-
rals (pl + ksp + q + opx + g) are intensively deformed,

Fig. 17 – Petrography (with generic mineral assemblages) of isotropic charnockites.



114 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

fractured, grinded, and replaced by an amphibolite facies
assemblage of bi + amph + ilm (Fig. 18); 

c) Enderbites: banded, medium to coarse grained
sub-euhedral pl + opx + cpx + g metamorphic peak para-
genesis, replaced by the amph + pl ± bi assemblage is a
common feature of these basic charnockites. The large
amount of amphibole and small amount of biotite imprint
a granonematoblastic texture to this rock. Contrary to
charnockites (s. s.), enderbites show large quantity of
clinopyroxene, probably due to its more calcic composi-
tion. In fact, it is possible to observe amphibole inclu-
sions in pyroxene and at the same time amphibole replac-
ing both orthopyroxene and clinopyroxene (Fig. 19). 

4.4. Blastomylonites

Migmatites and charnockites are profusely retro-
gressed and deformed in the near region of Santo
António de Pádua, centre of the APPS. There, it is impos-
sible to determine the rocks’ sources, because of the blas-
tomylonitic transformation they have experienced.
Therefore, the global denomination of blastomylonite is
employed. In a petrographic point of view they are equi-
valent to their undeformed counterparts, with the excep-
tion of having a profuse equigranular mylonitic texture
with abundant cracked, grinded and finely recrystalized
mineral grains (Fig. 20). Mineralogical replacement of
metamorphic peak assemblage progresses in the same

Fig. 18 – Petrography (with generic mineral assemblages) of deformed and sheared charnockites.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 115

Fig. 19 – Petrography (with generic mineral assemblages) of coarse grained enderbites.

way as previously stated, with the exception that in blas-
tomylonites there are only remnants of the high grade
paragenesis. 

5. ANALYTICAL METHODS 

Samples were prepared for the different types of
analyses at the Instituto de Geociências da Universidade
de São Paulo and at the Departamento de Geologia da
Universidade de Lisboa. 

Mineral composition data was determined on carbon
coated polished thin sections using a JEOL JXA 733
wavelength dispersive Electron Microprobe, at the
Centro de Geologia da Faculdade de Ciências da
Universidade de Lisboa (CeGUL). Minerals were
analysed with an acceleration voltage of 15 kV and a

current of 10 nA, using a beam of 5 µm. Both natural and
synthetic silicates and oxides were used as standards. 

6. MINERAL CHEMISTRY SYNTHESIS 

Extensive mineral chemistry descriptions of these
rocks are accessible elsewhere (BENTO DOS SANTOS,
2008; BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2006; 2008a; MUNHÁ et
al., 2008). A brief portrayal of the São Fidelis – Santo
António de Pádua sector rocks, with main focus on blas-
tomylonites, is presented in this chapter. Because blasto-
mylonites are the result of late retrogression of the
SFSAP sector granulites and are composed of different
parageneses according to their protoliths, they commonly
show a great range of compositional values in the
mineral chemistry results. 



116 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

6.1. Feldspars

Although anorthite contents in plagioclase (Xan) of
all rock types rarely have a pronounced zoning from core
to rim (maximum zoning is 0.1 for Xan, with cores
having a general slightly lower anorthite content), diffe-
rent samples of the same rock type from different places
show high scope of values, ranging from Xan = 0.29 to
0.51 for charnockites (s. s.), from Xan = 0.30 to 0.47 for
enderbites, Xan = 0.27 to 0.39 for metatexites, Xan = 0.35
to 0.43 for diatexites and Xan = 0.35 to 0.50 for the inter-
layered amphibolites in metatexites. Blastomylonites
show the greatest range in anorthite content because of
the protholiths composition, ranging from Xan = 0.17 to
0.55. K-feldspars are almost pure orthoclases, having a
maximum Xab of 0.13. 

6.2. Garnet 

Almandine-rich phases are present in all rock types,
with Xalm always higher than 0.54, and always with
Mg-richer cores compared to the rims. Although, all rock
types show the same zoning pattern from core (Mg-rich)

to rim (Fe-rich), they all have different range of values,
namely Xalm = 0.66 to 0.75 and Xpy = 0.09 to 0.21 for
charnockites (s. s.), Xalm = 0.62 to 0.70 and Xpy = 0.11
to 0.15 for enderbites, Xalm = 0.58 to 0.75 and Xpy= 0.17
to 0.37 for metatexites, Xalm = 0.54 to 0.67 and Xpy =
0.07 to 0.09 for diatexites and Xalm = 0.59 to 0.77 and
Xpy = 0.11 to 0.19 for blastomylonites, making the meta-
texites the richest in pyrope content and poorer in grossu-
lar content (maximum Xgr of 0.05) whereas diatexites
have the richest grossular content (Xgr = 0.21 to 0.27).
When compared with charnockites (s. s.), enderbites are
naturally richer in calcium having Xgr ranging from 0.15
to 0.22, while their acidic counterparts range from 0.02
to 0.18. Spessartite content is always low, reaching a top
content of 0.13 in charnockites and diatexites, while
enderbites and metatexites are always below 0.05. 

6.3. Pyroxenes 

In charnockites, orthopyroxenes have enstatite
contents (Xen) that range from 0.39 to 0.48 with a maxi-
mum 3% wollastonite content (Xwo) and Al2O3 contents
ranging from 0.76 to 3.40 Wt %. They are slightly zoned

Fig. 20 – Blastomylonite petrography with generic mineral assemblages present in these rocks: blastomylonitized migmatites (a-b); blastomylonitized
charnockites (c-d).



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 117

with Mg-richer cores. Enderbites have similar core to rim
zoning pattern and enstatite content ranging from 0.41 to
0.44 and top 2 % wollastonite content, whereas the Al2O3
content is lower, spanning from 0.59 to 0.98 Wt %. The
only blastomylonitic sample with orthopyroxene has
identical enstatite and Al2O3 contents as enderbites.
Amphibolites included in the metatexites have higher
enstatite values ranging from 0.51 to 0.52 and low Al2O3
content, ranging from 0.76 to 0.95 Wt %. Clinopyro-
xenes are commonly unzoned from core to rim, having a
wollastonite content of 0.42 to 0.48 for all samples and
enstatite contents of 0.30 to 0.35 for enderbites and blas-
tomylonites, and 0.37 to 0.41 for amphibolites. 

6.4. Biotite 

Enderbites and diatexites have low-Mg biotites ranging
from XMg = 0.42 to 0.43 and XMg = 0.36 to 0.38,
respectively, while charnockites and blastomylonites have
low to high-Mg biotites ranging from XMg = 0.39 to 0.55.
TiO2 contents are relatively high for enderbites (TiO2 = 
= 5.7 – 5.8 Wt %) and charnockites (TiO2 = 3.8 – 6.3 Wt %),
as expected for higher grade rocks, but also for blastomy-
lonites (TiO2 = 4.9 – 5.8 Wt %). Diatexites have smaller
TiO2 values ranging from 3.7 to 4.5 Wt %. Metatexites
and amphibolites have Fe-poor biotites; XMg values
span from 0.52 to 0.76 and 0.55 to 0.65, respectively.
Their TiO2 contents are also similar (3.7 – 4.5 Wt %). 

6.5. Amphiboles 

Amphiboles are typically hornblendes with XMg
values spanning from 0.35 to 0.54 in charnockites, ender-
bites and diatexites, with enderbites having progressively
Mg-richer amphiboles. However, the amphibole TiO2
contents of diatexites is lower (TiO2 = 1.1 – 1.5 Wt %) than
granulites (TiO2 = 1.8 – 2.4 Wt %). Amphibolites have
the richest TiO2 and Mg contents in amphibole, ranging
from TiO2 = 1.0 – 3.0 Wt % and XMg = 0.54 – 0.73. 

7. GEOTHERMOBAROMETRY

A geothermobarometric study in the blastomylonitic
occurrences was performed in order to constrain the
maximum metamorphic conditions for the beginning of
the APPS. Therefore, as described in the previous chapter,

core and rim major element analysis of each mineral was
attained. 

Temperature estimates for the blastomylonitic occur-
rences were determined using the g-bi Fe-Mg exchange
thermometer of FERRY &amp;amp; SPEAR (1978) corrected by
HODGES &amp;amp; SPEAR (1982), the g-cpx Fe-Mg exchange
thermometer of ELLIS &amp;amp; GREEN (1979), the g-amph Fe-Mg
exchange thermometer of GRAHAM &amp;amp; POWELL (1984),
the amph-pl Na-Ca exchange thermometer of HOLLAND
&amp;amp; BLUNDY (1994), the 2 pyroxenes thermometer and the
ol – cpx thermometer of ANDERSEN &amp;amp; LINDSLEY (1988).
Pressures were determined using the GDISP barometer
of ECKERT &amp;amp; NEWTON (1991), the GASP barometer of
NEWTON &amp;amp; HASELTON (1981), the GRIPS and GRAIL
barometers of GHENT &amp;amp; STOUT (1984) and the g-amph
barometer of KOHN &amp;amp; SPEAR (1990). 

Blastomylonites show retrogressed maximum tem-
peratures and pressures ranging from 785 to 615 °C and
8.2 to 6.4 kbar. These temperature estimates are clearly
within range of other existing results for the central RFB,
such as BASCOU et al. (2002), KUHN et al. (2004), and
SCHMITT et al. (2004). There are few works with pres-
sure estimates for the central RFB, but these new results
are higher than previously stated by other authors (REGO,
1989; KUHN et al., 2004; NOGUEIRA et al., 2004). 

These temperature and pressure estimates must be
considered as minimum conditions for formation of these
blastomylonites as they present highly retrogressed T and
P, and obviously much lower conditions than the gra-
nulitic protoliths from which they derived. Therefore, it
is shown that the APPS associated deformation occurred
at high-grade temperatures, which is compatible with field
and geochronological data now presented. Core to rim
compositional zoning for blastomylonites show !T = –150
to –250° C and !P = –1.5 to –2.5 kbar (T ~ 500 °C and
P ~ 5 kbar) after maximum metamorphic conditions, that
are globally considered as resulting from the continuous
chemical reequilibration caused by extensive long-term
shearing. 

8. THERMOCHRONOLOGICAL DATA FOR
THE CENTRAL RIBEIRA FOLD BELT

Because thermochronological studies use the integra-
tion of several geochronological systems with the respec-
tive closure temperature of that isotopic system, they are
extremely important in depicting how different rock
types were cooled, and ultimately how the exhumation



118 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

process occurred, namely tectonic/geodynamic evolution
from rock-forming temperatures to late-exhumation
times. 

Several studies performed in the south, central and
north zones of the Ribeira Fold Belt (DIAS NETO, 2001;
BENTO DOS SANTOS, 2008; MUNHÁ et al., 2005, respec-
tively) have shown that after metamorphic peak condi-
tions were reached at ~ 590 – 565 Ma (TASSINARI et al.,
2006), a long-term slow cooling regime was maintained
until 520 – 470 Ma (Fig. 21) when rocks began to cool
rapidly by thrusting onto cooler basement or associated
with post-orogenic fault tectonics, probably related with
the initial stages of Paraná basin-type sedimentary
infilling (BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2007; 2008b). 

9. DISCUSSION 

Previous works in other sectors of the Ribeira Fold
Belt (MACHADO et al., 1996; SCHMITT, 2001; HEILBRON
&amp;amp; MACHADO, 2003) suggest a prior event to D1 that
correspond to the earlier imbrication nappes thrust
system. Along the studied area there are no structural
evidence of this previous to D1 event (here called D0) but
it was clearly registered by geochronological results
around 630 – 610 Ma (MACHADO et al., 1996; TASSINARI
et al., 2006; BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2007). The
referred geochronological data points out the beginning
of the earlier collision stages, between the Congo and
S. Francisco cratons. 

The structural field studies combined with the
previous thermochronological data suggest that D1
deformation phase is responsible for the early exhuma-
tion of the majority of migmatites and blastomylonites,
as well as some charnockites whereas the majority of
charnockites were maintained in high depths and are
slowly exhumed along the lateral ramps of the branches
of the collision asymmetrical flower structure. The
tectonic imbrication, related with deformation partition,
results in a non-homogeneous exhumation: whereas in
the central axis of APPS the exhumation and ascension of
the blastomylonites is swift with a strong retrogression of
the lithologies, along the lateral branches the processes is
much slower because of the small dip angle (5 to 10°) of
the thrusts associated with the oblique stretching along
these planes (30-45° of obliquity). That geometrical
characteristic produces only a high retrogression on the
charnockite borders whereas the “boudin”-like batholith
cores remained virtually undeformed and with a
preserved granulitic paragenesis. Another characteristic
feature of this tectonic exhumation style is the presence
of the dextral lateral shears along very discrete shear
thrusts with a notorious deformation partition – that
includes very deformed corridors separating blocks with
almost no within deformation, as can be seen in Pedreira
do Itereré where side-by-side rocks have a garnet – whole
rock Sm-Nd ages with a 40 Ma age difference (BENTO
DOS SANTOS et al., 2007; BENTO DOS SANTOS et al.,
2008b), showing very disparate exhumation styles and
rates (see Fig. 21). 

Fig. 21 – Thermochronological evolution of the studied rocks (BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2007a; BENTO DOS SANTOS, 2008). It is possible to
observe 2 different cooling paths between metatexites and blastomylonites (squares), that reach T &amp;lt;650 ºC before 520 Ma and charnockites
and associated aplites and orthogneisses (circles) that reach T &amp;lt;650 ºC at 520 – 470 Ma.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 119

Within this tectonic model, it is evident that the
global evolution of the APPS system (during D1 and D2
event) from early-collision to late-exhumation times
influenced the rates of exhumation in the different zones
of the APPS system, as well as the lithologic associations
formed during this orogeny. Therefore, it is not strange to
find the main blastomylonitic occurrences in the central
part of the APPS and the isotropic (or less deformed)
charnockites (inferred as the last to drop from the high
temperature conditions; BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2007)
in the lateral part of the flower structure (Fig. 22). 

A multiscale repeated geometry from microscale to
megascale/mapping low scale dimension was observed
in the studied area. An example of this peculiar geome-
tric pattern can be observed in the repeated changes of
the structural features near the rigid bodies (i.e. sigmoid
biotite shape near garnets on the petrographic scale, or
metatexites non-asymmetrical kinematics body with
dextral shear criteria attitudes in the vicinities of
charnockite “boudin”-like bodies on the regional scale). 

The new structural and thermobarometric data
obtained suggests that the APPS activity began at an

early stage in the global tectonic evolution of Ribeira
Fold Belt. Because blastomylonites (the deformed and
highly retrograded granulite counterparts) show esti-
mated mineral temperatures of almost 800° C (HOLLAND
&amp;amp; BLUNDY, 1994), it must be assumed that these rocks
were retrogressed by D2 deformation phase (APPS
megashear corridors) when this crustal segment still
presented very high temperatures. PORCHER et al. (1995)
and BASCOU et al. (2002) also obtained very high
temperatures for these blastomylonites in the near areas
of Santo António de Pádua. These results are compatible
with previous works developed by MACHADO et al.
(1996) that suggest that APPS megashear may have
begun around 600 to 550 Ma ago and BENTO DOS
SANTOS et al. (2007) that constrained that initial activity
at around 575 to 550 Ma. 

The APPS megastructure was responsible in an early
stage for the exhumation of deep rocks by a system of
earlier thrusts, corresponding to a mainly collision stage
that probably generated a symmetrical flower structure
from which there are no evidence nowadays. These
earlier deformation stages and thrust system evidence

Fig. 22 – Tectonic implications on the exhumation styles of different parts of the APPS and consequent deformation/preservation of the different rocks with
blastomylonite occurrence in the central part of the shear system and charnockite occurrence in the lateral branches of the flower structure.



120 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

were nearly totally obliterated by the dextral main shear
system where deformation partition was concentrated at
discrete almost vertical surfaces. Inside the almost
preserved blocks, between those discrete surfaces, it is
possible to observe some antithetical sinistral kinematics
in a globally dextral regime. This phenomenon occurs
where the deformation partition is so intense that the
rheological behaviour of a material in the vicinities of a
strong dextral shear corridor is forced to have the oppo-
site kinematics (CARRERAS, 2001) (Fig. 23). This is also
suggested for the escape tectonics proposed by VAUCHEZ
et al. (1992) and EGYDIO-SILVA et al. (2002) for the
south and south-central RFB that probably caused the
antithetic shears observed by DIAS NETO et al. (2006) in
the São Sebastião – Ilha Bela region. 

The previously referred thermochronological data
(DIAS NETO, 2001; BENTO DOS SANTOS et al., 2007) and
the structural observations for the D2 deformation phase
supports the existence of very long-term transpressive
dextral regime for the APPS activity that may have lasted
from metamorphic peak ages (about 575 Ma) to late
exhumation of some charnockites (about 490 Ma) when
D3 thermal collapse granite emplacement and a global
thermal relaxation with layer-type opening of D3b
discontinuities occurred.

The structural framework present in the SE Brazilian
Ribeira Fold Belt underlines an oblique collision
between two Paleoproterozoic cratons (being the present
geographic coordinates of São Francisco at NW and West
Congo at SE) and their suture corresponding to the main
transpressive shear corridor in the area – APPS. This

collision scar is also marked by the Dom Silvério Group
800 Ma ophiolitic remnants (PEDROSA SOARES et al.,
2001) that represent a post-1 Ga (TROMPETTE, 2002)
oceanization period to the north. Although, the presence
of these oceanic slivers would be more probable to the
SW (our study area), because of the larger space between
the two cratons prior to the collision, these ophiolitic
slices do not outcrop, probably because of the much
stronger deformation imposed by the paleotopographic
coast lines that induced a closer proximity and the
respective larger strain rate. 

10. CONCLUSIONS 

Although in the study area there is no structural
evidence for the D0 thrust nappe system, geochronologi-
cally it is inferred by the oldest 630 to 610 Ma ages
previously obtained, considered as belonging to the
initial stages of continental collision. A &gt; 35 Ma period
of orthogonal shortening between the two cratons
occurred until ~ 575 – 565 Ma when metamorphic peak
conditions were reached, simultaneously with the deve-
lopment of the D1 flower thrust system. When orthogo-
nal shortening turned rheologically problematic, because
rocks could not absorb further shortening, D2 dextral
transpressive regime became the main deformation phase
soon after the granulitic metamorphic peak at T ~ 800° C.
This dextral cinematic change associated with the original
São Francisco and West Congo cratons shapes produced
an asymmetric flower structure with a more developed

Fig. 23 – Special antithetical sinistral kinematics in a globally dextral regime caused by differential deformation rates.



Geodynamic evolution of the São Fidelis – Santo António de Pádua sector, central Ribeira Fold Belt, SE Brazil 121

SE branch. The SE branch shows triclinic fabric features
(DIAS NETO et al., 2006) with a strong oblique stretching
lineation that was responsible for a very slow exhuma-
tion in the lateral branches of this flower structure that
may have lasted for 80 to 100 Ma. When the long-term
transpressive exhumation associated with gravitatio-
nal/erosional collapse of the orogen (progressive thin-
ning of the lithosphere) ceased, D3 relaxation opening
with granitoid/pegmatitic emplacement occurred. 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 

FAPESP, POCA-PETROLOG (CEGUL, UI: 263;
POCTI/FEDER) and GEODYN (POCTI – ISFL – 5 – 32)
and a PhD scholarship from FCT (SFRH/BD/17014/2004)
co-financed by FEDER provided support for field and
analytical work. Teresa Palácios and Octávio Chaveiro
are gratefully acknowledged for long-term logistic
support. The authors are very grateful to Ricardo Cara-
nova by the elaboration and graphic treatment of some
figures. The authors are also grateful for the comments
and suggestions of Prof. Fernando Noronha and an
anonymous reviewer that greatly added to the improve-
ment of this work. 

REFERENCES

ALKMIN, F., MARSHAK, S., PEDROSA-SOARES, A., PERES, G., CRUZ, S.,
WHITTINGTON, A. (2006) – Kinematic evolution of the
Araçuaí-West Congo orogen in Brazil and Africa: Nutcracker
tectonics during the Neoproterozoic assembly of Gondwana.
Precambrian Research, 149, 43-64. 

ANDERSEN, D., LINDSLEY, D. H. (1988) – Internally consistent solution
models for Fe-Mg-Mn-Ti oxides: Fe-Ti oxides. American
Mineralogist, 73, 714-726. 

BASCOU, J., RAPOSO, M. I. B., VAUCHEZ, A., EGYDIO-SILVA, M. (2002)
– Titanohematite lattice preferred orientation and magnetic
anisotropy in high-temperature mylonites. Earth and
Planetary Science Letters, 198, 77-92. 

BENTO DOS SANTOS, T. (2008) – Petrologia e termocronologia de granu-
litos no sector central da Faixa Ribeira (Região de São
Fidelis, Rio de Janeiro, Brasil). Unpublished PhD thesis,
University of Lisbon, Lisbon, 388. 

BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., MUNHÁ, J., TASSINARI, C., DIAS NETO, C.,
FONSECA, P. (2006) – Petrologia, Geoquímica e Geocro-
nologia de Granulitos no sector São Fidelis – Santo António
de Pádua, RJ, SE Brasil. VII Congresso Nacional de
Geologia, 1, 241-244. 

BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., MUNHÁ, J., TASSINARI, C., FONSECA, P., DIAS
NETO, C. (2007) – Thermochronological evidence for long-
-term elevated geothermal gradients in Ribeira Belt, SE
Brazil. Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 71, 15, 1, A79. 

BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., MUNHÁ, J., TASSINARI, C., FONSECA, P., DIAS
NETO, C. (2008a) – Metamorphic evolution of Central Ribeira
Belt (SE Brazil) based on pseudosections and P-T-t paths.
Geophysical Research Abstracts, 10, EGU2008-A-00262. 

BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., FONSECA, P., MUNHÁ, J., TASSINARI, C., DIAS
NETO, C. (2008b) – Structural and thermochronological
constrains on the tectonic evolution of Ribeira Belt, SE Brazil.
Geophysical Research Abstracts, 10, EGU2008-A-00261. 

CAMPOS NETO, M. C. (2000) – Orogenic systems from Southwestern-
-Gondwana: an approch to Brasiliano – Pan-Africano Cycle and
collage in Southeastern Brazil. In: Cordani, U. G., Milani, E. J.,
Thomaz-Filho, A., Campos, D. A. (Eds.) Tectonic Evolution of
South América. Rio de Janeiro, 335-365. 

CAMPOS NETO, M. C., FIGUEIREDO, M. C. H. (1995) – The Rio Doce
orogeny, Southeastern Brazil. Journal of South American
Earth Sciences, 8, 2, 143-162. 

CARRERAS, J. (2001) – Zooming on Nothern Cap de Creus shear zones.
Journal of Structural Geology, 23, 1457-1486. 

CLIFT, P., DEWEY, J., DRAUT, A., CHEW, D., MANGE, M., RYAN, P.
(2004) – Rapid tectonic exhumation, detachment faulting and
orogenic collapse in the Caledonides of Western Ireland.
Tectonophysics, 384, 1-4, 91-113. 

CORDANI, U. G. (1971) – Síntese da geocronologia Pré-Cambriana da
região costeira atlântica meridional da América do Sul. Extended
Abstract of the 25th Congresso Brasileiro de Geologia, 179-180. 

CORDANI, U. G., DELHAL J., LEDENT, D. (1973) – Orogenéses super-
posées dans te Précambrien du Brésil sud-oriental (Etats de
Rio de Janeiro et de Minas Gerais). Revista Brasileira de
Geociências, 3, 1-22. 

DIAS NETO, C. M. (2001) – Evolução tectono-termal do complexo costeiro
faixa de dobramentos Ribeira em São Paulo. Unpublished PhD
Thesis, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, 160. 

DIAS NETO, C., FONSECA, P., MUNHÁ, J., EGYDIO-SILVA, M., RIBEIRO, A.
(2006) – The flower structure in the Costeiro Complex
(Ribeira Belt), São Sebastião (São Paulo, Brazil). Cadernos
do Laboratorio Xeoloxico de Laxe, 31, 105-126. 

EBERT, H. D., HASUI, Y. (1998) – Transpressional tectonics and strain
partitioning during oblique collision between three plates in
the Precambrian of south-east Brazil. In: Holdsworth, R. E.,
Strachan, R. A., Dewey, J. F. (Eds.) Continental Transpres-
sional and Transtensional Tectonics, 135, 231-252. 

ECKERT JR., J. O., NEWTON, R. C. (1991) – The !H of reaction and reca-
libration of garnet-pyroxene-plagioclase-quartz geobarome-
ters in the CMAS system by solution calorimetry. American
Mineralogist, 76, 148-160. 

EGYDIO-SILVA, M., VAUCHEZ, A., BASCOU, J., HIPPERTT, J. (2002) –
High-temperature deformation in the Neoproterozoic trans-
pressional Ribeira Belt, southeast Brazil. Tectonophysics,
352, 203-224. 

ELLIS, D. J., GREEN, D. H. (1979) – An experimental study of the effect
of Ca upon Garnet-Clinopyroxene Fe-Mg exchange equili-
bria. Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology, 71, 13-22. 

FERRY, J. M., SPEAR, F. S. (1978) – Experimental calibration of the
partioning of Fe and Mg between biotite and garnet.
Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology, 66, 113-117. 

FONSECA, P., BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., MUNHÁ, J., TASSINARI, C., DIAS
NETO, C. (2008) – Thermochronological and structural analy-
sis of the geodynamic evolution of Ribeira Belt, SE Brazil.
Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta, 72, 12, 1, A276. 



122 T. M. BENTO DOS SANTOS; P. E. FONSECA; J. M. MUNHÁ; C. C. G. TASSINARI &amp;amp; C. DIAS NETO

GHENT, E. D., STOUT, M. Z. (1984) – TiO2 activity in metamorphosed
pelitic and basic rocks: principles and applications to meta-
morphism in southeastern Canadian Cordillera. Contributions
to Mineralogy and Petrology, 86, 248-255.

GRAHAM, C. M., POWELL, R. (1984) – A garnet-hornblende geothermo-
meter: Calibration, testing, and application to the Pelona Schist,
southern California: Journal of Metamorphic Geology, 2, 13-31. 

HEILBRON M., MACHADO, N. (2003) – Timing of Terrane Accretion in
the Neoproterozoic-Eopaleozoic Ribeira Orogen SE Brazil.
Precambrian Research, 125, 87-112. 

HEILBRON, M., TUPIMAMBÁ, M., ALMEIDA, J. C. H., VALERIANO, C. M.,
VALADARES, C. S., DUARTE, B. P. (1998) – New constraints on
the tectonic organization and structural styles related to the
Brasiliano collage of the central segment of RFB, SE Brazil.
Extended Abstract of the 14th International Conference on
Basement Tectonics, 15-17. 

HEILBRON, M., VALERIANO, C. M., TUPIMAMBÁ, M., ALMEIDA, J. C. H.,
VALADARES, C., SILVA, L. G. E., NVA, D. B., DIOS, F. B. (1993) –
Compartimentação tectónica e evolução geológica do segmento
central da Faixa Ribeira, a Sul do Cráton do São Francisco.
Extended Abstract of the II Simpósio do CSF, 263-265. 

HODGES, K. V., SPEAR, F. S. (1982) – Geothermometry, geobarometry
and the Al2SiO5 triple point at Mt. Moosilauke, New
Hampshire. American Mineralogist, 67, 1118-1134. 

HOLLAND, T. J. B., BLUNDY, J. D. (1994) – Non-ideal interactions in
calcic amphiboles and their bearing on amphibole-plagioclase
thermometry. Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology, 116,
433-447. 

KOHN, M. J., SPEAR, F. S. (1990) – Two new geobarometers for garnet
amphibolites, with applications to southeasthern Vermont.
American Mineralogist, 75, 89-96. 

KUHN, A., STUWE, K., TROUW, R. A. J. (2004) – Metamorphic evolution
of the RFB: Evidence from outcrops in the Rio de Janeiro
Area, Brazil. Journal of Petrology, 45, 11, 2303-2323. 

MACHADO, N., VALLADARES, C., HEILBRON, M., VALERIANO, C. (1996)
– U-Pb geochronology of the central RFB Brazil and impli-
cations for the evolution of the Brazilian Orogeny.
Precambrian Research, 79, 347-361. 

MUNHÁ, J., BENTO DOS SANTOS, T., TASSINARI, C., FONSECA, P. (2008) –
Pseudosection and thermobarometry constraints on the P-T-t
evolution of Ribeira Belt, SE Brazil. Geochimica et
Cosmochimica Acta, 72, 12, 1, A664. 

MUNHÁ, J., CORDANI, U., TASSINARI, C., PALÁCIOS, T. (2005) – Petro-
logia e Termocronologia de gnaisses migmatíticos da Faixa
de Dobramentos Araçuaí Espírito Santo, Brasil. Revista
Brasileira de Geociências, 35, 1, 123-134. 

NEWTON, R. C., HASELTON, H. T. (1981) – Thermodynamics of the
garnet-plagioclase-Al2SiO5-quartz geobarometer. In: Newton,
R. C., Navrotsky, A, Wood, B. J. (Eds) Advances in Physical
Geochemistry. New York, 1, 131-147.

NOGUEIRA, J., CHOUDHURI, A., BELLO, R. (2004) – Inclusões fluidas em
granulitos e caminhos P-T-t retrometamórficos para o complexo
Juiz de Fora. Revista Brasileira de Geociências, 34, 4, 509-520.

PEDROSA SOARES, A. C., NOCE, C. M., WIEDMANN-LEONARDOS, C. M.,
PINTO, C. P. (2001) – The Araçuaí-West Congo Orogen in Brazil:
an overview of a confined orogen formed during Gondwanaland
assembly. Precambrian Research, 110, 307-323.

PEDROSA-SOARES, A. C., WIEDEMANN-LEONARDOS, C. M. (2000) –
Evolution of the Araçuai Belt and its connection to the RFB,
Eastern Brazil. In: Cordani, U. G., Milani, E. J., Thomaz-Filho,
A., Campos, D. A (Eds.) Tectonic Evolution of South America.
Rio de Janeiro, 265-285.

PIPER, J. (2000) – The Neoproterozoic Supercontinent: Rodinia or Paleo-
pangea? Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 176, 131-146.

PORCHER, C., FERNANDES, L., EGYDIO-SILVA, M., VAUCHEZ, A. (1995) –
Dados preliminares do metamorfismo M1 da Faixa Ribeira:
Região de Três Rios e Santo Antônio de Pádua (RJ). Abstract
of the V Simpósio de Estudos Tectônicos, 71-73.

POWELL, R., HOLLAND, T. (1999) – Relating formulations of the thermo-
dynamics of mineral solid solutions: Activity modelling pyro-
xenes, amphiboles and micas. American Mineralogist, 84, 1-14.

REGO, I. T. S. F. (1989) – Petrologia e geoquímica da unidade charnockítica
Bela Joana, Região de São Fidélis – RJ. Unpublished PhD
Thesis, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, 333. 

SANDERSON, D.J., MARCHINI, W.R.D. (1984) – Transpression. Journal
of Structural Geology, 6, 449-459. 

SCHMITT, R. S. (2001) – A Orogenia Búzios – um evento tectono-
metamórfico Cambro-Ordoviciano caracterizado no domínio
tectónico Cabo Frio, Faixa Ribeira, sudeste do Brasil, Rio de
Janeiro. Unpublished PhD Thesis, Federal University of Rio
de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, 273. 

SCHMITT, R. S., TROUW, R. A. J., SCHMUS, W. R., PIMENTEL, M. M.
(2004) – Late amalgamation in the central part of West
Gondwana: new geochronological data and the characteriza-
tion of a Cambrian collision orogeny in the RFB (SE Brazil).
Precambrian Research, 133, 29-61. 

TASSINARI, C., CAMPOS NETO, M. C. (1988) – Precambrian continental
crust evolution of southeastern S‹o Paulo State-Brazil: based
on isotopic evidence. Geochimica Brasiliensis, 2, 2, 175-183. 

TASSINARI, C., MUNHÁ, J., TEIXEIRA, W., PALÁCIOS, T., NUTMAN, A.,
SOSA, C., SANTOS, A., CALADO, B. (2004) – The Imataca
complex, NW Amazonian Craton, Venezuela: Crustal evolu-
tion and integration of geochronological and petrological
cooling histories. Episodes, 27, 1, 3-12. 

TASSINARI, C., MUNHÁ, J., DIAS NETO, C., BENTO DOS SANTOS, T.,
CORDANI, U., NUTMAN, A., FONSECA, P. (2006) – Constrains
on the thermochronological evolution of Ribeira Fold Belt,
SE Brazil: evidence for long-term elevated geothermal gradi-
ent of Neoproterozoic orogenies. Extended Abstract of the V
Simpósio Sud-Americano de Geologia Isotópica, 200-203. 

TEYSSIER, C., TIKOFF, B., MARKLEY, M. (1995) – Obliqúe plate motion
and continental tectonics. Geology, 23, 5, 447-450.

TROMPETTE, R. (2000) – Gondwana evolution; its assembly at around
600 Ma. Compte Rendu de la Academie des Sciences de
Paris, Sciences de la Terre et des planètes, 330, 305-315.

TROUW, R. A., HEILBRON, M., RIBEIRO, A., PACIULLO, F., VALERIANO,
C., ALMEIDA, J. H., TUPINAMBÁ, M., ANDREIS, R. (2000) – The
central segment of the RFB. In: Cordani, U. G., Milani, E. J.,
Thomaz-Filho, A., Campos, D. A (Eds.) Tectonic Evolution of
South America. Rio de Janeiro, 297-310.

TUPINAMBÁ, M. (1999) – Evolução tectônica e magmática da Faixa
Ribeira na região serrana do Estado do Rio de Janeiro. Unpu-
blished PhD Thesis, University of São Paulo, São Paulo, 236.

VAUCHEZ, A., AMARO, V., ARCHANJO, C. (1992) – The Borborema shear
zone system: a tectonic model. Abstract of the XXXVII Con-
gresso Brasileiro de Geologia, 371-372.

VAUCHEZ, A., TOMMASI, A., EGYDIO-SILVA, M. (1994) – Self-indentation of
a heterogeneous continental lithosphere. Geology, 22, 967-970.

Artigo recebido em Outubro de 2009
Aceite em Novembro de 2009


</field>
	</doc>
</add>