<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.12989</field>
		<field name="filename">187_001008854.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
1 

 

 

UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL 

INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS 

PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOCIÊNCIAS 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

EVOLUÇÃO TERMOTECTÔNICA DA MARGEM 

CONTINENTAL BRASILEIRA 

 

CHRISTIE HELOUISE ENGELMANN DE OLIVEIRA 

 

 

 

ORIENTADORA – Profa. Dra. Andréa Ritter Jelinek 

 

 

 

 

Volume Único 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Porto Alegre – 2016 

 



2 

 

 

UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL 

INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS 

PROGRAMA DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO EM GEOCIÊNCIAS 

 

 

 

 

 

 

EVOLUÇÃO TERMOTECTÔNICA DA MARGEM 

CONTINENTAL BRASILEIRA 

 

CHRISTIE HELOUISE ENGELMANN DE OLIVEIRA 

 

 

ORIENTADORA – Profa. Dra. Andréa Ritter Jelinek 

 

BANCA EXAMINADORA  

 Prof. Dr. Felipe Guadagnin – Universidade Federal do Pampa 

 Prof. Dr. Léo Afraneo Hartmann – Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul 

 Dr. Wilson Wildner – CPRM 

 

 

Tese de Doutorado apresentada como 

requisito parcial para obtenção do Título de 

Doutora em Ciências. 

 

 

Porto Alegre – 2016  

 



UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL 
Reitor: Rui Vicente Oppermann

Vice-Reitora: Jane Fraga Tutikian

INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS
Diretor: André Sampaio Mexias
Vice-Diretor: Nelson Luiz Sambaqui Gruber

__________________________
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul - Campus do Vale Av. Bento Gonçalves, 9500 - Porto Alegre - RS - Brasil 
CEP: 91501-970 / Caixa Postal: 15001.
Fone: +55 51 3308-6329  Fax: +55 51 3308-6337
E-mail: bibgeo@ufrgs.br 

CDU 55CDU 55
___________________________________________________________
Catalogação na Publicação
Biblioteca Instituto de Geociências - UFRGS
Sônia Teresinha Duarte de Oliveira CRB 10/2310

Oliveira, Christie Helouise Engelmann de 
    Evolução Termotectônica da Margem Continental Brasileira . /
Christie Helouise Engelmann de  Oliveira. - Porto Alegre:
IGEO/UFRGS, 2016.
     [77 f.] il.

    Tese (Doutorado).- Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul.
Doutorado em Geociências. Instituto de Geociências. Porto Alegre, RS -
BR, 2016.

        Orientador(es):Andréa Ritter Jelinek

    1. Margem continental brasileira 2. Traços de fissão 3. Rifte 4. Bacia
de Campos I. Título.



2 

 

AGRADECIMENTOS 

 

 Agradeço a todos que de uma forma ou de outra contribuíram para a 

realização desta Tese de Doutorado. 

 Agradeço à UFRGS, ao Instituto de Geociências e ao Programa de Pós 

Graduação (PPGGEO). 

 Agradeço à minha orientadora, por todos os ensinamentos e oportunidades, 

pela amizade, e por confiar e acreditar em mim.  

 Obrigada ao Farid Chemale, por sempre ter me dado oportunidades e 

orientações. 

 Ao meu amigo e colega de doutorado, Marcos Bicca, pelas discussões 

geológicas e amizade. Ao André Santos, por me ajudar com as amostras e pela 

oportunidade de poder co-orientá-lo no Temático. 

 Obrigada à minha mãe, irmãos, sobrinhos, cunhados e cunhada, pelo apoio e 

momentos de companhia e carinho.  

 Ao Jeferson Schmidt, meu muito obrigada pelo amor, carinho, compreensão e 

apoio. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



1 

 

RESUMO 

 

A margem continental brasileira denota estruturas geomorfológicas moldadas 

durante vários episódios de atividade tectônica iniciados no Neoproterozoico, 

durante o Ciclo Brasiliano/Pan-Africano, e originada por processos de rifteamento e 

subsequente separação entre América do Sul e África no Cretaceo Inferior. Com o 

objetivo de estabelecer um modelo de história termotectônica para a margem 

continental brasileira, foram realizadas as seguintes análises: (i) traços de fissão em 

apatita e/ou zircão na margem sul, no Escudo Sul-Rio-Grandense e na Bacia do 

Camaquã; (ii) traços de fissão em apatita no embasamento onshore e poços offshore 

da Bacia de Santos (margem sudeste); e, (iii) integração e reinterpretação dos dados 

traços de fissão em apatita disponíveis ao longo de toda a margem continental 

brasileira. As idades traços de fissão em apatita ao longo da margem variam de 

~385-10 Ma. As idades centrais traços de fissão em zircão obtidas na Bacia do 

Camaquã variam de ~386 a 210 Ma e são mais jovens do que a idade de deposição, 

apresentando sinais de reset parcial e/ou total após a deposição. Alguns cristais de 

zircão com idades Meso-Neoproterozoicas definem uma proveniência inicial, e os 

mais jovens de 147-104 Ma (Cretaceo Inferior) representam cristais que foram 

completamente resetados e registram o início da separação entre a América do Sul 

e a África. A modelagem térmica dos poços offshore da Bacia de santos indicou que 

a geração de óleo na bacia começou em 55-25 Ma. Os dados revelam que a 

margem continental foi caracterizada por pelo menos três eventos de resfriamento 

acelerado pós Ciclo Brasiliano: Cretaceo Inferior, Cretaceo Superior e Paleógeno-

Neógeno. Estes eventos são relacionados aos processos de abertura do Oceano 

Atlântico Sul e às fases rifte e pós-rifte, com reativações tectônicas ao longo da 

margem e cuja denudação estimada pode ser relacionada ao influxo sedimentar nas 

bacias offshore. A margem continental sul e o cráton São Francisco registram os 

eventos de resfriamento mais antigos, desde o Ordoviciano e o Permiano 

respectivamente, como reflexo das orogenias Famatiniana e Gondwanide. 

 

 

 



2 

 

ABSTRACT 

The Brazilian continental margin denotes geomorphological structures formed during 

several episodes of tectonic activity initiated in the Neoproterozoic during the 

Brasiliano/Pan African Cycle and originated by rifting and subsequent breakup of 

South America and Africa in the Early Cretaceous. In order to establish a 

thermotectonic history model for the Brazilian continental margin these analyzes 

were performed: (i) apatite and/or zircon fission tracks in the southern margin, Sul-

Rio-Grandese Shield and Camaquã Basin; (Ii) apatite fission tracks in onshore 

basement and offshore boreholes of the Santos Basin (southeast margin); and, (iii) 

integration and reinterpretation of the available apatite fission tracks along the 

Brazilian continental margin. The apatite fission track ages along the margin range 

from ca. 385-10 Ma. The zircon fission track central ages along the Camaquã Basin 

vary from ca. 386 to 210 Ma and are younger than the depositional age and show 

signs partial of partially and/or totally reset after deposition. A few zircon grains with 

Meso-Neoproterozoic ages define an initial provenance age, and the youngest ages 

of 147-104 Ma (Early Cretaceous) represent zircon grains that have been completely 

reset and record the time of the initial breakup between South America and Africa. 

The borehole thermal modeling of the Santos Basin indicates that the oil generation 

started at 55-25 Ma. The data show that the continental margin was characterized by 

at least three accelerated cooling events after the Brasiliano cycle: Early Cretaceous, 

Late Cretaceous and Paleogene-Neogene. These events are related to the opening 

processes of the South Atlantic Ocean and to the rift and post-rift phases, with 

tectonic reactivations along the margin and whose estimated denudation can be 

related to the sedimentary influx in the offshore basins. The south continental margin 

and the San Francisco craton record the older cooling events, from the Ordovician to 

the Permian respectively, as reflection of the Famatinian and Gondwanide orogenies. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



1 

 

SUMÁRIO 

 

Sobre a estrutura da Tese ........................................................................... 4 

1 INTRODUÇÃO ............................................................................................ 5 

1.1 SÍNTESE DO MÉTODO TRAÇOS DE FISSÃO  .......................................... 7 

1.1.1 Traços de fissão em apatita ....................................................................... 8 

1.1.2 Traços de fissão em zircão ........................................................................ 11 

1.2 SÍNTESE INTEGRADORA ........................................................................... 12 

1.3 CONSIDERAÇÕES FINAIS .......................................................................... 17 

REFERÊNCIAS .............................................................................................. 18 

ARTIGO 1 - Evidence of post-Gondwana breakup in Southern Brazilian 

Shield: Insights from apatite and zircon fission track thermochronology ........ 

 

26 

ARTIGO 2 - Thermotectonic history of the southeastern Brazilian margin: 

Evidence from apatite fission track data of the offshore Santos Basin and 

continental basement ..................................................................................... 

 

 

41 

ARTIGO 3 - História termotectônica da margem continental brasileira a partir 

de dados de traços de fissão em apatita ........................................................ 

 

55 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

3 



2 

 

Sobre a Estrutura desta Tese: 

 

 Esta tese de Doutorado está estruturada em torno de artigos publicados e 

submetidos a revisão em períodos científicos, cuja organização compreende as 

seguintes partes principais: 

 

 a) Introdução sobre o tema e descrição do objeto de pesquisa de Doutorado, 

em que estão sumarizados os objetivos e a filosofia de pesquisa desenvolvidos, o 

estado da arte sobre o tema de pesquisa e uma síntese integradora contendo os 

principais resultados e interpretações obtidos. 

 

 b) Artigos publicados e submetidos em periódicos com corpo editorial 

permanente e revisores independentes, escritos pela autora durante o 

desenvolvimento de seu Doutorado. 

4 



5 

 

 

1 INTRODUÇÃO  

 As margens continentais representam áreas de transição entre crosta 

oceânica e continental, onde há predomínio de uma tectônica relativamente simples 

nas bacias offshore e uma mais complexa nas regiões continentais. Elas preservam 

a história de erosão continental, subducção oceânica, variação climática, mudanças 

no nível do mar, produtividade biológica e inúmeros outros processos, sendo que o 

conhecimento de sua formação fornece ferramentas para entender uma boa porção 

da história do nosso planeta (Falvey &amp;amp; Middleton, 1981). 

 Margens continentais tipo rifte, passiva ou Atlântica, são formadas pela 

separação continental, com o desenvolvimento de falhas extensionais e bacias do 

tipo rifte, e subsequente expansão do fundo oceânico, acompanhado ou não de 

soerguimento regional e vulcanismo (Beaumont, 1989). A estruturação e estratigrafia 

deste tipo de margem é dominada por soerguimento e subsidência tectônica, que 

ocorre antes, durante e após a separação continental, dado que sua evolução 

geológica e estrutural é um processo prolongado e complexo (p.ex., Burk &amp;amp; Drake, 

1974; Falvey, 1974). 

 A margem continental brasileira denota estruturas geomorfológicas moldadas 

durante vários episódios de atividade tectônica iniciados no Neoproterozoico, sendo 

sua topografia e relevo atuais semelhantes em muitos aspectos àqueles de outras 

margens continentais tipo rifte ao redor do globo terrestre (p.ex., Austrália, oeste da 

África, Noruega, Índia Ocidental). Ela faz parte do sistema de riftes do Atlântico Sul, 

originado pela separação do Gondwana Ocidental no Cretaceo Inferior, cuja abertura 

iniciou-se no sul e propagou-se ao norte ao longo de reativações tectônicas de 

antigos lineamentos (Nürnberg &amp;amp; Müller, 1991; Meisling et al., 2001; Torsvik et al., 

2009). A natureza da margem influenciou o desenvolvimento das bacias 

sedimentares offshore e das bacias intracontinentais, sendo que os sistemas de rifte 

Mesozoico-Cenozoico paralelos à costa estão presentes também offshore. 

 A margem continental norte está assentada sobre as rochas Pré-Cambrianas 

do Escudo Brasileiro e não exibe elevação tão alta perto do litoral, mas é 

caracterizada por alguns platôs costeiros. No sudeste, a margem apresenta uma 

morfologia característica de margem continental tipo rifte, com bacias sedimentares 

offshore (Santos, Campos e Espírito Santo) e um lineamento estrutural dominante 

paralelo à margem e topografia elevada (Serra do Mar e Serra da Mantiqueira), 



6 

 

 

separados por uma planície costeira relativamente estreita (Gallagher et al., 1994). 

Ao sul, a topografia fica progressivamente mais baixa e não há embasamento Pré-

Cambriano exposto no sul do cráton Rio de la Plata. 

 Métodos termocronológicos de baixa temperatura como traços de fissão em 

apatita e zircão, têm sido amplamente utilizados para entender o desenvolvimento 

de margens tipo rifte, quantificar taxas de exumação e denudação, fornecer idades e 

taxas de movimentação ao longo de falhas e zonas de cisalhamento, e identificar as 

características de proveniência e evolução termotectônica de terrenos fonte (Garver 

&amp;amp; Brandon, 1994; Carter &amp;amp; Moss, 1999; Gallagher &amp;amp; Brown, 1999; Bernet et al., 

2001; Raab et al., 2005; Jelinek et al., 2014). Na margem continental brasileira, a 

maioria dos estudos termocronológicos têm se concentrado na margem sudeste com 

amostras provenientes do embasamento e de bacias Terciarias onshore (Gallagher 

et al., 1994, 1995; Jelinek et al., 2003; Tello Saenz et al., 2003; Hackspacher et al., 

2007; Hiruma et al., 2010; Cogné et al., 2011; Karl et al., 2013; Franco-Magalhaes et 

al., 2014), onde se concentram as maiores bacias petrolíferas offshore.  

 Apesar do grande número de trabalhos termocronológicos realizados na 

margem continental brasileira, a parte sul e as bacias offshore carecem de tais 

dados, assim como uma integração dos dados disponíveis na literatura para toda a 

margem. Com isto, a presente tese teve como objetivo principal a análise da 

evolução termotectônica da margem continental brasileira com o uso da 

termocronologia (traços de fissão em apatita e/ou zircão). Para isso, os objetivos 

específicos foram: (i) datação por traços de fissão em apatita e/ou zircão de 

amostras da margem sul (Escudo Sul-Rio-Grandense e Bacia do Camaquã); (ii) 

datação por traços de fissão em apatita de amostras da margem sudeste (Bacia de 

Santos) (iii) modelamento das histórias térmicas; (iv) determinação dos principais 

eventos termotectônicos, das paleotemperaturas máximas e das taxas de 

denudação e/ou soterramento; (v) correlação das taxas de denudação com a 

sedimentação nas bacias offshore; (vi) integração com dados disponíveis na 

literatura; e, (vii) geração de um modelo de distribuição das idades por traços de 

fissão em apatita e dos eventos termotectônicos para a margem continental 

brasileira. 

 

 

 



7 

 

 

1.1 SÍNTESE DO MÉTODO TRAÇOS DE FISSÃO   

 A técnica de datação por traços de fissão foi proposta ainda na década de 60 

por Price &amp;amp; Walker (1963) e desenvolvida por Naeser (1967) e Wagner (1968). Os 

princípios analíticos da técnica se baseiam no fenômeno de que a fissão espontânea 

dos átomos de 
238

U contido no retículo cristalino dos minerais causa danos a este 

retículo (traços de fissão), sendo utilizados minerais (termocronômetros) 

naturalmente enriquecidos neste elemento como o zircão, a titanita e a apatita. 

Esses traços são continuamente produzidos no mineral ao longo do tempo, e podem 

ser observados ao microscópio após um ataque químico conveniente. Outros 

minerais, como epidoto, granada e micas são também utilizados, mas são muito 

menos importantes em aplicações de rotina devido às concentrações geralmente 

baixas de urânio.  

 Em princípio, vários parâmetros geológicos (tempo, temperatura, taxa de 

resfriamento, danos por radiação, pressão, etc.) são capazes de influenciar a 

estabilidade dos traços de fissão nos minerais de modo que haja a reconstituição 

das zonas desarranjadas e ocorra o apagamento do traço. A temperatura é o 

parâmetro que mais produz efeitos consideráveis durante um período de tempo 

geológico. Quando os traços são submetidos a temperaturas superiores àquelas de 

bloqueio para um dado termocronômetro, os traços sofrem encurtamento e redução 

na densidade, processo este chamado de annealing (Jelinek et al., 2010).  

 Outros fatores também podem afetar a estabilidade térmica dos traços de 

fissão nos minerais, como a composição química, no caso da apatita, e a 

acumulação de danos na rede cristalina, no caso do zircão. Em temperaturas 

suficientemente baixas, o annealing torna-se tão lento que, para efeitos práticos, 

traços novos e antigos são totalmente preservados. Com o aumento da temperatura, 

a taxa de annealing aumenta até atingir o ponto em que os traços não persistem 

durante um tempo geológico significativo. O intervalo entre estas temperaturas ou 

profundidades, em que os traços de fissão são parcialmente encurtados ou 

apagados, é conhecido como zona de annealing parcial (Reiners &amp;amp; Brandon, 2006), 

sendo que não há uma única zona de annealing parcial, pois o grau de annealing 

depende da história tempo-temperatura. 

 Outro conceito utilizado é temperatura de fechamento (Tc) (Fig. 1), baseado 

no trabalho de Dodson (1973). De maneira geral, o fechamento ocorre quando um 



8 

 

 

sistema isotópico se torna fechado para a perda de isótopos pai e filho. No sistema 

traços de fissão, a Tc representa a temperatura da rocha na idade termocronológica 

de resfriamento, em que há retenção quase que total dos traços (retenção de 90% 

na maioria dos casos ou T90%), ou seja, o fechamento do sistema traços de fissão. 

 

 

Figura 1. Intervalo aproximado da temperatura de fechamento para vários minerais, 

suas respectivas técnicas de datação e o possível processo geológico associado. 

 

 Dentre as possíveis aplicações da técnica podemos destacar estudos sobre 

evolução de eventos tectônicos, no qual é possível estimar as taxas de 

erosão/soerguimento/denudação envolvidos no processo, estudos de eventos 

hidrotermais, estudos de proveniência (Jelinek et al., 2010), e estudos aplicados 

diretamente à evolução de bacias sedimentares (Armstrong, 2005). 

 

1.1.1 Traços de fissão em apatita 

 A apatita é o termocronômetro mais utilizado devido a sua vasta presença nas 

rochas e por ter suas condições físico-químicas facilmente reproduzidas em 

laboratório (Jelinek et al., 2010). Em contraste com o comportamento estável e 

elevada resistência físico-química do zircão, a apatita é instável em água ácida e 

tem baixa resistência, representando o primeiro ciclo detrítico. A análise traço de 



9 

 

 

fissão em apatita é amplamente utilizada na reconstrução de histórias térmicas de 

baixa temperatura de rochas ao longo do tempo, como de bacias sedimentares. 

Outra aplicação bastante importante é na geologia do petróleo, uma vez que a 

temperatura de fechamento da apatita coincide com a janela de maturação dos 

hidrocarbonetos, tornando o método uma importante ferramenta na exploração de 

óleo e gás. 

 A zona de annealing da apatita varia entre 60 e 120 °C. Wagner (1972) 

propôs três zonas de estabilidade da apatita associadas à temperatura: a) Zona de 

Estabilidade Total (ZET), para temperaturas inferiores a 60 °C; b) Zona de Annealing 

Parcial (ZAP), para temperaturas entre 60 e 120 °C; e c) Zona de Annealing Total 

(ZAT), para temperaturas superiores a 120 °C (Fig. 2). As amostras que ocupam o 

campo da ZET têm idades traços de fissão muito próximas à idade estratigráfica ou 

de cristalização da rocha, e têm os comprimentos dos traços de fissão preservados e 

próximos ao comprimento original de 16 ?m. Para as amostras que ocupam a ZAP, 

os traços de fissão já apresentam indícios de encurtamento e somente metade dos 

traços de fissão são preservados, apresentando uma idade inferior àquela registrada 

para as amostras da ZET. Na ZAT, os traços de fissão são totalmente apagados, o 

que impossibilita a determinação de suas histórias térmicas. A medida do 

comprimento dos traços na apatita permite reconstruir a história térmica da amostra. 

Uma vez que a baixa temperatura de annealing da apatita resulta em idades traços 

de fissão geralmente mais jovens que a idade estratigráfica das amostras, é possível 

estimar taxas de denudação e soerguimento de bacias, e obter a idade de eventos 

térmicos relacionados. 

 Outro parâmetro que influencia a temperatura de annealing dos traços de 

fissão em apatita é a sua composição química. A apatita é um mineral fosfático cuja 

fórmula química é geralmente escrita como Ca
5
(PO4)

3
[F,Cl,OH] (Deer et al., 1969). 

Os três ânions de F
?1

, Cl
?1

, e OH
?1

 podem substituir uns aos outros, no mesmo sítio 

cristalográfico, formando flúor-apatitas, cloro-apatitas e hidroxi-apatitas, 

respectivamente. Green et al. (1986) verificou que uma cloro-apatita é mais 

resistente ao annealing do que uma flúor-apatita, ou seja, a estabilidade térmica da 

apatita diminui com a diminuição do teor de cloro. Os outros sítios, preferencialmente 

em flúor-apatitas, também podem sofrer substituições como o C por Mn, Sr, Fe, Na e 

elementos terras raras (particularmente o Ce), e o sítio do P por Si, S e C (Deer et 

al., 1969; Young et al., 1969; Roeder et al., 1987). 



10 

 

 

 

 

Figura 2. Modelo esquemático das zonas de estabilidade dos traços de fissão em 

apatita. Três opções de soerguimento e denudação são mostradas para a mesma 

origem na ZAP: (A) resfriamento rápido; (B) resfriamento lento; (C) resfriamento 

complexo. Na opção A, a amostra A2 apresenta idade mais antiga que A1 (ts: 

temperatura da superficíe; gg: gradiente geotérmico) (Fonte: Naeser et al., 1989). 

 

 Na determinação da composição da apatita da amostra analisada, utilizam-se 

parâmetros cinéticos que permitem agrupar grãos com comportamentos 

semelhantes durante o modelamento térmico. Os parâmetros mais utilizados são: 

determinação do conteúdo de Cl com o uso de microssonda eletrônica, e 

determinação do Dpar. O Dpar é a média aritmética do diâmetro paralelo ao eixo 

cristalográfico “c” do cristal formada pela intersecção de um etch pit (i.e., traço de 

fissão ou outra imperfeição cristalográfica) com a superfície de polimento do cristal 

(Donelick, 1993). O etch pit de uma apatita é alongado paralelamente ao eixo 

cristalográfico “c” e tende a exibir uma forma hexagonal. O Dpar tem uma correlação 

positiva com os teores de Cl e OH e uma correlação negativa com o teor de F da 

apatita (Burtner et al., 1994; Donelick et al., 2005), ou seja, fornece indícios quanto à 



11 

 

 

composição da apatita analisada, devendo ser feita no mínimo 4 medições para 

cada grão datado ou em que se mediu o comprimento de traços. 

 

1.1.2 Traços de fissão em zircão 

 O zircão (ZrSiO4) é um mineral acessório comum em vários tipos de rocha e 

possui elevada resistência físico-química, resistindo aos sucessivos ciclos de 

deposição, erosão e metamorfismo, e possui elevada concentração de urânio e tório. 

A datação traços de fissão em zircão detrítico tem sido utilizada com sucesso para 

identificar as características de proveniência e evolução termo-tectônica de terrenos 

fonte (p. ex., Garver &amp;amp; Brandon, 1994; Carter &amp;amp; Moss, 1999; Bernet et al., 2001; 

Fellin et al., 2006; Cao et al., 2013), assim como fornecer a idade de deposição em 

sequências sedimentares.  

 A densidade dos traços de fissão observáveis no zircão depende de sua 

história térmica, e eles só são retidos dentro da estrutura do cristal em temperaturas 

inferiores a aproximadamente 180-320 °C e por períodos de 106-108 anos, valores 

equivalentes ao metamorfismo de baixo grau (Tagami et al., 1998; Garver et al., 

1999). De maneira geral, utiliza-se para os traços de fissão em zircão uma Tc de 240 

± 30 °C (Yamada et al., 1995; Brandon et al., 1998; Bernet &amp;amp; Garver, 2005), sendo 

que essa temperatura é influenciada pela taxa de resfriamento e danos por radiação 

no zircão. Brandon &amp;amp; Vance (1992) sugerem que o Tc 90% (ca. 240 °C) corresponde 

a uma profundidade de 7,5-8 km, assumindo um gradiente geotérmico continental 

típico de 30°C/km e uma temperatura superficial média de ~10 °C.  

 Faixas de temperatura mais reduzidas podem ocorrer para o annealing parcial 

dependendo da acumulação de danos por radiação na rede cristalina 

(metamictização) do zircão (Kasuya &amp;amp; Naeser, 1988; Carter &amp;amp; Bristow, 2000). A 

metamictização altera a estrutura cristalina do zircão (transição de um estado 

cristalino para amorfo) afetando suas propriedades de annealing: grãos com baixo 

dano por radiação têm uma estrutura mais cristalina, são mais resistentes ao 

annealing (~280-300 °C) e requerem mais tempo de ataque químico; grãos com 

significativo dano por radiação possuem uma estrutura amorfa, são menos 

resistentes ao annealing (~180-200 °C) e requerem menos tempo de ataque químico 

(Garver et al., 2005). O zircão metamíctico também é mais propenso ao 

intemperismo, podendo ser destruído seletivamente durante a diagênese, 



12 

 

 

metamorfismo, transporte fluvial, ou mesmo durante a moagem da amostra (Malusà 

et al., 2013). 

 O fato da temperatura de annealing do zircão ser superior à de outros 

termocronômetros o torna mais resistente ao annealing térmico em bacias 

sedimentares após a deposição, e, com isso, as idades traços de fissão obtidas 

podem indicar idades de resfriamento de áreas fontes (proveniência) e serem 

associadas a idades deposicionais de sequências sedimentares. Mudanças nas 

idades traços de fissão em zircão ao longo das sequências estratigráficas de uma 

bacia podem ser utilizadas para reconstruir mudanças nos padrões de sedimentação 

e para reconstruir a história de soerguimento e erosão das rochas fontes. Em 

temperaturas mais elevadas (&gt;320 °C), desde que a rocha permaneça a estas 

temperaturas por um período de tempo geológico significativo (&gt;106 anos), todos os 

grãos são resetados e as idades fornecem informações sobre a história térmica pós-

deposicional da bacia sedimentar. 

 As rochas exumadas que foram soterradas e aquecidas a 180-280 °C têm 

normalmente uma população de grãos totalmente resetados e uma grande 

variedade de idades de grãos parcialmente resetados ou que representam as idades 

de proveniência. Consequentemente, em estudos onde uma população jovem foi 

identificada, não está claro se as idades dos grãos mais velhos retém a informação 

de proveniência original, se foram parcialmente resetados, ou ambos. Porém, é 

evidente que rochas aquecidas a temperaturas entre 180 e 220 °C têm potencial 

para gravar tanto reset térmico, quanto informações de proveniência originais e 

eventos térmicos na própria área fonte (Bernet &amp;amp; Garver, 2005). 

 No zircão, diferentemente da apatita, a medida do comprimento dos traços 

para a modelagem da história térmica não é aplicada, pois há uma grande diferença 

nos tempos de ataque químico e resposta ao ataque nos cristais de uma mesma 

amostra, principalmente em cristais de zircão detrítico (Bernet &amp;amp; Garver, 2005). 

 

 

1.2 SÍNTESE INTEGRADORA 

 Há mais de duas décadas a evolução da história termotectônica da margem 

continental brasileira vem sendo estudada através da termocronologia. A partir dos 

resultados obtidos nas análises termocronológicas realizadas ao longo desta tese, e 



13 

 

 

da integração e reinterpretação dos dados de traços de fissão em apatita disponíveis 

para toda a margem continental brasileira, foi possível estabelecer um modelo de 

evolução termotectônica para a margem. As idades traços de fissão em apatita ao 

longo da margem variam de ~385-10 Ma e todas são consideravelmente mais jovens 

do que a idade de cristalização ou metamorfismo de suas rochas hospedeiras, 

sendo relacionadas a eventos de resfriamento, soerguimento e denudação. 

 A margem continental sul brasileira, mais precisamente no estado do Rio 

Grande do Sul, é composta principalmente pelas rochas do Escudo Sul-Rio-

Grandense de idade Arqueana à Eopaleozoica (Fernandes et al., 1992; Chemale Jr., 

2000; Hartmann et al., 2007), e pelas rochas da Bacia de Camaquã, gerada nos 

ciclos sedimentares tardi- a pós-orogênicos do Ciclo Brasiliano (Chemale et al., 

1995; Paim et al., 2000). O Escudo Sul-Rio-Grandense é composto por quatro 

unidades limitadas por zonas de cisalhamento regionais de direção NE-SW e NW-

SE: Terreno Taquarembó, Terreno Tijucas, Terreno São Gabriel e Batólito de 

Pelotas. 

 Com o objetivo de melhorar a compreensão sobre a evolução termotectônica 

da margem sul, foram realizadas análises por traços de fissão em apatita e/ou zircão 

em amostras do embasamento (Terreno Taquarembó e Batólito de Pelotas) e da 

Bacia do Camaquã, sendo que as análises por traços de fissão em zircão só foram 

realizadas nas amostras da bacia. Os dados obtidos foram integrados com os dados 

publicados por Borba et al. (2002 e 2003) e Bicca et al. (2013). As idades traços de 

fissão em apatita obtidas variam de 340 ± 33 a 77 ± 6 Ma e foram interpretadas 

como idades de resfriamento, representando eventos de denudação regional, uma 

vez que são mais jovens do que o Ciclo Brasiliano/Pan-Africano que afetou as 

rochas do Escudo Sul-Rio-Grandense antes de 500 Ma. As idades não 

apresentaram nenhuma correlação com a altitude, como era esperado para uma 

região de relevo moderado.  

 As idades centrais traços de fissão em zircão ao longo da Bacia do Camaquã 

variam de ca. 386 a 210 Ma e são mais jovens do que a idade de deposição, 

apresentando sinais de reset parcial e/ou total após a deposição. Alguns cristais de 

zircão com idades Meso-Neoproterozoicas definiram uma proveniência inicial, 

correlacionáveis às idades obtidas por Oliveira et al. (2014) nas mesmas amostras 

pelo método U-Pb em zircão. As idades traços de fissão em zircão mais jovens, de 

147-104 Ma (Cretaceo Inferior), possivelmente representam cristais que foram 



14 

 

 

completamente resetados e registram o início da separação entre a América do Sul 

e a África (p. ex., Nürnberg &amp;amp; Müller, 1991). 

 Com base na modelagem da história térmica foi possível identificar os 

eventos de resfriamento na região e quantificar as taxas de denudação, que têm um 

efeito significativo na evolução da topografia regional. O primeiro evento de 

resfriamento na margem sul começou no Ordoviciano e continuou durante o 

Carbonífero. Este episódio afetou principalmente as unidades mais ocidentais do 

escudo e reflete o possível soerguimento da área em resposta à colisão entre o 

terreno Precordillera (Famatina e Cuyania) e o cráton Rio de la Plata, na margem 

Pacífica do Gondwana ocidental durante a Orogenia Famatiniana, e continuou 

durante a Orogenia Gondwanide. 

 O evento de resfriamento Permo-Triássico afetou as rochas do Terreno São 

Gabriel e parte do Batólito de Pelotas, e foi relacionado ao processo orogênico tardio 

do Gondwanides ao longo da borda sul do Gondwana ocidental, e a consequente 

reativação das estruturas N-S e NE-SW do embasamento. O início da abertura do 

Oceano Atlântico Sul é registrado principalmente no Batólito de Pelotas, região mais 

próxima à margem, com a reativação das estruturas Pré-Cambrianas como 

consequência desta extensão. As idades traços de fissão em zircão da Bacia do 

Camaquã mostraram que durante este período a temperatura foi alta o suficiente 

para resetar total ou parcialmente os cristais de zircão, devido ao alto stress 

termotectônico. O último evento de resfriamento registrado na margem sul é 

relacionado com a separação final entre a América do Sul e a África, no início do 

Cretaceo Superior, e um aumento das taxas de resfriamento no Cenozoico, 

provavelmente como resultado do ajuste das placas após a separação e reativações 

neotectônicas associadas à evolução do rifte Atlântico Sul. 

 Na margem continental sudeste e leste, diversos estudos utilizando traços de 

fissão em apatita foram realizados desde a década de 90, utilizando amostras do 

embasamento e das bacias terciarias terrestres, e os dados foram interpretados em 

termos de denudação e movimentação ao longo das falhas (p.ex., Gallagher et al., 

1994; Tello Saenz et al., 2003; Hackspacher et al., 2004; Hiruma et al., 2010; Cogné 

et al., 2012; Franco-Magalhães et al., 2010, 2014; Karl et al., 2013). Os dados traços 

de fissão em apatita publicados para esta parte da margem mostram uma tendência 

geral semelhante à observada em outras margens do tipo rifte, com idades mais 

jovens em direção à costa. 



15 

 

 

 O Arco de Ponta Grossa, na região de Curitiba, é um alto topográfico 

caracterizado por um grande número de diques associados ao magmatismo Paraná-

Etendeka (Zalán et al., 1990), e apresenta as idades traços de fissão em apatita 

mais jovens de toda a margem continental (Franco-Magalhaes et al., 2010). Franco-

Magalhaes et al. (2010) atribuem estas idades mais jovens (&lt;20 Ma) à reativação 

das zonas de cisalhamento do Pré-Cambriano e ao soerguimento/exumação da 

área, levando à formação de bacias terciarias, como a Bacia de Curitiba (Salamuni, 

1988). A reativação tectônica Cenozoica do embasamento continental e 

consequente formação das bacias terciarias também é sugerida por outros autores 

ao longo da margem sudeste e leste (p. ex., Hiruma et al., 2010; Cogné et al., 2012; 

Karl et al., 2013). 

 Entre as bacias sedimentares offshore da margem sudeste, a Bacia de 

Santos é a maior, originada pela separação do Gondwana ocidental no Cretaceo 

Inferior. As análises termocronológicas traços de fissão em apatita em amostras 

onshore do embasamento e de furos offshore da Bacia de Santos resultaram em 

idades centrais de 157,0 ± 35,0 a 21,0 ± 1,8 Ma para o embasamento, e de 208,0 ± 

11,0 a 6,5 ± 1,1 Ma para os furos. A partir da modelagem térmica, foi possível 

verificar que as amostras do embasamento atingiram as máximas paleotemperaturas 

durante a separação final da América do Sul e África (ca. 95 Ma). O primeiro evento 

termotectônico registrado nas amostras do embasamento e da bacia ocorreu durante 

o Cretaceo Superior, relacionado ao soerguimento e denudação da Serra do Mar e 

da Serra da Mantiqueira, como é observado em outras regiões da margem sudeste e 

leste.  

 As amostras do embasamento experimentaram um evento de resfriamento 

final durante o Cenozoico, cuja denudação estimada pode ser relacionada às 

espessuras de sedimeto na bacia offshore. Outros autores (p. ex., Gallagher et al., 

1994, 1995; Hiruma et al., 2010; Jelinek et al., 2014) também discutem que as altas 

taxas de denudação pós-rifte indicadas para a margem sudeste e leste refletem a 

geometria e o momento da reativação tectônica pós-rifte de estruturas 

intracontinentais maiores, e as taxas de denudação são correlacionáveis às 

espessuras do registro sedimentar offshore nas bacias de Santos e Espírito Santo. 

Há evidência de um resfriamento rápido durante o período Neógeno, relacionado à 

reativação das zonas de cisalhamento do Pré-Cambriano e à mudança do sistema 

de drenagem Paraíba do Sul. A modelagem térmica, com base nos traços de fissão 



16 

 

 

em apatita, indicou que a geração de óleo na Bacia de Santos começou em 55-25 

Ma e continuou até o Plioceno-Pleistoceno. 

 Na margem nordeste, na região do cráton São Francisco, as idades traços de 

fissão variam de ca. 386-95 Ma, com uma maior concentração de idades &gt;145 Ma 

(Harman et al., 1998; Cupertino, 2000; Turner et al., 2008; Japsen et al., 2012; 

Jelinek et al., 2014), e um antigo episódio de resfriamento durante o Permiano e 

Jurássico Inferior, reflexo da Orogenia Gondwanide (Jelinek et al., 2014). Os 

modelos de história térmica apresentados por Jelinek et al. (2014) não mostram 

evidência de resfriamento significativo durante a formação das bacias de margem 

tipo rifte nesta região, o que implica que a área não foi significativamente afetada 

pelos processos tectônicos e térmicos relacionados ao rifteamento. Os modelos são 

apoiados pela evolução das bacias do nordeste, que apresentam fases 

essencialmente não-magmáticas pré-rifte e rifte (Chang et al., 1992). 

 Na Província Borborema, região norte da margem continental, as idades 

traços de fissão em apatita variam de 357-52 Ma (Harman et al., 1998; Morais Neto 

et al., 2008, 2009; Turner et al., 2008; Japsen et al., 2012; Jelinek et al., 2014), 

sendo que a maior parte é relacionada ao evento de resfriamento do Cretaceo (&lt;145 

Ma) correspondente à abertura do Oceano Atlântico Sul. O desequilíbrio térmico na 

crosta na Província Borborema durante a ruptura do Gondwana e abertura do 

Oceano Atlântico Sul sugerido por Lima et al. (2015), e o magmatismo sin- e pós-rifte 

(60-40 Ma) presentes ao longo da margem equatorial brasileira (Mizusaki et al., 

2002), influenciaram a evolução dessa parte da margem e registraram esses 

eventos nas idades traços de fissão em apatita. 

 Esse padrão de idades traços de fissão e eventos de resfriamento ao longo 

da margem continental brasileira não está apenas relacionado ao processo de 

rifteamento, como pode ser visto no grande número de amostras com idades entre 

135 e 66 Ma, mas envolve outros processos importantes como: (i) soerguimento 

isostático em resposta à denudação da margem continental e sedimentação nas 

bacias onshore e offshore, sugeridos e detalhados por Gallagher et al. (1994) e 

Gilchrist &amp;amp; Summerfield (1994); (ii) magmatismo pós-rift e reativação tectônica das 

principais estruturas intracontinentais, que ocasionaram uma denudação localmente 

acelerada sobreposta ao padrão regional secular (Gallagher &amp;amp; Brown, 1999; 

Cobbold et al., 2001); e, (iii) influência e registro de orogenias pré-rifte em regiões 

com características cratônicas. 



17 

 

 

1.3 CONSIDERAÇÕES FINAIS 

 Os dados e conclusões obtidos ao longo do desenvolvimento desta Tese de 

Doutorado, apresentados sob a forma de artigos científicos, permitem destacar as 

seguintes considerações finais: 

 (1) Através do uso da termocronologia de baixa temperatura, geotectônica e 

conceitos de evolução de margens tipo rifte, foi possível estabelecer um modelo de 

evolução termotectônica para a margem continental brasileira com base nas idades, 

nos eventos de resfriamento, soerguimento e denudação. 

 (2) O uso do método traços de fissão em zircão em rochas sedimentares da 

Bacia do Camaquã definiu algumas idades de proveniência e registrou a idade de 

início da separação entre a América do Sul e a África, recomendando-se o uso do 

método em outras bacias sedimentares e margens tipo rifte, a fim de determinar a 

proveniência e a idade do rifteamento. 

 (3) A aplicabilidade do método traços de fissão em apatita mostrou-se 

eficiente na determinação da idade de formação do óleo em poços offshore da Bacia 

de Santos, uma vez que a temperatura de fechamento deste termocronômetro é a 

mesma da janela de maturação dos hidrocarbonetos. Assim, como sugestão para 

trabalhos futuros, a integração dos traços de fissão em apatita com outros métodos 

geoquímicos (p. ex., reflectância em vitrinita) e geofísicos (p. ex., sísmica, perfil log), 

permitirá um modelamento mais preciso da história de soterramento da bacia, 

formação, migração e maturação do óleo, auxiliando na determinação das reservas 

petrolíferas da margem continental brasileira. 

 (4) A margem continental brasileira apresenta um grande número de dados 

traços de fissão em apatita, com apenas algumas áreas carecendo de tais dados, 

como a região do estado de Santa Catarina, sul da Bahia, Pernambuco e Rio 

Grande do Norte. Porém, a aplicação de outros métodos termocronológicos como 

traços de fissão em zircão ainda é bastante restrita, abrindo espaço para futuros 

estudos ao longo da margem brasileira. 

 



18 

 

 

REFERÊNCIAS 

 

Armstrong, P.A. 2005. Thermochronometers in Sedimentary Basins. In: Reiners, 

P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Ed.) Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques, 

Interpretations, and Applications. Washington: Mineralogical Society of 

America, Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry, v. 58, p.499-525. 

Beaumont, C. 1989. A physical explanation of the relation between flank uplifts and 

the breakup unconformity at rifted continental margins. Geology, 17(8): 760-

764. 

Bernet, M. &amp;amp; Garver, J.I. 2005. Fission-track analysis of detrital zircon. In: Reiners, 

P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Ed.) Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques, 

Interpretations, and Applications. Washington: Mineralogical Society of 

America, Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry, v. 58, p.205-238. 

Bernet, M., Zattin, M., Garver, J.I., Brandon, M.T., Vance, J.A. 2001. Steady-state 

exhumation of the European Alps. Geology, 29, 35-38. 

Bicca, M.M., Chemale Jr., F., Jelinek, A.R., Oliveira, C.H.E., Guadagnin, F., 

Armstrong, R. 2013. Tectonic evolution and provenance of the Santa Bárbara 

Group, Camaquã Mines region, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. Journal of South 

American Earth Sciences, 48, 173-192. 

Borba, A.W., Lima, E.F., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Sparrenberg, I., 

Barros, C.E. 2003. Significance of Late Paleozoic Fission-track Ages in 

Volcanic Rocks from the Lavras Do Sul Region, Southernmost Brazil. 

Gondwana Research, 6, 79-88. 

Borba, A.W., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M., Mizusaki, A.M.P. 2002. Uplift and denudation 

of the Caçapava do Sulgranitoids (southern Brazil) during Late Paleozoic and 

Mesozoic: constraints from apatite fission-track data. Journal of South American 

Earth Sciences, 15, 683-692. 

Brandon, M.T., Roden-Tice, M.K., Garver, J.I. 1998. Late Cenozoic exhumation of 

the Cascadia accretionary wedge in the Olympic Mountains, northwest 

Washington State. Geological Society of America Bulletin, 110, 985-1009. 

Brandon, M.T. &amp;amp; Vance, J.A. 1992. New statistical methods for analysis of fission 

track grain-age distributions with applications to detrital zircon ages from the 



19 

 

 

Olympic subduction complex, western Washington State. American Journal of 

Sciences, 292, 565-636. 

Burk, C.A. &amp;amp; Drake C.L. (Ed.). 1974. The geology of continental margins. Springer. 

Burtner, R.L., Nigrini, A., Donelick, R.A. 1994. Thermochronology of Lower 

Cretaceous source rocks in the Idaho-Wyoming thrust belt. American 

Association of Petroleum Geologists Bulletin, 78, 1613-1636. 

Cao, K., Wang, G., van der Beek, P., Bernet, M., Zhang, K. 2013. Cenozoic thermo-

tectonic evolution of the northeastern Pamir revealed by zircon and apatite 

fission-track thermochronology. Tectonophysics, 589, 17-32. 

Carter, A. &amp;amp; Bristow, C.S. 2000. Detrital zircon geochronology: enhancing the quality 

of sedimentary source information through improved methodology and 

combined U-Pb and fission-track techniques. Basin Research, 12, 47-57. 

Carter, A. &amp;amp; Bristow, C.S. 2003. Linking hinterland evolution and continental basin 

sedimentation by using detrital zircon thermochronology: a study of the Khorat 

Plateau Basin, eastern Thailand. Basin Research, 15, 271-285. 

Carter, A. &amp;amp; Moss, S.J. 1999. Combined detrital-zircon fission-track and U-Pb dating: 

a new approach to understanding hinterland evolution. Geology, 27, 235-238. 

Chang, H.K., Kowsmann, R.O., Figueiredo, A.M.F., Bender, A. 1992. Tectonics and 

stratigraphy of the East Brazil Rift system: an overview. Tectonophysics, 213(1): 

97-138. 

Chemale Jr., F. 2000. Evolução geológica do Escudo Sul-rio-grandense. In: Holz, M., 

De Ros, L.F. (Ed.) Geologia do Rio Grande do Sul. Porto Alegre: 

CIGO/UFRGS, p.13-52. 

Chemale Jr., F., Hartmann, L.A., Silva, L.C. 1995. Stratigraphy and Tectonism of 

Precambrian to Early Paleozoic Units. XVIII Acta Geologica Leopoldensia, 42, 

5-117. 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E., Mount, V.S. 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely rifted 

margin, Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG Bulletin, 

85(11): 1925-1944. 

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R. 2011. Post-rift reactivation of the onshore 

margin of southeast Brazil: evidence from apatite (U–Th)/He and fission-track 

data. Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 309(1), 118-130. 

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R., Riccomini, C., Gautheron, C. 2012. 

Post?breakup tectonics in southeast Brazil from thermochronological data and 



20 

 

 

combined inverse?forward thermal history modeling. Journal of Geophysical 

Research: Solid Earth, 117(B11). 

Cupertino, J.A. 2000. Evolução tectono-climática na fase Rifte das bacias de 

Camamu, parte norte, e sul do Recôncavo, com ênfase na utilização de 

isótopos estáveis e traços de fissão. Porto Alegre. Tese de Doutorado, 

Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências, Instituto de Geociências, 

Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 

Deer, W.A., Howie R.A., Zussman J. 1969. An Introduction to the Rock-forming 

Minerals. John Wiley and Sons, New York. 

Dodson, M.H. 1973. Closure Temperature in Cooling Geochronological and 

Petrological systems. Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology, 40, 259-274. 

Donelick, R.A. 1993. A method of fission track analysis utilizing bulk chemical etching 

of apatite. U.S. Patent Number 5267274. 

Donelick, R.A., O’Sullivan, P.B., Ketcham, R.A. 2005. Apatite Fission-Track Analysis. 

In: Reiners, P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Ed.) Low-Temperature Thermochronology: 

Techniques, Interpretations, and Applications. Washington: Mineralogical 

Society of America, Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry, v. 58, p.49-94. 

Engelmann de Oliveira, C.H.E., Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F., Cupertino, J.A. 2016. 

Thermotectonic history of the southeastern Brazilian margin: Evidence from 

apatite fission track data of the offshore Santos Basin and continental 

basement. Tectonophysics, 685, 21-34. 

Falvey, D.A. 1974. The development of continental margins in plate tectonic theory. 

The APEA Journal, 14: 95-107. 

Falvey, D.A. &amp;amp; Middleton, M.F. 1981. Passive continental margins: evidence for a 

prebreakup deep crustal metamorphic subsidence mechanism. Oceanologica 

Acta, Special issue. 

Fellin, M.G., Vance, J.A., Garver, J.I., Zattin, M. 2006. The thermal evolution of 

Corsica as recorded by zircon fission-tracks. Tectonophysics, 421(3), 299-317. 

Fernandes, L.A.D., Tommasi, A., Porcher, C.C. 1992. Deformation patterns in the 

southern Brazilian branch of the Dom Feliciano Belt: a reappraisal. Journal of 

South America Earth Sciences, 5(1), 77-96. 

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Hackspacher, P.C., Glasmacher, U.A., Saad, A.R. 2010. 

Rift to post-rift evolution of a “passive” continental margin: the Ponta Grossa 

Arch, SE Brazil. International Journal of Earth Sciences, 99(7), 1599-1613. 



21 

 

 

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B., Cuglieri, M.A.A., Hackspacher, P.C., Saad, A.R. 2014. 

Long-term landscape evolution and post-rift reactivation in the southeastern 

Brazilian passive continental margin: Taubaté basin. International Journal of 

Earth Sciences, 103(2), 441-453. 

Gallagher, K. &amp;amp; Brown, R. 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic  

margins of southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore 

sedimentation. In: Cameron, N.R., Bate, R.H., Clure, V.S. (Eds.), The Oil and 

Gas Habitats of the South Atlantic. Geological Society, London, pp. 41-53. 

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., Mantovani, M.S.M. 1994. The denudation history 

of the onshore continental margin of SE Brazil inferred from apatite fission track 

data. Journal of Geophysical Research, 99(B9), 18117-18145. 

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., Mantovani, M.S.M. 1995. Denudation, fission track 

analysis and the long-term evolution of passive margin topography: application 

to the southeast Brazilian margin. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 

8(1), 65-77. 

Garver, J.I. &amp;amp; Brandon, M.T. 1994. Fission-track ages of detrital zircon from 

Cretaceous strata, southern British Columbia: Implications for the Baja BC 

hypothesis. Tectonics, 13, 401-420. 

Garver, J.I., Brandon, M.T., Roden-Tice, M.K., Kamp, P.J.J. 1999. Exhumation 

history of orogenic highlands determined by detrital fission track 

thermochronology. In: Ring, U., Brandon, M.T., Willett, S.D., Lister, G.S. (Ed.) 

Exhumation Processes: Normal faulting, Ductile Flow, and Erosion. Geological 

Society Special Publications, v. 154, p. 283-304. 

Garver, J.I., Reiners, P.W., Walker, L.J., Ramage, J.M., Perry, S.E. 2005. 

Implications for Timing of Andean Uplift from Thermal Resetting of Radiation-

Damaged Zircon in the Cordillera Huayhuash, Northern Peru. The Journal of 

Geology 113, 117-138. 

Gilchrist, A.R. &amp;amp; Summerfield, M.A. 1994. Tectonic models of passive margin 

evolution and their implications for theories of long-term landscape 

development. In: Kirkby, M.J. (Ed.). Process Models and Theoretical 

Geomorphology. John Wiley and Sons, Chichester, p.55-84. 

Hackspacher, P.C., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Ribeiro, M.C.S., Fetter, A.H., Neto, J.H., Tello, 

C.E.S., Dantas, E.L. 2004. Consolidation and break-up of the South American 



22 

 

 

platform in southeastern Brazil: tectonothermal and denudation histories. 

Gondwana Research, 7(1), 91-101. 

Hackspacher, P.C., Godoy, D.F., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Neto, J.C.H., Franco, A.O.B. 2007. 

Modelagem térmica e geomorfologia da borda sul do Cráton do São Francisco: 

termocronologia por traços de fissão em apatita. Brazilian Journal of Geology, 

37(4), 76-86. 

Harman, R., Gallagher, K., Brown, R., Raza, A. Bizzi, L. 1998. Accelerated 

denudation and tectonic/geomorphic reactivation of the cratons of northeastern 

Brazil during the Late Cretaceous. Journal of Geophysical Research, 103(B11): 

27091-27105. 

Hartmann, L.A., Chemale Jr., F., Philipp, R.P. 2007. Evolução geotectônica do Rio 

Grande do Sul no Pré-Cambriano. In: Ianuzzi, R., Frantz, J.C. (Ed.) 50 anos de 

Geologia. Porto Alegre: Editora Comunicação e Identidade, p.97-123. 

Hiruma, S.T., Riccomini, C., Modenesi-Gauttieri, M.C., Hackspacher, P.C., Hadler 

Neto, J.C., Franco-Magalhães, A.O.B. 2010. Denudation history of the Bocaina 

Plateau, Serra do Mar, southeastern Brazil: relationships to Gondwana breakup 

and passive margin development. Gondwana Research, 18, 674-687. 

Japsen, P., Bonow, J.M., Green, P.F., Cobbold, P.R., Chiossi, D., Lilletveit, R., 

Magnavita, L.P., Pedreira, A. 2012. Episodic burial and exhumation in NE Brazil 

after opening of the South Atlantic. GSA Bulletin, 124: 800816. 

Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F., van der Beek, P.A., Guadagnin, F., Cupertino, J.A., 

Viana, A. 2014. Denudation history and landscape evolution of the northern 

East-Brazilian continental margin from apatite fission-track thermochronology. 

Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 54, 158-181. 

Jelinek, A.R., Gomes, C.H., Dias, A.N.C., Guadagnin, F., Chemale, F.Jr., Souza, I.A. 

2010. Termocronologia aplicada às Geociências: análise por traços de fissão. 

Pesquisas em Geociências, 37 (3), 191-203. 

Jelinek, A.R., Neto, A.C.B., Poupeau, G. 2003. Análise por traços de fissão em 

apatitas do Distrito Fluorítico de Santa Catarina: relações entre hidrotermalismo 

e evolução da margem continental. Brazilian Journal of Geology, 33(3), 289-

298. 

Karl, M., Glasmacher, U.A., Kollenz, S., Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Stockli, D.F., 

Hackspacher, P.C. 2013. Evolution of the South Atlantic passive continental 



23 

 

 

margin in southern Brazil derived from zircon and apatite (U–Th–Sm)/He and 

fission-track data. Tectonophysics, 604, 224-244. 

Lima, M.V.A., Berrocal, J., Soares, J.E., Fuck, R.A. 2015. Deep seismic refraction 

experiment in northeast Brazil: New constraints for Borborema province 

evolution. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 58: 335-349. 

Malusà, M.G., Carter, A., Limoncelli, M., Villa, I.M., Garzanti, E. 2013. Bias in detrital 

zircon geochronology and thermochronometry. Chemical Geology, 359, 90-107. 

Meisling, K.E., Cobbold, P.R., Mount, V.S. 2001. Segmentation of an obliquely rifted 

margin, Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG bulletin, 

85(11), 1903-1924. 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Thomaz-Filho, A., Milani, E.J., Cesero, P. 2002. Mesozoic and 

Cenozoic igneous activity and its tectonic control in northeastern Brazil. Journal 

of South American Earth Sciences, 15 (2): 183-198. 

Morais Neto, J.M., Green, P.F., Karner, G.D., Alkmim, F.F. 2008. Age of the Serra do 

Martins Formation, Borborema Plateau, northeastern Brazil: constraints from 

apatite and zircon fission track analysis. Boletim de Geociências da Petrobras, 

16(1): 23-52. 

Morais Neto, J.M., Hegarty, K.A., Karner, G.D., Alkmim, F.F. 2009. Timing and 

mechanisms for the generation and modification of the anomalous topography 

of the Borborema Province, northeastern Brazil. Marine and Petroleum 

Geology, 26: 1070-1086. 

Naeser, C.W. 1967. The use of apatite and shpene for fission track age 

determinations. Geological Society of America Bulletin 78, 1523-1526. 

Nürnberg, D. &amp;amp; Müller, R.D. 1991. The tectonic evolution of the South Atlantic from 

Late Jurassic to present. Tectonophysics, 191: 27–53. 

Oliveira, C.H.E., Chemale, F., Jelinek, A.R., Bicca, M.M., Philipp, R.P. 2014. U–Pb 

and Lu–Hf isotopes applied to the evolution of the late to post-orogenic 

transtensional basins of the dom feliciano belt, Brazil. Precambrian Research, 

246, 240-255. 

Oliveira, C.H.E., Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F., Bernet, M. 2016. Evidence of post-

Gondwana breakup in Southern Brazilian Shield: Insights from apatite and 

zircon fission track thermochronology. Tectonophysics, 666, 173-187. 



24 

 

 

Paim, P.S.G., Chemale Jr., F., Lopes, R.C. 2000. A Bacia do Camaquã. In: Holz, M., 

DeRos, L.F. (Eds.), Geologia do Rio Grande do Sul. CIGO-UFRGS, Porto 

Alegre, p.231-274. 

Price, P.B. &amp;amp; Walker, R.M. 1963. Fossil tracks of charged particles in mica and the 

age of minerals. Journal of Geophysics Research, 68, 4847-4862. 

Raab, M.J., Brown, R.W., Gallagher, K., Weber, K., Gleadow, A.J.W. 2005. 

Denudational and thermal history of the Early Cretaceous Brandberg and 

Okenyenya igneous complexes on Namibia's Atlantic passive margin. 

Tectonics, 24, TC3006. 

Reiners, P.W. &amp;amp; Brandon, M.T. 2006. Using thermochronology to understand 

orogenic erosion. Annu. Rev. Earth Planet. Sci., 34, 419-466. 

Roeder, P.L., MacArthur, D., Ma, X.P., Palmer, G.R., Mariano, A.N., 1987. 

Cathodoluminescence and microprobe study of rare-earth elements in apatite. 

American Mineralogist, 72, 801-811. 

Salamuni, E. 1998. Tectônica da bacia sedimentar de Curitiba (PR). Tese de 

Doutorado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, Instituto de 

Geociências e Ciências Exatas, Universidade Estadual Paulista. 

Tagami, T., Galbraith, R.F., Yamada, R., Laslett, G.M. 1998. Revised annealing 

kinetics of fission tracks in zircon and geological implications. In: Van den 

Haute, P., De Corte, F. (Ed.) Advances in Fission-track geochronology, p. 99-

112. 

Tello Saenz, C., Hackspacher, P.C., Neto, J.H., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, 

L.F.B., Paulo, S.R. 2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene 

tectonic reactivation through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambrian areas 

of southeast Brazil: association with the opening of the South Atlantic Ocean. 

Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 15(7), 765-774. 

Torsvik, T.H., Rousse, S., Labails, C., Smethurst, M.A. 2009. A new scheme for the 

opening of the South Atlantic Ocean and the dissection of an Aptian salt basin. 

Geophysical Journal International, 177(3), 1315-1333. 

Turner, J.P., Green, P.F., Holford, S.P., Lawrence, S.R. 2008. Thermal history of the 

Rio Muni (West Africa) e NE Brazil margins during continental breakup. Earth 

and Planetary Science Letters, 270: 354-367. 

Wagner, G.A. 1968. Fission track dating of apatites. Earth and Planetary Science 

Letters, 5, 463-468. 



25 

 

 

Wagner, G.A. 1972. The geological interpretation of fission track age. Transactions of 

American Nuclear Society, 15, 117. 

Yamada, R., Tagami, T., Nishimura, S., Ito, H. 1995. Annealing kinetics of fission 

tracks in zircon: an experimental study. Chemical Geology (Isotope Geoscience 

section), 122, 249-58. 

Young, E.J., Myers, A.T., Munson, E.L., Conklin, N.M. 1969. Mineralogy and 

geochemistry of fluorapatite from Cerro de Mercado, Durango, Mexico. U.S. 

Geological Survey Professional Paper, 650-D, D84-D93. 

Zalán, P.V., Wolff, S., Conceição, A., Marques, M.A.M., Astolfi, I.S., Vieira, V.T., 

Appi, O.A. 1990. Bacia do Paraná. In: Raja Gabaglia, G. P. e Milani, E.J. (Eds.). 

Origem e Evolução de Bacias Sedimentares. Ed. Gávea, Petrobras, p.135-168. 



Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187

Contents lists available at ScienceDirect

Tectonophysics

journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/tecto
Evidence of post-Gondwana breakup in Southern Brazilian Shield:
Insights from apatite and zircon fission track thermochronology
Christie Helouise Engelmann de Oliveira a,?, Andréa Ritter Jelinek a, Farid Chemale Jr. b, Matthias Bernet c
a Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil
b Instituto de Geociências, Universidade de Brasilia, Brazil
c Institut des Sciences de la Terre (ISTerre), Université Joseph Fourier, France
? Corresponding author.
E-mail address: christie.oliveira10@gmail.com (C.H.E.

http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2015.11.005
0040-1951/© 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
a b s t r a c t
a r t i c l e i n f o
Article history:
Received 30 July 2015
Received in revised form 29 October 2015
Accepted 5 November 2015
Available online 14 November 2015
Apatite and zircon fission track thermochronology studies are applied to basement and sedimentary rocks from
the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield to unravel the tectonic history of the onshore southernmost Brazilian margin. The
Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield is a major geotectonic feature of southernmost Brazil that includes Paleoproterozoic
basement areas and Neoproterozoic fold belts linked to the Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny. Crustal reworking
and juvenile accretion events related to this cycle were dated in the region between 900 and 500 Ma and were
responsible for the assembly of southwestern Gondwana in southeastern South America. Apatite fission track
(AFT) ages range from 340 ± 33 to 77 ± 6 Ma and zircon fission track (ZFT) ages range from ca. 386 to
210 Ma. Based on thermal history modeling, the most part of the samples record an early cooling event during
the Carboniferous, which reflect the main tectonic activity of the final stages of the Gondwanides at the Pacific
margin of West Gondwana. Subsequently, the Permo-Triassic cooling event is related to the last stages of the
Gondwanides, with convergence along the southern border of Western Gondwana and consequent reactivation
of N-S and NE-SW trending basement structures. The onset of initial breakup of southwestern Gondwana with
opening of the South Atlantic Ocean is mostly recorded in the eastern terrain and ZFT ages show that the temper-
ature during this period was high enough for total or at least partial resetting of fission tracks in zircon. The last
cooling event of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield records the final breakup between South America and Africa,
which began during the Late Cretaceous. However, the Cenozoic rapid cooling episode probably is a result of
plate adjustment after breakup and neotectonic reactivation of faults associated with South Atlantic rift
evolution.

© 2015 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
Keywords:
Gondwana
Apatite fission track
Zircon fission track
Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield
Camaquã Basin
1. Introduction

The South Atlantic Ocean Margin results from the breakup of Gond-
wana during Early Cretaceous times and exhibits much more variety of
topography and geology than the conjugate margin of Africa. From the
Chain Fracture Zone in the north to the Falkland Agulhas Fracture
Zone in the south, the South American Margin is segmented in various
ways (e.g., Cappelletti et al., 2013; Chaboureau et al., 2013; Nürnberg
and Müller, 1991). In the north, the margin is underlain by Precambrian
rocks of the Brazilian Shield, has a dominant structural lineament paral-
lel to the margin and high topography. To the south, the topography
gets progressively lower and in the south of the Rio de la Plata craton
there is no Precambrian basement exposed (Fig. 1). The nature of the
margin has influenced the development of offshore sedimentary basins
and onshore intracontinental basins.
Oliveira).
On the South American Margin most thermochronology studies
have focused on southeastern Brazil (e.g., Cogné et al., 2011, 2012;
Franco-Magalhaes et al., 2014; Gallagher et al., 1994, 1995; Hackspacher
et al., 2007; Hiruma et al., 2010; Jelinek et al., 2003; Karl et al., 2013;
Tello Saenz et al., 2003), where the rifted-margin escarpment is most
clearly expressed, such as Serra do Mar and Serra da Mantiqueira. In
contrast, the uplift and denudation history of the margin further to the
south have not been studied in much detail until now. Borba et al.
(2002, 2003) and Bicca et al. (2013) used AFT data focused on relatively
restricted areas to constrain denudation in the NW cratonic interior of
the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield. In order to improve the understanding
of the thermotectonic evolution of this last sector of south Brazilian
continental margin 57 new thermochronological data were obtained:
37 new AFT ages from basement and detrital samples and 20 new ZFT
ages from detrital samples. AFT and ZFT cooling ages are related to the
continental breakup between South America and Africa and the quanti-
tative thermal histories derived from the data provide the denudation
rates, which have a significant effect on the evolution of continental
topography and allow us to reconstruct the low-temperature cooling
history of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield.

http://crossmark.crossref.org/dialog/?doi=10.1016/j.tecto.2015.11.005&amp;amp;domain=pdf
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2015.11.005
mailto:christie.oliveira10@gmail.com
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2015.11.005
http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/00401951
www.elsevier.com/locate/tecto


Fig. 1. Geotectonic map of South America with location of the study area (modified from Basei et al., 2010).

174 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
2. Geologic setting

The Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield, situated in the southwest Gondwana,
comprises rock assemblages generated between Archean and
Cambrian-Ordovician (Chemale Jr., 2000; Fernandes et al., 1992;
Hartmann et al., 2007) including Dom Feliciano Belt. The Dom Feliciano
Belt is an orogenic belt formed as result of the tectonic accretion of the
Rio de la Plata, Kalahari and Congo cratons during formation of West
Gondwana (e.g., Chemale et al., 1995; Fernandes et al., 1992) in the
Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny.

The Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield is composed of the following four
units (Fig. 2) bounded by NE-SW and NW-SE oriented regional
Brasiliano shear zones: (1) the Taquarembó Terrane, bounded in the
north by the NW-SE trending Ibaré shear zone and in the east by the



Fig. 2. Geotectonic map of southern Brazil (modified after Chemale Jr., 2000; Zerfass et al., 2005) with sample locations for this study, Bicca et al. (2013) and Borba et al. (2002, 2003).
Samples are identified by AFT age.

175C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
NE-SW trending Caçapava do Sul shear zone, is composed primarily
of Paleoproterozoic granulites with protolith ages of 2.45 Ga and
metamorphic events dated at 2.1–2.0 Ga (Hartmann et al., 2008a), sev-
eral granite intrusions dated at 0.65–0.55 Ga (Gastal et al., 2005) and
Neoproterozoic to Eopaleozoic volcano-sedimentary rocks (Wildner
et al., 2002); (2) the Tijucas Terrane, bounded in the west by the
ductile–brittle Porongos fault and in the east by conjugate Passo do
Marinheiro and Dorsal de Canguçu shear zones, is composed of
metasedimentary rocks intercalated with metavolcanic rocks of the
Porongos Complex, whose age is constrained at ca. 780 Ma, (Chemale
Jr., 2000; Saalmann et al., 2011), older basement portions of granitic–
gneissic rocks of the Encantadas Complex dated at 2.2–2.3 Ga
(Hartmann et al., 2003; Philipp et al., 2008; Saalmann et al., 2011) and
granitic intrusions and sedimentary rocks dating to 0.65–0.55 Ga;
(3) the São Gabriel Terrane, bounded to the south by the Ibaré shear
zone and to the east by the Caçapava do Sul shear zone, consists of a
tectonic juxtaposition of ophiolite slabs, volcanic-arc-related rocks, plu-
tonic granite–gneissic rocks with a Neoproterozoic juvenile signature,
volcano-sedimentary rocks formed between 1.0 and 0.69 Ga (Babinski
et al., 1996; Chemale Jr., 2000; Hartmann et al., 2007, 2011; Saalmann
et al., 2005), and 0.63–0.47 Ga old late- to post-orogenic granite intru-
sions and volcano-sedimentary cover rocks (in the Camaquã Basin);
and (4) the Pelotas Batholith, bounded in the west by the Passo do
Marinheiro and Dorsal de Canguçu shear zones, is represented predom-
inantly by granite rocks with ages of 0.65–0.55 Ga (Babinski et al., 1997;
Hartmann et al., 2000; Philipp and Machado, 2005; Philipp et al., 2003;
Silva et al., 1999), reworking of Paleoproterozoic crust and, more rarely,
Archean rocks (Leite et al., 2000; Philipp et al., 2003).

2.1. Camaquã Basin

The Camaquã Basin consists of a NE-SW-elongated basin (Fig. 2)
generated in the late- to post-orogenic sedimentary cycles of the
Brasiliano orogeny in the Dom Feliciano Belt (e.g., Chemale et al.,
1995; Paim et al., 2000). Structurally, the Camaquã Basin may be de-
fined as a depositional locus with superposition of various basinal cycles
distinguished by age and tectonic setting (Borba, 2006; Chemale, 1993;
Oliveira et al., 2014; Paim et al., 2000). The basin contains a record of
three primary basinal cycles developed in various tectonic settings:
(1) Maricá Group is the basal cycle deposited in a retroarc foreland,
and consists of a 4000-m-thick sedimentary package with a minor
contribution from acidic volcanic activity unconformably overlying
the São Gabriel Terrane. Deposition of this group occurred between
601 ± 13 and 593 ± 6 Ma (Almeida et al., 2012; Paim et al., 2000);
(2) Bom Jardim Group represents the middle cycle deposited in a
strike-slip setting from 593 ± 6 to 580 ± 3.6 Ma (Almeida et al.,
2012; Janikian et al., 2012; Remus et al., 1999). The Bom Jardim Group
consists of a 2000-m-thick volcano-sedimentary sequence overlying
the Maricá Group along an angular unconformity; and, (3) the upper
cycle was deposited in a transtensional environment and comprises
the Santa Bárbara Group (including Acampamento Velho Formation)
and Guaritas Group. The Santa Bárbara Group consists of a ca. 2500-
m-thick volcano-sedimentary sequence and was deposited from
574 ± 7 to 549.3 ± 5 Ma (Bicca et al., 2013; Janikian et al., 2012;
Oliveira et al., 2014; Sommer et al., 2005). The Guaritas Group repre-
sents the last depositional episode preserved in the Camaquã Basin
with ca. 800-m-thick. This group was deposited in a N40E-trending
transtensional rift basin (e.g., Borba, 2006; Chemale, 1993) and consists
of sandstones and conglomerates. The deposition of the Guaritas Group
occurred between 547 ± 6.3 Ma and 473.7 ± 9.4 Ma (Almeida et al.,
2012; Hartmann et al., 2008b; Maraschin et al., 2010; Oliveira et al.,
2014).

3. Samples and analytical methods

Twenty-seven outcrop samples and 17 samples of three boreholes
(CQP-01, CQP-02 and CQP-03, drilled by the Geological Survey of
Brazil—CPRM) were collected along the Taquarembó Terrane, São Ga-
briel Terrane, including the Camaquã Basin, and Pelotas Batholith
(Fig. 2; Table 1). Details of the lithology of each sample are provided
in Table 1. Outcrop samples were collected along NW-SE transects
crosscutting the Taquarembó Terrane, São Gabriel Terrane and
Camaquã Basin, and NW-SE and NE-SW trending transects in the Pe-
lotas Batholith. The boreholes CQP-01 and CQP-02 have a depth of
1200 m (Fig. 3). The CQP-01 is located southeast of Caçapava do Sul
and CQP-02 is located in the Minas do Camaquã. The borehole CQP-
03 is located north of the CQP-02 and has a depth of 1250 m (Fig. 3).
Borehole samples were collected at different depths intervals, as



Table 1
Details of fission track samples.

Sample Lithology Stratig. age Latitude Longitude Elevation Depth Dating

(Ma) S E (m) (m) method

Taquarembó Terrane
TFRS-05 Granulite 2450 31.10 54.44 188 * AFT
TFRS-06 Granite 650–550 31.29 54.06 253 * AFT

São Gabriel Terrane
TFRS-12 Granite 561–541 30.50 53.46 353 * AFT
PRD-02 Granite 561–541 30.51 53.46 350 * AFT

Pelotas Batholith
PJV-07 Granite 550 30.51 51.92 312 * AFT
PJV-11 Granite 650–550 30.07 51.02 74 * AFT
PJV-14 Granite 550 30.31 51.60 268 * AFT
TFRS-07 Granite 650–550 31.57 53.39 422 * AFT
PRD-04 Granite 550 31.15 52.83 330 * AFT
PRD-05 Granite 550 31.08 52.77 220 * AFT
PJV-17 Granite 595 31.41 52.65 333 * AFT
PRD-10 Granite 610–550 30.57 52.68 440 * AFT
PRD-12 Gneiss 600 30.56 52.45 440 * AFT
TFRS-08 Granite gneiss 650–550 31.72 52.89 18 * AFT
PJV-02 Granite 650–550 30.82 52.17 89 * AFT
PJV-03b Granite 650–550 30.80 53.19 189 * AFT
PJV-03c Granite 650–550 30.82 52.11 189 * AFT
PJV-04 Granite 650–550 30.79 52.11 208 * AFT
PJV-05 Granite 650–550 30.75 52.11 198 * AFT
PJV-06 Granite 650–550 30.55 51.99 270 * AFT
PRD-18 Granite gneiss 650–550 30.78 51.98 240 * AFT
PRD-19 Granite 550 30.87 51.94 140 * AFT

Camaquã Basin
GU-01 Sandstone 553–465 30.74 53.20 * * ZFT
GU-02 Sandstone 553–465 30.76 53.19 * * ZFT
PS-01 Conglomerate 580–545 30.54 53.55 176 * ZFT
PS-03 Conglomerate 580–545 30.62 53.54 397 * ZFT
TFRS-11 Sandstone 553–465 30.80 53.19 123 * AFT

Borehole CQP-01
T01-11 Sandstone 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 41 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T01-35 Sandstone 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 134 ZFT
T01-56 Sandstone 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 218 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T01-82 Conglomerate 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 318 ZFT
T01-103 Sandstone 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 400 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T01-130 Conglomerate 553–465 30.68 53.33 * 507 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T01-144 Sandstone 580–545 30.68 53.33 * 569 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T01-176 Sandstone 580–545 30.68 53.33 * 729 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT

Borehole CQP-02
T02-07 Conglomerate 580–545 30.90 53.43 * 27 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T02-64 Sandstone 580–545 30.90 53.43 * 271 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T02-104 Sandstone 580–545 30.90 53.43 * 469 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T02-149 Sandstone 580–545 30.90 53.43 * 694 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T02-202 Siltstone 580–545 30.90 53.43 * 926 ZFT

Borehole CQP-03
T03-03 Sandstone 580–545 31.03 53.47 * 12 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T03-156 Sandstone 580–545 31.03 53.47 * 657 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT
T03-203 Sandstone 580–545 31.03 53.47 * 884 AFT
T03-249 Sandstone 580–545 31.03 53.47 * 1096 AFT &amp;amp; ZFT

176 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
shown in Table 1. Apatite and zircon grains were separated from samples
using standard crushing, magnetic and heavy liquid separation methods.

3.1. Apatite and zircon fission-track analysis

Apatite aliquots were mounted in epoxy, polished and etched for
20 s in a 5.5 M HNO3 solution at 21 °C to reveal the spontaneous fission
tracks. Zircon aliquots were mounted in Teflon®, polished and etched in
a eutectic NaOH-KOH melt at 228 °C. We adopted the multi-mount
technique and prepared two zircon mounts per sample (Bernet and
Garver, 2005; Naeser et al., 1987) and etched for different lengths of
time, with etching times ranging between 8 and 40 h.

All apatite and zircon samples were dated by the external detector
method (Hurford, 1990) using low-U mica sheets as external detectors.
Zircon samples were irradiated with Fish Canyon Tuff age standard and
CN2 dosimeter glasses at the well-thermalized FRM II Research Reactor
of the Technical University Munich, Germany. Apatite samples were ir-
radiated at the same reactor and at the well-thermalized IPEN-CNEN
Reactor, São Paulo, Brazil, with Durango age standard and CN1 and
CN5 dosimeter glasses. After irradiation, mica detectors were etched
in 48% HF for 18 min at 20 °C to reveal the induced fission tracks.

ZFT analyses on all samples were performed at the fission-track
laboratory of the Institut des Sciences de la Terre (ISTerre) in Grenoble,
France, utilizing an Olympus BX51 microscope (1250×, dry) and the
FTStage 4.04 system (Dumitru, 1993), while AFT analyses were
performed at the Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, uti-
lizing a Leica DM 6000 M Microscope (1000×, dry). We aimed at dating
at least 20 grains per sample. Eleven AFT samples and 14 ZFT samples do



Fig. 3. Fission-track ages plotted against samples depth from the boreholes of the Camaquã Basin. AFT and ZFT data are shown as age ranges with errors.

177C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
not meet these criteria (Table 2); we decided to retain them nonetheless,
because their ages broadly agree with the nearby samples that do have
good-quality measurements. AFT and ZFT central ages were calculated
according to the ?-calibration method (Hurford, 1990). Throughout
this study, fission-track age errors are quoted at the 1? confidence
level and were derived by the conventional method (Green, 1981).
The ?2-squared test was used to quantify age homogeneity; when
P(?2) N5%, fission-track samples contain a single age population
(Galbraith and Green, 1990, 1993). For samples from sedimentary
rocks which failed the ?2-test and have an age-dispersion over 15%
may reflect a mixture of different age components. The software
“RadialPlotter” (Vermeesch, 2009) was used in order to statistically
separate different age populations. In a first step, the auto mixture
model was applied. Samples which revealed only one age component
were further tested applying a two component mixture model.

AFT lengths were measured on horizontal confined fission tracks.
Where possible, 100 natural confined tracks were measured to
construct an AFT length–frequency distribution, a number that was not
always attained. Etch pit diameter (Dpar; Donelick et al., 2005) values
and the chemical compositions (in particular the Cl concentration)
were used as kinetic parameter. Microprobe analysis for chemical com-
positions was carried out in the Department of Geology, Universidade
Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Brazil using a JEOL JXA-8230 Electron
Microprobe.

3.2. Thermal history modeling

Apatite thermal history modeling was performed with HeFTy 1.8.3
(Ketcham, 2005). In this study, AFT data are modeled using the multi-
kinetic annealing model of Ketcham et al. (2007), with Cl content or
Dpar values as a kinetic parameter. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was
employed to assess the fit between modeled and measured track-
length distributions. The inversions modeling were run with 10,000
randomly chosen time-temperature (t–T) histories for each sample;
such that sufficient model paths were available to clearly differentiate
between “good fit” and “acceptable fit” solutions (cf. Ketcham, 2005 for
details and definitions of “good” and “acceptable” fits). Depending on
the fission-track parameters (i.e., ages and lengths) and the geological
background and cooling history of different areas, we restricted the con-
ditions for inversion modeling as follows: (a) an initial constraint was set
at 200 ± 20 °C at a time span older than the corresponding ZFT central
age. For samples that do not have ZFT age we used as initial constraint
the end of the Brasiliano orogeny (ca. 550–450 Ma), the last tectono-
thermal event that affected the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield rocks; (b) a
large t–T box was imposed with T closed limits in the base of the apatite
partial annealing zone temperature (120 °C) and at the paleo-surface
temperature (20 ± 10 °C). The t closed limits are the oldest AFT grain
age and the central sample age; (c) a constraint was set in 40–120 °C
at a time corresponding the youngest pooled age (b200 Ma); and (d) a
present mean surface temperature of ca. 20 ± 5 °C provided the final
modeling constraint.

The quantification of denudation was estimated based on geother-
mal gradients measured from the data of the Paraná Basin in southern
Brazil (Hurter and Pollack, 1996). Since insufficient measurements are
available to assess the spatial variation in geothermal gradient of the
Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield, we assumed a constant and linear geother-
mal gradient over geological times (25 °C/km) for the reconstruction
of the rocks denudation histories.

4. Results

AFT and ZFT ages and confined track length measurement from the
different tectonic blocks are presented in Table 2. Sample locations and
AFT ages obtained together with existing AFT ages from the literature
(Bicca et al., 2013; Borba et al., 2002, 2003) are presented in Figure 2.
Cooling histories for all samples are presented in Figures 4–8.

4.1. Apatite fission-track data

AFT central ages measured range from 340 ± 33 (sample TFRS-06)
to 77 ± 6 Ma (sample PJV-07). Three AFT sedimentary samples from
the Camaquã Basin (T03-03, T03-203 and T03-249; Table 2) failed the
?2-squared test and have an age-dispersion over 15%, indicating that
more than one age component is present in the obtained single grain
age population. All AFT central ages are much younger than the
Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny that last affected the Sul-Rio-Grandense



Table 2
Apatite and zircon fission track data from the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield, southern Brazil.

Sample Dating
method

N ?s (Ns) (×105) ?i (Ni) (×105) ?d (Nd) (×105) Central
age (Ma)

±1?
(Ma)

?2 (%) U content
(ppm)

Cl (wt.%) Dpar
(?m)

n MTL
(?m)

Std. dev.
(?m)

Taquarembó Terrane
TFRS-05 AFT 22 24.03 (1144) 3.15 (150) 2.32 (16,493) 298.0 26.0 100 16.6 0.259 * 35 11.4 1.2
TFRS-06 AFT 25 18.21 (1029) 2.09 (118) 2.32 (16,493) 340.0 33.0 100 11.0 0.032 * 66 11.2 1.4

São Gabriel Terrane
TFRS-12 AFT 30 25.44 (1908) 4.27 (320) 2.32 (16,493) 234.0 14.0 99 22.4 0.009 * 32 11.3 1.5
PRD-02 AFT 20 6.94 (294) 3.73 (158) 5.07 (7600) 161.0 16.0 98 9.0 0.004 * 84 12.4 1.8

Pelotas Batholith
PJV-07 AFT 24 7.63 (458) 5.42 (325) 3.22 (15,546) 77.3 5.8 92 20.5 0.006 * 29 10.1 1.7
PJV-11 AFT 25 17.34 (1084) 12.13 (758) 12.07 (16,440) 95.4 4.5 100 40.0 0.008 * 93 11.3 1.8
PJV-14 AFT 11 2.76 (76) 2.04 (56) 12.07 (16,440) 91.0 16.0 77 6.7 0.005 * 3 12.9 0.5
TFRS-07 AFT 19 15.05 (715) 5.41 (257) 2.32 (16,493) 110.4 8.0 86 28.4 * * * * *
PRD-04 AFT 20 42.03 (688) 18.39 (301) 5.07 (7600) 197.0 14.0 99 44.2 0.024 * 162 11.8 1.6
PRD-05 AFT 15 9.84 (247) 6.17 (155) 5.07 (7600) 138.0 14.0 87 14.8 0.009 * 42 13.8 1.3
PJV-17 AFT 25 19.18 (1199) 7.92 (495) 12.07 (16,440) 160.8 8.6 94 26.1 0.005 * 83 10.7 1.6
PRD-10 AFT 25 24.99 (634) 8.91 (226) 5.07 (7600) 241.0 19.0 93 21.4 0.003 * 53 12.0 1.7
PRD-12 AFT 9 36.33 (289) 12.82 (102) 5.07 (7600) 243.0 28.0 56 30.8 0.035 * 32 13.0 1.7
TFRS-08 AFT 29 33.01 (2393) 7.43 (539) 2.32 (16,493) 175.2 8.4 100 39.1 * 2.10 69 12.0 1.4
PJV-02 AFT 23 9.44 (543) 3.43 (197) 12.07 (16,440) 183.0 15.0 100 11.3 0.005 * 59 10.4 1.5
PJV-03b AFT 24 24.45 (1467) 7.98 (479) 12.07 (16,440) 203.0 11.0 100 26.3 0.011 * 82 10.3 1.4
PJV-03c AFT 23 51.46 (777) 13.58 (205) 12.07 (16,440) 250.0 20.0 100 44.8 0.004 * 102 11.1 1.6
PJV-04 AFT 24 21.09 (1086) 4.80 (247) 3.22 (15,546) 240.0 17.0 99 18.2 * 1.45 89 10.2 1.6
PJV-05 AFT 10 29.08 (727) 6.28 (157) 3.22 (15,546) 252.0 22.0 91 23.8 * * * * *
PJV-06 AFT 28 30.06 (2104) 9.07 (635) 12.07 (16,440) 219.0 9.9 31 29.9 * 1.33 52 10.9 1.9
PRD-18 AFT 21 24.1 (641) 6.92 (184) 5.07 (7600) 298.0 25.0 80 16.6 0.004 * 57 11.2 1.4
PRD-19 AFT 11 26.3 (290) 6.71 (74) 5.07 (7600) 334.0 44.0 100 16.1 0.007 * 28 11.5 1.4

Camaquã Basin
GU-01 ZFT 12 145.11 (1096) 6.36 (48) 2.63 (4367) 386.0 57.0 78 88.2 * * * * *
GU-02 ZFT 3 171.54 (299) 12.62 (22) 2.63 (4367) 227.0 56.0 15 175.1 * * * * *
PS-01 ZFT 22 141.58 (1986) 7.2 (101) 2.63 (4367) 334.0 34.0 58 99.9 * * * * *
PS-03 ZFT 7 119.54 (506) 6.14 (26) 2.63 (4367) 332.0 67.0 97 85.2 * * * * *
TFRS-11 AFT 45 23.47 (2640) 5.22 (587) 2.32 (16,493) 176.4 9.4 7 27.4 0.029 * 53 11.9 1.4
T01-11 AFT 30 8.53 (318) 10.13 (378) 11.35 (6808) 146.0 11.0 48 10.9 * 1.90 38 11.0 1.1

ZFT 23 115.53 (1611) 8.61 (120) 2.63 (4367) 230.0 23.0 33 119.4 * * * * *
T01-35 ZFT 11 156.91 (1094) 8.03 (56) 2.63 (4367) 332.0 45.0 88 111.4 * * * * *
T01-56 AFT 5 10.97 (102) 11.29 (105) 11.35 (6808) 166.0 25.0 33 12.1 * * * * *

ZFT 3 95.55 (230) 4.57 (11) 2.63 (4367) 355.0 109.0 71 63.4 * * * * *
T01-82 ZFT 28 140.83 (2782) 6.88 (136) 2.63 (4367) 356.0 44.0 0 95.5 * * * * *
T01-103 AFT 24 14.99 (715) 14.05 (670) 11.35 (6808) 185.0 11.0 12 15.1 * 1.88 44 11.0 1.4

ZFT 14 149.38 (1401) 8.96 (84) 2.63 (4367) 287.0 36.0 20 124.2 * * * * *
T01-130 AFT 4 11.22 (46) 6.10 (25) 11.35 (6808) 301.0 95.0 14 6.5 * * * * *

ZFT 20 121.94 (1589) 5.76 (75) 2.63 (4367) 359.0 42.0 73 79.8 * * * * *
T01-144 AFT 16 13.99 (270) 10.93 (211) 11.35 (6808) 221.0 20.0 55 11.7 * * * * *

ZFT 11 156.63 (819) 9.75 (51) 2.63 (4367) 274.0 40.0 66 135.3 * * * * *
T01-176 AFT 30 10.91 (566) 9.92 (515) 11.35 (6808) 190.0 12.0 45 10.6 * 2.14 31 11.2 1.2

ZFT 24 124.96 (1701) 8.67 (118) 2.63 (4367) 253.0 24.0 63 120.3 * * * * *
T02-07 AFT 18 6.61 (211) 4.20 (134) 11.35 (6808) 270.0 30.0 91 4.5 * * * * *

ZFT 11 99.24 (659) 6.93 (46) 2.63 (4367) 250.0 39.0 72 94 * * * * *
T02-64 AFT 26 14.79 (719) 9.63 (468) 11.35 (6808) 263.0 19.0 19 10.3 * 1.93 19 11.2 1.2

ZFT 24 133.04 (2098) 9.13 (144) 2.63 (4367) 251.0 23.0 33 125.8 * * * * *
T02-104 AFT 21 18.70 (619) 9.55 (316) 11.35 (6808) 339.0 25.0 50 10.7 * * * * *

ZFT 2 157.43 (196) 7.23 (9) 2.63 (4367) 369.0 126.0 17 100.3 * * * * *
T02-149 AFT 30 12.37 (490) 11.79 (467) 11.35 (6808) 180.0 14.0 20 12.6 * * * * *

ZFT 4 158.35 (368) 11.62 (27) 2.63 (4367) 210.0 40.0 97 161.2 * * * * *
T02-202 ZFT 6 109.61 (373) 6.76 (23) 2.63 (4367) 277.0 59.0 38 93.8 * * * * *
T03-03 AFT 31 17.31 (850) 13.48 (662) 11.35 (6808) 226.0 15.0 2 14.5 * 1.78 25 11.0 1.2

ZFT 11 122.59 (814) 7.68 (51) 2.63 (4367) 273.0 39.0 79 106.6 * * * * *
T03-156 AFT 24 17.90 (580) 13.58 (440) 11.35 (6808) 226.0 16.0 30 14.6 * 1.79 24 10.9 1.0

ZFT 8 126.04 (544) 7.18 (31) 2.63 (4367) 298.0 63.0 13 99.6 * * * * *
T03-203 AFT 22 18.33 (660) 18.42 (663) 11.35 (6808) 178.0 23.0 0 19.8 * * * * *
T03-249 AFT 12 15.36 (258) 12.44 (209) 11.35 (6808) 224.0 32.0 1 13.3 * 1.57 6 10.9 0.9

ZFT 6 152.88 (571) 11.51 (43) 2.63 (4367) 231.0 48.0 8 159.7 * * * * *

N: number of grains analyzed to determine track densities; ?s: measured spontaneous track density; :Ns number of spontaneous tracks counted; :?i measured induced track density; Ni:
number of induced tracks counted; ?d: track density measured in glass dosimeter; Nd: number of tracks counted in determining ?d; ?2: Chi-square probability; n: number of confined
tracks lengths measured; MTL: mean track length; Dpar: mean etch pit diameter of all measured etch pits; std. dev.: standard deviation of track length distribution of individual track mea-
surements; (*): not analyzed. Note: ZFT and AFT ages from the Camaquã Basin, except TFRS-11 sample, were calculated by C.H.E. Oliveira using ?-CN2 = 132.57 and ?-CN5 = 308.99 re-
spectively. The rest AFT ages were determined by L. Oliveira as well using ?-CN1 = 111.36 and ?-CN5 = 345.51.

178 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
Shield rocks before 500 Ma; we therefore interpret the ages as
representing cooling ages, which could represent regional denudation
events. As expected for such a large area of relatively subdued relief,
the collective AFT dataset does not show any systematic correlation
between AFT age and elevation. The large majority of the samples were
collected from elevations b300 m; although a few samples from some-
what higher elevations (300–440 m) were collected from the summit
surfaces of the Caçapava do Sul High and Dorsal de Canguçu shear zone.



Fig. 4. AFT radial plots (from RadialPlotter by Vermeesch, 2009) and thermal history models derived using HeFTy software (Ketcham, 2005) from the Taquarembó Terrane. Green, purple
and blue lines represent acceptable, good and weighted mean fitting t–T paths. The blue boxes are t–T constraints.

179C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
The confined track-length distributions are both unimodal and
bimodal, with MTL ranging from 10.1 ?m (sample PJV-07; n = 29) to
13.8 ?m (sample PRD-05; n = 42). The large majority of MTL lie in the
11–12 ?m range (Table 2). The Cl contents of 18 samples (Table 2)
range from 0.003 (sample PRD-10) to 0.259 wt.% (sample TFRS-05). In
most of the analyzed apatite grains, Dpar values do not vary much,
ranging between 1.33 and 2.14 ?m (Table 2), indicating fairly similar
chemical compositions and relatively fluorine rich apatite grains
(Burtner et al., 1994) with a low resistance to annealing (Ketcham
et al., 1999).

4.2. Zircon fission-track data

ZFT central ages were obtained from the Camaquã Basin and range
from ca. 386 to 210 Ma (Table 2 and Fig. 3). Within the uncertainties
of the data, ZFT ages are generally older than AFT ages for the same
samples, consistent with relative closure temperatures of these two
systems. For T02-07 and T02-64 samples, ZFT age is slightly younger
than corresponding AFT age, which is probably related to the very low
uranium content of these samples (e.g., Bernet and Garver, 2005;
Rahn et al., 2004). Detrital zircon grains are characterized by uranium
concentrations of 65–175 ppm (Table 2) obtained from measurable
spontaneous track densities. Only few countable low-U zircon grains
presents oldest ZFT ages and younger ZFT ages occur in grains with a
higher U content. Only one ZFT sample analyzed (T01-82; Table 2) failed
the ?2-squared test and have an age-dispersion over 15%, indicating that
more than one age component is present in the obtained single grain
age population.

ZFT dataset does not show any systematic correlation between ZFT
age and depth or elevation, apparently only correlation between ZFT
age and different group of the Camaquã Basin (Fig. 3). In order to im-
prove the statistics, we decided to pool the ZFT ages of different detrital
Fig. 5. AFT radial plots (from RadialPlotter by Vermeesch, 2009) and thermal history models de
and blue lines represent acceptable, good and weighted mean fitting t–T paths. The blue boxes
samples that belong to the same Camaquã Basin group. ZFT ages obtained
according to the different groups of the Camaquã Basin are presented in
Figure 9. Santa Bárbara Group outcrop samples (PS-01 and PS-03) pres-
ent an average age of 333 ± 34 Ma. However, the borehole samples are
younger: samples of the CQP-01 (T01-144 and T01-176) present an
average age of 255 ± 20 Ma; samples of the CQP-02 (T02-07, T02-64,
T02-104, T02-149 and T02-202) present an average age of 258 ±
17 Ma; and samples of the CQP-03 (T03-03, T03-156 and T03-249)
present an average age of 265 ± 27 Ma. Outcrop samples of the Guaritas
Group (GU-01 and GU-02) present an average age of 399 ± 44 Ma; and
borehole samples of the CQP-01 (T01-11, T01-35, T01-56, T01-82, T01-
103 and T01-130) present two ZFT age populations with peak ages of
361 ± 33 (83.9%) Ma and 173 ± 29 (16.1%) Ma.

All ZFT central ages are much younger than depositional age of the
Camaquã Basin and show that ZFTs were partially and/or totally reset
after deposition. Furthermore, these data are not useful for a provenance
analysis, nor do they reflect the source cooling signal.

4.3. Thermal history modeling

In order to further constrain the thermal and denudation history of
the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield, t–T histories have been modeled for 27
selected samples for which track-length measurements were available.

Good fitting t–T paths from the Taquarembó Terrane samples (TFRS-
05, TFRS-06) (Fig. 4) show relatively fast cooling from the zircon partial
annealing zone to the top of the apatite partial annealing zone (60 °C) at
ca. 425–360 Ma. Thereafter, the samples were reheated to temperatures
of ca. 60 °C at ca. 55 Ma before it cooled to present surface conditions.

Thermal history modeling from the São Gabriel Terrane (TFRS-12,
PRD-02) show relatively fast cooling through the apatite partial anneal-
ing zone during the first cooling event. The rocks appear to have resided
at that temperature for ca. 60 Myr (Fig. 5). Thereafter, the samples were
rived using HeFTy software (Ketcham, 2005) from the São Gabriel Terrane. Green, purple
are t–T constraints.



180 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
reheated to a Tmax of 63 °C at ca. 75 Ma before cooling to present
surface temperatures started.

Samples from the easternmost shield, Pelotas Batholith (Figs. 6 and
7), initially cooled at around 320–80 Ma. The majority of samples show
Fig. 6. AFT radial plots (from RadialPlotter by Vermeesch, 2009) and thermal history models de
blue lines represent acceptable, good and weighted mean fitting t–T paths. The blue boxes are
accelerated final cooling from temperatures of 75–60 °C to the surface
temperature in Cenozoic time. The other samples PRD-04, PRD-05,
PRD-10, PRD-12 and PRD-19 show slow cooling from temperatures of
60–45 °C to surface temperatures in the last 140–80 Ma (Cretaceous).
rived using HeFTy software (Ketcham, 2005) from the Pelotas Batholith. Green, purple and
t–T constraints.



Fig. 7. AFT radial plots (from RadialPlotter by Vermeesch, 2009) and thermal history models derived using HeFTy software (Ketcham, 2005) from the Pelotas Batholith. Green, purple and
blue lines represent acceptable, good and weighted mean fitting t–T paths. The blue boxes are t–T constraints.

181C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
Good fitting t–T paths from the borehole samples of the Camaquã
Basin (Fig. 8) show relatively slow cooling from the zircon partial
annealing zone to the top of the apatite partial annealing zone (60 °C)
at ca. 540–355 Ma. Thereafter, the samples were reheated to tempera-
tures of 70–95 °C at ca. 75–15 Ma before it cooled to present outcrop
conditions. The inverse model of the TFRS-11 outcrop sample (Fig. 8) in-
dicates a cooling step from the temperature regime of the zircon partial
annealing zone to paleo-surface conditions at ca. 170 Ma. Thereafter,
this sample reached Tmax of ca. 55 °C at ca. 40 Ma before it cooled
back to the surface conditions.

5. Interpretations and discussion

The final tectonic evolution of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield involved
the collision (595–540 Ma) between the Rio de la Plata (western) and
the Kalahari (eastern) plates. In this crustal segment of South America,
this period was characterized by escape tectonics (Almeida et al., 2000;
Chemale et al., 2012; Fernandes et al., 1992), with developing of the
late to post-orogenic basins and associated magmatism. The South
America remained relatively stable during the transition Cambrian–
Ordovician.

A multi-thermochronological approach combining fission-track sys-
tems sensitive to different temperatures ranging from ca. 240 to 60 °C
was applied in this study. All AFT and ZFT central ages are much younger
than Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny that last affected the rocks of the
Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield before 500 Ma (Fig. 10). We therefore inter-
pret the AFT ages as representing cooling ages (after full annealing
during burial heating for the detrital samples), which could represent
reactivation of the Precambrian structures with regional denudation
events. The data obtained from ZFT analysis in the sedimentary rocks of
the Camaquã Basin show evidence for post depositional partial and/or
total annealing indicated by age components younger than depositional
ages.

5.1. Tectonic-thermal evolution of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield basement
rocks

The first cooling episode of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield basement
rocks occurred in Carboniferous time (ca. 350 Ma) and affected units
of the Taquarembó Terrane (TFRS-05 and TFRS-06; Fig. 4) and samples
from the easternmost central part of the Pelotas Batholith, PRD-18 and
PRD-19 (Fig. 7). This denudation process is herein correlated to those
tectonic events situated in western and southern sectors of the South
American platform, in Chile, central Argentina and Patagonia, where
they contain records of pre, syn and post-orogenic magmatism due to
subduction process associated with the San Rafael or Gondwanides
Orogeny (Mpodozis and Kay, 1992; Pankhurst et al., 2006; Ramos,
2008; Ramos et al., 2014). The evolution of these areas is represented
by Upper Devonian to Carboniferous subduction to collisional related
magmatism and Permian–Triassic late to post orogenic magmatism
(Pankhurst et al., 2006; Ramos and Alemand, 2000).The propagation
of stresses related to this event could be responsible for promoting
uplift and denudation along the Precambrian NW-SE trending Ibaré
and NE-SW trending Caçapava do Sul shear zones (Chemale Jr., 2000;



Fig. 8. AFT radial plots (from RadialPlotter by Vermeesch, 2009) and thermal history models derived using HeFTy software (Ketcham, 2005) from the Camaquã Basin. Green, purple and
blue lines represent acceptable, good and weighted mean fitting t–T paths. The blue boxes are t–T constraints.

182 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
Fernandes et al., 1992), which delineate Taquarembó Terrane. The
estimated amount of denudation from 445 to 300 Ma range from
1560 to 3880 m, which yields an average long-term denudation rate
of 11–27 m/My.

The last stages of the Gondwanides are recorded in the Permo-
Triassic cooling episode, which affected São Gabriel Terrane samples
(TFRS-12; and NR, GS-1, GS-3, GN-1 and GN-2 from Borba et al.,
2002), and part of the Pelotas Batholith (PJV-02, PJV-03b, PJV-03c,
PJV-04, PJV-06, PRD-10 and PRD-12), which records amounts of denu-
dation of 2760 and 3120 m and an average long-term denudation rate
of 24–32 m/My. This cooling episode can be connected to the wide-
spread late Permian–Triassic magmatism of Choiyoi Group (Kay et al.,
1989; Mpodozis and Kay, 1992), formed in a large-scale extensional
tectonic environment after the main stages of the Gondwanide or San
Rafael orogenies (Fig. 11). This magmatism is well documented at the
Western South America Margin in the Andean Mountains and Patagonia
(e.g., Ramos, 2008; Ramos and Alemand, 2000) and consequent reacti-
vation of basement structures N-S and NE-SW trending (Riccomini
et al., 2005) in order parts of the Brazilian margin. The Permo-Triassic
events also affected the southern margin of South Africa where base-
ment rocks were uplifted to form the Cape Fold Belt and associated
Karoo Foreland Basin (Cawood and Buchan, 2007).

AFT age of 161 ± 16 Ma on sample PRD-02 of the São Gabriel Terrane,
near from NW-SE trending Arroio Mangueirão fault, precedes the onset
of initial breakup of southwestern Gondwana and are clearly related to
this fault as a consequence of the NNW-SSE extension (Fig. 11). Other
Jurassic–Cretaceous cooling episodes are recorded in samples of the
Pelotas Batholith, near to the NE-SW trending (e.g., Dorçal de Canguçu,
Passo do Marinheiro and Porto Alegre shear zones): PRD-04, PRD-05,
PJV-14, PJV-17 and TFRS-08. This period may reflect an important reacti-
vation of these structures that delimits the Pelotas Batholith during the
separation of the South American and African plates (Fig. 11).



Fig. 9. Radial and density plots showing single grain ZFT age distributions and calculated age components (using RadialPlotter of Vermeesch, 2009).

183C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
The samples of the São Gabriel Terrane from this study and from
Borba et al. (2002) and two samples of the Pelotas Barholith (PJV-07
and PJV-11) record a cooling episode during the Late Cretaceous. The
South Atlantic margins are characterized by voluminous igneous activi-
ty at ca. 90 Ma (Mizusaki et al., 1998, 2002; Thomaz Filho et al., 2000)
coincident with the final breakup between South America and Africa
(Fig. 11). Other studies in southeastern Brazil (e.g., Cogné et al., 2011,
2012; Franco-Magalhaes et al., 2014; Gallagher et al., 1994, 1995; Karl
et al., 2013) have emphasized that the Late Cretaceous cooling may be
linked to the uplift and denudation of the southeastern Brazilian margin
in Serra do Mar and Serra da Mantiqueira.

The last cooling episode of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield basement
rocks occurred during the Cenozoic. The units of the Taquarembó
Terrane record ca. 1560 m of Eocene (54–48 Ma) denudation, from tem-
peratures of 59 °C to surface conditions. In contrast, the samples of the
Pelotas Batholith record a cooling from temperatures of 75 °C to surface
conditions. This rapid cooling during the Cenozoic is result from
the plate adjustment of breakup with denudation and consequently
deposition of the Pelotas Basin sediments (Fig. 11).

5.2. Tectonic-thermal evolution of the Camaquã Basin

All thermal models derived from AFT data of the sandstones and
conglomerates from the Camaquã Basin (Fig. 8) indicate that after
deposition the samples were reheated to temperatures of N200 °C. The
modeled reheating affecting the rocks is supported by petrography ob-
servations of e.g. De Ros et al. (1994), Borba and Mizusaki (2002) and
Maraschin et al. (2010). These authors identified in the sandstones
of the Santa Bárbara and Guaritas groups quartz overgrowth, which
generally starts at temperatures of ca. 70 °C (e.g. Haszeldine et al.,
1984), dissolution of detrital K-feldspar grains (ca. 50–150 °C;
Wilkinson et al., 2001) and replacement by authigenic clay minerals
(kaolinite) and illite–smectite mixed layer, which occurs at tempera-
tures of ca. 50–150 °C (e.g., Verdel et al., 2012; Wilkinson et al., 2001).
The calcitic matrix present in the sandstones shows evidence of partial
dissolution with generation of intergranular secondary porosity due to
increasing temperature (Worden and Burley, 2003).

The reheating of the rocks in Camaquã Basin is recorded in ZFT
central ages of the samples. ZFT central ages are clearly younger than
depositional age and show signs of partially and/or totally reset after de-
position. The zircon grains show in general three fission-track central
age peaks of 440–300 Ma (Silurian to Carboniferous), 290–235 Ma
(Permo–Triassic) and 202–144 Ma (Jurassic–Cretaceous), as shown in
Figures 3 and 10. A few zircon grains from the Santa Bárbara and
Guaritas groups with ages of ca. 1150–760 Ma (Fig. 9), Meso-
Neoproterozoic ages, define an apparent older population and we also
interpret these grains as having been only partially annealed, and per-
haps starting with an initial provenance age. These provenance ages
are concordant with the U–Pb geochronological data in detrital zircon
obtained by Oliveira et al. (2014) in the same samples of this basin.
The youngest ZFT ages (Fig. 9) of 147–104 Ma (Early Cretaceous) are
not well resolved but possibly represent zircon grains that have been
completely reset and record the time of the initial breakup between
South America and Africa (e.g., Nürnberg and Müller, 1991).

AFT central ages from Camaquã Basin range between 339 and
146 Ma, corresponding to Early Carboniferous until Late Jurassic, with
confined tracks lengths of 10.4 to 11.9 ?m. Borba et al. (2003) dated vol-
canic rocks from the Camaquã Basin with AFT method and obtained
ages between 289 ± 15 and 278 ± 15 Ma. Bicca et al. (2013) obtained
AFT central ages between 362 ± 35 and 133 ± 8 in the same region of
the borehole CQP-02. The new AFT data of this study and those from
Borba et al. (2003) and Bicca et al. (2013) are very similar and have



Fig. 10. Low temperature thermochronology cooling ages from the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield together with events affecting the southernmost Brazil. The cooling age data are shown as age
ranges with modeled periods of enhanced cooling.

184 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
significant Devonian to Permian age components. Thus, the Paleozoic
cooling trend inferred from the thermal history curves (Fig. 8, except
TFRS-11) began in the Ordovician and continued during the Carbonifer-
ous and part of the Permian, until ca. 285 Ma. This continuous and rela-
tively slow cooling trend may reflect the possible uplift of the area in
response to the collision between Precordillera terrane (Famatina and
Cuyania) and Rio de la Plata craton, to the western Gondwana Pacific
margin during the Famatinian orogeny, and continued during the
Gondwanide orogeny (Fig. 11).

The samples from Borba et al. (2003) and only one sample from this
study (T03-249) record a subsequent cooling event during the Late
Cretaceous (90–70 Ma) (Fig. 8) which may be correlated to the final
breakup between South America and Africa (Fig. 11), when South
Atlantic margins are characterized by voluminous igneous activity at
ca. 90 Ma (Mizusaki et al., 1998, 2002; Thomaz Filho et al., 2000).

The Camaquã Basin started its final inversion history in Cenozoic
time (Fig. 8), when samples (except TFRS-11) reached temperatures
above 70 °C. These data indicate a constant exhumation from 58
to 16 Ma, but more active during the past 15 Ma. The amount of denu-
dation in the last 15 Ma range from 1040 to 2640 m, which yields an
average long-term denudation rate of 176–69 m/My.

6. Conclusion

New AFT and ZFT data combined with published thermochronology
data, allow constraining the tectonic-thermal history of the onshore



Fig. 11. Schematic thermotectonic evolution of the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield through time.

185C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
southernmost Brazilian margin and the evolution of the Sul-Rio-
Grandense Shield. The main results of this study are:

(1) ZFT central ages along the Camaquã Basin are clearly younger than
the depositional age and show signs of partially and/or totally reset
after deposition. A few zircon grains, with Meso-Neoproterozoic
ages, define an initial provenance age. The youngest ZFT ages of
147–104 Ma (Early Cretaceous) are not well resolved but possibly
represent zircon grains that have been completely reset and record
the time of the initial breakup between South America and Africa.
(2) The first cooling event in Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield began at
the Ordovician and continued during Carboniferous time.
This episode mainly affected the westernmost units of the
Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield and reflects tectonic activity of
the main tectonic stages of the Famatinian and Gondwanide
orogenies.

(3) The Permo-Triassic cooling event is related the late orogenic pro-
cess of the Gondwanides along the southern border of Western
Gondwana and the consequent reactivation of basement struc-
tures N-S and NE-SW trending in South America.



186 C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
(4) The onset of initial breakup of southwestern Gondwana with
opening of the South Atlantic Ocean is mostly recorded in the
Pelotas Batholith, with reactivation of the Precambrian struc-
tures as a consequence of the extension. ZFT ages from the
Camaquã Basin show that the temperature during this period
was high enough to reset or partially reset the zircon.

(5) A later cooling event related to the final breakup between South
America and Africa in the Sul-Rio-Grandense Shield started in
Late Cretaceous. However, the main rapid cooling episode starting
in Cenozoic probably as resulting from the plate adjustment of
breakup and the neotectonic reactivations associated with the
South Atlantic rift evolution.
Acknowledgments

The authors acknowledge to CPRM and VOTORANTIN metal compa-
ny for borehole samples, and Project FAURGS/FINEP/CTPETRO
21.01.0310.00 for basement samples. The first author thanks CAPES
(the research fund of Brazilian Ministry of Education) for the grant
(Proex/2013-5). We are grateful for reviews of Victor Ramos and an
anonymous reviewer that led to improvements in the manuscript.

References

Almeida, F.F.M., Brito Neves, B.B., Carneiro, C.D.R., 2000. The origin and evolution of the
South American Platform. Earth Sci. Rev. 50, 77–111.

Almeida, D.P.M., Chemale Jr., F., Machado, A., 2012. Late to Post-Orogenic Brasiliano-Pan-
African Volcano-Sedimentary Basins in the Dom Feliciano Belt Southernmost Brazil.
In: Al-Juboury, A.I. (Ed.), Petrology—New Perspectives and Applications. InTech—Open
Acess Publisher, Rijeka, pp. 73–135.

Babinski, M., Chemale Jr., F., Hartmann, L.A., Van Schmus, W.R., Silva, L.C., 1996. Juvenile
accretion at 750–700 Ma in southern Brazil. Geology 24, 439–442.

Babinski, M., Chemale Jr., F., Van Schmus, W.R., Hartmann, L.A., Silva, L.C., 1997. U–Pb and
Sm–Nd geochronology of the Neoproterozoic granitic–gneissic Dom Feliciano Belt,
southernmost Brazil. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 10, 263–274.

Basei, M.A.S., Brito Neves, B.B., Sija Jr., O., Babinski, M., Pimentel, M.M., Tassinari, C.C.G.,
Hollanda, M.H.B., Nutman, A., Cordani, U.G., 2010. Contribution of SHRIMP U–Pb
zircon geochronology to unravelling the evolution of Brazilian Neoproterozoic fold
belts. Precambrian Res. 183, 112–144.

Bernet, M., Garver, J.I., 2005. Fission-track analysis of detrital zircon. In: Reiners, P.W.,
Ehlers, T.A. (Eds.), Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques, Interpretations,
and ApplicationsReviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry vol. 58. Mineralogical
Society of America, Washington, pp. 205–238.

Bicca, M.M., Chemale Jr., F., Jelinek, A.R., Oliveira, C.H.E., Guadagnin, F., Armstrong, R.,
2013. Tectonic evolution and provenance of the Santa Bárbara Group, Camaquã
Mines region, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 48, 173–192.

Borba, A.W., 2006. Evolução geológica da “Bacia do Camaquã” (Neo-proterozóico e
Paleozóico inferior do Escudo Sul-riograndense, RS, Brasil): uma visão com base na
integração de ferramentas de estratigrafia, petrografia e geologia isotópica (Ph. D.
thesis) UFRGS, Porto Alegre (110 pp.).

Borba, A.W., Mizusaki, A.M.P., 2002. Significado Tectônico dos Depósitos de Leques
Aluviais da Formação Santa Bárbara (Eo-Paleozóico) na Região de Caçapava do Sul
(RS, Brasil). Pesqui. Geociênc. 29 (1), 31–41.

Borba, A.W., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M., Mizusaki, A.M.P., 2002. Uplift and denudation of the
Caçapava do Sulgranitoids (southern Brazil) during Late Paleozoic and Mesozoic:
constraints from apatite fission-track data. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 15, 683–692.

Borba, A.W., Lima, E.F., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Sparrenberg, I., Barros,
C.E., 2003. Significance of Late Paleozoic fission-track ages in volcanic rocks from
the Lavras Do Sul Region, Southernmost Brazil. Gondwana Res. 6, 79–88.

Burtner, R.L., Nigrini, A., Donelick, R.A., 1994. Thermochronology of Lower Cretaceous source
rocks in the Idaho–Wyoming thrust belt. Am. Assoc. Pet. Geol. Bull. 78, 1613–1636.

Cappelletti, A., Tsikalas, F., Nestola, Y., Cavozzi, C., Argnani, A., Meda, M., Salvi, F., 2013.
Impact of lithospheric heterogeneities on continental rifting evolution: constraints
from analogue modelling on South Atlantic margins. Tectonophysics 608, 30–50.

Cawood, P.A., Buchan, C., 2007. Linking accretionary orogenesis with supercontinent
assembly. Earth Sci. Rev. 82, 217–256.

Chaboureau, A.C., Guillocheau, F., Robin, C., Rohais, S., Moulin, M., Aslanian, D., 2013.
Paleogeographic evolution of the central segment of the South Atlantic during Early
Cretaceous times: paleotopographic and geodynamic implications. Tectonophysics
604, 191–223.

Chemale Jr., F., 1993. Bacias molássicas brasilianas. Acta Geol. Leopold. 37, 109–118.
Chemale Jr., F., 2000. Evolução geológica do Escudo Sul-rio-grandense. In: Holz, M., De

Ros, L.F. (Eds.), Geologia do Rio Grande do Sul. CIGO/UFRGS, Porto Alegre, pp. 13–52.
Chemale Jr., F., Hartmann, L.A., Silva, L.C., 1995. Stratigraphy and Tectonism of Precambri-

an to Early Paleozoic Units. XVIII Acta Geol. Leopold. 42, 5–117.
Chemale Jr., F., Mallmann, G., Bitencourt, M.F., Kawashita, K., 2012. Time constraints on

magmatism along the Major Gercino Shear Zone, southern Brazil: implications for
West Gondwana reconstruction. Gondwana Res. 22, 184–199.
Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R., 2011. Post-rift reactivation of the onshore margin
of southeast Brazil: evidence from apatite (U–Th)/He and fission-track data. Earth
Planet. Sci. Lett. 309, 118–130.

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R., Riccomini, C., Gautheron, C., 2012. Post-breakup
tectonics in southeast Brazil from thermochronological data and combined inverse-
forward thermal history modeling. J. Geophys. Res. 117, B11413.

De Ros, L.F., Morad, S., Paim, P.S.G., 1994. The role of detrital composition and climate on
the diagenetic evolution of continental molasses: evidence from the Cambro-
Ordovician Guaritas sequence, southern Brazil. Sediment. Geol. 92, 197–228.

Donelick, R.A., O'Sullivan, P.B., Ketcham, R.A., 2005. Apatite Fission-Track Analysis. In:
Reiners, P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Eds.), Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques,
Interpretations, and ApplicationsReviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry vol. 58.
Mineralogical Society of America, Washington, pp. 49–94.

Dumitru, T.A., 1993. A new computer-automated microscope stage system for fission-
track analysis. Nucl. Tracks Radiat. Meas. 21, 575–580.

Fernandes, L.A.D., Tommasi, A., Porcher, C.C., 1992. Deformation patterns in the southern
Brazilian branch of the Dom Feliciano Belt: a reappraisal. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 5 (1),
77–96.

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B., Cuglieri, M.A.A., Hackspacher, P.C., Saad, A.R., 2014. Long-term
landscape evolution and post-rift reactivation in the southeastern Brazilian passive
continental margin: Taubaté basin. Int. J. Earth Sci. (Geol. Rundsch.) 103, 441–453.

Galbraith, R.F., Green, P.F., 1990. Estimating the component ages in a finite mixture. Int.
J. Radiat. Appl. Instrum. Part D 17, 197–206.

Galbraith, R.F., Green, P.F., 1993. Statistical models for mixed fission track ages. Nucl.
Tracks Radiat. Meas. 21, 459–470.

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., Mantovani, M.S.M., 1994. The denudation history of the
onshore continental margin of SE Brazil inferred from apatite fission track data.
J. Geophys. Res. 99 (B9), 18,117–18,145.

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., Mantovani, M.S.M., 1995. Denudation, fission track
analysis and the long-term evolution of passive margin topography: application to
the southeast Brazilian margin. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 8, 65–77.

Gastal, M.C.P., Lafon, J.M., Hartmann, L.A., Koester, E., 2005. Sm–Nd isotopic compositions
as a proxy for magmatic processes during the Neoproterozoic of the southern
Brazilian shield. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 18, 255–276.

Green, P.F., 1981. “Track-in-track” length measurements in annealed apatites. Nucl. Tracks
5, 121–128.

Hackspacher, P.C., Godoy, D.F., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Hadler Neto, J.C., Franco, A.O.B., 2007.
Modelagem térmica e geomorfologia da borda sul do Cráton do São Francisco:
termocronologia por traços de fissão em apatita. Rev. Bras. Geosci. 37 (4 - suplemento),
76–86.

Hartmann, L.A., Leite, J.A.D., Silva, L.C., Remus, M.V.D., McNaughton, N.J., Groves, D.I.,
Fletcher, I.R., Santos, J.O.S., Vasconcellos, M.A.Z., 2000. Advances in SHRIMP geochro-
nology and their impact on understanding the tectonic and metallogenic evolution of
southern Brazil. Aust. J. Earth Sci. 47 (5), 829–844.

Hartmann, L.A., Santos, J.O.S., Leite, J.A.D., Porcher, C.C., McNaughton, N.J., 2003. Metamor-
phic evolution and U–Pb zircon SHRIMP geochronology of the Belizário ultramafic
amphibolite, Encantadas Complex, southernmost Brazil. An. Acad. Bras. Cienc. 75
(3), 393–403.

Hartmann, L.A., Chemale Jr., F., Philipp, R.P., 2007. Evolução geotectônica do Rio Grande do
Sul no Pré-Cambriano. In: Ianuzzi, R., Frantz, J.C. (Eds.), 50 Anos de Geologia. Editora
Comunicação e Identidade, Porto Alegre, pp. 97–123.

Hartmann, L.A., Liu, D., Wang, Y., Massonne, H.J., Santos, J.O.S., 2008a. Protolith age of
Santa Maria Chico granulites dated on zircons from an associated amphibolite-
facies granodiorite in southernmost Brazil. An. Acad. Bras. Cienc. 80 (3),
543–551.

Hartmann, L.A., Santos, J.O.S., McNaughton, N.J., 2008b. Detrital zircon U–Pb age data, and
Precambrian Provenance of the Paleozoic Guaritas Formation, Southern Brazilian
Shield. Int. Geol. Rev. 50, 364–374.

Hartmann, L.A., Philipp, R.P., Santos, J.O.S., McNaughton, N.J., 2011. Time frame of
753–680 Ma juvenile accretion during the São Gabriel orogeny southern Brazilian
Shield. Gondwana Res. 19, 84–99.

Haszeldine, R.S., Samson, I.M., Cornford, C., 1984. Quartz diagenesis and convective fluid
movement: Beatrice oilfield, UK North Sea. Clay Miner. 19, 391–402.

Hiruma, S.T., Riccomini, C., Modenesi-Gauttieri, M.C., Hackspacher, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C.,
Franco-Magalhães, A.O.B., 2010. Denudation history of the Bocaina Plateau, Serra do
Mar, southeastern Brazil: relationships to Gondwana breakup and passive margin
development. Gondwana Res. 18, 674–687.

Hurford, A.J., 1990. International union of geological sciences subcommission on geochro-
nology recommendation for the standardization of fission track dating calibration
and data reporting. Nucl. Tracks Radiat. Meas. 17 (3), 233–236.

Hurter, S.J., Pollack, H.N., 1996. Terrestrial heat flow in the Paraná Basin, southern Brazil.
J. Geophys. Res. 101 (B4), 8659–8671.

Janikian, L., Almeida, R.P., Fragoso-Cesar, A.R.S., Martins, V.T.S., Dantas, E.L., Tohver, E.,
McReath, I., D'Agrella-Filho, M.S., 2012. Ages (U–Pb SHRIMP and LA ICPMS) and strat-
igraphic evolution of the Neoproterozoic volcano-sedimentary successions from the
extensional Camaquã Basin, Southern Brazil. Gondwana Res. 21, 466–482.

Jelinek, A.R., Bastos Neto, A.C., Poupeau, G., 2003. Análise por Traço de Fissão do Distrito
Fluorítico de Santa Catarina: Relações entre hidrotermalismo e Evolução da Margem
Continental. Rev. Bras. Geosci. 33, 289–298.

Karl, M., Glasmacher, U.A., Kollenz, S., Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B., Stockli, D.F., Hackspacher,
P.C., 2013. Evolution of the South Atlantic passive continental margin in southern
Brazil derived from zircon and apatite (U–Th–Sm)/He and fission-track data.
Tectonophysics 604, 224–244.

Kay, S.M., Ramos, V.A., Mpodozis, C., Sruoga, P., 1989. Late Paleozoic to Jurassic silicic
magmatism at the Gondwana margin: analogy to the Middle Proterozoic in North
America? Geology 17, 324–328.

http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0020
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0020
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0020
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0370
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0370
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0370
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0370
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0030
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0030
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0375
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0375
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0375
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0375
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0035
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0035
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0055
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0055
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0060
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0060
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0070
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0075
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0075
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0080
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0080
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0095
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0095
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0095
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0380
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0380
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0380
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0380
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0105
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0105
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0115
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0115
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0115
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0120
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0120
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0125
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0125
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0130
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0130
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0130
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0145
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0145
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0385
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0385
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0385
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0155
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0155
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0155
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0175
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0175
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0175
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0180
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0180
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0190
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0190
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0190
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0210
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0210
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0210
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0215
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0215
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0215


187C.H.E. Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 666 (2016) 173–187
Ketcham, R.A., 2005. Forward and inverse modeling of low-temperature
thermochronometry data. Rev. Mineral. Geochem. 58, 275–314.

Ketcham, R.A., Donelick, R.A., Carlson, W.D., 1999. Variability of apatite fission-track
annealing kinetics: III. Extrapolation to geological time scales. Am. Mineral. 84,
1235–1255.

Ketcham, R.A., Carter, A.C., Donelick, R.A., Barbarand, J., Hurford, A.J., 2007. Improved
modeling of fission-track annealing in apatite. Am. Mineral. 92, 799–810.

Leite, J.A.D., Hartmann, L.A., Fernandes, L.A.D., McNaughton, N.J., Soliani, E., Koester,
E., Santos, J.O.S., Vasconcellos, M.A.Z., 2000. Zircon U–Pb SHRIMP dating of
gneissic basement of the Dom Feliciano Belt, southernmost Brazil. J. S. Am.
Earth Sci. 13, 739–750.

Maraschin, A.J., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Zwingmann, H., Borba, A.W., Sbrissa, G.F., 2010. Illite
authigenesis in sandstones of the Guaritas Allogroup (Early Paleozoic): implications
for the depositional age, stratigraphy and evolution of the Camaquã Basin (Southern
Brazil). J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 29, 400–411.

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Thomaz Filho, A., Cesero, P.D., 1998. Ages of the magmatism and the
opening of the south Atlantic Ocean. Pesquisas 25 (2), 47–57.

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Thomaz-Filho, A., Milani, E.J., Cesero, P., 2002. Mesozoic and Cenozoic
igneous activity and its tectonic control in northeastern Brazil. J. S. Am. Earth Sci.
15 (2), 183–198.

Mpodozis, C., Kay, S.M., 1992. Late Paleozoic to Triassic evolution of the Gondwana
margin: evidence from Chilean Frontal Cordilleran Batholiths (28°S to 31°S). Geol.
Soc. Am. Bull. 104, 999–1014.

Naeser, N.D., Zeitler, P.K., Naeser, C.W., Cerveny, P.F., 1987. Provenance studies by fission
track dating of zircon—etching and counting procedures. Nucl. Tracks Radiat. Meas.
13, 121–126.

Nürnberg, D., Müller, R.D., 1991. The tectonic evolution of the South Atlantic from Late
Jurassic to present. Tectonophysics 191, 21–53.

Oliveira, C.H.E., Chemale Jr., F., Jelinek, A.R., Bicca, M.M., Philipp, R.P., 2014. U–Pb and Lu–
Hf isotopes applied to the evolution of the late to post-orogenic transtensional basins
of the Dom Feliciano belt, Brazil. Precambrian Res. 246, 240–255.

Paim, P.S.G., Chemale Jr., F., Lopes, R.C., 2000. A Bacia do Camaquã. In: Holz, M., DeRos, L.F.
(Eds.), Geologia do Rio Grande do Sul. CIGO-UFRGS, Porto Alegre, pp. 231–274.

Pankhurst, R.J., Rapela, C.W., Fanning, C.M., Márquez, M., 2006. Gondwanide continental
collision and the origin of Patagonia. Earth Sci. Rev. 76, 235–257.

Philipp, R.P., Machado, R., 2005. The Neoproterozoic to Cambrian granitic magmatism of
Pelotas Batholith, Southern Brazil. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 19, 61–478.

Philipp, R.P., Machado, R., Chemale Jr., F., 2003. Reavaliação e novos dados
geocronológicos (Ar/Ar Rb/Sr e Sm–Nd) do Batólito Pelotas no Rio Grande do Sul:
implicações petrogenéticas e idade de reativação das zonas de cisalhamento. Geol.
USP Sér. Cient. 3, 71–84.

Philipp, R.P., Lusa, M., Nardi, L.V.S., 2008. Geochemistry and petrology of dioritic, tonalitic
and trondhjemitic gneisses from Encantadas Complex, Santana da Boa Vista,
southernmost Brazil: a Paleoproterozoic continental-arc magmatism. An. Acad.
Bras. Cienc. 80, 735–748.

Rahn, M.K., Brandon, M.T., Batt, G.E., Garver, J.I., 2004. A zero-damage model for fission-
track annealing in zircon. Am. Mineral. 89, 473–484.

Ramos, V.A., 2008. Patagonia: a Paleozoic continent adrift? J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 26, 235–251.
Ramos, V.A., Alemand, A., 2000. Tectonic evolution of the Andes. In: Cordani, U.G., Milani,

E.J., Thomaz Filho, A., Campos, D.A. (Eds.), Tectonic Evolution of South America. 31st
International Geological Congress, Rio de Janerio, pp. 635–685.
Ramos, V.A., Chemale Jr., F., Naipauer, M., Pazos, P., 2014. A provenance study of the Paleo-
zoic Ventania System (Argentina): Transient complex sources from Western and
Eastern Gondwana. Gondwana Res. 26, 719–740.

Remus, M.V.D., McNaughton, N.J., Hartmann, L.A., Koppe, J.C., Fletcher, I.R., Groves, D.I.,
Pinto, V.M., 1999. Gold in the Neoproterozoic juvenile Bossoroca Volcanic Arc of
southernmost Brazil: isotopic constraints on timing and sources. J. S. Am. Earth Sci.
12, 349–366.

Riccomini, C., Velázquez, V.F., Gomes, C.B., 2005. Tectonic controls of the Mesozoic and
Cenozoic alkaline magmatism in central southeastern Brazilian platform. In: Comin-
Chiaramonti, P., Gomes, C.B. (Eds.), Mesozoic to Cenozoic Alkaline Magmatism in
the Brazilian Platform. Edusp/Fapesp, São Paulo, pp. 31–55.

Saalmann, K., Hartmann, L.A., Remus, M.V.D., Koester, E., Conceição, R.V., 2005. Sm–Nd
isotope geochemistry of metamorphic volcano sedimentary successions in the São
Gabriel Block, southernmost Brazil: evidence for the existence of juvenile
Neoproterozoic oceanic crust to the east of the Rio de la Plata craton. Precambrian
Res. 136, 159–175.

Saalmann, K., Gerdes, A., Lahaye, Y., Hartmann, L.A., Remus, M.V.D., Läufer, A., 2011. Mul-
tiple accretion at the eastern margin of the Rio de la Plata craton: the prolonged
Brasiliano orogeny in southernmost Brazil. Int. J. Earth Sci. 100, 355–378.

Silva, L.C., Hartmann, L.A., McNaughton, N.J., Fletcher, I.R., 1999. SHRIMP U/Pb zircon
timing of Neoproterozoic granitic magmatism and deformation in the Pelotas
Batholith in southernmost Brazil. Int. Geol. Rev. 41, 531–551.

Sommer, C.A., Lima, E.F., Nardi, L.V.S., Figueiredo, A.M.G., Pierosan, R., 2005. Potassic and
low- and high-Ti mildly alkaline volcanism in the Neoproterozoic Ramada Plateau,
southermost Brazil. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 18 (3), 237–254.

Tello Saenz, C.A., Hackspacher, P.C., Hadler, N.J.C., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Paulo, S.R., Ribeiro,
L.F.B., 2003. Recognition of cretaceous, Paleocene and Neogene tectonic reactivation,
through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambrian areas of the Southeast Brazil:
association with the South Atlantic Ocean Opening. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 15, 137–142.

Thomaz Filho, A., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Milani, E.J., Cesero, P., 2000. Rifting and magmatism as-
sociated with the South America and Africa break up. Rev. Bras. Geosci. 30 (1), 17–19.

Verdel, C., van der Pluijm, B., Niemi, N., 2012. Variation of illite/muscovite 40Ar/39Ar age
spectra during progressive low-grade metamorphism: and example from the US
Cordillera. Contrib. Mineral. Petrol. 164 (3), 521–536.

Vermeesch, P., 2009. RadialPlotter: a Java application for fission track, luminescence and
other radial plots. Radiat. Meas. 44, 409–410.

Wildner, W., Lima, E.F., Nardi, L.V.S., Sommer, C.A., 2002. Volcanic cycles and settingin the
Neoproterozoic III to Ordovician Camaquã Basin succession in southern Brazil:
characteristics of post-collisional magmatism. J. Volcanol. Geotherm. Res. 118, 261–283.

Wilkinson, M., Miliken, K.L., Haszeldine, R.S., 2001. Systematic destruction of K-feldspar in
deeply buried rift and passive margin sandstones. J. Geol. Soc. Lond. 158, 675–683.

Worden, R.H., Burley, S.D., 2003. Sandstone diagenesis: the evolution of sand to stone. In:
Burley, S.D., Worden, R. (Eds.), Sandstone Diagenesis: Recent and Ancient (Reprint
Series 4 of the IAS). Wiley-Blackwell, pp. 3–44.

Zerfass, H., Chemale Jr., F., Lavina, E., 2005. Tectonic control of the Triassic Santa Maria
supersequence of the Paraná Basin, Southernmost Brazil, and its correlation to the
Waterberg Basin, Namibia. Gondwana Res. 8 (2), 163–176.

http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0220
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0220
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0230
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0230
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0230
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0225
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0225
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0235
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0235
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0235
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0240
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0240
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0240
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0240
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0245
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0245
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0250
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0250
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0250
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0255
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0255
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0255
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0260
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0260
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0260
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0265
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0265
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0270
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0270
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0270
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0275
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0275
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0280
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0280
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0290
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0290
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0295
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0295
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0295
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0295
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0285
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0285
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0285
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0285
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0300
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0300
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0305
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0390
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0390
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0390
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf1000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf1000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf1000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0310
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0310
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0310
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0315
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0315
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0315
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0315
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0325
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0325
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0325
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0325
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0325
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0320
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0320
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0320
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0330
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0330
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0330
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0335
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0335
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0335
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0340
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0340
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0340
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0345
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0345
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0350
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0350
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0350
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0355
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0355
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0395
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0395
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0395
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0360
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0360
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0400
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0400
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0400
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0365
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0365
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(15)00604-6/rf0365


Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34

Contents lists available at ScienceDirect

Tectonophysics

journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/tecto
Thermotectonic history of the southeastern Brazilian margin: Evidence
from apatite fission track data of the offshore Santos Basin and
continental basement
Christie Helouise Engelmann de Oliveira a,?, Andréa Ritter Jelinek a, Farid Chemale Jr. b, José Antônio Cupertino c
a Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil
b Universidade do Vale do Rio dos Sinos, Brazil
c PETROBRAS, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
? Corresponding author.
E-mail address: christie.oliveira10@gmail.com (C.H. En

http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012
0040-1951/© 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
a b s t r a c t
a r t i c l e i n f o
Article history:
Received 29 March 2016
Received in revised form 11 July 2016
Accepted 17 July 2016
Available online 20 July 2016
The Santos Basin is the largest offshore sedimentary basin in the southeastern Brazilian margin and originated by
breakup of West Gondwana in the Early Cretaceous. We carried out a new thermochronological study by apatite
fission track analysis from borehole samples of the Santos Basin and its continental basement to constrain the
tectonic history of the southeastern Brazilian margin. Apatite fission track central ages of the basement and bore-
hole samples vary from 21.0 ± 1.8 to 157.0 ± 35.0 Ma and from 6.5 ± 1.1 to 208.0 ± 11.0 Ma, respectively. From
thermal modeling, the basement samples reached the maximum paleotemperatures during the final breakup of
South America and Africa. The onshore basement and offshore basin record an early thermotectonic event during
the Late Cretaceous linked to the uplift and denudation of the Serra do Mar and Serra da Mantiqueira. Maturation
of the organic matter in the offshore basin is related with the progressive increase of the geothermal gradient due
to burial. The thermal modeling indicates that the oil generation window started at 55–25 Ma. The basement
samples experienced the final cooling during the Cenozoic, with an estimated amount of denudation linked to
the sedimentary influx in the offshore basin. A rapid cooling during the Neogene becomes evident and it is linked
to the reactivation along Precambrian shear zones and change of the Paraíba do Sul drainage system.

© 2016 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.
Keywords:
Southeastern Brazilian margin
Apatite fission track
Offshore Santos Basin
Basement
1. Introduction

The southeastern Brazilian margin constitutes part of the South
Atlantic rift system originated by breakup of West Gondwana in the
Early Cretaceous. The opening of the South Atlantic developed by
diachronous rifting, which initiated in the south in the Late Triassic-
Early Jurassic and propagated to the north along reactivated older
tectonic lineaments (e.g., Meisling et al., 2001; Nürnberg and Müller,
1991; Torsvik et al., 2009). Initially, the divergent plate motion was
E-W directed, but progressively changed to a NE-SW direction, with
transtension along the eastern Brazilian margin (Macdonald et al.,
2003; Rabinowitz and LaBrecque, 1979).

Breakup of the paleocontinent at 130 Ma was affected by
widespread rifting and the impact of the volcanic activity of the
Paraná-Etendeka province (e.g., Macdonald et al., 2003; Zalán et al.,
1991). The plume-related volcanic activity caused the lifting of the
crust, including the exposure of the Precambrian basement followed
by erosion and deposition. Today, the southeastern Brazilian margin
has a characteristic passive continental margin morphology with
gelmann de Oliveira).
offshore sedimentary basins (Santos, Campos and Espírito Santo)
separated from continental elevated region (Serra do Mar) by a relatively
narrow coastal plain (Gallagher et al., 1994).

Thermochronological methods such as apatite fission track (AFT)
have been used extensively to understand the development of rift mar-
gins, quantifying rates of surface and rock uplift, and providing timing
and rates of movement along faults and shear zones (e.g., Gallagher
and Brown, 1999; Jelinek et al., 2014; Raab et al., 2005). The earlier
AFT studies in southeastern Brazil have been carried out on results of
basement rocks and onshore Tertiary basins, and the data were
interpreted in terms of denudation and movement along faults (Cogné
et al., 2012; Franco-Magalhaes et al., 2010, 2014; Gallagher et al.,
1994; Hackspacher et al., 2004; Hiruma et al., 2010; Karl et al., 2013;
Tello Saenz et al., 2003).

This study provides new evidence that constrains the
thermotectonic history of the Santos Basin with AFT data from onshore
basement outcrops and offshore borehole samples (Fig. 1) from Drift
stage (Fig. 2). The primary aim of this study is to establish the timing
and magnitude of major cooling events and to quantify the associated
denudation of the margin topography and the burial history of the
offshore basin. The data are interpreted in the context of the regional
tectonic setting and enhance the extensive thermochronometry data

http://crossmark.crossref.org/dialog/?doi=10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012&amp;amp;domain=pdf
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012
mailto:christie.oliveira10@gmail.com
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012
http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/journal/00401951
www.elsevier.com/locate/tecto


Fig. 1. Simplified geotectonic map of the southeastern Brazilian margin with location of samples. (a) General location. (b) Studied area. (1) Jundiuvira-Boquira-Rio Preto shear zone;
(2) Além Paraíba shear zone; (3) Cubatão shear zone.

22 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
set across this region providing a thermotectonic history of the south-
eastern Brazilian margin. We show that AFT cooling ages are related to
the continental breakup that led to the separation of South America
and Africa and the quantitative thermal histories derived from the
data provide the denudation rates, which have a significant effect on
the evolution of the offshore basin and the maturation of the organic
matter starting at 55–25 Ma.

2. Geological setting

The geology onshore of the Santos Basin is characterized by
Precambrian-Cambrian basement provinces, predominantly granites
and gneisses, formed during the Brasiliano/Pan-African orogeny
(e.g., Brito Neves et al., 2014; Schmitt et al., 2008). The basement
rocks are affected by Neoproterozoic NE-trending strike-slip shear
zones and subordinated NW-oriented structures (Ebert et al., 1996;
Heilbron et al., 2000). The assemblages are partially overlain by a
sedimentary sequence of Ordovician to Jurassic siliciclastic and carbon-
ate rocks of the Paraná Basin (Fig. 1). In the Early Cretaceous, synchro-
nous with opening of the South Atlantic Ocean, basalt flows of the
Paraná-Etendeka province covered the Paraná Basin (Zalán et al.,
1991). Following continental breakup, a second magmatic episode
occurred (80–50 Ma) producing alkaline intrusive bodies along the
Cabo Frio High (Almeida et al., 1996; Moreira et al., 2006).

Extensional and compressional stress events operated during the
post-breakup development of several onshore Tertiary basins (São
Paulo, Taubaté, Resende and Volta Redonda) along the Serra da
Mantiqueira and Serra do Mar ranges (Cobbold et al., 2001). The depo-
sition of these basins occurred at ca. 48 Ma (Riccomini et al., 2004), but
according Cogné et al. (2012) could be as old as Paleocene. Offshore,
seismic and stratigraphic studies (e.g., Contreras et al., 2010; Modica
and Brush, 2004) show that the southeastern Brazilian margin is typi-
cally of a passive margin, but underwent tectonic reactivation during
the Late Cretaceous, Paleogene and Neogene (e.g., Cobbold et al., 2001).

In this context, the Santos Basin is the largest offshore sedimentary
basin in the southeastern Brazilian margin developed on a tectonic
framework of NNE–SSW direction approximately parallel to the coast
line (Fig. 1). The basin is limited by the Florianópolis High in the south
and the Cabo Frio High in the north (Moreira et al., 2007).

The development of the Santos Basin included the five major devel-
opment stages (Fig. 2) of pre-rift (150–138 Ma), rift (ca. 138–123 Ma),
post-rift (ca. 123–113 Ma), drift I (113–66 Ma) and drift II (66–0 Ma)
(modified after Moreira et al., 2007). The rift structures are mainly
NE–SW trending, represented by normal faults bounding horsts and
grabens, locally intruded by syn- and post-rift magmatic rocks. The
post-rift phase is characterized by diminishing activity of large faults
and a regional unconformity that bevels the topography at 117 Ma.
This unconformity separates continental lacustrine sediments from
sediments of transitional to marine environments (Mohriak et al.,
2008).

The initiation of the drift phase is marked by the cessation of rifting
and the transition from continental to oceanic conditions. The drift I se-
quences are characterized by salt deposition (Ariri Formation), which
was restricted to a short time span at 113 Ma. The salt layer extends



Fig. 2. Tectonostratigraphic chart for the Santos Basin (modified from Moreira et al., 2007). Red rectangle marks the units studied.

23C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
across the West African and Brazilian continental margins (Mohriak
et al., 2008). Post-Albian time is characterized by widespread salt
tectonics, which apparently controlled most of the shallower structures
present on the eastern Brazilian margin. In the drift II stage (Late
Cretaceous–Tertiary), continental divergence and regional thermal sub-
sidence caused open marine conditions with deposition of the Itajaí-Açu
Formation. The spatial distribution of offshore clastic sedimentation in-
dicates a highly variable flux over time, potentially due to variations in
the rate of onshore erosion and changing positions of major rivers
(e.g., Cogné et al., 2012; Contreras et al., 2010; Mohriak et al., 2008).
These have important consequences for burial, maturation and preser-
vation of hydrocarbons in the basin.



24 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
3. Materials and methods

Thirty outcrop basement samples and 30 detrital samples from eight
offshore boreholes were collected along the southeastern Brazilian
margin in the Santos Basin (Figs. 1 and 3). The locations of samples
are marked in Fig. 1, and their lithological characteristics are listed in
Tables 1 and 2. The present-day well temperatures were provided by
Petrobras (Table 2). The outcrop samples were collected along NE–SW
transects crosscutting the Mantiqueira province and the shear zones
(see Fig. 1), and one sedimentary rock (TR9SP2) from the Paraná
Basin. Two deep-water offshore (F and N) and other shallow-water
boreholes were studied. AFT borehole samples consist of drill cuttings.

Apatite grains were separated using standard crushing, sieving,
magnetic and heavy liquid separation methods. Apatite aliquots were
mounted in epoxy, polished and etched for 20 s in a 5.5 M HNO3 solution
at 21 °C to reveal the spontaneous fission tracks. Apatite samples were
dated by the external detector method (Hurford, 1990) using low-U
mica sheets as external detectors. The samples were irradiated at the
well-thermalized IPEN-CNEN Reactor, São Paulo, Brazil, with Durango
age standard and CN1, CN2, CN5 and NBS962 dosimeter glasses. After
irradiation, mica detectors were etched in 48% HF for 18 min at 20 °C
to reveal the induced fission tracks.

AFT analyses were performed at the Universidade Federal do Rio
Grande do Sul, Brazil, utilizing a Leica DM6000 M Microscope (1000×,
dry). We dated at least 20 grains per sample. We retained some samples
with the results without meeting these criteria (Tables 1 and 2) because
their ages broadly agree with the nearby samples that have good-
quality measurements. AFT central ages were calculated according to
the ?-calibration method (Hurford, 1990). Throughout this study, fis-
sion track age errors are quoted at the 1? confidence level and were de-
rived by the conventional method (Green, 1981). The ?2-squared test
(?2) was used to quantify age homogeneity; when ?2 N 5%, fission
track samples contain a single age population (Galbraith and Laslett,
1993). Samples from sedimentary rocks which failed the ?2 and have
an age-dispersion over 15% may reflect a mixture of different age com-
ponents. The software “RadialPlotter” (Vermeesch, 2009) was used in
order to statistically separate different age populations. In a first step,
Fig. 3. Interpolated image of apatite fission track ages across the southeastern Braz
we applied the auto mixture model. Samples which revealed only one
age component were further tested applying a two component mixture
model.

AFT lengths were measured on horizontal confined fission tracks.
Where possible, 100 natural confined tracks were measured to con-
struct an AFT length-frequency distribution, a number that was not al-
ways attained. Etch pit diameter (Dpar; Donelick et al., 2005) values
and the chemical compositions (in particular the Cl concentration)
were used as a kinetic parameter. Apatite Cl (wt%) content was deter-
mined using a CAMECA SX50 electron microprobe on an acceleration
voltage of 15 keV with 25 nA beam current and 20 ?m beam diameter
at Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.

Apatite thermal history modeling was carried out using the QTQt
software (Gallagher, 2012) with the multi-kinetic annealing model
of Ketcham et al. (2007) and Cl content and Dpar values as a kinetic
parameter for the borehole and basement samples, respectively. The
priors on the general time-temperature were set to 75 ± 75 Ma and
70 ± 70 °C for the borehole samples. In order to derive an unbiased
inference of the thermal history from the thermochronological
data, we employed no pre-defined constraints on the inverse models
except for the present surface temperature (20 ± 5 °C for the base-
ment samples, and present-day well temperature for the borehole
samples). Moreover, each borehole sample is given a specific
constraint reflecting its stratigraphic age. For thermal histories
represented in this study, each inversion was run at 100,000 Burn-
in and 100,000 Post-burn-in iterations, respectively, which are
sufficient to provide stable solutions (see discussion in Gallagher,
2012). Both samples from a given borehole are modeled together fol-
lowing the vertical profile sampling strategy adopted in Gallagher
et al. (2005) and implemented in QTQt.

The quantification of denudation and burial histories were based on
geothermal gradients measured from the data of the continental margin
of Brazil (Hamza et al., 2005). We assume a constant and linear geother-
mal gradient over geological times and suppose that the geothermal
gradient is linear (25 °C/km) for which we reconstructed the denuda-
tion and burial histories of the Santos Basin. The synoptic maps of AFT
ages and denudation rates for the different time intervals inferred
ilian margin. Sample locations for this study and previous work are indicated.



Table 1
Summary of basement apatite fission track data.

Sample Lithology Latitude Longitude Elevation N ?s Ns ?i Ni ?d Nd Central ±1? ?2 U Dpar n MTL S. D.

(m) (×105) (×105) (×105) Age (Ma) (Ma) (%) (ppm) (?m) (?m) (?m)

TR7RJ4 Gneiss ?22.45 ?43.21 931 5 9.81 82 3.23 27 9.70 4400 157.0 35.0 81 13.3 – – – –
TR7RJ5 Gneiss ?22.55 ?43.23 620 26 10.20 700 5.32 364 7.90 3177 101.8 6.6 94 24.6 2.68 29 12.23 1.60
TR7RJ6 Gneiss ?22.59 ?43.27 458 15 20.30 416 14.80 302 7.90 3177 73.1 5.5 94 68.2 2.75 18 13.28 1.59
TR7RJ7 Diorite ?22.62 ?43.29 175 26 5.43 402 3.97 294 8.30 4000 76.2 5.8 80 17.5 – – – –
TR8RJ8 Gneiss ?22.36 ?44.39 541 26 4.48 601 7.68 1031 9.70 4400 30.5 1.6 70 31.5 2.06 29 12.81 1.54
TR8RJ10 Gneiss ?22.49 ?44.25 510 21 11.50 458 8.67 345 7.90 3177 70.4 5.0 77 40.0 2.74 37 12.56 1.71
TR11RJ1 Gneiss ?21.65 ?42.36 120 24 3.82 205 3.11 167 5.90 2130 48.7 5.1 100 19.2 2.58 27 12.25 1.82
TR11RJ2 Gneiss ?21.91 ?42.73 102 20 7.99 592 7.15 530 7.98 2097 48.0 2.9 94 35.7 – 50 12.93 1.39
TR11RJ3 Gneiss ?22.08 ?43.05 202 20 16.60 522 11.70 369 5.90 2130 56.1 3.8 66 72.6 – 61 12.19 1.91
TR11RJ4 Gneiss ?22.16 ?43.31 252 23 13.40 531 9.46 374 6.04 2330 57.7 3.9 99 57.2 – 50 12.50 1.72
TR11RJ5 Granite ?22.33 ?43.54 438 17 12.20 410 9.64 323 7.98 2097 54.5 4.1 93 48.1 – 25 12.51 1.53
TR11RJ6 Gneiss ?22.43 ?43.74 330 22 10.50 342 7.87 257 6.04 2330 54.1 4.5 98 47.6 – 14 12.69 0.99
TR11RJ7 Gneiss ?22.48 ?43.89 312 23 8.42 433 5.35 275 7.98 2097 67.5 5.2 98 8.5 – 31 10.19 2.04
TR11RJ8 Gneiss ?22.49 ?44.06 330 23 10.90 440 5.45 219 9.70 4400 100.8 8.0 95 22.4 – – – –
TR11RJ9 Gneiss ?22.56 ?44.17 367 25 18.20 863 8.80 418 8.00 2511 88.6 5.3 96 43.8 2.81 60 10.64 2.27
TR11RJ10 Gneiss ?22.52 ?44.71 410 8 4.82 308 3.08 197 8.00 2511 66.2 6.5 34 15.3 – 8 9.18 0.90
TR9SP2 Sandstone ?23.92 ?48.29 611 24 8.85 288 6.02 196 9.70 4400 76.5 7.1 100 24.7 2.63 25 11.04 2.12
TR9SP4 Diorite ?24.08 ?48.36 720 23 6.05 447 3.69 273 10.20 4443 89.6 6.9 100 14.4 3.19 21 12.86 1.67
TR9SP7 Granite ?24.71 ?47.55 5 21 5.59 523 5.37 502 8.00 2511 44.9 2.8 65 26.7 – 31 12.26 2.45
TR10SP1 Gneiss ?23.97 ?48.88 650 7 11.60 72 5.65 35 10.20 4443 112.0 23.0 68 22.1 3.17 21 11.28 1.85
TR10SP14 Schist ?24.76 ?47.89 99 11 8.63 179 4.29 89 9.70 4400 105.0 14.0 76 17.6 – 8 11.60 2.31
TR10SP16 Granite ?25.12 ?48.08 32 23 69.40 307 41.80 185 5.90 2130 65.8 6.1 89 258.7 2.51 30 11.78 1.81
TR10SP17 Gabbro ?25.21 ?48.05 21 24 66.50 438 49.80 328 8.00 2511 57.4 4.2 100 247.8 – 27 12.24 2.31
TR10SP18 Granite ?25.18 ?48.07 30 20 37.00 200 70.10 379 5.90 2130 21.0 1.8 66 433.7 – 30 11.77 1.74
TR11SP11 Gneiss ?22.86 ?44.93 545 22 20.60 744 5.83 211 7.98 2097 150.0 12.0 100 29.1 2.74 34 11.68 1.66
TR11SP12 Gneiss ?23.35 ?46.02 581 20 8.16 365 5.66 253 7.98 2097 61.9 5.1 100 28.2 – 26 12.50 1.22
TR11SP13 Gneiss ?23.41 ?46.19 622 20 10.60 441 7.04 294 7.98 2097 64.3 4.8 92 35.1 – 31 12.81 2.05
TR11SP14 Granite ?23.47 ?46.43 700 21 4.35 829 2.40 457 5.90 2130 71.4 4.5 38 14.8 2.55 37 12.29 2.46
TR11SP15 Gneiss ?24.38 ?47.49 210 20 8.60 565 5.41 355 6.04 2330 64.6 4.4 86 32.7 3.00 35 13.29 1.72
TR11SP19 Gneiss ?24.29 ?47.44 60 21 41.20 231 23.70 133 7.98 2097 74.4 8.1 100 118.4 2.66 23 12.48 2.06

N: number of grains analysed to determine track densities; ?s: measured spontaneous track density; Ns: number of spontaneous tracks counted; ?i: measured induced track density; Ni:
number of induced tracks counted; ?d: track density measured in glass dosimeter; Nd: number of tracks counted in determining ?d; 1?: standard deviation; ?2: Chi-square probability; n:
number of confined tracks lengths measured; MTL: mean track length; Dpar: mean etch pit diameter of all measured etch pits; S. D.: standard deviation of track length distribution of
individual track measurements; (–): not analysed. Note: AFT ages were calculated by S.Guedes using ?-CN1 = 108.03 and ?-CN2 = 135.08.

25C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
from the modeling were created by Inverse Distance Weighting (with
N = 10) interpolating the data using ArcGIS™ software.

4. Results

AFT data are applied in basement and sedimentary rocks from the
Santos Basin to evaluate the tectonic evolution of the southeastern
Brazilian margin. AFT ages and confined track length measurements
from the basement and borehole samples are presented in Tables 1
and 2, respectively. AFT radial plots of the borehole samples are present-
ed in Supplementary Material. Sample locations and interpolate AFT
ages obtained together with existing AFT ages from the literature are
presented in Fig. 3. The cooling histories for basement samples are
presented in Fig. 4 and the associated predictions in Supplementary
Material. The cooling histories with associated predictions for borehole
samples are presented in Figs. 6-13.

4.1. Basement rocks

AFT central ages measured from the basement rocks of the Santos
Basin range from 157 ± 35.0 (sample TR7RJ4) to 21 ± 1.8 Ma (sample
TR10SP18). Sample TR9SP2 located in the Paraná Basin has a central
age of 76.5 ± 7.1 Ma. All AFT ages passed in the ?2 indicating one age
population and show no clear correlation with elevation. Few confined
tracks were observed and measured in the samples; we decided to retain
them nonetheless, because they agree with the nearby samples that do
have good-quality measurements. Mean track lengths vary between
9.18 ± 0.90 ?m (TR11RJ10; n = 8) and 13.29 ± 1.72 ?m (TR11SP15;
n = 35) with track length distributions predominantly unimodal.
There is no clear relationship between the AFT age and mean track
lengths suggesting that these samples have experienced a complicated
thermal history. The Dpar values (Table 1) indicate fairly similar chemi-
cal compositions and relatively chlorine-rich apatite grains (Burtner
et al., 1994) with a high resistance to annealing (Donelick et al., 2005).

Thermal history modeling of the samples from the Jundiuvira-
Boquira-Rio Preto shear zone show reheating through the apatite partial
annealing zone (60 °C) at 75 Ma to a maximum paleotemperature of
92 °C at 35 Ma. Thereafter, the samples were cooled to present surface
conditions (Fig. 4a).

Samples from the Além Paraíba shear zone (Fig. 4b) and northern
coast (Fig. 4c) record a reheating through the apatite partial annealing
zone (60 °C) at 175 Ma, where they appear to have resided until ca.
85 Ma with a maximum paleotemperature of 104 °C. Thereafter, the
samples were cooled to present surface conditions with an accelerated
final cooling in the last 4 Ma for Além Paraíba samples.

Samples from Cubatão shear zone (Fig. 4d) and TR11SP14 (Fig. 4e)
register a similar cooling pattern, with a relatively slow cooling from
paleotemperatures between 106 and 98 °C at 78 Ma. For the southern
coast samples (Fig. 4f), the modeling results suggest an initial cooling
at 85 Ma and an accelerated cooling phase at 13 Ma, continuing to the
present-day.

Thermal history modeling of the TR9SP2 sample (Fig. 4g), from the
Paraná Basin, indicates heating after deposition until 107 °C at
162 Ma. Thereafter, the sample was cooled to present surface conditions
with an accelerated final cooling in the last 20 Ma.

4.2. Borehole samples

4.2.1. Borehole A
Samples from borehole A yielded AFT ages that increase system-

atically with depth from 59.5 ± 5.1 Ma at a depth of 1026 m to
97.6 ± 8.6 Ma at a depth of 2615 m (Fig. 5), with no variation in



Table 2
Summary of borehole samples apatite fission track data.

Sample Depth Stratigraphy T N ?s Ns ?i Ni ?d Nd Central ±1? ?2 U Cl n MTL S. D. Group I Group II Group III

(m) Age (Ma) (°C) (×105) (×105) (×105) Age (Ma) (Ma) (%) (ppm) (wt%) (?m) (?m) Age (Ma) (%) Age (Ma) (%) Age (Ma) (%)

Borehole A
TI-A2 1026 65–39 36 30 8.40 630 5.57 418 2.36 613 59.5 5.1 2 88.3 0.11 82 8.88 2.47 45 (55) 85 (45) –
TI-A3 1273 83–65 42 30 11.50 861 6.96 522 2.36 613 67.1 3.8 70 110.3 0.10 100 9.64 2.14 – – –
TI-A4 1329 86–83 43 30 10.30 771 5.73 430 2.36 613 73.4 5.1 27 90.9 0.10 100 8.83 1.75 – – –
TI-A5 2615 112–97 70 28 12.60 883 5.17 362 2.36 613 97.6 8.6 1 82.0 – 58 9.24 1.60 40 (3) 68 (30) 123 (67)

Borehole B
TI-B1 1410 65–39 36 22 10.80 595 7.15 393 2.36 613 61.5 5.1 11 113.2 0.17 80 9.35 2.43 – – –
TI-B4 2947 83–65 80 30 11.70 876 5.24 393 2.36 613 88.8 6.6 7 83.0 0.13 79 7.84 2.10 – – –
TI-B5 3510 83–65 98 30 7.75 581 4.01 301 2.36 613 63.4 9.3 0 63.6 0.80 100 8.29 1.76 17 (19) 71 (41) 126 (40)
TI-B6 3590 83–65 99 30 12.10 326 7.56 204 10.50 7259 125.0 14.0 10 28.6 – – – – – – –

Borehole F
TI-F2 4544 83–65 83 30 3.85 289 6.93 520 10.50 7259 44.2 4.4 2 26.3 0.11 14 9.29 0.70 28 (40) 58 (60) –

Borehole J
TII-J1 1660 65–39 41 28 7.83 587 3.68 276 2.36 613 86.1 6.3 58 58.3 0.11 100 9.06 2.28 – – –
TII-J2 1705 65–39 42 30 6.55 491 5.09 382 2.36 613 52.5 3.8 61 80.7 0.19 100 8.94 2.14 – – –
TII-J3 1944 65–39 49 30 5.87 440 3.96 297 2.36 613 60.2 6.1 33 62.8 0.10 100 9.83 2.10 – – –
TII-J6 2942 83–65 80 30 8.72 654 4.55 341 2.29 5285 75.5 5.0 92 74.2 0.04 48 11.02 1.39 – – –
TII-J7 3350 83–65 93 30 6.49 487 4.31 323 2.29 5285 53.9 5.2 4 70.2 0.10 100 10.46 1.39 37 (48) 75 (52) –
TII-J8 3405 83–65 95 30 7.83 587 5.63 422 2.29 5285 45.1 5.0 0 91.8 0.34 61 8.38 1.61 14 (15) 48 (73) 111 (12)

Borehole L
TII-L1 3225 83–65 89 30 14.30 1069 9.93 745 10.50 7259 110.2 8.1 0 37.7 0.08 81 9.70 1.62 39 (6) 105 (70) 163 (24)
TII-L4 3403 83–65 95 30 4.95 513 6.47 670 10.50 7259 60.4 6.5 0 24.5 0.06 100 9.45 1.23 12 (4) 46 (56) 103 (40)
TII-L5 3485 83–65 98 30 6.67 500 6.75 506 10.50 7259 67.4 8.4 0 25.6 0.07 84 8.71 1.65 19 (18) 68 (56) 139 (26)
TII-L6 4205 86–83 123 30 0.84 63 10.30 769 10.50 7259 6.5 1.1 6 38.9 – – – – – – –

Borehole N
TII-N1 2582 65–39 42 30 6.59 494 5.28 396 10.50 7259 97.2 7.2 63 20.0 – 15 12.47 1.20 – – –
TII-N3 2836 83–65 50 30 17.50 1311 7.28 546 10.50 7259 186.7 9.5 99 27.6 – 100 11.60 1.61 – – –
TII-N4 2886 83–65 50 30 15.70 1178 5.08 381 2.29 5285 121.3 7.2 76 82.9 0.07 31 11.84 1.63 – – –
TII-N5 2921 83–65 52 30 16.50 1238 6.17 463 10.50 7259 208.0 11.0 70 23.4 0.07 96 12.92 1.48

Borehole AH
AH1 2163 65–39 67 15 5.96 112 8.46 159 6.01 7715 74.0 12.0 7 17.9 – 26 10.31 1.75 – – –
AH2 2459 80–65 76 30 8.98 345 15.00 577 6.01 7715 57.7 3.9 90 31.7 – 52 10.65 1.94 – – –
AH3 3044 80–65 93 30 8.92 446 11.70 586 6.01 7715 73.3 5.1 30 24.8 – 53 9.30 2.19 – – –
AH4 4020 80–65 121 30 4.60 103 11.70 263 6.01 7715 39.2 5.3 15 24.8 – – – – – – –
AH5 4084 86–83 123 16 4.07 54 18.40 245 6.01 7715 27.3 6.1 0 39.0 – – – – 9 (42) 47 (58) –
AH6 4496 86–83 135 25 2.74 71 9.62 249 6.01 7715 34.1 5.9 1 20.3 – – – – 4 (7) 32 (70) 58 (23)

Borehole AI
AI2 2597 65–39 80 26 8.57 224 8.83 231 6.01 7715 93.3 8.8 81 18.7 – 19 8.74 2.12 – – –
AI5A 4763 86–83 142 14 5.70 34 5.03 30 6.01 7715 109.0 27.0 95 10.6 – 51 8.14 1.90 – – –

N: number of grains analysed to determine track densities; ?s: measured spontaneous track density; Ns: number of spontaneous tracks counted; ?i: measured induced track density; Ni: number of induced tracks counted; ?d: track density measured
in glass dosimeter; Nd: number of tracks counted in determining ?d; 1?: standard deviation; ?2: Chi-square probability; n: number of confined tracks lengths measured; MTL: mean track length; Dpar: mean etch pit diameter of all measured etch pits;
S. D.: standard deviation of track length distribution of individual track measurements; (–): not analysed. Note: AFT ages were calculated by L. Oliveira using ?-CN1 = 150.31 and ?-NBS962 = 345.5, and ?-CN5 = 322.7 by A. Borba.

2
6

C
.H
.En

gelm
an

n
de

O
liveira

et
al./

Tecton
oph

ysics
68

5
(20

16)
2
1–

34



Fig. 4. Map shows principal tectonic features and black dots indicate basement samples with temperature–time (T–t) models from different regions. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and
lowermost (red) samples are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The grey box highlight the stratigraphic age of the Paraná Basin. (a) Jundiuvira-Boquira-Rio
Preto shear zone, (b) Além Paraíba shear zone, (c) Northern coast, (d) Cubatão shear zone, (e) Sample TR11SP14, (f) Southern coast, and (g) Paraná Basin.

27C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
mean track lengths over the same depth range. The mean track
lengths are very short and similar in all samples, with a symmetrical
distribution and standard deviations. Two samples (TI-A2 and TI-A5)
failed the ?2 and have an age-dispersion over 15%, indicating that
more than one age component is present in the obtained single grain
age population. The most AFT central ages (except T1-A4) have the
same stratigraphic age of the samples. The Cl contents of samples are
between 0.10 and 0.11 wt%.

The model from the borehole A indicates a heating to depths equiv-
alent to a maximum paleotemperature of 85 °C at ca. 5 Ma (Fig. 6).
Thereafter, the samples were cooled to the present-day temperature
conditions.



Fig. 5. Relationship between AFT age and depth of the borehole samples.

28 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
4.2.2. Borehole B
Borehole B yielded AFT ages which increase systematically with

depth (Fig. 5). The mean track lengths are short and very similar in all
samples, with a symmetrical distribution and standard deviations. The
TI-B5 sample is characterized by ?2 values equal zero. AFT central ages
of the TI-B1 and TI-B5 samples have the same stratigraphic age, while
AFT central ages of the TI-B4 and TI-B6 samples are older than the
stratigraphic age. The Cl contents of samples range between 0.13 and
0.80 wt%.

Samples from borehole B record a reheating to depths equivalent to
a maximum paleotemperature of 90 °C at 10 Ma (Fig. 7). Following
heating the TI-B1 and TI-B4 samples record a period of rapid cooling
to the present-day temperature conditions.
4.2.3. Borehole F
AFT central age from the TI-F2 sample is 44.2 ± 4.4 Ma with short

mean track length of 9.29 ?m and standard deviation of 0.70 at a
Fig. 6. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole A. (a) The expected thermal histo
are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for
grey boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of t
symbols) AFT ages and MTL versus depth.
depth of 4544 m. The AFT data failed the ?2 and the age component
analysis indicates two age groups at 58 ± 9 Ma and 28 ± 6 Ma. AFT cen-
tral age and age groups are younger than the deposition age suggesting
post-depositional annealing. The Cl content of the sample ranges
between 0.13 and 0.80 wt%. Immediately following deposition, the
TI-F2 sample shows a heating phase to the present-day temperature
conditions (Fig. 8).

4.2.4. Borehole J
Samples from borehole J yielded AFT ages which decrease systemat-

ically with depth from 86.1 ± 6.3 Ma at a depth of 1660 m to 45.1 ±
5.0 Ma at a depth of 3405 m (Fig. 5). The mean track lengths are short
and have a symmetrical distribution. The TII-J7 and TII-J8 samples failed
the ?2 and have an age-dispersion over 15%. Only AFT central age of the
TII-J1 is older than the stratigraphic age, AFT central ages of the other
samples are younger or equal to the stratigraphic age. The Cl contents
of the samples range between 0.04 and 0.34 wt%.

The model for borehole J registers a heating to the apatite partial an-
nealing zone (60 °C) at ca. 25 Ma, which continued to a maximum
paleotemperature of 87 °C at ca. 11 Ma (Fig. 9). An accelerated cooling
started after this period until ca. 1 Ma at 60 °C. Thereafter, TI-J1 and
TI-J2 samples were cooled while the other samples were reheated to
the present-day temperature conditions.

4.2.5. Borehole L
Samples from borehole L yielded AFT ages which decrease systemat-

ically with depth from 110.2 ± 8.1 Ma at a depth of 3225 m to 6.5 ±
1.1 Ma at a depth of 4205 m (Fig. 5), with short mean track lengths
also decreasing systematically from 9.70 ?m to 8.71 ?m, over the same
depth range. Only TII-L6 sample passed the ?2 and the AFT age is
much younger than stratigraphic age. The Cl contents of samples are
0.06 and 0.08 wt.%. Thermal history modeling of the L samples show
relative slow heating until ca. 85 °C at 5 Ma, with subsequently rapid
reheating episode after this time until to the present-day temperature
conditions (Fig. 10).

4.2.6. Borehole N
Borehole N yielded AFT ages which increase systematically with

depth (Fig. 5). All AFT central ages are older than the depositional age.
The mean track lengths are very similar in all samples, ranging between
11.60 and 12.92 ?m, with a symmetrical distribution and standard devi-
ations between 1.20 and 1.63 ?m. The Cl contents of TII-N4 and TII-N5
samples are 0.07 wt%.

The modeled thermal history from the borehole N (except TII-N1)
suggests rapid heating phase after deposition until ca. 58 °C at 58 Ma
ry for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples
the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The
he T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open



Fig. 7. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole B. (a) The expected thermal history for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples are
shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The grey
boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of the T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open symbols) AFT
ages and MTL versus depth.

Fig. 8. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole F. (a) The expected thermal history for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples are
shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The grey
boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of the T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open symbols) AFT
ages and MTL versus depth.

Fig. 9. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole J. (a) The expected thermal history for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples are
shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The grey
boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of the T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open symbols) AFT
ages and MTL versus depth.

29C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34



Fig. 10. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole L. (a) The expected thermal history for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples
are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The
grey boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of the T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open
symbols) AFT ages and MTL versus depth.

30 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
(Fig. 11). After this time, the samples were cooled until to the deposition
of the TII-N1 sample. Following cooling the samples remained at rela-
tively constant temperatures for 35 Ma which was followed by a period
of rapid reheating to the present-day temperature conditions.

4.2.7. Borehole AH
Borehole AH yielded AFT ages of 74.0 ± 12.0 Ma at a depth of 2163 m

and 34.1 ± 5.9 Ma for the deeper sample at a depth of 4496 m. All AFT
ages except one (AH1) are younger than the stratigraphic age. The mean
track lengths are short and have a symmetrical distribution. The AH5
and AH6 samples failed the ?2 and have an age-dispersion over 15%,
revealing two age groups in AH5 and three age groups in AH6.

The modeling results from the borehole AH provide a slow reheating
to ~85 °C after deposition (ca. 55 Ma). From ca. 45 Ma, the expected
thermal history suggests that the samples have resided below the
apatite partial annealing zone until the present-day temperature
conditions (Fig. 12).

4.2.8. Borehole AI
Samples from borehole AI yielded AFT ages which increase with

depth (Fig. 5). The mean track lengths are very short and similar in
the samples, ranging between 8.14 and 8.74 ?m, with a symmetrical
distribution and standard deviations between 1.90 and 2.12 ?m. AFT
central ages are older than the depositional age.
Fig. 11. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole N. (a) The expected thermal hist
are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for
grey boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of t
symbols) AFT ages and MTL versus depth.
The AI model indicates reheating to depths equivalent to a
maximum paleotemperature of 75 °C at ca. 20 Ma (Fig. 13). After this
time, the samples were followed by a period thermal stability for 10 Ma.

5. Discussion

5.1. Tectonic-thermal evolution of the basement samples

Basement AFT ages of this study integrated with other studies (Fig. 3)
reveal a trend of increasing ages with distance of the coast, which is a
common pattern in passive continental margins (e.g., Gallagher et al.,
1994; Gallagher and Brown, 1997). However, in detail, the pattern is
more complex and AFT ages require thermal models to represent the
thermotectonic events age of the area.

Over the whole onshore area two periods seem important:
(a) during the Late Cretaceous (ca. 92–78 Ma), and (b) during the
Cenozoic. Only the Paraná Basin records a cooling event during the
Late Jurassic (ca. 162 Ma), which preceded the onset of breakup of
southwestern Gondwana. The estimated amount of denudation in
Pre-rift stage (150–138 Ma) is 76 m, which yields an average long-
term denudation rate of 6.3 m/My (Fig. 14a). During the Rift and Post-
rift phase (Fig. 14b and c), the denudation was restricted to the
southern area and the rates were slow (b20 m/My). The variations in
the rate and spatial distribution of denudation over time imply substan-
tial differences in the offshore clastic sedimentation observed by
ory for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples
the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The
he T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open



Fig. 12. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole AH. (a) The expected thermal history for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples
are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The
grey boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of the T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open
symbols) AFT ages and MTL versus depth.

31C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
Contreras et al. (2010; and references therein), which can be related to
the dynamics of the drainage system.

The Além Paraíba and Cubatão shear zones, northern and southern
coast, TR9SP4, TR11SP13 and TR11SP14 samples started a cooling/
denudation event during the Late Cretaceous. This timing is consistent
with other studies in the area (e.g., Cogné et al., 2012; Gallagher et al.,
1994; Hiruma et al., 2010; Karl et al., 2013) and is linked to the uplift
and denudation of the Serra do Mar and Serra da Mantiqueira. In NE
Brazil a similar timing of cooling was inferred by Jelinek et al. (2014;
and references therein) for the Mantiqueira Province. The inferred ther-
mal histories imply substantial differences in the amount of denudation
along the area. The amount of denudation ranges from a minimum of ca.
40 m along the northern and central area to a maximum of 1500 m in
the southern area (Fig. 14d). During this time, the Paraíba do Sul drain-
age system tended to focus clastic influx into the central and southern
Santos Basin (Cobbold et al., 2001; Modica and Brush, 2004). The spatial
extent and timing of this denudational episode coincides with the Drift I
stage, and is consistent with the high rates of sediment supply in the off-
shore Santos Basin identified by Contreras et al. (2010) from seismic
studies in depositional sequences.

The most basement samples (except the samples from Jundiuvira-
Boquira Rio Preto and Paraná Basin) also reached the maximum
paleotemperature during the Late Cretaceous (85–78 Ma). This maxi-
mum paleotemperature can be connected to the final breakup between
Fig. 13. Thermal history and associated prediction for borehole AI. (a) The expected thermal hist
are shown in heavy lines, together with their 95% credible intervals. The credible intervals for
grey boxes highlight the stratigraphic age of the samples. Insets (a–i) show burial detail of t
symbols) AFT ages and MTL versus depth.
South America and Africa. The propagation of stresses related to this
event is responsible for igneous activity along the southeastern margin
dated at ca. 90 Ma (Mizusaki et al., 1998; Thomaz Filho et al., 2000).

The post-rift or drifting phase in passive margins is typically domi-
nated by salt tectonics (Allen and Allen, 2013). In the offshore Santos
Basin, the displacement of salt occurred in the Cenomanian in the
deep portions of the basin. An important salt window was created for
the hydrocarbon accumulation (Chang et al., 2008). Other authors
(Cobbold et al., 2001; Contreras et al., 2010) related tectonic reactiva-
tion during the Turonian–Early Campanian (90–80 Ma) in the offshore
Santos Basin, where the sequences tilted by up to 20°.

During the Cenozoic event (Drift II stage) the samples continued
cooling until the present-day temperature, with estimated amount of
denudation range from 1200 to 3600 m (Fig. 14e). The Paraná Basin,
southern coast and Além Paraíba shear zone samples experienced
rapid cooling during the Neogene, after 20 Ma. This episode could be
linked to the uplift of the south area and change of the drainage system,
including the Paraíba do Sul. Cobbold et al. (2001) and Cogné et al.
(2012) suggest that during the uplift of the area, the reactivation of
the Precambrian shear zones led to the formation of a new drainage
system with continental sediment supply diverted to the northern.
The Cenozoic tectonic reactivation of onshore basement and Tertiary
basins is also suggested by other authors from thermochronological
data (e.g., Cogné et al., 2012; Hiruma et al., 2010; Karl et al., 2013).
ory for borehole samples. T–t paths of the uppermost (blue) and lowermost (red) samples
the lower thermal history include the uncertainty inferred for the temperature offset. The
he T–t models from borehole. (b) Graph of observed (fill symbols) and predicted (open



Fig. 14. Reconstructed denudation history of the southeastern Brazilian margin. The maps show the inferred amount and the spatial variation of denudation at different time intervals:
(a) 150–138 Ma, (b) 138–123 Ma, (c) 123–113 Ma, (d) 113–66 Ma, and (e) 66–0 Ma.

32 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
The onshore erosional history during the Cenozoic may be linked to the
sedimentary influx in the offshore basin, with total thicknesses of the
basin fill ranging between 300 and 3000 m (Contreras et al., 2010).

5.2. Tectonic-thermal evolution of the borehole samples

All borehole thermal models (Figs. 6–13) indicate burial after
deposition, with relative increase in temperature during the Eocene.
This temperature increase is interpreted as related to the burial history
and magmatic activities in the basin, previously dated at 48.9 Ma (Ar–Ar
method; Moreira et al., 2007). This increase affected the tectonic evolu-
tion and petroleum accumulation and exploration in the basin. Most
AFT ages are equal or younger than the stratigraphic age demonstrating
that the samples experienced paleotemperatures below the apatite
partial annealing zone (60–120 °C) during burial.

The presence of more than one population of AFT ages in some
samples (see Table 2) is considered the result of partial annealing of
apatites from different sediment sources and variations in apatite
composition (e.g., Barbarand et al., 2003; Green et al., 1985). Different
sediment sources are supported by the presence of pre-depositional
ages and single grain ages of the samples. The variations in apatite com-
position can be observed in the standard deviation of the chlorine con-
tent of the samples (Table 2) and show no clear correlation with single
grain age. A Late Cretaceous age is present in all samples and linked to
the age of the uplift and denudation of the Serra do Mar and Serra da
Mantiqueira basement rocks. In passive margins, the sediment supply
is principally controlled by rivers eroding the continental land surface,
whereby major river systems build submarine fans that may extend di-
rectly onto oceanic crust (Allen and Allen, 2013). In onshore Santos
Basin, the Paraíba do Sul drainage system promoted the continental ero-
sion and sediment supply to the offshore basin.

The increased burial since the Paleogene caused by sediment influx
and flexural-isostatic bending described by Contreras et al. (2010) is ev-
idenced in thermal models. The progressively burial of sedimentary
layers over time in sedimentary basins causes thermal maturation
(e.g., Allen and Allen, 2013). Thermal modeling (except borehole
N) indicates that burial temperature and time residence with conse-
quently organic maturation levels were attained after deposition. The
burial of these boreholes during Paleogene was estimated around
2000–2700 m and maximum temperatures of 70–95 °C. Such estimates



33C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
are in agreement with denudation performed from basement samples
(Fig. 14) and similar to the maximum thickness observed today
(Fig. 2). According to Chang et al. (2008), the oil generation window
of the Itajaí-Açu Formation (Late Cretaceous) in the Santos Basin started
during the Maastrichtian with a generation peak in the Oligocene. Data
from the thermal modeling suggest that the oil generation window
started at 55–25 Ma and continues until Pliocene–Pleistocene,
coincident with the apatite partial annealing zone.

The effect of the temperature indicated by fission track analysis on
oil generation depends on the organic matter type and the time–
temperature history. Heavier oil components are generally generated
first and then cracked into lighter components at higher temperatures,
resulting in an oil window between 1000 and 3000 m depth
(Hantschel and Kauerauf, 2009).

From Neogene, the offshore thermal models seem to have experi-
enced a change in the burial history. During this period, the southern
and central boreholes experienced a phase of cooling, while the north-
ern boreholes experienced a phase of reheating. This period may be
linked to the organization of the coast-parallel Paraíba do Sul drainage
system, with sediment starvation in the south and center of the Santos
Basin and continental sediment supply diverted to the northern
(e.g., Contreras et al., 2010; Modica and Brush, 2004). According to
Contreras et al. (2010), a high sediment supply increased at 15 Ma
and lower accommodation rates resulted in overall progradation in
the basin. The reheating observed in thermal models is the consequence
of the burial of the northern border. The burial depth of the boreholes
was estimated around 400–700 m. However, the northernmost bore-
hole J shows a phase of cooling after 11 Ma (Fig. 9). We cannot exclude
the same possibility of burial in this borehole, but the data are not able
to resolve this. We suggest that this difference was due to the reactiva-
tion of the rift transfer zones. Finally, Cobbold et al. (2001) suggest
Neogene left-lateral reactivation of two main transfer zones near Cabo
Frio High, culminating in the formation of the Cabo Frio anticline.

6. Conclusions

New AFT data combined with published thermochronology data
constrain the thermotectonic evolutionary model of the basement and
offshore Santos Basin. The main results of this study are:

(1) The borehole thermal modeling indicates that the oil generation
window started at 55–25 Ma and continued until the Pliocene–
Pleistocene.

(2) A Late Cretaceous event started in the continental basement and
is linked to the uplift and denudation of the Serra do Mar and
Serra da Mantiqueira. This event is recorded in the single grain
ages of the borehole samples.

(3) The basement samples reached the maximum paleotemperature
during the Late Cretaceous, coincident with the final breakup be-
tween South America and Africa.

(4) The basement samples experienced the final cooling during the
Cenozoic, with estimated amount of denudation linked to the
burial histories of the boreholes until the Neogene.

(5) A rapid cooling during the Neogene is evidenced and linked to
the reactivation along Precambrian shear zones and changes in
the Paraíba do Sul drainage system.

Acknowledgements

The authors acknowledge Project FAURGS/FINEP/CTPETRO
21.01.0310.00 for basement samples and Petrobras for borehole
samples. The first author thanks CAPES (the research fund of Brazilian
Ministry of Education) for the grant (Proex/2013-5). We are grateful
to the professor Léo A. Hartmann and the reviewers that led to improve-
ment in the manuscript.
Appendix A. Supplementary data

Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx.
doi.org/10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012.
References

Allen, P.A., Allen, J.R., 2013. Basin Analysis: Principles and Application to Petroleum Play
Assessment. third ed. John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons, London.

Almeida, F.F.M., Carneiro, C.D.R., Mizusaki, A.M.P., 1996. Correlação do magmatismo das
Bacias da Margem Continental Brasileira com o das áreas emersas adjacentes. Rev.
Bras. Geosci. 23 (3), 125–138.

Barbarand, J., Carter, A., Wood, I., Hurford, T., 2003. Compositional and structural control
of fission track annealing in apatite. Chem. Geol. 198 (1), 107–137.

Brito Neves, B.B., Fuck, R.A., Pimentel, M.M., 2014. The Brasiliano collage in South
America: a review. Braz. J. Geol. 44 (3), 493–518.

Burtner, R.L., Nigrini, A., Donelick, R.A., 1994. Thermochronology of Lower Cretaceous
source rocks in the Idaho-Wyoming thrust belt. Am. Assoc. Pet. Geol. Bull. 78,
1613–1636.

Chang, H.K., Assine, M.L., Corrêa, F.S., Tinen, J.S., Vidal, A.C., Koike, L., 2008. Sistemas
petrolíferos e modelos de acumulação de hidrocarbonetos na Bacia de Santos. Rev.
Bras. Geosci. 38 (2), 29–46.

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E., Mount, V.S., 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely rifted margin,
Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG Bull. 85 (11), 1925–1944.

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R., Riccomini, C., Gautheron, C., 2012. Post-breakup
tectonics in southeast Brazil from thermochronological data and combined inverse-
forward thermal history modeling. J. Geophys. Res. 117, B11413.

Contreras, J., Zühlke, R., Bowman, S., Bechstädt, T., 2010. Seismic stratigraphy and subsi-
dence analysis of the southern Brazilian margin (Campos, Santos and Pelotas basins).
Mar. Pet. Geol. 27 (9), 1952–1980.

Donelick, R.A., O'Sullivan, P.B., Ketcham, R.A., 2005. Apatite Fission-Track Analysis. In:
Reiners, P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Eds.), Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques,
Interpretations, and Applications. Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry 58.
Mineralogical Society of America, Washington, pp. 49–94.

Ebert, H.D., Chemale Jr., F., Babinski, M., Artur, A.C., Van Schmus, W.R., 1996. Tectonic
setting and U/Pb zircon dating of the plutonic Socorro Complex in the transpressive
Rio Paraíba do Sul Shear Belt, SE Brazil. Tectonics 15 (2), 688–699.

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Hackspacher, P.C., Glasmacher, U.A., Saad, A.R., 2010. Rift to post-
rift evolution of a “passive” continental margin: the Ponta Grossa Arch, SE Brazil. Int.
J. Earth Sci. 99 (7), 1599–1613.

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B., Cuglieri, M.A.A., Hackspacher, P.C., Saad, A.R., 2014. Long-term
landscape evolution and post-rift reactivation in the southeastern Brazilian passive
continental margin: Taubaté basin. Int. J. Earth Sci. 103 (2), 441–453.

Galbraith, R.F., Laslett, G.M., 1993. Statistical models for mixed fission track ages. Nucl.
Tracks Radiat. Meas. 21, 459–470.

Gallagher, K., 2012. Transdimensional inverse thermal history modeling for quantitative
thermochronology. J. Geophys. Res. 117. http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2011JB008825.

Gallagher, K., Brown, R., 1997. The onshore record of passive margin evolution. J. Geol.
Soc. 154 (3), 451–457.

Gallagher, K., Brown, R., 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic margins of
southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore sedimentation.
In: Cameron, N.R., Bate, R.H., Clure, V.S. (Eds.), The Oil and Gas Habitats of the
South Atlantic. Geological Society, London, pp. 41–53.

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J., Mantovani, M.S.M., 1994. The denudation history of the
onshore continental margin of SE Brazil inferred from apatite fission track data.
J. Geophys. Res. 99 (B9), 18117–18145.

Gallagher, K., Stephenson, J., Brown, R., Holmes, C., Fitzgerald, P., 2005. Low temperature
thermochronology and modeling strategies for multiple samples 1: Vertical profiles.
Earth Planet. Sci. Lett. 237, 193–208.

Green, P.F., 1981. A new look at statistics in fission-track dating. Nucl. Tracks 5 (1), 77–86.
Green, P.F., Duddy, I.R., Gleadow, A.J.W., Tingate, P.R., Laslett, G.M., 1985. Fission-track

annealing in apatite: track length measurements and the form of the Arrhenius
plot. Nucl. Tracks Radiat. Meas. 10 (3), 323–328.

Hackspacher, P.C., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Ribeiro, M.C.S., Fetter, A.H., Hadler Neto, J.C., Tello Saenz,
C.A., Dantas, E.L., 2004. Consolidation and break-up of the South American platform in
Southeastern Brazil: tectonothermal and denudation histories. Gondwana Res. 7 (1),
91–101.

Hamza, V.M., Dias, F.J.S., Gomes, A.J.L., Terceros, Z.G.D., 2005. Numerical and functional
representations of regional heat flow in South America. Phys. Earth Planet. Inter.
152, 223–256.

Hantschel, T., Kauerauf, A.I., 2009. Fundamentals of Basin and Petroleum Systems Modeling.
Springer Science &amp;amp; Business Media, New York.

Heilbron, M., Mohriak, W.U., Valeriano, C.M., Milani, E.J., Almeida, J., Tupinambá, M., 2000.
From collision to extension: the roots of the southeastern continental margin of
Brazil. In: Talwani, M. (Ed.)Atlantic Rifts and Continental Margins, Geophysical
Monograph Series 115. American Geophysical Union, pp. 1–34.

Hiruma, S.T., Riccomini, C., Modenesi-Gauttieri, M.C., Hackspacher, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C.,
Franco-Magalhães, A.O.B., 2010. Denudation history of the Bocaina Plateau, Serra do
Mar, southeastern Brazil: relationships to Gondwana breakup and passive margin
development. Gondwana Res. 18, 674–687.

Hurford, A.J., 1990. International union of geological sciences subcommission on geochro-
nology recommendation for the standardization of fission track dating calibration
and data reporting. Nucl. Tracks Radiat. Meas. 17 (3), 233–236.

doi:10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012
doi:10.1016/j.tecto.2016.07.012
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0010
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0020
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0020
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0025
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0030
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0030
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0030
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0035
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0035
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0040
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0045
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0050
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0055
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0055
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0055
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0060
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0060
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0060
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0065
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0070
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0070
http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2011JB008825
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0080
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0080
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0085
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0090
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9000
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0095
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0100
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0105
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0105
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0105
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0110
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0115
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0115
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0120
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0120
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0120
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0125
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0125
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0125
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0130
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0130
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0130


34 C.H. Engelmann de Oliveira et al. / Tectonophysics 685 (2016) 21–34
Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F., van der Beek, P.A., Guadagnin, F., Cupertino, J.A., Viana, A., 2014.
Denudation history and landscape evolution of the northern East-Brazilian continen-
tal margin from apatite fission-track thermochronology. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 54,
158–181.

Karl, M., Glasmacher, U.A., Kollenz, S., Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Stockli, D.F., Hackspacher,
P.C., 2013. Evolution of the South Atlantic passive continental margin in southern
Brazil derived from zircon and apatite (U–Th–Sm)/He and fission-track data.
Tectonophysics 604, 224–244.

Ketcham, R.A., Carter, A.C., Donelick, R.A., Barbarand, J., Hurford, A.J., 2007. Improved
modeling of fission-track annealing in apatite. Am. Mineral. 92, 799–810.

Macdonald, D., Gomez-Perez, I., Franzese, J., Spalletti, L., Lawver, L., Gahagan, L., Paton, D.,
2003. Mesozoic break-up of SW Gondwana: implications for regional hydrocarbon
potential of the southern South Atlantic. Mar. Pet. Geol. 20 (3), 287–308.

Meisling, K.E., Cobbold, P.R., Mount, V.S., 2001. Segmentation of an obliquely rifted
margin, Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG Bull. 85 (11),
1903–1924.

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Thomaz-Filho, A., Cesero, P., 1998. Ages of the magmatism and the
opening of the South Atlantic Ocean. Pesqui. Geociênc. 25 (1), 47–57.

Modica, C.J., Brush, E.R., 2004. Postrift sequence stratigraphy, paleogeography, and fill
history of the deep-water Santos Basin, offshore southeast Brazil. AAPG Bull. 88 (7),
923–945.

Mohriak, W., Nem?ok, M., Enciso, G., 2008. South Atlantic divergent margin evolution:
rift-border uplift and salt tectonics in the basins of SE Brazil. Geol. Soc. Lond., Spec.
Publ. 294 (1), 365–398.

Moreira, J.L.P., Esteves, C.A., Rodrigues, J.J.G., Vasconcelos, C.S., 2006. Magmatismo,
sedimentação e estratigrafia da porção norte da Bacia de Santos. Bol. Geociênc.
Petrobras 14 (1), 161–170.

Moreira, J.L.P., Madeira, C.V., Gil, J.A., Machado, M.A.P., 2007. Bacia de Santos. Bol.
Geocienc. Petrobras 15 (2), 531–549.

Nürnberg, D., Müller, R.D., 1991. The tectonic evolution of the South Atlantic from Late
Jurassic to present. Tectonophysics 191, 27–53.
Raab, M.J., Brown, R.W., Gallagher, K., Weber, K., Gleadow, A.J.W., 2005. Denudational and
thermal history of the Early Cretaceous Brandberg and Okenyenya igneous
complexes on Namibia's Atlantic passive margin. Tectonics 24, TC3006.

Rabinowitz, P.D., LaBrecque, J., 1979. The Mesozoic South Atlantic Ocean and evolution of
its continental margins. J. Geophys. Res. 84, 5973–6002.

Riccomini, C., Sant’Anna, L.G., Ferrari, A.L., 2004. Evolução geológica do Rift Continental do
Sudeste do Brasil. In: Mantesso-Neto, V., Bartorelli, A., Carneiro, C.D.R., Brito-Neves,
B.B. (Eds.), Geologia do Continente Sul-Americano: Evolução da Obra de Fernando
Flávio Marques de Almeida. Edições Beca, São Paulo, pp. 383–405.

Schmitt, R.S., Frimmel, H.E., Fairchild, T.R., 2008. Neoproterozoic–Early Paleozoic events in
Southwest Gondwana: introduction. Gondwana Res. 13, 435–436.

Tello Saenz, C., Hackspacher, P.C., Neto, J.H., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Paulo, S.R.,
2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene tectonic reactivation
through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambrian areas of southeast Brazil:
association with the opening of the South Atlantic Ocean. J. S. Am. Earth Sci. 15 (7),
765–774.

Thomaz Filho, A., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Milani, E.J., Cesero, P., 2000. Rifting and magmatism
associated with the South America and Africa break up. Rev. Bras. Geosci. 30 (1),
17–19.

Torsvik, T.H., Rousse, S., Labails, C., Smethurst, M.A., 2009. A new scheme for the opening
of the South Atlantic Ocean and the dissection of an Aptian salt basin. Geophys. J. Int.
177 (3), 1315–1333.

Vermeesch, P., 2009. RadialPlotter: a Java application for fission track, luminescence and
other radial plots. Radiat. Meas. 44, 409–410.

Zalán, P.V., Wolff, S., Astolfi, M.A.M., Vieira, I.S., Conceição, J.C.J., Appi, V.T., Santos Neto,
E.V., Cerqueira, J.R., Marques, A., 1991. The Paraná Basin, Brazil. In: Leighton (Ed.),
Interior Cratonic Basins. Memoir 51. AAPG, Tulsa, Oklahoma, pp. 681–708.

http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0135
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0140
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9005
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0145
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0145
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0150
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0155
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0155
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0160
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0165
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0170
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0175
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0175
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0180
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0180
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0185
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf201607
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf201607
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf9015
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0190
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0190
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0195
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0200
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0205
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0210
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0210
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0215
http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0040-1951(16)30264-5/rf0215


 

 

UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO RIO GRANDE DO SUL 

INSTITUTO DE GEOCIÊNCIAS 

Pesquisas em Geociências 

 

 
Porto Alegre, 30 de novembro de 2016. 

 
À 
Christie Helouise Engelmann de Oliveira &amp;amp; Andréa Ritter Jelinek  

 
Venho comunicar o recebimento do manuscrito listado, submetido para 

publicação em Pesquisas em Geociências, órgão de divulgação científica editado pelo 
Instituto de Geociências da Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 

Contudo, para dar prosseguimentos às atividades editoriais, é necessário atenção 
aos seguintes itens, necessitando, portanto, de nova submissão. 

Abaixo seguem alguns itens com inconsistências, dentre os diversos encontrados. 
 

? Os termos referentes aos períodos/sistemas estão, em sua maioria, 
grafados em espanhol. Rever e ajustar em todo o texto. 

? O artifício et al. deve ser grafado em itálico, no texto e nas figuras. 
? A figura 8 precisa ser ajustada. 
? Há várias correções a serem feitas nas referências bibliográficas. 

 
Agradeço a seleção de Pesquisas em Geociências para a publicação de sua 

contribuição. Uma nova versão é aguardada até o dia 07/12/2016. 
 
 

Manuscrito 642: História termotectônica da margem continental brasileira a partir de 
dados de traços de fissão em apatita. Autoras: Christie Helouise Engelmann de Oliveira &amp;amp; 
Andréa Ritter Jelinek. 
 

Atenciosamente, 

 
Prof. Dr. Paulo Alves de Souza 

Editor Chefe 
Pesquisas em Geociências 

Instituto de Geociências – Departamento de Paleontologia e Estratigrafia 

Av. Bento Gonçalves, n? 9500 - Bloco 1 - Prédio 43127 

CEP 91.540-000, Porto Alegre, RS, Brasil. 
Email: paulo.alves.souza@ufrgs.br 



30/11/2016 Gmail ­ Submissão de artigo

https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/?ui=2&amp;amp;ik=2f1e13110c&amp;amp;view=pt&amp;amp;search=inbox&amp;amp;msg=158b5c6d9605bae0&amp;amp;siml=158b5c6d9605bae0 1/1

Christie Oliveira &lt;christie.oliveira10@gmail.com&gt;

Submissão de artigo 
Christie Oliveira &lt;christie.oliveira10@gmail.com&gt; 30 de novembro de 2016 13:07
Para: Pesquisas em Geociências &lt;pesqgeoc@ufrgs.br&gt;

Prezado Paulo A. Souza,

Em anexo, segue o manuscrito "História termotectônica da margem continental brasileira a partir de dados de traços
de fissão em apatita" com as devidas correções/ajustes solicitados.

As correções foram feitas conforme as solicitações, com exceção da referência de Ribeiro et al. (2005) (linha 536 do
manuscrito original e 541 no manuscrito corrigido), em que "Parana basin" foi publicado sem o acento pelos autores.

Obrigada pelo pronto envio.

Atenciosamente,
Christie H. Engelmann de Oliveira.
[Texto das mensagens anteriores oculto]

2 anexos

Carta submissao.pdf
72K

Engelmann de Oliveira &amp;amp; Jelinek_Pesquisas em Geociências_30nov.pdf 
1457K

https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/?ui=2&amp;amp;ik=2f1e13110c&amp;amp;view=att&amp;amp;th=158b5c6d9605bae0&amp;amp;attid=0.1&amp;amp;disp=attd&amp;amp;realattid=f_iw52g7732&amp;amp;safe=1&amp;amp;zw
https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/?ui=2&amp;amp;ik=2f1e13110c&amp;amp;view=att&amp;amp;th=158b5c6d9605bae0&amp;amp;attid=0.2&amp;amp;disp=attd&amp;amp;realattid=f_iw52g77a3&amp;amp;safe=1&amp;amp;zw


1 

 

História termotectônica da margem continental brasileira a partir de dados 1 

de traços de fissão em apatita 2 

 3 

Thermotectonic history of the Brazilian continental margin from apatite 4 

fission track data 5 

 6 

Christie Helouise ENGELMANN DE OLIVEIRA¹ &amp;amp; Andréa Ritter JELINEK² 7 

(1)
    Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências, Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do 8 

Rio Grande do Sul. Av. Bento Gonçalves, 9.500, CEP 91.501-970, Porto Alegre, Brasil. E-mail: 9 
christie.oliveira10@gmail.com. 10 

(2)
    Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. Av. Bento Gonçalves, 11 

9.500, CEP 91.501-970, Porto Alegre, Brasil. E-mail: andrea.jelinek@ufrgs.br. 12 
 13 

Resumo - A margem continental brasileira denota estruturas geomorfológicas moldadas 14 
durante vários episódios de atividade tectônica iniciados no Neoproterozoico. Com o 15 
objetivo de estabelecer um modelo de história termotectônica para a margem continental 16 
brasileira, foi realizada a integração e reinterpretação dos dados traços de fissão em 17 
apatita (TFA) disponíveis ao longo de toda a margem continental. As idades TFA variam 18 
de ~385-10 Ma. Os dados TFA revelam que a margem continental foi caracterizada por 19 
pelo menos três eventos de resfriamento acelerado pós Ciclo Brasiliano: Cretaceo 20 
Inferior, Cretaceo Superior e Paleógeno-Neógeno. Os eventos são relacionados aos 21 
processos de abertura do Oceano Atlântico Sul e às fases rifte e pós-rifte, com reativações 22 
tectônicas ao longo da margem. A Província Mantiqueira e o cráton São Francisco 23 
registram eventos de resfriamento mais antigos, desde o Ordoviciano e o Permiano, 24 
respectivamente, que afetaram de modo variado diferentes partes dessas províncias como 25 
reflexo das orogenias Famatiniana e Gondwanide.  26 
Palavras-chave: Gondwana, rifte, resfriamento, soerguimento.  27 
 28 
Abstract - The Brazilian continental margin shows geomorphological structures formed 29 
during several episodes of tectonic activity initiated in the Neoproterozoic. In order to 30 
establish a thermotectonic history model for the Brazilian continental margin, an 31 
integration and reinterpretation of the apatite fission track (AFT) data was performed. 32 
AFT ages range from ~385 to 10 Ma. The AFT data reveal that the continental margin 33 
was characterized by at least three accelerated cooling events post Brasiliano Cycle: Early 34 
Cretaceous, Late Cretaceous and Paleogene-Neogene. The events are related to the 35 
opening processes of the South Atlantic Ocean and to the rift and post-rift phases, with 36 
tectonic reactivations along to the margin. The Mantiqueira Province and the São 37 
Francisco Craton record the oldest cooling events, from the Ordovician to the Permian, 38 
respectively, which affected the various parts in varying ways as evidence of the 39 
Famatinian and Gondwanide orogenies. 40 
Keywords: Gondwana, rift, cooling, uplift. 41 

 42 

 43 

1 Introdução  44 

 45 

mailto:christie.oliveira10@gmail.com


2 

 

A margem continental brasileira denota estruturas geomorfológicas moldadas durante 46 

vários episódios de atividade tectônica iniciados no Neoproterozoico, sendo sua topografia e 47 

relevo atuais semelhantes em muitos aspectos àqueles de outras margens continentais tipo 48 

rifte ao redor do globo terrestre (p. ex., Austrália, oeste da África, Noruega, Índia Ocidental). 49 

Ela faz parte do sistema de riftes do Atlântico Sul, originado pela separação do Gondwana 50 

Ocidental no Cretaceo Inferior, cuja abertura iniciou-se no sul e propagou-se ao norte ao 51 

longo de reativações tectônicas de antigos lineamentos (Nürnberg &amp;amp; Müller, 1991; Meisling 52 

et al., 2001; Torsvik et al., 2009). A natureza da margem influenciou o desenvolvimento das 53 

bacias sedimentares offshore e das bacias intracontinentais, sendo que os sistemas de rifte 54 

Mesozoico-Cenozoico paralelos à costa estão presentes também offshore. A separação do 55 

paleocontinente em ~130 Ma foi afetada por rifteamento generalizado e pelo vulcanismo da 56 

Província Paraná-Etendeka (Zalán et al., 1991; Macdonald et al., 2003). A atividade 57 

vulcânica relacionada à pluma causou a subida da crosta, incluindo a exposição do 58 

embasamento Pré-Cambriano, seguido de erosão e deposição. 59 

Há mais de duas décadas, a evolução da história termotectônica da margem 60 

continental brasileira vem sendo estudada através da técnica TFA. O método 61 

termocronológico de baixa temperatura TFA é utilizado para determinar histórias térmicas da 62 

crosta superior terrestre ao longo do tempo (i.e.,&amp;lt;150 °C em escalas de tempo de 1-500 Ma; 63 

Gallagher &amp;amp; Brown, 1997) e tem sido amplamente utilizado para entender o desenvolvimento 64 

de margens tipo rifte, quantificar taxas de exumação e denudação e fornecer idades e taxas de 65 

movimentação ao longo de falhas e zonas de cisalhamento (Gallagher &amp;amp; Brown, 1999; Raab 66 

et al., 2005; Jelinek et al., 2014). O primeiro estudo com TFA no Brasil foi desenvolvido na 67 

margem sudeste por Gallagher et al. (1994), e os dados foram interpretados em termos de 68 

história térmica e denudação da margem.  69 

Neste trabalho, é apresentada uma integração dos dados TFA disponíveis para a 70 

margem continental brasileira. Os dados foram interpretados no contexto de tectônica 71 

regional, resultando em uma história termotectônica da margem continental brasileira para 72 

temperaturas abaixo de ~120 °C, em que os dados indicam que as idades de resfriamento TFA 73 

estão relacionadas aos eventos pré-, sin- e pós-rifte. Através do uso de uma plataforma de 74 

Sistema de Informação Geográfica e modelamento de dados mostramos como grandes 75 

conjuntos de dados regionais podem ser apresentados de maneira que seus padrões de 76 

variação possam ser facilmente compreendidos.  77 

 78 



3 

 

 79 

2. Área, material e métodos 80 

 81 

2.1 Contexto geológico 82 

  83 

 A margem continental brasileira resulta da ruptura do paleocontinente Gondwana e 84 

está assentada sobre as rochas pré-rifte do embasamento que têm uma longa história 85 

geológica. O processo de ruptura do Gondwana Ocidental e consequente abertura do 86 

Atlântico Sul começou na parte do sul da América do Sul durante o Triássico Superior-87 

Jurássico Inferior e propagou-se ao norte, alcançando a margem equatorial no Aptiano 88 

Superior-Albiano Inferior (Nürnberg &amp;amp; Müller, 1991; Meisling et al., 2001; Torsvik et al., 89 

2009). A abertura do Atlântico Sul foi precedida por volumoso magmatismo toleítico 90 

induzido pela Pluma Tristão da Cunha entre 145 e 130 Ma, originando a Província Paraná-91 

Etendeka, localizada no sul da América do Sul e oeste da África (Zalán et al., 1991; Meisling 92 

et al., 2001; Macdonald et al., 2003). 93 

 As rochas do embasamento revelam uma segmentação ao longo da margem 94 

continental brasileira que reflete diferentes províncias estruturais (Fig. 1). Essas províncias 95 

foram esboçadas pela primeira vez no trabalho de Almeida et al. (1981), com base na natureza 96 

do embasamento cristalino e da cobertura sedimentar. Recentemente, no contexto da colagem 97 

do Neoproterozoico, Brito Neves &amp;amp; Fuck (2013) revisaram o conceito. A Província da 98 

Mantiqueira, situada ao longo da parte sul e sudeste da costa atlântica, ocupa a maior parte da 99 

margem, desde o estado do Rio Grande do Sul até parte do estado da Bahia, e é afetada 100 

principalmente pelo Ciclo Brasiliano. Na parte sudeste, na área da Bacia de Santos, onde a 101 

escarpa da margem tipo rifte é mais claramente expressa, esta província apresenta altitudes 102 

superiores a 1500 m (Serra do Mar e Serra da Mantiqueira). 103 



4 

 

 104 

Figura 1. Mapa geotectônico das províncias da margem continental brasileira (Modificado de 105 

Brito Neves &amp;amp; Fuck, 2013).  106 

Figure 1. Geotectonic provinces map of the Brazilian continental margin (Modified by Brito 107 

Neves &amp;amp; Fuck, 2013). 108 

  109 

 O cráton São Francisco, contíguo à parte noroeste do cráton do Congo na África 110 

Ocidental antes da ruptura do Pangea (Neves, 2003), cobre quase todo o estado da Bahia e 111 

grande parte do estado de Minas Gerais, e é caracterizado por uma vasta planície interna e 112 

alguns platôs com elevações entre 500 e 1000 m na parte centro-leste (Almeira, 1977; 113 

Almeida et al., 1981). É constituído por rochas intensamente deformadas e metamorfizadas de 114 

idade Arqueana a Paleoproterozoica, sobrepostas pelos sedimentos plataformais Meso- e 115 

Neoproterozoico dos supergrupos de Espinhaço e São Francisco e limitado por cinturões de 116 

dobramento Brasiliano Neoproterozoico desenvolvidos durante as orogenias colisionais que 117 

resultaram na formação do Gondwana Ocidental. 118 

 A Província da Borborema, localizada na margem nordeste brasileira, foi afetada pelo 119 

intensamente pelo Ciclo Brasiliano e é subdividida em três sub-províncias: sul, Zona 120 

transversal (Central) e norte, limitadas pelos importantes lineamentos brasilianos de Patos e 121 

Pernambuco (Neves, 2003; Van Schmus et al., 2011). A província é coberta a oeste por 122 



5 

 

rochas sedimentares Fanerozoicas e vulcânicas da Bacia do Parnaíba, e ao norte e leste por 123 

depósitos costeiros Meso-Cenozoicos. O contexto geomorfológico da província não exibe alto 124 

topográficos próximo ao litoral, mas é caracterizado pelo Platô da Borborema, que se eleva da 125 

planície costeira até ~1000 m ao norte do rio São Francisco, cuja origem epirogênica está 126 

relacionada com a ruptura do supercontinente Gondwana e ao magmatismo intraplaca 127 

Cenozoico (Lima et al., 2015). 128 

 A Bacia do Paraná é uma das maiores bacias intracratônicas originada do Ordoviciano 129 

ao Cretaceo e localizada na porção sudoeste do supercontinente Gondwana durante o Éon 130 

Fanerozoico (Milani, 1997). Seu relevo é constituído por altos planaltos (~1200 m) e cuestas 131 

concêntricas drenados pelos rios Uruguai e Paraná. A presença dos maiores fluxos de lava 132 

basáltica da Província Paraná-Etendeka na crosta continental e dos milhares de corpos 133 

intrusivos de diabásio associados, evidenciam uma história térmica incomum que resultou na 134 

deformação dos estratos. 135 

 136 

2.2 Dados 137 

  138 

 A base de dados utilizada foi constituída por uma série de dados publicados nos 139 

últimos 22 anos por diferentes autores (Fig. 2 e 3), resultando em um total de 742 amostras 140 

com idades TFA e 592 comprimentos médios de traços (MTL). As altitudes registradas para 141 

cada amostra e os eventos termotectônicos obtidos em cada trabalho também foram utilizados 142 

no banco de dados para posterior correlação e interpretação. O conjunto de dados foi 143 

estruturado no software ArcGis em um mesmo sistema de projeção e datum (UTM-WGS-84). 144 

Os mapas de contorno foram modelados utilizando o método de interpolação por Vizinho 145 

Natural (Natural Neighbor), que não confere tendências e trabalha igualmente bem com 146 

dados regularmente e irregularmente distribuídos. 147 



6 

 

 148 

Figura 2. Mapa com a localização dos dados TFA publicados na margem sul, sudeste e leste 149 

do Brasil (Província Mantiqueira e Pacia do Paraná).  150 

Figure 2. Location map of the published AFTA data in the south, southeast and east Brazilian 151 

margin ( Mantiqueira Province and Paraná Basin). 152 

 153 



7 

 

 154 

Figura 3. Mapa com a localização dos dados TFA publicados na região norte da Província 155 

Mantiqueira, cráton São Francisco e Província Borborema.  156 



8 

 

Figure 3. Location map of the published AFTA data in the northern region of the Mantiqueira 157 

Province, San Francisco craton and Borborema Province. 158 

 159 

2.3 Método traços de fissão em apatita 160 

  161 

 O método TFA (Jelinek et al., 2010) baseia-se no fenômeno de que a fissão 162 

espontânea dos átomos de 
238

U contido no retículo cristalino da apatita causa danos a este 163 

retículo (traços de fissão). Estes traços formam-se a uma taxa constante, determinada pela 164 

constante de decaimento da fissão espontânea do 
238

U. O número de traços presentes num 165 

dado cristal de apatita depende tanto da concentração de urânio quanto do tempo que este 166 

traços demoraram para acumular-se. Através da contagem do número de traços que 167 

interceptam a superfície interna do cristal e do seu conteúdo de urânio, a idade traços de fissão 168 

pode ser calculada. 169 

 A temperatura afeta significativamente a quantidade e o comprimento dos traços de 170 

fissão. Quando os traços são submetidos a temperaturas superiores àquelas de bloqueio para 171 

um dado termocronômetro, &gt;60 °C no caso do TFA, os traços sofrem encurtamento e redução 172 

na densidade, processo este chamado de annealing (Jelinek et al., 2010). Portanto, os dados 173 

de comprimento dos traços de fissão fornecem informações sobre as variações de temperatura 174 

experimentadas pela rocha hospedeira, enquanto que a idade traços de fissão fornece 175 

informações sobre a duração dessas variações. A um elevado nível de annealing, acima de 176 

~120 °C durante escalas de tempo geológico, todos os traços são apagados e os seus 177 

comprimentos e idade traços de fissão são reduzidos a zero. Maiores detalhes sobre o método 178 

TFA são apresentados por Gleadow (1981), Green (1981), Laslett et al. (1987), Donelick et 179 

al. (2005), Tagami &amp;amp; O'Sullivan (2005) e Jelinek et al. (2010). 180 

 181 

3 Resultados 182 

 183 

As idades TFA da margem continental brasileira variam de ~385 a ~10 Ma (Fig. 4) e 184 

todas são consideravelmente mais jovens do que a idade de cristalização ou metamorfismo 185 

das rochas hospedeiras, indicando que foram expostas a temperaturas elevadas no passado e 186 

que muitas experimentaram temperaturas acima 120 °C, ocorrendo o total annealing das 187 

idades. As figuras 4 e 5 mostram claramente que as idades TFA próximas à costa atual do 188 

sudeste e nordeste brasileiro são relativamente jovens (20-100 Ma) e consideravelmente mais 189 



9 

 

jovens do que a idade da separação entre América do Sul e África. As idades TFA mais 190 

antigas do que a idade de ruptura do SW Gondwana (~195 Ma) ocorrem somente nas partes 191 

interiores da margem continental, no extremo sul da Província Mantiqueira (estado do Rio 192 

Grande do Sul), e no leste do cráton São Francisco. 193 

 194 

 195 



10 

 

Figura 4. Mapa das idades TFA da margem continental brasileira.  196 

Figure 4. AFT age map for Brazilian continental margin. 197 

 198 

 199 

Figura 5. Mapa de contorno das idades TFA ao longo da margem continental brasileira.  200 

Figure 5. Contour map of AFT ages across the Brazilian continental margin. 201 

 202 

Em geral, não há uma clara relação entre a idade TFA e a altitude (Fig. 6). No entanto, 203 

as idades TFA &gt;200 Ma tendem a estar associadas a altitudes mais baixas (&lt;500 m). A 204 

maioria das amostras com idade TFA do Cretaceo e Cenozoico apresentam MTL &gt;11,5 ?m 205 

(Fig. 7). Diversos autores (p. ex., Gallagher et al., 1994, Cogné et al., 2011) interpretaram a 206 

relação entre a idade TFA e o MTL na margem brasileira como um gráfico boomerang. Green 207 

(1986) demonstrou que esse padrão côncavo (concave-up) ocorre quando uma região 208 

experimenta uma fase de denudação acelerada, e é caracterizada por uma diminuição inicial 209 

nos MTL e idade, para um comprimento médio mínimo com idades intermediárias, seguido 210 

de um aumento progressivo nos MTL com idades sucessivamente mais jovens. No entanto, a 211 

relação entre as idades TFA e os MTL da margem brasileira (Fig. 7) não mostra um gráfico 212 

boomerang ideal, sugerindo uma complexa história térmica envolvendo vários episódios de 213 

resfriamento. 214 



11 

 

 215 

Figura 6. Relação entre as idades TFA e a altitude das amostras. 216 

Figure 6. Relationship between AFT ages and elevation of the samples. 217 

 218 

 219 

Figura 7. Relação entre as idades TFA e os MTL para todo o conjunto de dados. 220 

Figure 7. Relationship between AFT ages and MTL for the entire dataset. 221 

 222 

Todas as províncias estruturais (Fig. 8) apresentam longos MTL e idades AFT 223 

associadas com a separação continental entre América do Sul e África (~135-95 Ma), 224 

relacionados ao episódio de resfriamento e denudação que levou à formação dessas margens. 225 

Outro episódio de resfriamento, exceto para a Bacia do Paraná, pode ser inferido durante o 226 

magmatismo do Cretaceo Superior e do Paleógeno (Fig. 8A, 8B e 8C), e indica que as 227 

amostras resfriaram rapidamente a partir de temperaturas de ~120 °C no momento indicado 228 

pela idade TFA. 229 

A Bacia do Paraná registra apenas idades após a ruptura do SW Gondwana (Fig. 8D), 230 

com a maioria das idades datando do magmatismo Paraná-Etendeka, como consequência da 231 

influência térmica e total annealing em termos de idades traços de fissão. As distribuições dos 232 



12 

 

MTL nas amostras desta província são particularmente intermediários a curtos (&lt;14 ?m, Fig. 233 

8D). Tais distribuições de MTL podem ser qualitativamente interpretadas em termos de 234 

arrefecimento prolongado, como consequência da lenta denudação ocorrida após a ruptura. 235 

 236 

 237 



13 

 

Figura 8. Relação entre as idades TFA e os MTL para as amostras da (A) Província 238 

Borborema (A), cráton São Francisco (B), Província Mantiqueira (C) e Bacia do Paraná (D). 239 

As três faixas sombreadas indicam o tempo aproximado antes da ruptura do SW Gondwana 240 

(cerca de 195 Ma), o intervalo de tempo da separação entre América do Sul e África (135-95 241 

Ma) e o magmatismo do Cretacico Superior e Paleogénico (80-40 Ma). 242 

Figure 8. Relationship between AFT ages and MTL for the samples from Borborema Province 243 

(A), São Francisco craton (B), Mantiqueira Province (C) and Paraná Basin (D). The three 244 

shaded bands indicate the approximate time before of SW Gondwana breakup (ca. 195 Ma), 245 

the spread time of South America and Africa breakup (135-95 Ma) and the Late Cretaceous 246 

and Paleogene magmatism (80-40 Ma). 247 

 248 

 249 

4 Discussão dos resultados 250 

 251 

Dados TFA fornecem importantes informações termotectônicas dos eventos ocorridos 252 

ao longo dos últimos 500 Ma na história geológica. Em escala regional, a resposta 253 

geomorfológica aos processos de rifteamento e ruptura continental, indicada pela cronologia, 254 

variou significativamente ao longo da margem continental brasileira (Fig. 4 e 5). Os dados 255 

TFA mostram que o desenvolvimento pós Ciclo Brasiliano da margem brasileira foi 256 

caracterizado por pelo menos três eventos de resfriamento acelerado: Cretaceo Inferior, 257 

Cretaceo Superior e Paleógeno-Neógeno. Somente a Província Mantiqueira e o cráton São 258 

Francisco registram eventos de resfriamento mais antigos desde o Ordoviciano e o Permiano, 259 

respectivamente, que afetaram de modo variado diferentes partes dessas províncias. 260 

Na margem extremo sul da Província Mantiqueira (estado do Rio Grande do Sul), as 261 

antigas idades TFA estão relacionadas ao resfriamento contínuo e relativamente lento durante 262 

o Paleozoico (Ordoviciano ao Permiano), e refletem o possível soerguimento da área em 263 

resposta à colisão entre o terreno Precordillera e o cráton Rio de la Plata, na margem oeste do 264 

Gondwana Ocidental durante as orogenias Famatiniana e Gondwanide (Oliveira et al., 2016). 265 

Esta parte da margem brasileira é caracterizada por uma topografia relativamente baixa e uma 266 

grande planície costeira, não apresentando uma característica morfológica de margem 267 

continental passiva. De modo contrário, a margem continental sudeste e leste brasileira, parte 268 

da Província Mantiqueira, apresenta uma morfologia de margem continental passiva 269 

característica, com as bacias sedimentares offshore (bacias de Santos, Campos e Espírito 270 



14 

 

Santo) separadas da região continental elevada (Serra do Mar e Serra da Mantiqueira) por 271 

uma planície costeira relativamente estreita (Gallagher et al., 1994). As idades TFA refletem 272 

esta morfologia de margem passiva, com um aumento das idades de 40-90 Ma na planície 273 

costeira para &gt;300 Ma no interior continental, configurando uma maior denudação na 274 

planície, como sugerido por diversos autores (p. ex., Gallagher et al., 1994, 1995; Gallagher 275 

and Brown, 1999; Carmo, 2005; Hiruma et al., 2010; Engelmann de Oliveira et al., 2016). 276 

Os dados da região sudeste do Brasil também apresentam idades significativamente 277 

mais jovens do que a idade do rifteamento que levou à formação da margem continental (Fig. 278 

4 e 8). Para a maior parte da margem, e por grande parte dos autores relacionados (Fig. 2 e 3), 279 

o resfriamento relativamente rápido durante o Paleógeno-Neógeno é interpretado como 280 

resultado de episódios de aumento nas taxas de denudação relacionados à formação e 281 

reativação de blocos de falha de alto ângulo que se moveram em resposta às tensões 282 

intraplaca. Os episódios de denudação também são contemporâneos à deposição de rochas 283 

sedimentares clásticas nas bacias da margem sudeste brasileira. Diversos autores (p. ex., 284 

Gallagher et al., 1994, 1995; Hiruma et al., 2010; Jelinek et al., 2014; Engelmann de Oliveira 285 

et al., 2016) discutem que as altas taxas de denudação pós-rifte indicadas para a margem, 286 

provavelmente refletem a geometria e o momento da reativação tectônica pós-rifte de 287 

estruturas intracontinentais maiores, e as taxas de denudação são correlacionáveis às 288 

espessuras do registro sedimentar offshore nas bacias de Santos e Espírito Santo.  289 

O Arco de Ponta Grossa, na região de Curitiba, apresenta as idades TFA mais jovens 290 

de toda a margem continental (Fig. 4; Franco-Magalhaes et al., 2010). A região é um alto 291 

topográfico caracterizado por um grande número de diques associados ao magmatismo 292 

Paraná-Etendeka e limitado por zonas de cisalhamento NW-SE (Zalán et al., 1990). Segundo 293 

Gallagher et al. (1994), as amostras presentes nesta região sofreram annealing total em 294 

termos de idade de traços de fissão, como consequência da influência térmica do magmatismo 295 

a aproximadamente 130 Ma . No entanto, isso teria sido efetivamente instantâneo e seria 296 

esperado que todas as idades TFA fossem semelhantes à idade do magmatismo. Desta forma, 297 

Franco-Magalhaes et al. (2010) atribuem as idades mais jovens (&lt;20 Ma) à reativação das 298 

zonas de cisalhamento do Pré-Cambriano e ao soerguimento/exumação da área, levando à 299 

formação de bacias terciarias. A reativação tectônica Cenozoica do embasamento continental 300 

e consequente formação das bacias terciarias também é sugerida por outros autores na 301 

margem sudeste (p. ex., Hiruma et al., 2010; Cogné et al., 2012; Karl et al., 2013; Engelmann 302 

de Oliveira et al., 2016). 303 



15 

 

Ao contrário da margem sudeste, a margem nordeste, na região do cráton São 304 

Francisco, registra idades TFA mais antigas e um episódio de resfriamento durante o 305 

Permiano e Jurássico Inferior, reflexo da Orogenia Gondwanide (Jelinek et al., 2014). Esta 306 

região é típica da região semi-árida do nordeste caracterizada como um pediplano, com relevo 307 

monótono, vales estreitos e vertentes dissecadas, conhecida como Depressão Sertaneja. Os 308 

modelos de história térmica apresentados por Jelinek et al. (2014) não mostram evidência de 309 

resfriamento significativo durante a formação das bacias de margem passiva nesta região, o 310 

que implica que a área não foi significativamente afetada pelos processos tectônicos e 311 

térmicos relacionados ao rifteamento. Os modelos são apoiados pela evolução das bacias do 312 

nordeste, que apresentam fases essencialmente não-magmáticas pré-rifte e rifte (Chang et al., 313 

1992). O magmatismo nesta parte da margem está registrado ao sul (banco de Abrolhos e 314 

Royal Charlotte) e ocorreu durante o estágio pós-rifte, entre 60 e 40 Ma, relacionado ao 315 

movimento da placa Sul-Americana sobre hotspots (Chang et al., 1992, Mizusaki et al., 316 

2002). 317 

As idades TFA da Província Borborema são claramente mais jovens que as idades do 318 

cráton São Francisco, sendo que a maior parte é relacionada ao evento de resfriamento do 319 

Cretaceo (Fig. 8), correspondente à abertura do Oceano Atlântico Sul. Lima et al. (2015), 320 

utilizando métodos sísmicos, sugerem que o soerguimento do Platô Borborema foi causado 321 

por desequilíbrio térmico na crosta durante a ruptura do Gondwana e abertura do Oceano 322 

Atlântico Sul, no período Cretaceo. O desequilíbrio térmico e o magmatismo sin- e pós-rifte 323 

(60-40 Ma) presentes ao longo da margem equatorial brasileira, na Província Borborema 324 

(Mizusaki et al., 2002), influenciaram a evolução dessa margem e registraram esses eventos 325 

nas idades TFA. 326 

Esse padrão de idades TFA e eventos de resfriamento ao longo da margem continental 327 

brasileira não estão apenas relacionados ao processo de rifteamento, mas envolvem outros 328 

processos importantes como: (i) soerguimento isostático em resposta à denudação da margem 329 

continental e sedimentação nas bacias onshore e offshore, sugeridos e detalhados por 330 

Gilchrist &amp;amp; Summerfield (1994) e Gallagher et al. (1994); e, (ii) magmatismo pós-rift e 331 

reativação tectônica das principais estruturas intracontinentais, que ocasionaram uma 332 

denudação localmente acelerada sobreposta ao padrão regional secular (Gallagher e Brown, 333 

1999; Cobbold et al., 2001). 334 

  335 

   336 



16 

 

5 Conclusões 337 

  338 

 Os dados TFA discutidos por diferentes autores ao longo dos anos e integrados neste 339 

trabalho, permitiram estabelecer um modelo de história termotectônica para a margem 340 

continental brasileira, que é complexo e reflete controles litológicos e estruturais. Os 341 

principais resultados são: 342 

 (1) As idades TFA variam de ~385-10 Ma e todas são consideravelmente mais jovens 343 

do que a idade de cristalização ou metamorfismo de suas rochas hospedeiras. A presença de 344 

um grande número de amostras com idades entre 135 e 66 Ma é relacionada à separação 345 

continental e subsequente magmatismo e reativações tectônicas do Cretaceo Superior ao 346 

Paleógeno.  347 

 (2) Os dados TFA da margem continental sudeste brasileira mostram uma tendência 348 

geral semelhante à observada em outras margens do tipo rifte, com idades mais jovens em 349 

direção à costa. 350 

 (3) A maioria das idades TFA da Província Borborema está relacionada ao evento de 351 

resfriamento do Cretaceo, associado à abertura do Oceano Atlântico Sul. 352 

 (4) A Província Mantiqueira e o cráton São Francisco registram os eventos de 353 

resfriamento mais antigos, desde o Ordoviciano e o Permiano, respectivamente, que afetaram 354 

de modo variado diferentes partes destas províncias e refletem as orogenias Famatiniana e 355 

Gondwanide. 356 

 357 

Agradecimentos - Este estudo constitui parte da tese de doutorado da primeira autora junto ao 358 
Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências da UFRGS. 359 
 360 

 361 

Referências bibliográficas 362 

 363 

Almeida, F.F.M. 1977. O Cráton do São Francisco. Revista Brasileira de Geociências, 7: 349-364 

364. 365 

Almeida, F.F.M., Hasui, Y., Brito Neves, B.B. &amp;amp; Fuck, R.A. 1981. Brazilian structural 366 

provinces: an introduction. Earth-Science Reviews, 17(1-2): 1-29. 367 

Amaral, G., Born, H., Hadler, J.C.N., Iunes, P.J., Kawashita, K., Machado Jr., D.L., Oliveira, 368 

E.P., Paulo, S.R. &amp;amp; Tello, C.A.S. 1997. Fission track analysis of apatites from Sao 369 



17 

 

Francisco craton and Mesozoic alcaline-carbonatite complexes from central and 370 

southeastern Brazil. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 10(3): 285-294. 371 

Bicca, M.M., Chemale Jr., F., Jelinek, A.R., Oliveira, C.H.E., Guadagnin, F. &amp;amp; Armstrong, R. 372 

2013. Tectonic evolution and provenance of the Santa Bárbara Group, Camaquã 373 

Mines region, Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 374 

48: 173-192. 375 

Borba, A.W., Lima, E.F., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M., Mizusaki, A.M.P., Sparrenberg, I. &amp;amp; 376 

Barros, C.E. 2003. Significance of Late Paleozoic Fission-track Ages in Volcanic 377 

Rocks from the Lavras Do Sul Region, Southernmost Brazil. Gondwana Research, 6: 378 

79-88. 379 

Borba, A.W., Vignol-Lelargel, M.L.M. &amp;amp; Mizusaki, A.M.P. 2002. Uplift and denudation of 380 

the Caçapava do Sulgranitoids (southern Brazil) during Late Paleozoic and Mesozoic: 381 

constraints from apatite fission-track data. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 382 

15: 683-692. 383 

Brito Neves, B.B. &amp;amp; Fuck, R.A. 2013. Neoproterozoic evolution of the basement of the 384 

South-American platform. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 47: 72-89. 385 

Carmo, I.O. 2005. Geocronologia do Intemperismo Cenozóico no Sudeste do Brasil. Rio de 386 

Janeiro, 134p. Tese de Doutorado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geologia, 387 

Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro. 388 

Chang, H.K., Kowsmann, R.O., Figueiredo, A.M.F. &amp;amp; Bender, A. 1992. Tectonics and 389 

stratigraphy of the East Brazil Rift system: an overview. Tectonophysics, 213(1): 97-390 

138. 391 

Cobbold, P.R., Meisling, K.E. &amp;amp; Mount, V.S. 2001. Reactivation of an obliquely rifted 392 

margin, Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG Bulletin, 85 (11): 393 

1925–1944. 394 

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., &amp;amp; Cobbold, P.R. 2011. Post-rift reactivation of the onshore margin 395 

of southeast Brazil: evidence from apatite (U–Th)/He and fission-track data. Earth and 396 

Planetary Science Letters, 309(1): 118-130. 397 

Cogné, N., Gallagher, K., Cobbold, P.R., Riccomini, C. &amp;amp; Gautheron, C. 2012. Post-breakup 398 

tectonics in southeast Brazil from thermochronological data and combined inverse-399 

forward thermal history modeling. Journal of Geophysical Research, 117: B11413. 400 

Cupertino, J.A. 2000. Evolução tectono-climática na fase Rifte das bacias de Camamu, parte 401 

norte, e sul do Recôncavo, com ênfase na utilização de isótopos estáveis e traços de 402 



18 

 

fissão. Porto Alegre. Tese de Doutorado, Programa de Pós-graduação em Geociências, 403 

Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 404 

Donelick, R.A., O’Sullivan, P.B. &amp;amp; Ketcham, R.A. 2005. Apatite Fission-Track Analysis. In: 405 

Reiners, P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Ed.). Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques, 406 

Interpretations, and Applications. Washington: Mineralogical Society of America, 407 

Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry, v. 58, p. 49-94. 408 

Doranti-Tiritan, C. 2013. Evolução Geomórfica e Modelagem Termocinemática 3D da 409 

Região do Maciço Alcalino de Poços de Caldas (SP/MG). Rio Claro, 160p. Tese de 410 

Doutorado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geologia Regional, Instituto de 411 

Geociências e Ciências Exatas, Universidade Estadual Paulista. 412 

Engelmann de Oliveira, C.H.E., Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F. &amp;amp; Cupertino, J.A. 2016. 413 

Thermotectonic history of the southeastern Brazilian margin: Evidence from apatite 414 

fission track data of the offshore Santos Basin and continental basement. 415 

Tectonophysics, 685: 21-34. 416 

Fracalossi, C.P. 2007. Uso da termocronologia por traços de fissão em apatita no 417 

reconhecimento de áreas de recarga e análises isotópicas de 
234

U/
238

U em águas 418 

subterrâneas do aquífero Itararé no município de Americana (SP). Rio Claro, 81p. 419 

Dissertação de Mestrado, Instituto de Geociências e Ciências Exatas, Universidade 420 

Estadual Paulista. 421 

Franco, A.O., Hackspacher, P.C., Godoy, D.F., Ribeiro, L.F.B. &amp;amp; Guedes, S. 2005. História 422 

Térmica do Maciço Alcalino de Poços de Caldas (SP/ MP) e Adjacências Através da 423 

Análise de Datação Por Traços de Fissão em Apatitas. Revista Brasileira de 424 

Geociências, 35(3): 351-358. 425 

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Hackspacher, P.C., Glasmacher, U.A. &amp;amp; Saad, A.R. 2010. Rift to 426 

post-rift evolution of a “passive” continental margin: the Ponta Grossa Arch, SE 427 

Brazil. International Journal of Earth Sciences, 99(7): 1599-1613. 428 

Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B., Cuglieri, M.A.A., Hackspacher, P.C. &amp;amp; Saad, A.R. 2014. Long-429 

term landscape evolution and post-rift reactivation in the southeastern Brazilian 430 

passive continental margin: Taubaté basin. International Journal of Earth Sciences, 431 

103(2): 441-453. 432 

Gallagher, K. &amp;amp; Brown, R. 1997. The onshore record of passive margin evolution. Journal of 433 

the Geological Society, 154(3): 451-457. 434 



19 

 

Gallagher, K. &amp;amp; Brown, R. 1999. The Mesozoic denudation history of the Atlantic margins of 435 

southern Africa and southeast Brazil and the relationship to offshore 436 

sedimentation. Geological Society, London, Special Publications, 153(1): 41-53.  437 

Gallagher, K., Hawkesworth, C.J. &amp;amp; Mantovani, M.S.M. 1994. The denudation history of the 438 

onshore continental margin of SE Brazil inferred from apatite fission track data. 439 

Journal of Geophysical Research, 99(B9): 18117-18145. 440 

Genaro, D.T. 2008. Contribuição ao conhecimento de processos atuantes no rifteamento 441 

continental, por traços de fissão em zircões e apatitas, aplicados no rift continental do 442 

sudeste do Brasil, bacias de Taubaté, Resende, Volta Redonda e circunvizinhanças. 443 

Rio Claro, 131p. Dissertação de Mestrado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em 444 

Geociências, Universidade Estadual Paulista. 445 

Gilchrist, A.R. &amp;amp; Summerfield, M.A. 1994. Tectonic models of passive margin evolution and 446 

their implications for theories of long-term landscape development. In: Kirkby, M.J. 447 

(Ed.). Process Models and Theoretical Geomorphology. John Wiley and Sons, 448 

Chichester, p. 55-84. 449 

Gleadow, A.J.W. 1981. Fission-track dating methods: what are the real alternatives? Nuclear 450 

Tracks, 5: 3-14. 451 

Godoy. D.F. 2003. História térmica e denudação do maciço alcalino de Poços de Caldas e 452 

circunvizinhanças: Área Norte. Rio Claro, 74p. Trabalho de conclusão de curso, 453 

Instituto de Geociências e Ciências Exatas, Universidade Estadual Paulista. 454 

Godoy, D.F. 2006. Termotectônica por traços de fissão em apatitas dos altos estrutrais de 455 

Pitanga, Pau d'Álho e Jibóia-centro do Estado de São Paulo. Rio Claro, 86p. 456 

Dissertação de Mestrado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, Universidade 457 

Estadual Paulista. 458 

Green, P.F. 1981. A new look at statistics in fission-track dating. Nuclear tracks, 5(1): 77-86. 459 

Hackspacher, P.C., Godoy, D.F., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Neto, J.C.H. &amp;amp; Franco, A.O.B. 2007. 460 

Modelagem térmica e geomorfologia da borda sul do Cráton do São Francisco: 461 

termocronologia por traços de fissão em apatita. Revista Brasileira de Geociências, 462 

37(4): 76-86. 463 

Hackspacher, P.C., Ribeiro, L.F.B., Ribeiro, M.C.S., Fetter, A.H., Hadler Neto, J.C., Tello 464 

Saenz, C.A. &amp;amp; Dantas, E.L. 2004. Consolidation and break-up of the South American 465 

platform in Southeastern Brazil: tectonothermal and denudation histories. Gondwana 466 

Research, 7(1): 91-101. 467 



20 

 

Hadler Neto J.C., Paulo S.R., Iunes P.J., Tello Saenz C.A., Balestrieri M.L., Bigazzi G., 468 

Curvo E.A.C. &amp;amp; Hackspacher P.C. 2001. A PC compatible Brazilian software for 469 

obtaining thermal histories using apatite fission track analysis. Radiation 470 

Measurements, 34:149-154. 471 

Harman, R., Gallagher, K., Brown, R., Raza, A. &amp;amp; Bizzi, L. 1998. Accelerated denudation 472 

and tectonic/geomorphic reactivation of the cratons of northeastern Brazil during the 473 

Late Cretaceous. Journal of Geophysical Research, 103(B11): 27091-27105. 474 

Hiruma, S.T., Riccomini, C., Modenesi-Gauttieri, M.C., Hackspacher, P.C., Hadler Neto, J.C. 475 

&amp;amp; Franco-Magalhaes, A.O.B. 2010. Denudation history of the Bocaina Plateau, Serra 476 

do Mar, southeastern Brazil: relationships to Gondwana breakup and passive margin 477 

development. Gondwana Research, 18: 674-687. 478 

Japsen, P., Bonow, J.M., Green, P.F., Cobbold, P.R., Chiossi, D., Lilletveit, R., Magnavita, 479 

L.P. &amp;amp; Pedreira, A. 2012. Episodic burial and exhumation in NE Brazil after opening 480 

of the South Atlantic. Geological Society of America Bulletin, 124: 800816. 481 

Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F., van der Beek, P.A., Guadagnin, F., Cupertino, J.A. &amp;amp; Viana, A. 482 

2014. Denudation history and landscape evolution of the northern East-Brazilian 483 

continental margin from apatite fission-track thermochronology. Journal of South 484 

American Earth Sciences, 54: 158-181. 485 

Jelinek, A.R., Gomes, C.H., Dias, A.N.C., Guadagnin, F., Chemale, F.Jr. &amp;amp; Souza, I.A. 2010. 486 

Termocronologia aplicada às Geociências: análise por traços de fissão. Pesquisas em 487 

Geociências, 37 (3): 191-203. 488 

Jelinek, A.R., Neto, A.C.B., &amp;amp; Poupeau, G. 2003. Análise por traços de fissão em apatitas do 489 

Distrito Fluorítico de Santa Catarina: relações entre hidrotermalismo e evolução da 490 

margem continental. Brazilian Journal of Geology, 33(3): 289-298. 491 

Karl, M., Glasmacher, U.A., Kollenz, S., Franco-Magalhaes, A.O., Stockli, D.F. &amp;amp; 492 

Hackspacher, P.C. 2013. Evolution of the South Atlantic passive continental margin in 493 

southern Brazil derived from zircon and apatite (U–Th–Sm)/He and fission-track data. 494 

Tectonophysics, 604: 224-244. 495 

Laslett, G.M., Green, P.F., Duddy, I.R. &amp;amp; Gleadow, A.J.W. 1987. Thermal annealing of 496 

fission tracks in apatite 2. A quantitative analysis. Chemical Geology: Isotope 497 

Geoscience Section, 65(1): 1-13. 498 



21 

 

Lima, M.V.A., Berrocal, J., Soares, J.E. &amp;amp; Fuck, R.A. 2015. Deep seismic refraction 499 

experiment in northeast Brazil: New constraints for Borborema province evolution. 500 

Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 58: 335-349. 501 

Macdonald, D., Gomez-Perez, I., Franzese, J., Spalletti, L., Lawver, L., Gahagan, L., ... &amp;amp; 502 

Paton, D. 2003. Mesozoic break-up of SW Gondwana: implications for regional 503 

hydrocarbon potential of the southern South Atlantic. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 504 

20(3): 287-308. 505 

Meisling, K.E., Cobbold, P.R. &amp;amp; Mount, V.S. 2001. Segmentation of an obliquely rifted 506 

margin, Campos and Santos basins, southeastern Brazil. AAPG bulletin, 85(11): 1903-507 

1924. 508 

Milani, E.J. 1997. Evolução tectono-estratigráfica da Bacia do Paraná e seu relacionamento 509 

com a geodinâmica fanerozóica do Gondwana sul-ocidental. Porto Alegre, 255p. Tese 510 

de Doutorado, Instituto de Geociências, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. 511 

Mizusaki, A.M.P., Thomaz-Filho, A., Milani, E.J. &amp;amp; Cesero, P. 2002. Mesozoic and Cenozoic 512 

igneous activity and its tectonic control in northeastern Brazil. Journal of South 513 

American Earth Sciences, 15 (2): 183-198. 514 

Morais Neto, J.M., Green, P.F., Karner, G.D. &amp;amp; Alkmim, F.F. 2008. Age of the Serra do 515 

Martins Formation, Borborema Plateau, northeastern Brazil: constraints from apatite 516 

and zircon fission track analysis. Boletim de Geociências da Petrobras, 16(1): 23-52. 517 

Morais Neto, J.M., Hegarty, K.A., Karner, G.D. &amp;amp; Alkmim, F.F. 2009. Timing and 518 

mechanisms for the generation and modification of the anomalous topography of the 519 

Borborema Province, northeastern Brazil. Marine and Petroleum Geology, 26: 1070-520 

1086. 521 

Neves, S.P. 2003. Proterozoic history of the Borborema province (NE Brazil): correlations 522 

with neighboring cratons and Pan-African belts and implications for the evolution of 523 

western Gondwana. Tectonics, 22: 1031. 524 

Nürnberg, D. &amp;amp; Müller, R.D. 1991. The tectonic evolution of the South Atlantic from Late 525 

Jurassic to present. Tectonophysics, 191: 27–53. 526 

Oliveira, S.G., Hackspacher, P.C., Neto, J.C.H., Iunes, P.J., Paulo, S.R., Ribeiro, L.F.B. &amp;amp; 527 

Saenz, C. A.T. 2008. Constraints on the evolution and thermal history of the 528 

continental platform of southeast Brazil, Sao Paulo state, using apatite fission track 529 

analysis (AFTA). Revista Brasileira de Geociências, 30(1): 107-109. 530 



22 

 

Oliveira, C.H.E., Jelinek, A.R., Chemale, F. &amp;amp; Bernet, M. 2016. Evidence of post-Gondwana 531 

breakup in Southern Brazilian Shield: Insights from apatite and zircon fission track 532 

thermochronology. Tectonophysics, 666: 173-187. 533 

Raab, M.J., Brown, R.W., Gallagher, K., Weber, K. &amp;amp; Gleadow, A.J.W. 2005. Denudational 534 

and thermal history of the Early Cretaceous Brandberg and Okenyenya igneous 535 

complexes on Namibia's Atlantic passive margin. Tectonics, 24: TC3006. 536 

Ribeiro, L.F.B. 2003. Morfotectônica da região centro-leste do estado de São Paulo e áreas 537 

adjacentes de Minas Gerais: Termocronologia &amp;amp; Paleotensões. Rio Claro, 203p. Tese 538 

de Doutorado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geociências, Instituto de Geociências 539 

e Ciências Exatas, Universidade Estadual Paulista. 540 

Ribeiro, L.F.B., Hackspacher, P.C., Ribeiro, M.C.S., Hadler Neto, J.C., Tello Saenz, C.A., 541 

Iunes, P.J., Franco, A.B. &amp;amp; Godoy, D.F. 2005. Thermotectonic and fault dynamic 542 

analysis of Precambrian basement and tectonic constraints within the Parana basin. 543 

Radiation Measurements, 39:669-673. 544 

Ribeiro, M.C.S., Hackspacher, P.C., Ribeiro, L.F.B. &amp;amp; Neto, J.C.H. 2011. Evolução tectônica 545 

e denudacional da Serra do Mar (SE/Brasil) no limite entre o Cretáceo Superior e 546 

Paleoceno, utilizando análises de traços de fissão e U-TH/HE em apatitas. Revista 547 

Brasileira de Geomorfologia, 12: 3-14. 548 

Silva, J.S. 2010. Reconstrução termocronologica do maciço alcalino de Poços de Caldas e 549 

áreas adjacentes por traços de fissão e (U-Th-Sm)\he em apatitas e zircão. Rio Claro. 550 

Trabalho de Conclusão de Curso, Instituto de geociências e Ciências Exatas, 551 

Universidade Estadual Paulista. 552 

Silva, L.G.A.E., 2006. A Interação entre os Eventos Tectônicos e a Evolução Geomorfológica 553 

da Serra da Bocaina, Sudeste do Brasil. Rio de Janeiro, 273p. Tese de Doutorado, 554 

Programa de Pós Graduação em Análise de Bacias e Faixas Móveis, Universidade do 555 

Estado do Rio de Janeiro. 556 

Soares, C.J., Guedes, S., Jonckheere, R., Hadler, J.C., Passarella, S.M. &amp;amp; Dias, A.N.C. 2015. 557 

Apatite fission?track analysis of Cretaceous alkaline rocks of Ponta Grossa and Alto 558 

Paranaíba Arches, Brazil. Geological Journal. 559 

Souza, D.H., Hackspacher, P.C., Doranti-Tiritan, C. &amp;amp; Godoy, D.F. 2014. Comparação da 560 

dinâmica evolutiva, em longo e curto prazo, entre o Planalto de Poços de Caldas e o 561 

Planalto de São Pedro de Caldas. Revista Brasileira de Geomorfologia, 16(2). 562 



23 

 

Tagami, T. &amp;amp; O’Sullivan, P.B. 2005. Fundamentals of fission-track thermochronology. In: 563 

Reiners, P.W., Ehlers, T.A. (Ed.). Low-Temperature Thermochronology: Techniques, 564 

Interpretations, and Applications. Washington: Mineralogical Society of America, 565 

Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry, v. 58, p. 19-47 566 

Tello Saenz, C., Hackspacher, P.C., Neto, J.H., Iunes, P.J., Guedes, S., Ribeiro, L.F.B. &amp;amp; 567 

Paulo, S.R. 2003. Recognition of Cretaceous, Paleocene, and Neogene tectonic 568 

reactivation through apatite fission-track analysis in Precambrian areas of southeast 569 

Brazil: association with the opening of the South Atlantic Ocean. Journal of South 570 

American Earth Sciences, 15(7): 765-774. 571 

Torsvik, T.H., Rousse, S., Labails, C. &amp;amp; Smethurst, M.A. 2009. A new scheme for the 572 

opening of the South Atlantic Ocean and the dissection of an Aptian salt basin. 573 

Geophysical Journal International, 177(3): 1315-1333. 574 

Turner, J.P., Green, P.F., Holford, S.P. &amp;amp; Lawrence, S.R. 2008. Thermal history of the Rio 575 

Muni (West Africa) e NE Brazil margins during continental breakup. Earth and 576 

Planetary Science Letters, 270: 354-367. 577 

Van Schmus, W.R., Kosuch, M. &amp;amp; Brito Neves, B.B. 2011. Precambrian history of the Zona 578 

Transversal of the Borborema Province. Journal of South American Earth Sciences, 579 

31: 227-252. 580 

Zalán, P.V., Wolff, S., Astolfi, M.A.M., Vieira, I.S., Conceição, J.C.J., Appi, V.T., Santos 581 

Neto, E.V., Cerqueira, J.R. &amp;amp; Marques, A. 1991. The Paraná Basin, Brazil. In: 582 

Leighton (Ed.). Interior Cratonic Basins. Memoir 51. AAPG, Tulsa, Oklahoma, p. 583 

681-708. 584 

Zalán, P.V., Wolff, S., Conceição, A., Marques, M.A.M., Astolfi, I.S., Vieira, V.T. &amp;amp; Appi, 585 

O.A. 1990. Bacia do Paraná. In: Raja Gabaglia, G. P. e Milani, E.J. (Eds.). Origem e 586 

Evolução de Bacias Sedimentares. Ed. Gávea, Petrobras, p.135-168. 587 


</field>
	</doc>
</add>