<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.15317</field>
		<field name="filename">2173_Dissertacao_Almeida_Helio_Corrigida.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Hélio Miguel dos Reis Almeida

Mesoscale Variability of the Brazil
Current in the Santos Bight: is it locally or

remotely forced?

A thesis submitted in partial fulfillment of

the requirements for the degree of Master of

Sciences in Oceanography, with emphasis in

Physical Oceanography, Instituto Oceanográ-

fico, Universidade de São Paulo.

Advisor: Prof. Dr. Ilson Carlos Almeida

da Silveira.

São Paulo
2017



Universidade de São Paulo

Instituto Oceanográfico

Mesoscale variability of the Brazil Current within the Santos

Bight: is it locally or remotely forced?

by

Hélio Miguel dos Reis Almeida

Versão Corrigida

A thesis submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Master of

Sciences in Oceanography, with emphasis in Physical Oceanography, Instituto Oceanográfico,

Universidade de São Paulo.

Evaluated in ______ / ______ / ________

——————————————————————————— ———————

Prof. Dr. Grade

——————————————————————————— ———————

Prof. Dr. Grade

——————————————————————————— ———————

Prof. Dr. Grade





“Mudar pra melhor, com certeza, quer

dizer que ia mudar melhor. Já tava bom,

diz que ia mudar ele pra melhor, não tava

muito bom. Tava meio ruim também,

tava ruim, agora parece que piorou.”

Unknown author, 2013

“Nós vamos deixar uma meta aberta.

Quando a gente atingir a meta, nós

dobramos a meta.”

Dilma Rousseff, 2015



Acknowledgements

My most heartfelt thanks goes to my advisor, professor, mentor and above all that, a dear

friend prrofessor Ilson Silveira. These two years of my MSc would not have been the same

without his advising, help and encouragement to always pursue my goals. I feel truly thankful

that he took a leap of faith on me. It has been inspiring to work with you and to learn from

you and your constant teaching passion. Working with you for sure shaped the researcher that

I will be, and for that I will always be thankful. Thanks for teaching me in several ways how

nonlinear both science and life are.

Secondly, a thanks to my parents who always stood strong no matter what and despite the

distance always encouraged me. For that I will always be thankful. This chapter in my life

would not be possible without their support.

I deeply thank professor Wandrey Watanabe who gave a fundamental help in the most diffi-

cult times of this work. Thank you for the helpful insights and precious suggestions. It was a

privilege to work and learn with you.

I would like to thank the IO-USP professors Belmiro Castro, Paulo Polito and Olga Sato for

their precious teaching. I proudly present myself as physical oceanographer today and a big

part of that is because of you.

I also thank professor Glenn Flierl for his precise insights and discussions. His help was

crucial to the development of this work and it was a privilege to discuss my findings with him.

I am deeply thankful to my brother Nuno Almeida who through good and bad times, troughs

and crests of happiness, was there for me. I could not be more thankful to you. You learned to

calm my spirit and to always have the right word to say. You’re the best brother in the world.

I am truly thankful to my labmates, Filipe Pereira, Ágata Braga, Daniel Melo, Guido, Fabrí-

cio Lapolli, Vadim Harlamov, Giuliana Lukine Tiago Biló, André Palóczy and Gilberto Watan-

abe. Thank you for the coffee breaks and good talks.

Although being labmates I am specially thankful to Pinguim (Dante Napolitano) and Patola

i



(Patrícia Baldasso) for being more than that and supporting me in a period that even I could not.

Part of the tenacity that I had in this two years was because of your support and advices.

I could not be more thankful to Iury Sousa who, although knowing me for only two years,

became my younger brother on the other side of the ocean. Thank you for keeping up with my

temper and for being there through good and bad times.

My dear Débora, there are not enough words to express how much I am thankful to have

you in my life. You made the problems seem small and easier to smile. Thank you for always

supporting me and believing in me even more than myself. Thanks for the help and support and

the laughs even after rough days.

I would like to thank to Nancy, the nice Japanese who became a dear friend during these two

years. I am deeply thankful for the conversations and the coffee breaks and ginger in this final

stage to relieve the stress.

I also like to thank to my São Paulo friends Matheus Cortezi, Mariana Benites, Márcio

Borges, Dalton, Thiago Almeida, Guilherme Caneli, Ana Paula Loureiro, Aninha Losnak.

A special thanks to Kamila and her family, Priscila Verlaine, Gui Bezerra, Shyveres, Hadassa,

Rosangela and Adauto. I can’t fully express how thankful I am to you all for all the uncondi-

tional help in the first stage of the adventure. You will always be my Brazilian family.

I would like to thank to my friends in Portugal, Hugo Oliveira, Inês Vaz, Tiago Pereira,

Evelyn Santos, Diana Nunes, Cristiana Sengo, Américo Ribeiro, Juan Oliveira, Filipe Tártaro,

Pedro Neves. Despite the distance and timezone they were always there for me during these

years. Always managed time to keep in touch and were there during good and bad moments.

A special thanks to my professor and mentor professor João Miguel Dias who was always

there to talk about everything and any thought along the path. I also thank him for being the

responsible for my early passion for physical oceanography. I owe to him the early passion and

will to teach.

I want to thank the Petróleo Brasileiro SA (PETROBRAS) for providing the CERES V data

set. I also deeply thank Dr. Wellington Ceccopieri Belo coordinator and idealizer of the CERES

project and an enthusiastic responsible for the LaDO-PETROBRAS partnership and supported

high-quality research.

Thanks to the Coordination of Improvement of Personal Higher Education (CAPES) that

provided the funding through the project "Rede de Estudos da Corrente do Brasil na Margem

Continental Sudeste-Sul (REMARSUL)".



Last but not least, because all the reasons above and even more, thanks Brazil.



List of Figures

1.1 Schematics of the surface circulation of the South Atlantic. Black solid lines

represent streamlines of the main currents and arrows represent the currents

direction. The South Atlantic Subtropical Gyre (?10°S-40°S, red solid lines) is
delimited by the South Equatorial Current (north), the Brazil Current (west) and

South Atlantic Current (south). The gray shades indicate the major topographic

features on the region. Adapted from Talley et al. (2011). . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2

1.2 The Brazil Current thickening along the Brazilian margin: (A) a three-dimensional

sketch of the South Equatorial Current (SEC) and Brazil Current (BC) and the

water masses being transported by both flow; (B) diagramatic representation of

the three SEC bifurcations, i.e. surface, pycnoclinic and intermediate. The ar-

rows represent poleward flow if pointing to the left or equatorward flow, if point-

ing to the right. Thicker arrows aim to represent the water mass at which the

core of the BC, Intermediate Western Boundary Current (IWBC), North Brazil

Under Current (NBUC) and Deep Western Boundary Current (DWBC) are found. 4

1.3 The Santos Bifurcation (SBi) structure as inferred from trajectories of ARGO

floats to the SBi: (A): original ARGO trajectories with floats which veered to

the north to join the IWBC are marked in green, and the ones which veered south

to join the BC are marked in cyan. The few magenta trajectories correspond to

float immersions greater than 1050 dbar. (B): Averaged float velocities in 1?×1?

boxes. Blue arrows are averaged velocities less than 5 cm s?1, yellow arrows

averaged velocities greater 5 cm s?1. According to Legeais et al. (2013). . . . . 5

1.4 Schematic of the two patterns by which Western Boundary Currents (WBCs)

separate from the continental margins: (A) smooth separation and Western

Boundary Current (WBC) extension formation. (B) reflection with a zonally-

damped stationary wave formed. Adapted from da Silveira et al. (1999). . . . . 6

iv



1.5 Schematics of Stommel’s explanation for a weaker and shallowed BC compared

to a stronger and deeper Gulf Stream (GS). The net volume transport budget

includes the wind and buoyancy driven flows. blue represents northward flow

and red, southward flow. Adapted from Stommel (1965). . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7

1.6 The four-layer Meridional Overturnig Circulation (MOC) global configuration

proposed by Schmitz (1995). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8

1.7 The updated Stommel (1961) conceptual model for the BC vertical structure

based on combined wind and MOC forcings. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8

1.8 The study area geographical limits and a schematic representation of mean large

scale circulation within. The arrow colors represent distinct water masses being

transported by the flow regime: Tropical Water (TW)-South Atlantic Central

Water (SACW) (red), Antarctic Intermediate Water (AAIW)-Upper Circumpolar

Deep Water (UCDW) (green) and North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) (blue).

Gray shades indicate the major topographic features on the region. . . . . . . . 9

1.9 Sea Surface Temperature (SST) field for the Santos Basin (SB) at 14/08/2005

with the BC meandering from Cape São Tomé (CST) to Cape Santa Marta (CSM).

Data from level 4 Multiscale Ultrahigh Resolution (MUR) of the Group for

High Resolution Sea Surface Temperature (GHRSST) analysis provided by

NASA. Quiver of geostrophic velocity from AVISO to the same day. . . . . . . 10

1.10 Instability wave propagation within the SBi as identified by Fernandes et al.

(2009). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11

1.11 Linear baroclinic instability phase speed and growth for for MARLIM, C3, and

W333 moorings: (A) growth rate and (B) phase speed. Source: Rocha et al.

(2014) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12

2.1 Comparison between the original AVISO Mean Dynamic Topography (MDT)

and the corrected MDT used in this work. (A): blue solid contours the ? provided

by AVISO and the red dashed contours the ? calculated from the 22 years data.

(B): the percentage of increasing of the ? compared with AVISO provided MDT,

black solid line the BC mean position in calculated ?. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17

2.2 Study area, yellow box the region used to calculate the climatological Brunt–Väisälä

profile. Gray shades indicate the major topographic features on the region. . . . 18



2.3 Example of annual signal adjustment for 5 years of data at one point in x-axis

of the Hovmöller diagram. Green line D (t ) is the Sea Level Anomaly (SLA)

signal and blue line Y (t ) the adjusted seasonal signal. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 19

2.4 Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) band-pass filter on SLA time series for the grid

point at 25.375?S and 44.375?W for the first 5 years of data. (A): blue line is the

raw data, green line the data filtered with FFT. (B): red line is the spectral power

[m2 day?1], yellow dashed line is in the 92 day period position, black dashed

lines the limits of 10% from central period and shaded black area is the portion

of the spectre line used to reconstruct the filtered data. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21

2.5 Example of the pathway and wavelength estimate using the SLA correlation

coefficient field. (A): SLA [m] fictitious field with a wave signal propagating

between 1000 and 1500 in y-axis. Rest of field is random noise. (B): correlation

field with a control point where the wave happens, magenta dot the position of

control time series. (C): orrelation field with a control point where there is no

presence of the wave, magenta dot the position of control time series. . . . . . . 22

2.6 Radon transform illustrative scheme. The gray square represent the original

data being rotated. Blue dashed line represent a relative sum of the radon space

at each angle for all r axis, being the angles 0?, 45? and 67.5?. . . . . . . . . . . 23

2.7 Mean Dynamic Topography map with filled contours as height in meters. The

green line is the path along the BCaxis chosen to do the Hovmöller diagram,

starting at the green dot and ending at the red dot, the black dot indicates the

mean latitude of the SBi along the green line (Rocha et al., 2014). . . . . . . . . 25

2.8 Hovmöller diagram of SLA for 22 year and subset of 2007-2010. . . . . . . . . . 26

2.9 Spectral mean energy [m2 day?1] for periods between 20 and 180 days, com-

puted to the north of the SBi. Red dot the period of maximum energy. . . . . . . 27

2.10 Spectral determination of most important wavenumber. (A) Spectral energy of

the Hovmöller diagram [Lo g 10 m2 day?1 km?1]. Blue line the bandpass filter

box centered in period of 92 days and range of ±10%. (B) Wavenumber spec-
trum [m2 km?1], black dots represent spectral resolution and red dot dominant

wavenumber. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 28



2.11 Correlation coefficient field of the SLA filtered data in to 92-D signal. (A): map

of correlation coefficient, green dot the position used to correlate with the rest

of the field and black line the Hovmöller diagram path used for the BC axis. (B):

same correlation coefficient field, black line the new Hovmöller diagram path

specific to this wave, green dot is the start and red cross the end of the path. . . 30

2.12 Same as the Figure 2.10 but for the new Hovmöller diagram path in Figure 2.11A. 31

2.13 Hovmöller diagram for six years of data along 92 wave path and data filtered

with bi-dimensional finite impulse response (FIR2D). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 32

2.14 Same as the Figure 2.9 but to the south of the bifurcation. Two red dots represent

the periods of 68 and 148 days. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33

2.15 Spectral determination of most important wavenumber for each maximum in

Figure 2.14. (A): spectral energy of Hovmöller diagram [Lo g 10 m2 day?1

km?1]. Blue lines represent the box where the spectrum was cut between range

of ±10% of the central period, solid line for 68 day period and dashed for 148.
(B): spectral mean power [m2 km?1], black dots represent spectral resolution

and red dot dominant wavenumber, solid line for 68 day and dashed for 148. . . 34

2.16 Same as Figure 2.11 but with data filtered in 68 day period. . . . . . . . . . . . . 35

2.17 Same as Figure 2.15 but for 68 day signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path

defined in Figure 2.16B. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 36

2.18 Same as Figure 2.13 but for 68-D signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path

defined in Figure 2.16B. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 36

2.19 Correlation field of data filtered to 148 days period. Path used to Hovmöller of

BC and new pass specific to the wave . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 38

2.20 Spectral determination of wavenumber for 68 day signal. . . . . . . . . . . . . . 39

2.21 Same as Figure 2.13 but for 148 day signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path

defined in Figure 2.19B. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40

2.22 Dispersion relation of known phenomena, green line dispersion relation of barotropic

and red line first baroclinic mode linear Rossby waves, black dashed line the

nondispersive line (NDL) f, blue dot the 148 day signal and blue star the 92 day

signal. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 45



2.23 Wavenumber frequency spectrum for the 92-D wave pathway. Spectral energy

[Lo g 10m2d a y ?1k m?1], black solid line the dispersion relation of first mode

linear Rossby waves (RW), white dashed line the NDL for this waves and blue

start the 92-D wave. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 46

2.24 Same as Figure 2.23 but for the 148-D wave pathway. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 47

3.1 The CERES V cruise Vessel Mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler (VMADCP)

sampling tracks (thick solid black lines). Solid red lines correspond to the tran-

sects used in this work to build the velocity sections. The color grading under-

neath the tracks denotes the bathymetry of the study area. The black dashed

line marks the position of the 200m isobath, which is the most accepted depth

to represent the shelf break in SB. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49

3.2 Maps of the CERES V. (A): observational streamfunction ?. (B): the associated

interpolation error at 30m. The gray area represents depths shallower than 100

m; the mangenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break position. . . . . . . . . . 51

3.3 Comparison between the (A) CERES V ?o and (B) AVISO streamfunction ?a

fields during the cruise period. The black solid line delimits the CERES V sam-

pling area. The gray area represents depths shallower than 100 m; the magenta

dashed curve denotes the shelf break position. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 52

3.4 Comparison between (A) the AVISO streamfunction field (?a ) during the CERES

V cruise and (B) its FFT-filtered version for a band centered in 68 days (?68).

The gray area represents depths shallower than 100 m; the mangenta dashed

curve denotes the shelf break position. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 53

3.5 The 68-D filtered total and anomaly AVISO streamfunction fields (?68 and

??68)for the CERES V cruise period. The gray area represents depths shallower

than 100 m; the mangenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break position. . . . . 54

3.6 The 68-D wave propagation: (A), (B), (C), (D), (E) and (F). The gray area

represents depths shallower than 100 m; the magenta dashed curve denotes the

shelf break position. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 55

3.7 Hovmöller diagram of the streamfuction anomaly of the AVISO series centered

at the CERES V period. The black arrows mark the anticyclone (crest) and

the cyclone (trough) of the 68-D wave captured by the cruise sampling. The

magenta dashed line denotes the CSM location. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56



3.8 The Jacobian between the CERES V ? field and the filtered AVISO ? field. . . 57

3.9 The VMADCP tracks (black thick solid lines) overlaid on the CERES V 30m

streamfunction field. The red thick solid line highlights the two transects which

vertical structure will be shown and described in this subsection. The gray area

represents depths shallower than 100 m; the mangenta dashed curve denotes the

shelf break position. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 58

3.10 Vertical section of the VMADCP profiled velocity of transect #3 (the northern red

transect in Figure 3.9). The black area represents the topography, and the ma-

genta dashed line the position of outermost station of lowered Acoustic Doppler

Current Profiler (LADCP) top-bottom profile carried out during the cruise and

described by Biló (2015). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 59

3.11 Southern red transect in Figure 3.9. Filed contour of cross-transect velocity,

black area the shelf break and slope and magenta dashed line the limit of LADCP

collected during the cruise and used by Biló (2015). . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 60



List of Tables

2.1 Main spectral characteristics of each dominant signal to south and north of SBi. 41

x



List of Acronyms

AAIW Antarctic Intermediate Water

ADT Absolute Dynamic Topography

BC Brazil Current

CF Cape Frio

CFE Cape Frio Eddy

CODAS Common Ocean Data Access System

CSM Cape Santa Marta

CST Cape São Tomé

DWBC Deep Western Boundary Current

EAC East Australian Current

FFT Fast Fourier Transform

FFT2D two dimensional Fast Fourier Transform

FIR2D bi-dimensional finite impulse response

GS Gulf Stream

IWBC Intermediate Western Boundary Current

KC Kuroshio Current

LADCP lowered Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler

MC Malvinas Current

xi



MDT Mean Dynamic Topography

MOC Meridional Overturnig Circulation

NADW North Atlantic Deep Water

NBUC North Brazil Under Current

NDL nondispersive line

OA Objective Analysis

PE primitive equation

PV potential vorticity

QG quasi-geostrophic

RC Recirculation Cell

RW Rossby waves

SAC South Atlantic Current

SACW South Atlantic Central Water

SASG South Atlantic Subtropical Gyre

SB Santos Basin

SBi Santos Bifurcation

SEC South Equatorial Current

SLA Sea Level Anomaly

SST Sea Surface Temperature

TW Tropical Water

UCDW Upper Circumpolar Deep Water

VMADCP Vessel Mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler

VTR Vitória-Trindade Ridge



WBC Western Boundary Current

WBCs Western Boundary Currents

WOA13 World Ocean Atlas 13



Contents

Page

List of Figures ix

List of Tables x

List of Acronyms xi

Abstract xvi

Resumo xviii

1 Introduction 1

1.1 Large Scale Circulation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2

1.1.1 Description . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2

1.1.2 Forcing . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6

1.2 The Study Area . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8

1.3 The BC mesoscale variability . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9

1.4 Thesis Hypothesis and Objectives . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13

1.4.1 Hypothesis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13

1.4.2 Objectives . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13

2 Mesoscale Variability from Satellite Altimetry 15

2.1 Datasets . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15

2.1.1 Altimetry . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15

2.1.2 Climatological hydrographic data . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17

2.2 Methods . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18

xiv



2.2.1 Annual signal removal . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18

2.2.2 Fast Fourier Transform . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 19

2.2.3 Correlation field . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21

2.2.4 Radon Transform . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 23

2.2.5 Explained variance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 23

2.3 Results and Discussion . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24

2.3.1 North of the Santos Bifurcation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 27

2.3.2 South of the Santos Bifurcation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 32

3 Quasi-Synoptic Observations 48

3.1 Dataset . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48

3.1.1 In situ Quasi-Synoptic Velocity Measurements . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48

3.2 Methods: Objective Mapping . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49

3.3 Results and Discussion . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50

3.3.1 Near-Surface Streamfunction Fields . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50

3.3.2 Velocity Vertical Sections . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 58

4 Summary and Conclusions 62

4.1 Future work . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65

Bibliography 72

xv



Abstract

The Brazil Current (BC) is possibly one of the least studied western boundary currents

(WBCs) in the world ocean. Its unique vertical structure makes this a different WBC in terms

of velocity and transport. Although significant progress has been made over the last decade,

the BC system variability within the Santos Bight (SB, 23?S-28?S) is very poorly understood

despite its strategic role for Brazil in terms of energy. The BC thickens and changes its vertical

structure and dynamical modal composition as it crosses the SB. As it enters the bight by trying

to contour Cape Frio (Cf, 23?S), the BC is about 500 m deep. As the current leaves the bight

south of Cape Santa Marta (CSM, 28?S) it is 1300 m. These differences in thickness and ac-

companying velocity vertical shear are due to the impinging branch of the intermediate South

Equatorial Current (SEC) generating the so called Santos Bifurcation (SBi). We here investigate

the subinertial variability of the BC system within the SB primarily using satellite altimetry data

and some traditional spectral analysis techniques. We also analyzed quasi-synoptic observations

of an oceanographic cruise, which was part of the IOUSP-PETROBRAS CERES Experiment.

We identified that there are different phenomena occurring to the north and to the south of the

bifurcation and this might be caused by the SBi feature itself and/or the consequential change in

the BC vertical structure downstream. North of the SBi, we detected oscillations with period of

92 days and a wavelength of 490 km and which represent about a fifth of the BC variability at

25?S. The 92-day oscillations are nonlinear vorticity waves, which are originated to the east of

35?W and propagate zonally towards the BC axis. These waves then perturb the current exciting

oscillatory motions of the same period and which propagate downstream. South of the SBi axis

(?28?S), we identified two different maxima in the ??k spectrum. They correspond to oscilla-
tions with periods (wavelengths) of 68 and 148 days (397 km and 790 km). The longer wave is

also a baroclinic first-mode nonlinear vorticity waves propagating with westward phase speed

of the nondispersive planetary Rossby waves of same period. They are originated in the ocean

interior and we were able to track its signal as far as 5?W. The 68-day waves has its existence

xvi



limited to vicinities of the BC. Phase speeds have approximately the BC axis orientation and

they can only be clearly detected between ? 27?S and ? 32?S. This propagating signal accounts
with a variance of ?21% on the BC axis. Quasi-synoptic observations allowed the mapping of
a anticyclone and a cyclone of such waves. They seem to have modal composition very similar

to the BC itself, which might provide additional evidence of local origin.

Keywords: Brazil Current, Subinertial Variability, Vorticity Waves, Nondispersive Line, San-

tos Bight.

xvii



Resumo

A Corrente do Brasil (CB) é provavelmente a Corrente de Contorno Oeste (CCO) menos

estudada dos oceanos mundiais. A sua estrutura vertical única es faz dela uma CCO diferente

em termos de velocidade e transporte. Apesar dos avanços significativos na última década, a

variabilidade da CB na Bacia de Santos (BS, 23?S-28?S) ainda é pouco conhecida, apesar do

papel estratégico da região na matriz energética brasileira. A CB se espessa mudando a sua

estrutura vertical e muda sua estrutura dinâmica no domínio da BS. Na região de Cabo Frio

(23?S) a corrente tem cerca de 500 m de profundidade. Ao sair da BS na região do Cabo de

Santa Marta (28?S) a corrente se estende até cerca de 1300 m. Estas variações na espessura

da corrente e consequente diferença no cisalhamento vertical de velocidade ocorrem devido à

presença da Corrente Sul Equatorial em nível intermediário na região gerando a Bifurcação

de Santos (BiS). Neste trabalho investigamos a variabilidade subinercial da CB na Bacia de

Santos usando primeiramente dado alimétrico e um conjunto de análise espectral. Foram depois

estudados fenômenos geradores dessa variabilidade com dados quasi-sinóticos do um cruzeiro

oceanográfico CERES V do conjunto IOUSP-PETROBRAS. Foram identificados fenômenos

diferentes no norte e sul da Bifurcação de Santos e esta diferença é provavelmente devido à

presença da bifurcação ou à mudança que esta causa na estrutura da CB. Ao norte da BiS

foi identificada uma oscilação com período de 92 dias e comprimento de onda de 490 km

explicando um quinto da variabilidade da CB em 25?S. A oscilação de 92 dias está relacionada

com ondas de vorticidade não lineares originadas a leste da corrente em ?35?W e se propagam
zonalmente até ao eixo da corrente. Estas ondas perturbam a corrente originando oscilações

com mesmo período e que propagam ao longo do eixo da corrente. Ao sul da BiS (?27?S)
foram identificados dois máximos no espectro k ??. Os máximos correspondem a oscilações
com período (comprimento de onda) de 68 e 148 dias (397 e 790 km). A onda com maior

comprimento de onda é também uma onda de vorticidade de primeiro modo baroclínico não

linear propagando para oeste com velocidade de fase de ondas de Rossby não dispersivas. Estas

xviii



ondas são originadas no interior da bacia oceânica e seu sinal foi identificado chegando até

5?W. A onda de 68 dias existe apenas no domínio da CB. Esta onda propaga fase num eixo

aproximadamente paralelo à CB e são detadas de forma clara apenas entre ? 27?S e ? 32?S.
Esta onda explica uma variância da CB de ?21% ao longo do seu eixo. Observações quasi-
sinóticas permitiram mapear um anticiclone e um ciclone associado a essa onda. Os vórtices

aparentam uma estrutura modal muito semelhante à da corrente.

Descritores: Corrente do Brasil, Variabilidade Subinercial, Ondas de Vorticidades, Linha

não dispersiva, Bacia de Santos.

xix



Chapter 1

Introduction

The Brazil Current (BC) is likely to be the least studied among of all the subtropical Western

Boundary Currents (WBCs). While only in the last twenty years, a more thorough kinematic pic-

ture of its vertical structure along its poleward path has emerged from the literature, its dynamics

is very much unknown. The first scientific article discussing possible dynamical mechanisms

which would explain its vigorous meandering off Southeast Brazil was published only in 2008

(Silveira et al., 2008). Moreover, most of the knowledge regarding the BC mesoscale variabil-

ity is restricted to the so-called "two-cape region" (22?S-24?S), which encompasses Cape São

Tomé (CST), the Campos Bight and Cape Frio (CF).

Due to its recent and growing relevance to Brazil’s energy backbone, and of course, due

to climate change understanding in the South Atlantic, the area corresponding to the Santos

Basin (SB) continental margin should be explored in terms of the BC mesoscale variability as

well as the associated sources and triggers. The current thesis aims to describe how and at

which time scales the BC meanders within the 23?S-30?S latitude range, as well as speculate

about the dynamics associated with such variabilities.

This initial chapter is organized as follows. In section 1.1, we overview the literature com-

prising the BC mean pattern and its connection to the South Atlantic Subtropical Gyre (SASG). In

section 1.3, we revise the known mesoscale variability of the BC. We present thesis motivation

and hypothesis, and the overall as well as the specific objectives in section 1.4.

1



1.1 Large Scale Circulation

1.1.1 Description

The WBCs, which close the world ocean subtropical gyres, are probably among the most

remarkable and studied large-scale features in Physical Oceanography. These currents are de-

scribed as narrow jets (width of 100-150 km), which flow poleward and serve as ducts for trans-

porting heat and salt from tropical to subtropical latitudes. Therefore, they play an important

role in regulating the climate and may influence the weather in such meridional range.

Figure 1.1: Schematics of the surface circulation of the South Atlantic. Black solid lines rep-
resent streamlines of the main currents and arrows represent the currents direction. The South
Atlantic Subtropical Gyre (?10°S-40°S, red solid lines) is delimited by the South Equatorial
Current (north), the Brazil Current (west) and South Atlantic Current (south). The gray shades
indicate the major topographic features on the region. Adapted from Talley et al. (2011).

The BC is the Western Boundary Current (WBC) which closes the SASG (Figure 1.1). Obser-

vations have consistently shown the BC as the weakest and shallowest (averaged over its entire

southward path) current compared with other WBCs, such as the Gulf Stream (GS), the Kuroshio

Current (KC), the East Australian Current (EAC), and the Agulhas Current (Talley et al., 2011).

The BC structure changes importantly with latitude, as the current thickens and increases its

2



volume transport. The thickening of the BC along its path is due to the unique vertical struc-

ture of South Atlantic’s South Equatorial Current (SEC). The SEC bifurcates at three different

latitudes as it impinges itself on Brazilian continental margin. As consequence of this SEC

"stratified" bifurcation structure, the SASG diminishes in meridional extension with depth. The

gyre is virtually 30? wide at surface and only about 12? at intermediate depths (600-1300 m).

The first (from north to south) of these three bifurcations (Figure 1.2) occurs at ? 14?S and
is responsible for the origin of the BC itself. North of the Vitória-Trindade Ridge (VTR), the BC

is basically a mixed-layer, no more than 200 m thick and transporting 2 Sv (1 Sv =106m3s?1) of

Tropical Water (TW) poleward (Soutelino et al., 2011, 2013). The second bifurcation occurs at

? 20?S and thickens the BC to 500 m transporting also South Atlantic Central Water (SACW) in
addition to TW. Its volume transport can reach 6-10 Sv and a vertical extent (Figure 1.2) which

includes the pycnocline (Campos et al., 1995; Silveira et al., 2004). The third and southermost

bifurcation is commonly referred in the literature as the Santos Bifurcation (SBi), and occurs at

intermediate levels between 25?S and 28?S (Boebel et al., 1999; Rodrigues et al., 2007; Legeais

et al., 2013; Rocha et al., 2014)(Figure 1.3).

This bifurcation decreases the vertical shear changing the BC from a almost purely baroclinic

jet (? 70% baroclinic) to a more barotropic (? 56% barotropic) (Rocha et al., 2014). South of
SBi, the BC is present from the surface and to intermediate levels over the shelf break, continental

slope and São Paulo Plateau. It flows poleward transporting TW, SACW, Antarctic Intermediate

Water (AAIW) and Upper Circumpolar Deep Water (UCDW) up to more than 18 Sv (e.g., Zemba,

1991; Stramma and England, 1999; Mémery et al., 2000). Beneath the BC system, there is

the Deep Western Boundary Current (DWBC) transports North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW)

bordering the Brazilian continental rise and adjacent abyssal plain (e.g., Meinen et al., 2012;

Garzoli et al., 2015) (Figure 1.2).

3



Figure 1.2: The Brazil Current thickening along the Brazilian margin: (A) a three-dimensional
sketch of the SEC and BC and the water masses being transported by both flow; (B) diagramatic
representation of the three SEC bifurcations, i.e. surface, pycnoclinic and intermediate. The
arrows represent poleward flow if pointing to the left or equatorward flow, if pointing to the
right. Thicker arrows aim to represent the water mass at which the core of the BC, IWBC, NBUC
and DWBC are found.

The BC separates from the margin at 38?S-40?S as it "collides" with the Malvinas Cur-

rent (MC). Volume transport estimates from the literature are on the 30-46 Sv range poleward

(Gordon and Greengrove, 1986; Rodrigues et al., 2010; Rocha et al., 2014; Schmid, 2014). De-

spite the BC being weaker then the GS, Gordon and Greengrove (1986) identified that the growth

rate of the BC transport along its path (? 5%) is similar to that of the other WBC.
As all southern hemisphere WBCs, the BC retroflects as it leaves the western boundary (Cam-

pos and Olson, 1991; da Silveira et al., 1999). This convoluted way of separating do not yield

to a nearly zonal extension to the east of the detachment latitude, as observed in the GS or KC

(Figure 1.4). Rather, the BC wraps itself on a large anticyclonic lobe and a zonally-damped sta-

tionary wave pattern develops. The formation of the South Atlantic Current (SAC) occurs only

to the west of the retroflection anticyclone. The SAC represents the southern border of the SASG

4



Figure 1.3: The SBi structure as inferred from trajectories of ARGO floats to the SBi: (A): orig-
inal ARGO trajectories with floats which veered to the north to join the IWBC are marked in
green, and the ones which veered south to join the BC are marked in cyan. The few magenta tra-
jectories correspond to float immersions greater than 1050 dbar. (B): Averaged float velocities
in 1?×1? boxes. Blue arrows are averaged velocities less than 5 cm s?1, yellow arrows averaged
velocities greater 5 cm s?1. According to Legeais et al. (2013).

(see Figure 1.1).

The retroflection lobe can be also interpreted as larger inner Recirculation Cell (RC) centered

in ? 35?S. This RC is elliptical in shape and its northern border can reach as north 32?S. Its
western border forms a counterflow to west of ? 53?W and which recirculates part of the BC
re-entering the main current at the RC northern tip latitude (Gordon and Greengrove, 1986;

Stramma and England, 1999; Vianna et al., 2007; Schmid, 2014). The relative small size of

5



Figure 1.4: Schematic of the two patterns by which WBCs separate from the continental margins:
(A) smooth separation and WBC extension formation. (B) reflection with a zonally-damped
stationary wave formed. Adapted from da Silveira et al. (1999).

the RC has been attributed to a possible double-subgyre system proposed by Tsuchiya (1985)

(from hydrography) and Vianna et al. (2007) (from altimetry and gravimetry): one centered in

in ? 22?S and the other centered in ? 32?S (Tsuchiya, 1985; Belo, 2011). The RC described here
can be thought as the inner recirculation portion of the southern subgyre.

1.1.2 Forcing

The WBCs are considered primarily wind-driven and usually extend from the surface to inter-

mediate levels (Pedlosky, 2013). Their generation has been explained by numerous theories, as

response to the wind stress and frictional forces (Sverdrup, 1947; Stommel, 1948; Munk, 1950;

Hughes and De Cuevas, 2001) or as a result of westward propagating planetary waves (Ander-

son and Gill, 1975; Young and Rhines, 1982). Focusing on the viscous forcing hypotheses, all

WBCs can be thought as the Sverdrup’s return current to the wind-driven Sverdrup equatorward

flow in the interior (i.e., away from the western boundary layer) of world ocean basins.

However, the simple nature of Sverdrupian return current for the WBCs, which would point

the wind stress as the sole driving mechanism can be easily doubted by in situ observations

oceanwide. In particular, the meridionally-changing BC vertical structure presented in the pre-

vious subsection illustrates that mass fluxes linked with what today is known as the MOC should

be considered as secondary forcing component as well.

Using the Atlantic Ocean as example, observations have shown that the transport of the

6



separating GS is at least three times larger than that of the separating BC (Talley et al., 2011).

However, there seems to be negligible differences between the strengths of North and South

Subtropical High Pressure centers, which supposedly would suffice to explain the WBC genera-

tion in both hemisphere. A first explanation for a stronger (weaker) and deeper (shallower) GS

(BC) was presented by Stommel (1965). The author proposed that wind-driven and buoyancy-

driven (or thermohaline) components of the circulation add up (oppose each other) for the GS

(BC) (Figure 1.5). The result of the combined forcing, as proposed by Stommel (1965), pre-

dicted elegantly the BC between the VTR SEC bifurcation (? 20?S) and the SBi (? 25?S): a
surface boundary current transporting TW near-surface and SACW at pycnocline depths and a

counterflow at intermediate levels, the IWBC, transporting AAIW in all its domain and UCDW

until it reaches the VTR at about 20?S (e.g., Stramma and England, 1999; Boebel et al., 1999;

Mémery et al., 2000).

Figure 1.5: Schematics of Stommel’s explanation for a weaker and shallowed BC compared to
a stronger and deeper GS. The net volume transport budget includes the wind and buoyancy
driven flows. blue represents northward flow and red, southward flow. Adapted from Stommel
(1965).

The simple thermohaline circulation box model first idealized by Stommel (1961) and used

to build the conceptual model presented in Figure 1.5 does not suffice to explain what nowa-

days is known of the BC vertical structure from its origin to its separation from the margin. It

is necessary to add complexity to the Meridional Overturnig Circulation (MOC) and show that

different water masses present distinct patterns of density-flux driven flow. Probably the most

detailed and complete MOC conceptual model is due to Schmitz (1995). As seen in Figure 1.6,

the proposed upper layer (i.e., the vertically averaged surface and pycnocline layers) and the

intermediate layer MOC flow patterns, coming from the Indian Ocean, reach the Brazilian conti-

7



nental margin at different latitudes and, therefore, weaken the wind-driven BC unequally in the

meridional direction.

Figure 1.6: The four-layer MOC global configuration proposed by Schmitz (1995).

We can certainly refine the Stommel (1961) for the combined wind and MOC forced BC

building upon the ideas of Schmitz (1995). We additionaly split the upper layer in surface

and pycnoclinic layers to obtain the "updated" Stommel (1961) conceptual model for the BC

vertical structure (Figure 1.7).

Figure 1.7: The updated Stommel (1961) conceptual model for the BC vertical structure based
on combined wind and MOC forcings.

8



1.2 The Study Area

Our study area (Figure 1.8) comprises the continental margin and abyssal plain adjacent

to the SB, which is limited on the north by the CF (22?) and on the south by the Cape Santa

Marta (CSM) (28?). In terms of mean flow patterns, the central portion of our investigated area

is characterized by the SBi at intermediate levels, and which sets the IWBC origin site within our

area. Therefore, the IWBC flows northward opposing a 600m-thick BC flowing southward on

the northern half of the area, while a 1300m-thick BC flows southward on the southern half of

our domain. The DWBC supposedly flows south entire the whole domain (Meinen et al., 2012;

Garzoli et al., 2015).

Figure 1.8: The study area geographical limits and a schematic representation of mean large
scale circulation within. The arrow colors represent distinct water masses being transported by
the flow regime: TW-SACW (red), AAIW-UCDW (green) and NADW (blue). Gray shades indicate
the major topographic features on the region.

The study area geomorphology deserves to be highlighted. The continental margin off CF

abruptly changes from a nearly north-south orientation to a northeast-southwest orientation.

At southern end of the SB, in the vicinities of CSM, the continental margin orientation veers

again and acquires a more north-south display. These changes in margin orientation and in the

subsequent BC axis positions impose some relevant dynamical constraints in mesoscale activity

within this region and which will be addressed next.

9



Figure 1.9: SST field for the SB at 14/08/2005 with the BC meandering from CST to CSM. Data
from level 4 Multiscale Ultrahigh Resolution (MUR) of the Group for High Resolution Sea
Surface Temperature (GHRSST) analysis provided by NASA. Quiver of geostrophic velocity
from AVISO to the same day.

1.3 The BC mesoscale variability

Besides its complex and unique meridionally-changing vertical structure, the BC develops

vigorous and rich mesoscale phenomena within out study region. We mean here by mesoscale

activity the occurrence of mesoscale meanders, eddies and rings of typically hundreds of kilo-

meters in length and of weeks to months in time. These kind of features have been reported by

several authors along all the BC path (e.g., Garfield, 1990; Campos et al., 1995; Schmid et al.,

1995; Silveira et al., 2008; Oliveira et al., 2009; Soutelino et al., 2013)(Figure 1.9). The BC

meandering in the SB has been described with hydrographic data, satellite data and numerical

modeling (Campos et al., 1995, 1996; Calado et al., 2008; Lorenzzetti et al., 2009). The rel-

evance of the mesoscale phenomena to the regional biological system should be emphasized

(Campos et al., 2000; Calado et al., 2010), as well as their importance to the operation of oil

rigs and oil-gas exploitation in the pre-salt reservoirs.

The BC mesoscale dynamics only very recently started to be addressed (Silveira et al., 2008;

Mano et al., 2009; Rocha et al., 2014; Biló, 2015). Silveira et al. (2008) were the first to focus

on the dynamical mechanisms responsible for generating the finite-amplitude meandering and

ring-shedding off the two-cape region. The authors used a current meter mooring at 22.7?S and

dynamical mode decomposition to characterize the mean current as an essentially baroclinic

jet due to the system BC-IWBC. The first dynamical mode structure detected by the authors

were due to intense velocity vertical shear associated with the opposing jets. Using a quasi-

10



geostrophic (QG) analytical model, Silveira et al. (2008) showed that baroclinic instability was

the primary mechanism for meander growth and found the most unstable waves with growth

rates of about 0.06 days?1, wavelength about 266 km and virtually zero phase speeds (quasi-

stationary waves).

In the attempt of further understand how the BC-IWBC system generates these unstable waves

in SB, Fernandes et al. (2009) used and idealized two-layer shallow water numerical model.

They generated the horizontal velocity profiles of the local currents as two opposing Gaussian-

shaped jets over a realistic bathymetry of the region. The authors obtained weakly unstable

waves, ? 0.02 day?1 growth rate, with 430 km and phase speed ? ?0.2 m s?1. These waves
growth in amplitude between 20?S?25?S but decrease far south of 25?S (Figure 1.10). Their
results showed the most unstable waves propagating poleward, contrarily to those found by Sil-

veira et al. (2008). The difference on the steering levels is probably mainly due to the simplified

vertical structure in two layers.

Figure 1.10: Instability wave propagation within the SBi as identified by Fernandes et al. (2009).

11



Figure 1.11: Linear baroclinic instability phase speed and growth for for MARLIM, C3, and
W333 moorings: (A) growth rate and (B) phase speed. Source: Rocha et al. (2014)

Rocha et al. (2014) pursued the understanding of the baroclinic instability on different BC

vertical structures north and south of the SBi employing four current meter mooring lines along

the current axis. The authors used a similar analytical approach to that used by Silveira et al.

(2008) and found at 22.7?S unstable quasi-stationary waves just as Silveira et al. (2008) did.

Contrarily to the waves found at 22.7?, the waves at 25? and 28? presented significant phase

propagation towards south (Figure 1.11). These authors identified the most unstable waves to

be shorter than those described by Fernandes et al. (2009) but with similar poleward phase

speed.

More recently, Biló (2015) studied the meandering of the BC at 23?S-30?S and found that

despite the baroclinic instability be responsible for draining the greatest part of the mean state

kinetic energy, the most unstable perturbations are linked to barotropic instabilities. Using a

linear primitive equation (PE) model, the author found waves with higher growth rate than of

those found by Rocha et al. (2014), but similar phase speed, being ?0.19, ?0.24 and ?0.26 m
s?1 at 24?S, 26?S and 30?S. The author also detected evidence of cyclonic meanders at ? 28?S
using satellite SST and chlorophyll-a data. The author estimated from satellite thermal imagery

the occurrence of 5 to 6 events per year of wave patterns with ?219 km of wavelength. Yet the
authors did not provide any insight regarding the dynamics of these cyclones and subsequent

anticyclones. Nonetheless, they account for almost 55% of the BC subinertial variability in the

12



region.

The studies listed above have studied the meandering of the BC and linked its possible driving

mechanisms to the structure of the BC velocity shear and potential vorticity. All the authors have

investigated the BC mesoscale variability as a response to local perturbations in the potential

vorticity (PV) field either associated with topographic forcing or volume transport fluctuations.

Therefore the possibility of remote sources perturbing the BC mean state has not been addressed

so far. These perturbations can appear as a result of westward propagating features such as

dispersive baroclinic planetary waves (Johns et al., 1990), the westward propagating Agulhas

rings (Guerra, 2011; Azevedo et al., 2012) and nonlinear eddies or waves (Chelton et al., 2011)

impinging on the BC.

Additionally, the investigation of the BC dynamics regionally in the SB is restricted to Oliveira

et al. (2009) and Biló (2015). The former author used surface drifter data and the latter, thermal

imagery and hydrographic survey data. However, nowadays altimetry data has increased its

global coverage and have a spatial resolution that resolves wavelength of instability-like waves

Chaigneau et al. (2008). This quasi-synoptic dataset creates the opportunity of studying the BC

mesoscale variability in larger domains such as this thesis study area.

1.4 Thesis Hypothesis and Objectives

1.4.1 Hypothesis

To date the BC variability within the SB has been only linked to either baroclinic or barotropic

instability processes and triggered by continental margin changes in orientation (Rocha et al.,

2014; Biló, 2015). Even tough the topographic forcing might account for part of the BC mean-

dering, no study has examined so far the current variability caused by PV remote sources.

There have been studies recently showing the importance of westward propagating nonlinear

cyclonic and anticyclonic eddies (Chelton et al., 2011). More recently, Polito and Sato (2015)

proposed the co-existence of linear Rossby waves and nonlinear eddies and that eddies ride the

waves with both features propagating westward. The nonlinear eddy-planetary wave system

could transport a considerable amount of energy and enstrophy that could perturb in the BC

mean field importantly.

Considering this knowledge gap on how the westward propagating features induce (or not)

mesoscale variability in the BC, we aim to test the following hypothesis in this thesis:

13



"The Brazil Current presents a relevant subinertial variability within the Santos Bight forced

remotely by perturbations caused by westward propagating structures from the interior of the

South Atlantic basin.".

1.4.2 Objectives

The general objective of this thesis is to investigate the remote forcing of the BC meandering

within the SB. In order to reach this overall goal, the following specific objectives will be sought:

• To characterize the spectral properties of the main variability features of the BC;

• To characterize the origin and propagating direction of the perturbation sources;

• To quantify the variance of the remotes sources inducing perturbations on the BC jet rela-

tive to the total variance of the current system; and

• To characterize the vertical structure and velocities of the perturbations.

This thesis is organized as follows. In chapter 2 we address the variability of the BC using

its surface signal measured from satellite altimetry remote observations. In chapter 3 we seek

to identify the features detected in the satellite data on in situ observational data from a hydro-

graphic cruise. In chapter 4, we summarize and conclude our findings. Furthermore this thesis

ends with recommended future work relating our findings and issues raised which are beyond

our work scopus.

14



Chapter 2

Mesoscale Variability from Satellite

Altimetry

In this chapter, we study the mesoscale variability of the BC within the SB seeking for remote

sources of perturbation of the BC axis. Nevertheless, we also search for local perturbation

sources, which are probably related to either topographic forcing or jet transport fluctuations.

However, we first must look for the dominant wave periods and wave lengths associated with

the meandering phenomena. Altimetry data is chosen to resolve the BC front and its deviations,

and to conduct our analyses. We are fully aware that the capability of resolving fast and/or short

duration phenomena is lost but, on the other hand, we do not have data gaps to deal with due to

unfavorable atmospheric conditions (i.e. cloud coverage), such as in infrared based SST satellite

data .

2.1 Datasets

2.1.1 Altimetry

The altimetry time series extends from the beginning of 1994 to the end of 2015. The series

consists of a level 4 Absolute Dynamic Topography (ADT) global field, obtained from a multi-

satellite coverage (TOPEX/Poseidon, Jason-1, Jason-2, ERS–1, ERS–2 e EnviSat). This image

composite series used two type satellite coverage, the European satellites (ERS–1, ERS–2 e

EnviSat) with ?35-day cycle and closer distance between tracks of ?85 km at the equator and
the Americans (TOPEX, Jason-1 e Jason-2) with a ?10-day cycle, but ?315 km along-track

15



distance. The data set built by encompassing all satellite measurements is interpolated from

only two satellites, one European and one American, to keep the statistical accuracy. The two-

satellite data is interpolated to a daily and regular cartesian grid of 0.25?×0.25? by Ssalto/Duacs1

and provided by AVISO2.

The AVISO final products are expressed as ADT and SLA. The dynamic topography and the

sea level deviations are related to each other by the hydrostatic equation:

?(x , y, t ) = ??(x , y, t )
g

, (2.1)

where ? is the SLA [in m] ?? is the geopotential anomaly [in m2 s?2] at surface level, and g ,

the effective gravity. We opt to employ the SLA throughout this work following the AVISO

site documentation and will use the terminology dynamical topography and sea level anomalies

interchangeably in the text. The data used, ADT, can be thought as the sum between a mean

state and its associated perturbations,

?a (x , y, t ) = ?(x , y ) +?(x , y, t ), (2.2)

being the ?(x , y ) the temporal mean dynamic topography, and ? its perturbations.

AVISO provides besides ADT (?a ) data, a mean state (MDT) (?) field. The latest MDT version

was released in April 2014, and it was calculated with 20 years of data from 1993 to 2012.

This recent ? field better estimates the mean state of the ocean compared to the previous one

(1993-1999), including long-term oscillations and accurate trend estimate of the sea level. The

background dynamic topography computed from conventional hydrography and float profiling

was calculated relative 1500 m. The most recent ADT was also obtained keeping the spatial

filter constant in all grid points with a low pass filter that cut off wavelengths shorter than 65 km

for the whole globe (SSALTO/Duacs, 2014).

As the MDT provided by AVISO is a mean estimated with data until 2012, we needed to

correct it using the remainder three year of altimetry data (from 2012-2015), and only after the

correction applied, we calculated the SLA using Equation 2.2. Figure 2.1 show the comparison

between the original and the corrected MDT as well as difference between both. It is observable

that the features in the mean field -as expected - are identical, the position of the BC axis is the

same but the values of the MDT based on the time mean of the ADT set presents an overall higher

surface height. We speculate that the differences in height are due to the sea level rise trend.
1Segment Sol multimissions d’ ALTimétrie, d’Orbitographie et de localisation/Data Unification and Altimeter

Combination System
2Archiving, Validation and Interpretation of Satellite Ocean data

16



Figure 2.1: Comparison between the original AVISO MDT and the corrected MDT used in this
work. (A): blue solid contours the ? provided by AVISO and the red dashed contours the ?
calculated from the 22 years data. (B): the percentage of increasing of the ? compared with
AVISO provided MDT, black solid line the BC mean position in calculated ?.

2.1.2 Climatological hydrographic data

It was used to calculate the Brunt–Väisälä frequency three-dimensional climatological fields

of temperature (Locarnini et al., 2013) and salinity (Zweng et al., 2013) from World Ocean

Atlas 13 (WOA13). This dataset comprehends 57 year of hydrographic data interpolated with

objective analysis to a 0.25? × 0.25? Cartesian grid with 102 depth levels. The Brunt–Väisälä
climatological profile was calculated in one area in the basin interior (yellow box in Figure 2.2).

17



Figure 2.2: Study area, yellow box the region used to calculate the climatological Brunt–Väisälä
profile. Gray shades indicate the major topographic features on the region.

2.2 Methods

2.2.1 Annual signal removal

To remove the annual signal and the seasonal oscillation of the data, we assumed that this

annual signal behaves as a sinusoidal function. Then, we can approximate to each data point a

function Y (t ), defined as

Y (t ) = A sin
(
2?

t

Ta

)
+ B cos

(
2?

t

Ta

)
, (2.3a)

Ta = 365, (2.3b)

with Ta and t units in days. After, the equation was adjusted to the data time series minimizing

root-mean-square error between data and Y (t )(Figure 2.3). Having this sinusoidal function to

seasonal signal then the resultant signal results simply as the subtraction between the data and

the seasonal adjusted signal. Being the SLA data at one data point (x0, y0) and all time series

SL A(x0, y0, t ), the data without the seasonal component will be N (x0, y0, t ) = SL A(x0, y0, t ) ?
Y (t ).

18



Figure 2.3: Example of annual signal adjustment for 5 years of data at one point in x-axis of the
Hovmöller diagram. Green line D (t ) is the SLA signal and blue line Y (t ) the adjusted seasonal
signal.

2.2.2 Fast Fourier Transform

The FFT technique is a computational algorithm to compute discrete Fourier Transform, a

mathematical technique that decomposes a signal in its multiple complex harmonics. By doing

so, one can convert a signal from its original time | space domain to a representation in the
wavenumber | frequency domain. In this work we used two types of FFT, the two dimensional
Fast Fourier Transform (FFT2D) and the one dimensional FFT.

The FFT2D is a two dimensional approach when the original signal is converted from a time-

space domain to a wavenumber-frequency domain. This spectral technique gives as result a

wavenumber-frequency (k ??) energy spectrum. In the present study we used this technique to
determine the two spectral properties of the studied phenomena, wavenumber and frequency.

Frequency determination

To identify the periods of the main variability phenomena we used the FFT2D of the auto-

correlation matrix of the data. The autocorrelation of the data removes random noisy signals

without losing the important spectral information. The main frequencies were identified by ap-

plying a bandpass filter to the k ?? spectrum of the autocorrelation with the following criteria:

1. Negative wavenumber and positive frequency, to select only south propagation features;

19



2. Frequency higher than 0.0349 day?1, separation between mesoscale and large-scale;

3. Frequency lower than 0.3141 day?1, nyquist frequency of data aquisition;

4. Wavenumber higher than nyquist wavenumber to remove non-propagating features;

5. Wavenumber lower than 0.0896 km?1, the mesoscale detection limit using AVISO data

(Chaigneau et al., 2008).

Having only the portion of the spectrum considered with this criteria we did a mean spectral

power with all wavenumber to each frequency. Therefore we calculate which is the mean energy

at every frequency considering all wavenumber inside the bandpass filter. This gives the peak

of frequency that are more important disregarding the wavenumber.

Wavenumber determination

To determine the wavenumber we considered each period maxima separately. We performed

the FFT2D of the data and to each period (T ) we used a bandpass filter with a range of T of

±10%. This filter, for any given T, considered the follow criteria:

1. Negative wavenumber and positive frequency, to select only south propagation features;

2. Frequency higher than 2?1.1T day
?1;

3. Frequency lower than 2?0.9T day
?1;

4. Wavenumber higher than nyquist wavenumber to remove non-propagating features;

5. Wavenumber lowerer than 0.0896 km?1, the mesoscale detection limit using AVISO data

(Chaigneau et al., 2008).

Having the filtered spectrum we calculated the mean power spectral of every wavenumber.

This results in a one dimensional wavenumber spectra with higher values of energy in the most

important wavenumbers linked to period T .

One dimensional FFT

To calculations used in the present study (i.e., correlation field) we needed the three di-

mensional ? data filtered in the time domain. Therefore we also used in this work the one

20



dimensional FFT. In order to do that we used the FFT to transform a array of ? from the time

domain to the period domain. To the period spectrum we applied a bandpass filter in the period

domain centered in the target period T with a range of ±10% (Figure 2.4). After determining
the band of period we used the inverse FFT to reconstruct the data with phenomena only in the

time range of interest.

With the three dimensional SL A(x , y, t ) field, for each point in space, the time series of SLA

was filtered with the one dimensional FFT as already explained.

Figure 2.4: FFT band-pass filter on SLA time series for the grid point at 25.375?S and 44.375?W
for the first 5 years of data. (A): blue line is the raw data, green line the data filtered with
FFT. (B): red line is the spectral power [m2 day?1], yellow dashed line is in the 92 day period
position, black dashed lines the limits of 10% from central period and shaded black area is the
portion of the spectre line used to reconstruct the filtered data.

2.2.3 Correlation field

Considering a three dimensional field of SLA it is possible to determine the presence of a

wave based on the correlation coefficient. This coefficient correlation was calculated between

the time series of a point where the wave signal is present and the time series at all spatial grid

points.

Considering a test fictitious SLA signal (upper Figure 2.5) with 400 km wavelength and 70

days of period happening at a restricted region of the SLA field and the remain signal as random

noise. Using the correlation coefficient with the point of control in the region where the wave is

present we identify troughs and crests of correlation with same wavelength of the troughs and

21



crest of SLA. Therefore this method is useful to determine the regions where there is signal of

the wave and thus its wavelength. Moreover when using this technique to a point in the field

where there is not the presence of the wave the correlation is nearlly zero for every grid-point

except the control (lower panel in Figure 2.5).

One important thing to this method is the amplitude of the noise signal compared to the

amplitude of the wave signal. To ensure this we used in this method the data previously fil-

tered according to section 2.2.2. Moreover we performed a Monte-Carlo statistical test to study

the statistical significance of the correlation. The grid points with correlation lower than the

statistical significance value were interpreted as zero.

Figure 2.5: Example of the pathway and wavelength estimate using the SLA correlation coef-
ficient field. (A): SLA [m] fictitious field with a wave signal propagating between 1000 and
1500 in y-axis. Rest of field is random noise. (B): correlation field with a control point where
the wave happens, magenta dot the position of control time series. (C): orrelation field with a
control point where there is no presence of the wave, magenta dot the position of control time
series.

22



2.2.4 Radon Transform

The phase speed of the propagating signal in the filtered data were calculated via Radon

transform. Radon space is given for a radius (r ) and angle (?)(Figure 2.6). So the projection of

a function in r with the angle ? is a radon transform

?{h}(r,?) =
? ??
??

h(x?, t ?)d s. (2.4a)

x? = r cos?? s sin? (2.4b)

t ? = r sin?? s cos? (2.4c)

where, ?{h} is the transform of one arbitrary function h and r and ? the distance and angle
of the Radon space. This method is used to estimate the phase speed of propagating signal when

one considers the Hovmöller diagram of the data as the h function. In this sense the function

is rotated for ??/2 &amp;lt;? &amp;lt;?/2 and for each angle the sum is made along the r -axis. When ? is
such that the troughs and crests are aligned with y-axis and perpendicular to r -axis, the variance

of the sums has a maximum. The phase speed can be inferred from ?, since tan(?) = ?t
?x .

Figure 2.6: Radon transform illustrative scheme. The gray square represent the original data
being rotated. Blue dashed line represent a relative sum of the radon space at each angle for all
r axis, being the angles 0?, 45? and 67.5?.

2.2.5 Explained variance

Considering a time series of SLA (?) and the data filtered in some temporal band (?f ) it is

possible to calculate how much the filtered explains of the total variance of the original data.

The explained variance of the original is given by

23



v f = 1 ?
?(???f )2
?(?)2

, (2.5)

where ?f is the SLA filtered in time.

2.3 Results and Discussion

As stated before, the primary goal of this work is to study the remote sources of subinertial

variability of the BC and how they account for the meandering of the jet within the SB.

Considering a QG framework one can recall that

? = g
f0
?a (2.6)

and considering that ? can be represented as

?(x , y, t ) = ?(x , y ) +??(x , y, t ), (2.7)

the sum of the mean state and the time dependent perturbations, then considering the previous

two equations and Equation 2.1,

?? = g
f0
?. (2.8)

According to the previous equation the perturbations of the QG streamfunction can be esti-

mated from SLA altimetry field. One technique to present such data and well known to study

propagating phenomena is the spatio-temporal diagram, also known as Hovmöller diagram. To

make this diagram, a path has been chosen taking in consideration the mean position of the BC

(Figure 2.7). This is defined as the region near the BC with maximum ??.
Nonetheless, the path chosen and hereafter considered as the BC-axis, was not along the

exact center of the current axis, rather it was dislocated approximately 36 km towards offshore.

This was done because the perturbations do not occur exactly along the current axis. Instead,

the current usually changes its core position towards offshore as it meanders. Moreover, some

of the perturbations seem to propagate along the BC but not centered in its axis, instead they

propagate attached to the current and centered further offshore.

The Hovmöller diagram path chosen to study the variability of the BC starts south of Patos

Lagoon (? 33?S) and ends near Cape Frio (? 23?S). One important process within the SB is the

24



Figure 2.7: Mean Dynamic Topography map with filled contours as height in meters. The green
line is the path along the BCaxis chosen to do the Hovmöller diagram, starting at the green dot
and ending at the red dot, the black dot indicates the mean latitude of the SBi along the green
line (Rocha et al., 2014).

SBi, both its importance and dynamical constraints it imposes have been discussed in section 1.3.

Therefore we used its approximate position (black dot in Figure 2.1) and studied the region north

and south of the SBi independently.

The ? for the chosen path was interpolated from the altimetry data. Its seasonal cycle and

linear trend have been removed in order to filter out anomalies that are related to annual oscil-

lations and long time trend of the current (subsection 2.2.1). The SLA field in the SB presents

signal of southwestward propagation along the BC axis (Figure 2.8). This propagation occurs

during the 22 years of data but is not constant in time nor in space. Although there is an alter-

nating pattern of maxima and minima of ?, the time mean of the propagation features changes

its mean values during the time series (i.e. difference between 1998-2001 and 2001-2004). This

process can be related to decadal or secular oscillation and is not relevant to the present study.

Besides the identified propagation pattern, when looking closer one can also note southward

propagation in a broader band of frequency. By looking to a smaller period of data, there seems

to happen a time modulation of the SBi position. This modulation occurs in the Hovmöller

diagram as a discontinuity of SLA that interrupt the propagation signal. This local maximum

25



Figure 2.8: Hovmöller diagram of SLA after removed the trend and yearly signal. A) Hovmöller
diagram of data time series between 1994 and 2016, black triangles represent the position of the
SBi in the Hovmöller diagram. Black dashed lane represent area subseted. B) subset of panel A
with day zero as 1s t of January of 2007 and ending in 1s t of January of 2010, black triangles
indicate the position of the SBi

changes its position with time, in early 2007 it was centered at ?1200 km of distance from
southernmost point, and between early 2008 and the end of 2010 it shifted to a smaller distance

(?900 km) therefore to south. This is probably the SBi surface signal and the interruptions
is due to its presence at intermediate levels. The difference in distance along the Hovmöller

diagram axis represents a variation of 2?, then this changing in position of the abovementioned

discontinuity is presumably linked to the long-term variability of the SBi latitude.

Given the regional importance of the SBi and the apparent discontinuity in propagation here-

after the spectral analysis will be applied in two different areas:

• North of the Santos Bifurcation;

• South of the Santos Bifurcation.

26



2.3.1 North of the Santos Bifurcation

To the north of the bifurcation the frequency mean spectrum presents an energy peak in the

period of 92 days (red dot) and two secondary peaks both at around 170 days Figure 2.9. The

rest of the energy is almost restricted to periods between 90 and 125 days with no significant

signal to periods smaller than 80 days. The second and third maximum values are in 160 and 175

days. (Mata et al., 2006) estimated the limit between low-frequency and mesoscale variability

to be of about 170 days. Therefore, since the second and third maximum are either out or in the

limit of mesoscale variability band, these periods were not addressed in this study. At the north

of the SBi there is a maximum of mesoscale variability with 92 days of period, and this is the

peak that we will study. Hereafter this peak will be mentioned as 92-D.

Figure 2.9: Spectral mean energy [m2 day?1] for periods between 20 and 180 days, computed
to the north of the SBi. Red dot the period of maximum energy.

To determine the wavenumber linked to the variability of 92-D signal we used the method

presented in section 2.2.2. The mean spectrum increases towards a maximum of energy in -

0.012 km?1 (red dot) and decreases after this value (Figure 2.10). To wavenumbers lower than

-0.020 km?1 the spectrum value is lower than a third of the maximum value. However, this

spectrum has a striking limitation in this band of wavenumber. Thus, due to data resolution,

the wavenumber peak linket to 92-D phenomena is centered in -0.012±0.002 km?1. This range
of wavenumber represents a 180 km range of wavelengths and this effect is enhanced given the

proximity to minimum wavenumber resolution.

27



Figure 2.10: Spectral determination of most important wavenumber. (A) Spectral energy of
the Hovmöller diagram [Lo g 10 m2 day?1 km?1]. Blue line the bandpass filter box centered
in period of 92 days and range of ±10%. (B) Wavenumber spectrum [m2 km?1], black dots
represent spectral resolution and red dot dominant wavenumber.

The main mesoscale variability of the BC at the north of the SBi have a characteristic period

of 92 days and wavelength of ?513 km. Moreover the signal propagates southwestward, with
signal along the BC axis. However information is needed to its origin site and propagation

pathway towards the current.

In order to analyze the propagation pathway through which the 92-D signal reaches the BC we

used the methodology explained in subsection 2.2.3. To study only the important signal we first

filtered the SLA data in the time domain with a tophat band-pass filter using one dimensional

FFT as described in section 2.2.2. This ensures that we remove propagation related to others

frequencies rather than 92-D signal. Nonetheless this method is solely a time domain filtering

and does not carries spatial information as the wavenumber has been already determined.

This correlation field shows an almost zonal westward propagation reaching the BC to the

north of the SBi along ? 25?S. Meridional elongated bands of correlation (i.e 32.5?W) are ev-
ident in the 92-D signal correlation field, which suggests a propagation as a wave front rather

than a sequence of cyclones and anticyclones. This elongated fronts are restricted to latitudes

between 23?S and 33?S.

Zhang et al. (2001) using a current meter mooring and satellite altimetry data identified a

maximum mesoscale variability of 100 days to the KC south of Taiwan. The authors identified

28



the source of this variability to be westward propagating eddies. However they did not found

phase propagation along the current, instead they identified this 100 day signal to be the main

source of variability in the KC transport. The authors identified this variability to be caused by

barotropic isntabilities. Due to the instabilities the current shift its axis and flows through a

different path. Chen et al. (2009) studied the KC near South China Sea with a longer time series

of altimetry data and identified the main mesoscale variability to be 94 days. Therefore both

authors looked to the same source of variability, given the 6 days difference. The variability

signal of the BC has a close period to the one found for the KC. However it does not seem to be

as eddies reaching the current but a westward propagating wave front.

The path defined based on the BC axis (black line in Figure 2.11A) is almost in southwest-

ward direction and the 92-D signal has a westward propagation direction. This difference in the

orientation between both causes the northern part of the troughs and crests to reach the BC first.

Therefore the arrival of a westward propagation wave can cause an apparent phase propagation

along the BC. Nonetheless it appears to exist an actual phase propagation along the BC with a

small tough and crest along the BC. This can be either be propagation along the current or the

wave front reaching the BC near CSM.

Using the technique in subsection 2.2.3 it is possible to estimate both the origin and the

wavelength of the wave by analyzing the correlation field of the time series of each spatial

point (Figure 2.11A). The estimated wavelength for the 92-D is 520 km and its origin seems

to be around 35?W. In addition to the origin site, this technique allows us to estimate a better

propagation path of the wave. This improved path is then used to make a Hovmöller diagram

using the same methodology applied to the BC axis case. As previously described, the annual

signal of the SLA has been removed and the wavelength of the 92-D is estimated with better

accuracy, as explained in section 2.2.2.

29



Figure 2.11: Correlation coefficient field of the SLA filtered data in to 92-D signal. (A): map
of correlation coefficient, green dot the position used to correlate with the rest of the field and
black line the Hovmöller diagram path used for the BC axis. (B): same correlation coefficient
field, black line the new Hovmöller diagram path specific to this wave, green dot is the start and
red cross the end of the path.

The wavenumber spectrum along the 92-D path yields again a single maximum, at wavenum-

ber -0.01235 km?1 (508 km wavelength), and the spectral energy is negligible to features smaller

than 205 km (Figure 2.12). The correlation field pathway is small, only two full wavelengths.

A possible explanation for this is that the wave exists only near the current. Due to the small

path chosen the wavenumber of maximum energy is near the limit of spectral resolution.

The frequency, wavenumber and pathway of the main BC variability source at north of the SBi

have been estimated. With these spectral information, we applied a FIR2D filter in the Hovmöller

diagram along the wave pathway. This type of filter preserves only the signal of a specific wave

(Polito and Liu, 2003).

Both the original 92-D Hovmöller diagram (zonal) and the filtered one present a westward

propagating signal Figure 2.13. In the filtered Hovmöller diagram it is observable that 92-D

signal vanishes (i.e., between days 1600 and 1800 in Figure 2.13). This absence of significant

signal of 92-D wave in the Hovmöller diagram can be either because we are looking at a inter-

mittent phenomena or it reaches the SB at different latitudes with time. In the last case we do not

sample the 92-D in this Hovmöller diagram but it is propagating towards the BC at latitudes be-

30



Figure 2.12: Same as the Figure 2.10 but for the new Hovmöller diagram path in Figure 2.11A.

tween 23?S-33?S other than 25?S. Having the filtered Hovmöller diagram to the 92-D pathway

we estimated phase speed with the Radon transform method as described in subsection 2.2.4.

Having the phase speed we calculated an improved and more accurate wavelength of this wave,

491 km.

Although not being permanent in the filtered Hovmöller diagram the 92-D wave accounts

for a variance of the SLA in its pathway of 21% (see subsection 2.2.5). However, in the BC axis

the 92-D signal explains 17% of the total variance. Even though we have other features along

the 25?S zonal line the 92-D wave accounts for one fifth of the its variance.

31



Figure 2.13: Hovmöller diagram for the last six years of data (2009-2015). (A) SLA Hovmöller
diagram for the path defined in Figure 2.11. (B) Filtered Hovmöller diagram using FIR2D with
the period and wavelength of 92-D.

2.3.2 South of the Santos Bifurcation

Variability to the south of the SBi was studied by using the same methodology employed to

the north of the SBi.

The frequency spectrum was calculated with the methodology described in section 2.2.2. The

spectrum has higher values of energy to the south of the SBi than to the north (Figure 2.14). The

maximum value in the south has a mean spectral power of 80 m2day?1, while the maximum

at north has only ?33 m2day?1. Moreover the BC to the south presents two maxima in the

32



mesoscale period range, 68 and 148 days (red dots). The semiannual variability in this case is

not clearly present, as in the spectrum for the northern part. The spectrum has a third maximum

around 92 days. Therefore as observed in Figure 2.11A there is variability to the south of the

SBi in 92 days period band. Since this third variability maximum is linked to the phenomena

already studied in the subsection 2.3.1 we will focus the study of the southern part to periods of

68 days and 148 days, hereafter 68-D and 148-D.

Figure 2.14: Same as the Figure 2.9 but to the south of the bifurcation. Two red dots represent
the periods of 68 and 148 days.

We applied the methodology described in section 2.2.2 to determine the wavenumber of both

68-D and 148-D signals (Figure 2.15).

The 68-D signal has a maximum in the wavenumber spectrum of -0.01630 km?1 - 385 km

wavelength. However because of the data sampling resolution this wavenumber actually rep-

resents a probable range of ?0.01770 k m?1 ? k ? ?0.01400 k m?1. Nevertheless this range is
smaller (94 km) than the one of the 92-D signal, since the wavenumber of 68-D signal is not as

close to the limit of wavenumber resolution.

The 148-D presents a wavenumber spectrum increasing towards a maximum of -0.00815 km?1.

The spectral resolution limitation is more problematic in this case since the wavenumber of

maximum energy is in the limit of wavenumber resolution, being the closest to zero, not con-

sidering non-propagating features. Therefore the wavenumber of 148-D is in a range between

?0.00612 km?1 and ?0.00978 km?1. This wavenumber range represents a wavelength range of
400 km.

33



Figure 2.15: Spectral determination of most important wavenumber for each maximum in Fig-
ure 2.14. (A): spectral energy of Hovmöller diagram [Lo g 10 m2 day?1 km?1]. Blue lines repre-
sent the box where the spectrum was cut between range of ±10% of the central period, solid line
for 68 day period and dashed for 148. (B): spectral mean power [m2 km?1], black dots represent
spectral resolution and red dot dominant wavenumber, solid line for 68 day and dashed for 148.

The region to the south of the SBi has two dominant mesoscale variability periods and for

practical matters, they were analyzed separately.

68 days signal

The main pathway of the 68-D signal is obtained by the same methods described in subsec-

tion 2.2.3. Figure 2.16A shows the correlation field obtained by comparing the time series of

altimetry with one in 46.125?W and 28.875?S (green point), the BC path is also showed.

The main pattern of the 68-D signal is two troughs of correlation, one to the north and one

to the south of the chosen point. It is observable in the correlation field that the values after this

two minima decrease rapidly, so only one and a half wavelength is clear as a pathway. Therefore

half a wavelength from the point of control there is not an obvious pattern of propagation. The

68-D correlation field appears as a wave propagating southwestward not purely parallel to the

BC axis, which makes this signal likely to be linked to the current meandering, or at least the BC

dynamics.

By measuring the distance between the troughs and crests of correlation, we estimated the

wavelength of 68-D to be 398 km. This wavelength is 13 km bigger than the estimated from

the spectrum of the BC Hovmöller diagram (Figure 2.15). From this correlation field, we can

34



estimate a better axis of propagation of the wave, which we used to make a new Hovmöller

diagram specific to the wave path (Figure 2.16B).

Figure 2.16: Same as Figure 2.11 but with data filtered in 68 day period.

With the new Hovmöller diagram we calculated a maximum wavenumber of -0.0169 km?1,

371 km wavelength, by using the method in section 2.2.2(Figure 2.17). Since the new Hov-

möller diagram presents only one and a half wavelength, the 68-D wavenumber is closer to

the spectral resolution limit than was the case when it was determined for the BC axis pathway

(Figure 2.15).

The result of the Hovmöller diagram along the 68-D signal pathway presents southwestward

propagation signal (Figure 2.18A). It can be noted that there are signals in other frequency bands

besides the 68-D. In order to isolate the 68-D signal, we applied the FIR2D filter, configured with

the estimated wavenumber, frequency and direction of propagation (Figure 2.18B).

The pathway of the wave according to Figure 2.16B has its northern point at 27?S. Therefore

we do not identify in Figure 2.18A the presence of the SLA discontinuity related to the SBi.

The filtered Hovmöller diagram shows the 68-D wave as a not intermittent phenomena like the

92-D. This signal exists in the entire time series. However in some periods (i.e. day 1400) the

68-D signal is not present in all the pathway. So there are time periods that the wave does not

reach the southern point of the estimated pathway (i.e, day 400 and day 1400 in Figure 2.17B).

35



Figure 2.17: Same as Figure 2.15 but for 68 day signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path
defined in Figure 2.16B.

Figure 2.18: Same as Figure 2.13 but for 68-D signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path
defined in Figure 2.16B.

36



The phase speed was estimated from the filtered Hovmöller diagram by using the Radon

transform, and then was obtained an improved estimative of the wavelength. The accurate wave-

length for the 68-D signal is 397 km. This wave explains 21% of the variance of the SLA along

the BC axis pathway, and it explains 27% along its propagation pathway from Figure 2.16B.

Nonetheless the 62-D wave accounts for at least one fifth of the variance of the BC within the

SB. The increase in explained variance shows the better sampling of the signal with the new

pathway.

148 days signal

By employing the same methodology used to analyze the 92-D and 68-D signals, we cal-

culated the correlation field compared to the time series of the point located at 46.125?W and

28.875?S, which is in the BC axis and south of the SBi, as was the case in the analysis of the

68-D signal.

The 148-D correlation field presents a preferential pathway through which the wave reaches

the BC in an almost zonal line centered in 28?S (Figure 2.19). Moreover there are elongated

bands of correlation for the 148-D signal suggesting a wave front propagating westward, simi-

lar to the one in 92-D. The wave fronts seem to be meridionaly restricted in the north to 23?S.

However within the SB the only clear wave reaching the BC is the one with a propagation path-

way centered in 28?S. Using this pathway we estimated a wavelength of 739 km for 148-D

wave, considering crests and troughs of correlation.

The 148-D wave does not present a propagation of troughs and crests along the BC axis within

the SB. This is due to the fact that the wave phase is not propagated along the current. Moreover

the correlation along the current axis is an elongated maximum which is possibly because the

148-D does not induces meandering of the BC. Instead the wave probably inserts(removes)

energy from the current causing an increase(decrease) of its signal as a whole within the SB.

Therefore, although the 148-D wave does not induces meandering of the BC, it modulates its

transport by changing its velocity.

37



Figure 2.19: Same as Figure 2.11 but with data filtered in 148 day period.

The improved pathway to make the Hovmöller diagram for the 148-D signal can be observed

in the Figure 2.19B. Along this pathway, even though there is a decrease in the correlation

fronts at ? 17?W, one can observe the alternating correlation pattern associated with a wave
in full longitudinal range. Although it may seem from this result that the 148-D propagates

towards the BC from at least ? 0?E, this methodology is not adequate to provide certainty to this
conclusion. Further studies are necessary to address this question.

By using the method described in section 2.2.2 for the Hovmöller diagram along the path of

the wave (almost zonal at 28?S), we obtained a spectral energy maximum in the wavenumber

of 0.00873 km?1 - 719 km wavelength (Figure 2.20). Wavelengths lower than ?400 km have
almost zero energy and the spectrum increases towards a maximum. Due to the length of the

path to the 148-D Hovmöller diagram (4300 km), this maximum of energy is not as in the

spectral limit as was the case when it was estimated from the Hovmöller diagram of the BC

(Figure 2.15).

Another difference is that the 148-D wavenumber spectrum does not present a single maxi-

mum and decreases rapidly towards wavenumbers near zero, like 68-D and 92-D (Figure 2.17

and Figure 2.12). Instead the spectrum presents a second maximum with a spectral energy close

the first. The second maximum have 99.4 % of the total spectral energy of the first. This sec-

38



Figure 2.20: Same as Figure 2.15 but for 148 day signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path
defined in ??.

ond maximum wavenumber is -0.00727 km?1 - 864 km. Since the FFT spreads the energy of

wavenumbers to a discrete spectrum, the presence of two close maximum is mostly due to the

wavelength of 148-D signal being between 719-864 km range.

The Hovmöller diagram of the 148-D pathway presents crests and troughs and a dominance

of a westward propagating features with a well defined phase speed (Figure 2.21A). We used the

FIR2D filter with a 148 day period and 719 km wavelength to isolate this dominant signal. The

filtered Hövmoller diagram presents a well defined propagating feature along all the pathway

defined for the 148-D signal (?4000 km). The propagation along the entire x-axis indicates a
phenomena that propagates from 5?W to 45?W. Moreover the 148-D is present in the filtered

diagram during all the time series. Although its values decrease sometimes (i.e., day 200 in

Figure 2.21) indicating this to be a permanent feature at this latitude.

A more accurate value of wavelength of the 148-D wave is 790 km, as estimated with Radon

transform using the filtered Hovmöller diagram. This wavelength explains the unique wavenum-

ber spectrum with two maxima (Figure 2.20B). Since we are observing a phenomena with a

wavenumber exactly between the two discrete maxima.

The 148-D wave has a maximum amplitude of 0.075 m and accounts for an explained vari-

ance of 25.7 % of the SLA in its propagation pathway. However, this explained variance de-

creases when the wave reaches the BC domain. The BC variance in its axis explained by the

148-D signal is 9%. This low variance of the SLA along the current axis is probably due to the

39



Figure 2.21: Same as Figure 2.13 but for 148 day signal in the new Hovmöller diagram path
defined in Figure 2.19B.

way how the wave transfers energy to the current. Although there is a transfer of high values

of energy to the current as the 148-D reaches the BC, this is done increasing and decreasing

the BC velocity and therefore its transport. Andres et al. (2008) using satellite altimetry and in

situ composit of data obtained an empirical function to estimate the transport of the KC. The

authors identified the main variability of the KC transport near the South China Sea in a range

of 100-170 days with the maximum of 150 days. Moreover the main variability of both KC and

BC are related to its transport modulation (Zhang et al., 2001).

Mata et al. (2006) used 6 moorings of current meter data to study the mesoscale variability

40



Table 2.1: Main spectral characteristics of each dominant signal to south and north of SBi.

Period [days] Wavelength [km] cp [ms?1]

North 92 491 0.06

South
68 397 0.07

148 790 0.06

of the EAC. The authors identified the mesoscale band to vary from the three moorings near the

slope (to the coastal part of the current) to the three in the outter part of the current (one in the

current’s core and the other two in the interior ocean). The variability of the EAC is dominated

by a period around 60 days near its core and coastal half. The moorings in the core of the

EAC have a maximum mesoscale variability in periods near 100 days. No spectral information

is available for the two moorings in the interior, however the variability period linked to the

current meandering (60 days) is similar to the one observed in this study for the BC at south of

the SBi.

We identified the spectral characteristics of the most important variability signals. Its fre-

quencies were obtained with the method in section 2.2.2 and the wavenumbers were estimated

with Radon transform. The spectral information of the signals to the north and south of the SBi,

as well as the phase speed of the phenomena, are listed in Table 2.1.

Taking in account the presented results so far about the 92-D, 68-D and 148-D signals, we

will try to elucidate what are the dynamics driving each one of them. The three waves differ,

besides its location to the north or south of the SBi, in the orientation of its propagation axis.

Therefore the dynamics of 68-D will be addressed separately from the 92-D and 148-D.

The 68-D wave propagates southwestward near the BC-axis. Therefore the signal of 68-D

is probably a variability linked to current meandering. Most of the recent studies of the BC

dynamics use a linear approach (Silveira et al., 2008; Rocha et al., 2014). Consequently the

importance of nonlinearity in the meandering of the BC have been neglected.

To access the importance of nonlinearity is to analyze the importance of advective terms. To

estimate the importance of advection of velocity compared with its local term, we will use the

ratio between both. Considering the total acceleration d ud t from the equation of motion as

?~u

?t
+~u ·?~u, (2.9a)

~u = ui? + v j? + w k? , (2.9b)

41



the dimension of each velocity term becomes

U

T
+U U

L
. (2.10)

The ratio between those two terms is

U 2L?1

U T ?1
= U 2T L?1U ?1 = U T L?1. (2.11)

The phase speed of a wave (C p ) have a dimension of

LT ?1. (2.12)

Then the ratio between the local and advective terms of the velocity, hereafter call as Li is given

by

Li = U T L?1 = U C ?1p , (2.13)

being U the tangential velocity. Given the phase speed of the 68-D wave in Table 2.1, to estimate

its linearity we need to determine U .

Considering a QG framework, ~ug is

ug = ?
??

?y
, (2.14a)

v g =
??

?x
, (2.14b)

taking the tangential velocity in meridional direction and the Equation 2.8,

v g =
g

f0

??

?x
. (2.15)

We calculate v g by discretizing Equation 2.15 so that
??
?x becomes

??
?x . Then we consider ??

the difference in SLA between a consecutive crest and a trough and ?x is the distance between

the same interval, which corresponds to half wavelength. The Li parameter of the 68-D wave is

2.25.

The meandering of the BC has recently been study within the SB as a result of baroclinic in-

stability (Rocha et al., 2014). The authors identified unstable waves with the same wavelength

at 25?S, however with twice the phase speed, i.e. half the period. At 28?S the authors did not

42



observed waves of 400 km to be unstable. Nonetheless the authors used an unidimensional in-

stability linear model and the results obtained might be due to the limitations of their method,

specially the disregard of nonlinearity. Moreover the authors used mooring current meters and

analyzed the BC meandering at 25?S and 28?S in the BC-axis. The 68-D as identified in the Fig-

ure 2.16 does not propagate along the exact current axis, instead a little offshore of it. Therefore

this can account for the difference in the waves found by the authors and ours.

At ? 23?S Silveira et al. (2008) studied the quasi-stationary meanders of the BC with a linear
baroclinic instability model and observed a similar wave in frequency and wavelength, but with

positive phase speed - i.e. northward propagation. These authors studied this as the formation of

the Cape Frio Eddy (CFE). The formation of this quasi-stationary eddies could be one possible

mechanism to generate the 68-D wave found in our study. The instability wave initially causes

the current to meander. After the meander is fully develop and the eddy is shed the current is

perturbed. This shedding of the CFE can generate perturbations to the south of CF and be the

responsible for the 68-D wave generation.

By utilizing SST data Biló (2015) identified a recurrent formation of cyclonic eddies, associ-

ated with a wave-like perturbation, between 27?S and 31?S. The author studied the recurrence

of the phenomena, observing an occurence of 5 to 6 events per year. This implies a period of

formation of cyclones between 73 and 60 days. The period of this cyclonic features resembles

a lot with the 68-D signal. The author identified this structures to be an important mechanism

of shelf-slope mass exchanges in this region. However, he obtained a wavelength of almost half

of that identified in this study, 219 km compared to 397 km. Moreover the cyclones occured

in the onshore side of the BC, near the shelf break. Taking in consideration the wavelength an

localization of the phenomena, we cannot state with certainty that we are looking at the same

phenomena described by Biló (2015), even though the period of occurrence is the same.

Nonetheless the 68-D wave can play an important role in shelf-slope water exchanges with

cyclones generating at every 68 days, and this can be of great importance to the local natural

system, i.e. primary productivity induced by cyclonic meander Campos et al. (2000).

The 92-D and 148-D signals propagate to west, also they propagate as a wave front. There-

fore based on this propagation direction we addressed first how these signals are related to first

mode RW. The linear dispersion relation is given by

? = ??k
k 2 + l 2 + R?2

d

, (2.16)

43



where ? is the frequency, k is the wavenumber, Rd is the deformation radius and ? is the

advection of planetary vorticity Gill (2016). To estimate this dispersion relation in the waves

propagating axis we calculated deformation radii using the methodology of Flierl (1978) and

the climatological Brunt-Väisälä frequency profile (Figure 2.2). The first baroclinic deformation

radius to the latitude of propagation is 51 km. Using the deformation radius and considering an

almost zonal propagation, k 2 À l 2, the dispersion relation becomes

? = ??k
k 2 + 51000?2 . (2.17)

Both the 148-D and 92-D signals do not match the Rossby waves (RW) dispersion relation

curve (Figure 2.22). However both dispersion relation of the signals are close to the line tangent

to the non-dispersive part of the RW, refered as the nondispersive line nondispersive line (NDL).

According to Early et al. (2011) the presence of features along this region of the spectrum is an

indicative of nonlinear processes. Using a shallow-water model with both linear and nonlinear

QG setup, he identified that when the nonlinear terms are negligible and they have only linear

waves, there is not the presence of energy along the NDL in the spectrum.

Morten (2017) used a single-layer, shallow-water, beta-plane, quasi-geostrophic, turbulence

model to study frequency-wavenumber spectrum, and identified the presence of energy along

the NDL in the case characterized by westward propagating coherent eddies.

The fact that these two signal are close to the NDL is probably due to the its nonlinearity

and the importance of advective terms. Using the Equation 2.13 the linearity parameter is 1.11

and 1.13 to 92-D and 148-D respectively. However both signals are along the NDL, the 148-

D signal is closer to the dispersion relation curve of RW than the 92-D. Therefore the 148-D

although seemingly a nonlinear phenomena could be a RW not along the dispersion relation

curve because of the over simplification of the linear theory used to estimate the dispersion

relation of the planetary waves.

Considering the linear theory, the 148-D frequency, wavenumber and the deformation radius,

? would have to be 2.7657 × 10?11m?1s?1. The local value of ? at ? 28?, axis of 148-D phe-
nomena, is 2.0157 × 10?11. The ? parameter can be better estimated considering in the linear
theory an effective ? term to get a more accurate linear dispersion relation of RW (e.g. Samelson,

2010). This effective ? term considers not only the advection of planetary vorticity, but also the

background velocity field and the effect of bottom slope.

44



Figure 2.22: Dispersion relation of known phenomena, green line dispersion relation of
barotropic and red line first baroclinic mode linear Rossby waves, black dashed line the NDL f,
blue dot the 148 day signal and blue star the 92 day signal.

Still according to the linear theory of RW

?

?Rd
? 0.5, (2.18)

which means that for each deformation radius there is a minimum(maximum) period(frequency).

Therefore, considering a fixed period, this means that for each period there is a minimum pos-

sible deformation radius and therefore a maximum latitude value, since in the linear theory Rd

is

Rd =
?

g ?H
| f0 |

, (2.19)

with H the local depth, g ? the reduced gravity and | f0 | the planetary vorticity. This restriction
in latitude is called the critical latitude of RW.

Therefore, for the local Rd of 51 km, the critical latitude is 29?S(17?S) for the 148-D(92-

D) phenomena. So, considering a linear theory approach the 92-D wave is 8? past its critical

latitude. Taking in account its critical latitude, linear parameter and dispersion relation, it is

strongly suggested that the 92-D is not a linear RW.

To further investigate the nonlinearity of this waves, we analyze the spectrum of both waves

to access if there are high values of energy along the NDL, in the site of the waves.

Spectrum at 25?

The 92-D wave has a zonal propagation pathway along the 25?S parallel. (Wortham and

Wunsch, 2014) using a spectral model identified the world oceans characteristic local zonal and

45



meridional wave number, period and phase speed. To the SB at this latitude their results are

approximately the same phase speed but a zonal wavelength two times bigger than found in this

study, therefore a period two times higher.

The spectrum of the Hovmöller diagram made for the propagation pathway of the 92-D

signal has great part of its energy along the NDL but scattered around it. The first maximum of

energy is related to non-propagating low-frequency phenomena. However the second maximum

is at 100 days and in the same wavelength of the 92-D wave. This second maximum of energy

is mostly due to the 92-D signal in this latitude (Figure 2.23).

The spectrum shows a trend to follow the NDL which indicates that the local phenomena are

linked to nonlinear terms. Energy in the NDL region is present in the k ?? spectrum when the
variability is dominated by the presence of coherent eddies. Therefore, and also considering the

wave-like propagation of fronts, the 92-D signal is most likely to be nonlinear wave instead of

a pathway of propagating nonlinear eddies (Wortham and Wunsch, 2014; Morten, 2017).

Figure 2.23: Wavenumber frequency spectrum for the 92-D wave pathway. Spectral energy
[Lo g 10m2d a y ?1k m?1], black solid line the dispersion relation of first mode linear RW, white
dashed line the NDL for this waves and blue start the 92-D wave.

Spectrum at 28?

The 148-D signal propagates along the 28?S parallel with a wavelength of 790 km. Wortham

and Wunsch (2014) identified in a spectral model a signal with similar wavelength, but a higher

period in this latitude, as in the 92-D signal.

46



The spectrum for this wave presents a narrower region of high energy, which is mostly re-

stricted to the NDL (Figure 2.24). Moreover it does not present a substantial spectral energy

along the RW linear dispersion relation curve. Therefore, there a high activity of nonlinear

processesis in this latitude.

Figure 2.24: Same as Figure 2.23 but for the 148-D wave pathway.

However, considering only the critical latitude of the 148-D signal as a linear wave, there is

a possibility that this signal is a RW. Further studies are needed in order to access the possibility

that this phenomena is a result of the interaction of propagating linear waves and nonlinear

eddies (Polito and Sato, 2015).

47



Chapter 3

Quasi-Synoptic Observations

In this chapter, we will use in situ observations to provide a three-dimensional view of me-

anders identified as the main sources of variability of the BC within SB. In particular, we focus

on showing evidence of the 68-D vorticity wave, its surface signature and vertical structure.

The longer waves associated with westward propagating signals from the interior of the South

Atlantic basin were not captured due to the synoptic cruise sampling strategy.

3.1 Dataset

3.1.1 In situ Quasi-Synoptic Velocity Measurements

The in situ velocity data set used in this work was obtained during the IOUSP-PETROBRAS

Oceanographic Expedition "CERES V", conducted by the R/V Alpha Crucis between Novem-

ber 1st and 23rd, 2013. The velocity data was acquired using a 75-kHz broadband VMADCP

with maximum profiling extent of about 500 m (which is dependent on sea conditions). The

data acquisition transects are presented in Figure 3.1. The data was processed with the standard

Common Ocean Data Access System (CODAS), following the procedures described in Firing

et al. (1995).

48



Figure 3.1: The CERES V cruise VMADCP sampling tracks (thick solid black lines). Solid red
lines correspond to the transects used in this work to build the velocity sections. The color
grading underneath the tracks denotes the bathymetry of the study area. The black dashed line
marks the position of the 200m isobath, which is the most accepted depth to represent the shelf
break in SB.

3.2 Methods: Objective Mapping

Objective Analysis (OA) is an optimal interpolation scheme traditionally used in mapping

oceanographic data (Bretherton et al., 1976; Carter and Robinson, 1987). The OA is least

squares scheme, based on the Gauss-Markov theorem. In this work, we use both scalar and

vector versions of OA to build velocity vertical sections and the horizontal velocity vector and

streamfunction maps.

This OA scheme first step consists of approximating (or fitting) the data (or sample) correla-

tion function to a horizontally isotropic Gaussian function given by

C (r ) = (1 ??2)e?r 2 /l 2c , (3.1)

being r the Euclidian distance between two data points, ? the uncorrelated error variance, l

49



is the correlation length. The fit nonlinearly provides the correlation length and linearly, the

sample error variance. The second step consists of applying the Gauss-Markov theorem in the

form of:

??j = C j i Ci i ?1?i , (3.2)

where ??j (?i) represents the j th grid point (the i th observation location) at which the quan-

tity ? is interpolated (was measured). Ci i is the data autocorrelation function and C j i is the

cross-correlation between data and gridded fields. We encourage the reader to seek Carter and

Robinson (1987) for more details. We should also mention the technique developed by Brether-

ton et al. (1976) used to map the streamfuction field from scattered velocity measurements is

applied to the CERES V VMADCP velocity vector measurements.

OA schemes considering either Equation 3.1 or its anisotropic version have been successfully

used to map scalar and vector fields related to the southwestern boundary currents (da Silveira

et al., 1994; Silveira et al., 2000, 2004; Goes et al., 2005; Silveira et al., 2008; Soutelino et al.,

2011). In particular, Silveira et al. (2000) (Goes et al. (2005)) introduced free-slip (no-slip)

boundary conditions within the OA scheme to constrain the mapped flow in the presence of

solid boundary in the area of interest. We opt here to apply no-slip boundary conditions by

introducing v = u = 0 input vector along an isobath, which is taken to be the limit between
seawater and land.

3.3 Results and Discussion

3.3.1 Near-Surface Streamfunction Fields

In order to identify the signature of the 68-D wave in the VMADCP data, we used the vector OA

to map the streamfunction ? directly from the observed u(x , y ) (v (x , y )), the zonal (meridional)

velocity component at a chosen depth. The correlation length and sample error variance used

in an a priori correlation function (Equation 3.1) were 1.2? and 0.1, respectively. The so-

called "observed streamfunction" virtually represents the geostrophic ? and, therefore the ?

distribution at near-surface can directly compared with the AVISO ?.

The shallowest VMADCP data bin is 30 m. This depth is embedded within the mixed layer

and take it as close enough to the surface to be compared with the AVISO ADT field. We also

imposed the no-slip boundary condition at the 30m isobath, which is found at the inner shelf

50



where neither the geostrophic balance is valid nor the BC is in this region. The ? map at 30 m

and its accompanying interpolation normalized error are presented in Figure 3.2.

Figure 3.2: Maps of the CERES V. (A): observational streamfunction ?. (B): the associated
interpolation error at 30m. The gray area represents depths shallower than 100 m; the mangenta
dashed curve denotes the shelf break position.

The ? distribution depicted in Figure 3.2 presents a highly meandering BC with incursions

(anticyclonic meanders) onto the shelf at 24.5?S and 28?S. Excursions (cyclonic meanders) can

be seen at 23?S, 26?S, 28?S and 30.5?S. Oceanward of the BC axis, an anticyclone-cyclone pair

51



Figure 3.3: Comparison between the (A) CERES V ?o and (B) AVISO streamfunction ?a fields
during the cruise period. The black solid line delimits the CERES V sampling area. The gray
area represents depths shallower than 100 m; the magenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break
position.

is clearly identified between 42?W and 46?W.

The investigation of the 68D wave signal was conducted using altimetry data in chapter 2. We

here seek to identify if any of the vorticity structures observed during the CERES V cruise are

related to those waves, which propagate southwestward parallel to the current axis. Figure 3.3

compares the near-surface ? (streamfuction from CERES V) with the ?a (streamfuction for the

averaged AVISO data during cruise) distribution. As expected due to averaging, interpolation

and synopticity issues, the BC meander amplitudes are smaller in the AVISO field than that

of the CERES V ? field. It is probably a precision issue associated with resolving the tides

and the geoid at shallower depths. Thus the ?a field is smoother. Nonetheless, the vortical

pair described in the last paragraph is identifiable in the AVISO map as well. In both maps,

the cyclone-anticyclone pair exhibits an approximately 400-km extension, which matches the

calculated 68-D wavelength.

In order to further pursue whether the vortical pair present in the "raw" AVISO map is related

52



Figure 3.4: Comparison between (A) the AVISO streamfunction field (?a ) during the CERES
V cruise and (B) its FFT-filtered version for a band centered in 68 days (?68). The gray area
represents depths shallower than 100 m; the mangenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break
position.

indeed to the 68-D wave, we apply the same filtering process employed in the analysis described

in chapter 2. We thus again use a band-pass FFT filter centered in period of 68-Ds and with a

range of 10%. The filtered ?68 field Figure 3.4 preserves the presence of both the cyclone and

anticyclone bordering the current. The basin interior is characterized by nearly zero velocities

and reassures in the spatial domain the findings of chapter 2: the 68-D vorticity waves are

intrinsically associated with the BC axis and motion.

The ?68 map reproduces the same two vortical features within the SB along the BC but the

anticyclone-cyclone extent is overestimated in about ?50 km if compared to both the non-
filtered ?a and the CERES V ?o . This difference could have occured because the ?a may

have merged the two adjacent anticyclones centered at (24?S, 44?W) and (26.5?S, 44?W) as a

single one. Aiming to unravel the reason, we rewrite Equation 2.2 in terms of the geostrophic

streamfunction using Equation 2.6 to obtain

53



Figure 3.5: The 68-D filtered total and anomaly AVISO streamfunction fields (?68 and ??68)for
the CERES V cruise period. The gray area represents depths shallower than 100 m; the man-
genta dashed curve denotes the shelf break position.

??(x , y, t ) = ?a (x , y, t ) ???(x , y ) ; (3.3)

where the ?a (x , y, t ),??(x , y ),??(x , y, t ) definitions are analogous to those of ?a (x , y, t ), ¯?(x , y ),

??(x , y, t ). We opt to present the ??68 field and compare it with the total ?68 (Figure 3.5). It is

clearly seen in the anomaly streamfunction field that both anticyclones at 44?W are identifiable.

The crest and trough of the 68-D vorticity wave pattern is shapely displayed. The masking

effect of such feature is due to the ??(x , y ) computed from the MDT.

The 68-D wave propagation axis is not fully aligned with the mean BC as well as totally

parallel to the shelf break either (Figure 3.6). But it is clear that vortical pair propagates south

at the phase speed of 0.07 m s?1 estimated in chapter 2. As it continues to propagate south-

westward, the wave train gets nearer the shelf break. Hence, it is likely that it can promote

shelf-slope exchange as predicted by Biló (2015). Moreover, the more oblique propagation the

wave exhibits relative to the BC axis, the weaker its signal is (Figure 2.18). One possibility is

54



that interaction with topography discontinues the wave pattern; another is the limitation of the

AVISO data in mapping accurately features at shallow depths. On the other hand, in the cases

the wave propagates exactly parallel to the current axis, its signal is not seen as attenuated in

the Hovmöller diagram.

Figure 3.6: The 68-D wave propagation: (A), (B), (C), (D), (E) and (F). The gray area represents
depths shallower than 100 m; the magenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break position.

We present in Figure 3.7 a Hovmöller diagram with a 6-year time series span centered in

55



time on the CERES IV cruise period. The intent is to produce here an analogous diagram to

that shown in Figure 2.18. We repeated the length time to allow the reader a comparison with

the figure from chapter 2 in terms of phase speeds (i.e., the troughs or crests distance-time

inclination). The anticyclone (to the north) and the cyclone (to the south) of the 68-D wave

displayed at Figure 3.3, Figure 3.4, Figure 3.5 and temporally followed through the six panels

of Figure 3.6 are marked by black arrows at its most upstream position. We do see a clear

southward propagation and a discontinuation at ?400 km in the distance axis, which coincides
with the CSM location (which is marked by a magenta dashed line). The wave structure to the

southwest of 400 km line displays bifurcations and much lower amplitude values of the features.

This probably indicate that either the wave ceased to exist somehow or it was reflected since its

trajectory may be oblique relative to the mean current path and hit the western boundary.

Figure 3.7: Hovmöller diagram of the streamfuction anomaly of the AVISO series centered at
the CERES V period. The black arrows mark the anticyclone (crest) and the cyclone (trough)
of the 68-D wave captured by the cruise sampling. The magenta dashed line denotes the CSM
location.

56



We now return to CERES V data aiming a more quantitative comparison between the ? and

? fields, rather the more qualitative one depicted in Figure 3.4. This time, however, we compare

the observational ? with the 68-D filtered version. We want prove that the vortical pair detected

in both maps is indeed the same feature depicted simultaneously by in situ measurements and

remote sensing. Therefore, the features should be located approximately in the same geograph-

ical location in both maps, despite the differences of original data coverage and interpolation

techniques. In order to do so, let us consider two scalar fields A(x , y ) and B (x , y ). A simple way

to evaluate whether they are parallel to each other is to calculate the Jacobian matrix of their

gradients. If they are parallel, then ?A ×?B = 0, i.e.,

J ( A, B ) = d e t
?
??A?x ?A?y
?B
?x

?B
?y

?
? = ?A

?x

?B

?y
? ?A
?y

?B

?x
, (3.4)

Therefore, if J ( A, B ) = 0, so is ?A × ?B = 0 and A and B are parallel. We then calculate the
Jacobian field of the filtered data with the cruise data (Figure 3.8). We should note that the

Jacobian field is higher where the ? fields differ more. As expected, the higher values are found

near shelf break. Nonetheless the Jacobian values within the two main vorticity structures

present in the filtered data are very low, which demonstrates that this cyclone and anticyclone

are positioned at similar location in both data sets. The features in the CERES V map are

smaller, which explains the increasing of the Jacobian values towards their edge. These size

differences can be due to distinct original data resolution, mapping procedures and filtering.

57



Figure 3.8: The Jacobian between the CERES V ? field and the filtered AVISO ? field.

3.3.2 Velocity Vertical Sections

In the previous subsection, we identified a 68-D crest-trough vortical pair in the CERES V

near-surface streamfunction maps and examined its correspondence on the AVISO streamfunc-

tion maps. In the present subsection, we describe two vertical sections of the same situ data

set that captured the anticyclone and the cyclone which form the pair. Figure 3.9 displays the

VMADCP tracks with the two transects that sampled the eddies in red.

Neither of the red-marked transects crossed the eddy but center. As a matter of fact, both

sampled their northeastern borders. Therefore, we do not expect to see velocities comparable

to those of the BC as seen in the ?,?a ,?68 and ??68 horizontal distributions. However, we do

expect to comment on their vertical structure.

58



Figure 3.9: The VMADCP tracks (black thick solid lines) overlaid on the CERES V 30m stream-
function field. The red thick solid line highlights the two transects which vertical structure will
be shown and described in this subsection. The gray area represents depths shallower than 100
m; the mangenta dashed curve denotes the shelf break position.

Anticyclonic Eddy transect

Figure 3.10: Vertical section of the VMADCP profiled velocity of transect #3 (the northern red
transect in Figure 3.9). The black area represents the topography, and the magenta dashed line
the position of outermost station of LADCP top-bottom profile carried out during the cruise and
described by Biló (2015).

59



In this transect (Figure 3.10), we note a BC well attached to the shelf break with a maximum

velocity of ? -0.75 m s?1. Although the VMADCP profiling extent did not capture the IWBC
domain, the velocities at 450 m depth are at ? -0.05 m s?1 and the BC velocities appear to be
decreasing with increasing depth. This shallow BC is due to the fact that this transect is to the

north of the SBi near the slope, and so the BC had not thicken yet. Biló (2015) analyzed the

top-bottom current pattern obtained by LADCP in the transect sampled during the CERES V

(November 2013) at same position of the northern red one shown in Figure 3.9. The authors

described that the BC reacher 500 m and the virtually 1500m-thick IWBC underneath it. Despite

our depth constraint the southwestern velocity decrease depicted with VMADCP data suggests a

similar current configuration is present in the CERES V cruise.

The BC volume transport is -14 Sv in the upper 450 m; its width is 160 km at the surface,

but the cruise did not sampled the whole current structure. Moreover the BC in this transect

is leaning towards the shelf, which is in accordance with the pattern of a frontal anticyclonic

meander, such as the depicted in the ?o map (Figure 3.9).

Oceanward of the inner two-lobe structure associated with BC frontal slope, a second eddy

sectional distribution can be identified in (Figure 3.10). This is the counterclock rotating feature

linked to the 68-D wave and the one we are interested in. Considering its velocity inversion

pattern, the inshore (offshore) lobe of the eddy, which is marked by the negative (positive)

velocities is centered at ?275 km (?350 km) from the transect starting point.
The anticyclone offshore lobe has a maximum velocity of 0.29 ms?1 and a transport of 5.9

Sv. This lobe is 140 km wide and reaches more than 450 m. The coastal lobe presents minimum

velocities of -0.15 ms?1 and is 70 km wide. Deeper than 200 m, its signal merges with the one

from the BC frontal meander, as seen by inspecting Figure 3.9. The difference in the velocities

between the two lobes might be caused by the cruise sampling, i.e., there is a 30? angle be-

tween the line joining the anticyclone centers and the transect orientation. For this reason, the

width and velocity between lobes differ importantly. The vertical extent of the better sampled

(offshore) lobe is comparable with that of the BC. The BC exhibits higher velocity values (in

magnitude) at surface, where its velocity shear is also stronger. Both features seem to be at least

500 m thick.

60



Cyclonic Eddy transect

Figure 3.11: Southern red transect in Figure 3.9. Filed contour of cross-transect velocity, black
area the shelf break and slope and magenta dashed line the limit of LADCP collected during the
cruise and used by Biló (2015).

The transect #4 (the southern red transect) seems as a virtual mirror image of transect #3,

both displayed in Figure 3.9. We observe a cyclonically meandering BC, which is distant from

the shelf break. This frontal cyclonic meander resembles the characteristics of others reported

by Campos et al. (1995) from geostrophic estimates. The inshore lobe presents a maximum of

0.38 m s?1. The maximum BC velocity is ?-0.55 m s?1 at its surface core. The BC vertical shear
seems to be weaker than that observed in the northern transect and presents a more vertically

elongated structure appearing to reach higher depths. At the corresponding CERES IV transect,

Biló (2015), through LADCP profiles, identified a BC which extended from the surface to 750 m

depth with the IWBC beneath it and flowing to north. The inner portion of the transect seems

still to be to the north of the SBi. As described by Boebel et al. (1999) and Legeais et al. (2013),

the bifurcation structure veers to south and develops a cyclonic retroflection at the shallowest

depths of the São Paulo Plateau.

Adjacent to the cyclonic frontal BC meander, transect #4 exhibits vortical lobes of opposite

signs associated with the trough of the 68-D wave. The coastal lobe of the 68-D cyclone has

a vertical structure similar to that of the current and reaching 0.17 m s?1 at 400 m depth. This

lobe maximum velocities are 0.29 m s?1 and its horizontal extension is of 88 km, with core

depth of ?80 m.The oceanic lobe has a horizontal extension of ?140 km and a maximum
velocity of -0.31 m s?1 with the maximum velocity at ? 110 m depth. Additionally, the volume

61



transport of the coastal (oceanic) lobes is 3.33 Sv (-6.6 Sv) . The discrepancy between these two

estimates might be related, as for transect #3, to the angle at which the ship track crossed the

vortical structure. The resemblance of the vertical structure between the 68-D through and the

BC suggests that both features present similar dynamical mode composition. Further sampling

of the eddies vertical structure ought to be done with longer transects and LADCP profiling

covering all their extensions.

62



Chapter 4

Summary and Conclusions

The goal of this work was to study the subinertial variability of the BC system within the SB,

and in order to accomplish that, we primarily used satellite altimetry data and some traditional

spectral analysis techniques. We also analyzed quasi-synoptic observations of an oceanographic

cruise, which was part of the IOUSP-PETROBRAS CERES Experiment and sampled the whole

SB.

The BC thickens and, therefore, changes its vertical structure and dynamical modal compo-

sition as it crosses the SB. As it enters the bight by trying to contour CF (23?S), the BC is about

500 m deep and transports TW and SACW. As the current leaves the bight south of CSM (28?S),

it is 1300 m deep and also transports AAIW and UCDW at subpycnocline levels. These differ-

ences in thickness and accompanying velocity vertical shear is due to the impinging branch of

the intermediate SEC and subsequent bifurcation as it hits the slope at central latitudes of the SB.

This oceanographic feature is referred in the literatures as the SBi.

We showed that there are different phenomena occurring to the north and to the south of the

bifurcation and this might be caused by the SBi feature itself and/or the consequential change

in the BC jet vertical structure downstream. For this reason, we carried out our investigation

examining two separate regions: north and south of the SBi axis. We studied the spectra splitting

the SB domain in the two areas and focused on the two most important peaks at each portion.

The Northern Study Area

North of the SBi, we found a spectrum peak in 175 days which we linked to linear Rossby

waves, and since it was in the range of semiannual phenomena, we did not further analyzed this

period band. The second peak in the northern region of the SB relates to a period of 92 days and

63



a wavelength of 490 km. This wave accounts for ?17% of the BC axis variability and subsequent
downstream propagation along the whole SBi extension. By extending our analysis towards the

interior of the South Atlantic basin, we identified that the 92-day wave signal propagating from

the east as a wave front and reaching the BC. These waves accounted for about ?21% of the
SLA variability at 25?S along the front path.

Certainly the question we asked was: what are these waves? Given their nearly-zonal prop-

agation, the northern area spectrum was first compared to the linear first-mode baroclinic plan-

etary Rossby waves dispersion curve. However, in order to be classified as so, the 490km wave

would have to present a much longer period than 92 days. If we keep this period, their critical

latitude would be 17?S, and the Rossby parameter ? would have to be much larger. As matter of

fact, the identified wave seems to propagate with a phase speed corresponding to a nondisper-

sive linear baroclinic planetary wave of 92 days. We observed that the northern area spectrum

concentrates energy in the vicinities of the so-called NDL. In particular, the (?,k ) pair for the

92-day/490km wave lies near the NDL. The literature has reported that waves with such char-

acteristics are related to nonlinear vorticity waves. Indeed, we calculated the relation between

advective and local terms from the momentum equation, and found the nonlinear parameter

for this wave to be 1.1. Therefore, we conclude that the 92-day oscillations are nonlinear vor-

ticity waves, which are originated to the east of 35?W and propagate zonally towards the BC

axis. These waves then perturb the current exciting oscillatory motions of the same period and

which propagate downstream. Our results suggest that the southward propagating wave train

are in phase with the incoming zonal wave front and account for 1/5 of the BC variability in the

northern area.

The Southern Study Area

South of the SBi axis, we identified two different maxima in the ?, k spectrum calculated

using the FFT2D. They correspond to oscillations with periods of 68 and 148 days. It should be

mentioned that the third maxima found is associated with the 92-day waves coming from the

northern area and propagating south.

The 148-day wave has a length of ?790 km. It is originated in the ocean interior and we were
able to track its signal as far as 5?W. Its propagation is nearly zonal to the west. Such as the 92-

day wave described above, this longer wave appears to be a baroclinic first-mode NDL wave. We

indeed estimated the nonlinear parameter as 1.13, virtually matching the classification we gave

64



to the 92-day wave in the northern area. We however should comment that the critical latitude

of a 148-day linear baroclinic Rossby wave is 29?S. It is therefore possible the existence of

linear Rossby wave with 148-day period, but with a half wavelength of the estimated signal

(420 km). Therefore, in order to match the linear dispersion curve, one possibility is that the

ambient potential vorticity gradient of such waves should include other terms other than the

planetary ?. The other possibility is an association between a linear wave and a nonlinear eddy,

which might propagate at same speed, such as proposed byPolito and Sato (2015). However,

given the obtained ?, k spectrum resemblance to the one presented by Wortham and Wunsch

(2014), we classify the 148-day oscillations as nonlinear vorticity waves.

The second spectrum maximum found south of the SBi was related to oscillations of 68-

day period and 397km wavelength. These waves differ from the previously described ones

because their existence is limited to vicinities of the BC. There is no evidence of westward-

propagating wave front coming from the ocean interior. Phase speeds have approximately the

BC axis orientation and they can only be clearly detected between ? 27?S and ? 32?S. This
propagating signal accounts with a variance of ?21% on the BC axis and almost 28% along the
wave ray tracing.

Due to its propagation axis and its wavelength, this was the only of three investigated wave-

lengths that was possible to search for the evidence in in situ observational data. In CERES V

cruise (1-23 November 2013), we identified a anticyclone-cyclone pair in the outer edge of the

BC. Using VMADCP data we identified a resemblance between the each eddy and the vertical

structure of the BC. This possibly suggests a similar dynamic modal composition a direct link

among the features. However, this needs to be further examined since the velocity profiling only

reached 450 m depth and the LADCP observations available reaches only the innermost part of

the oceanographic transects.

This wave is directly associated with the BC axis and thus can be related perturbations due

to instability in the current. Despite de recent studies regarding instability of the current, they

either did it with current meter data or did not considered the possible effect of the SBi in the

region (Rocha et al., 2014; Fernandes et al., 2009).

By positively testing this thesis hypothesis, we can state that the BC is both locally and

remotely forced. While the remote forcing is associated to impinging westward-propagating

wave fronts with periods of 92 and 148 days. The local forcing seems to produce 68-day

oscillations confined to the vicinities of the current axis.

65



4.1 Future work

From this work we were able to better understand the variability scales of the BC within the

SB, but there is still a lot to know and understand about the BC system in this region.

To better understand the periodic signals identified in the present work, we propose to

process-model to the SB domain. The use a QG nonlinear model or even PE model to access

what is the forcing of the locally-formed southward propagating waves. The interaction of the

incoming NDL waves with the BC and the topography should also be pursued through process

modeling. Moreover, the dynamical role of the SBi as a both a hydrodynamic barrier as well as

a source for perturbations to the BC and the IWBC should be explored using process modeling.

We also suggest the use of further studies and analyses using available observational data

from both quasi-synoptic and time series of currentmeter moorings. Improved spectral tech-

niques like two dimensional wavelets which do not impose constraints in the results like FFT2D

(i.e. permanent and recurrent features).

66



Bibliography

Anderson, D. L., and A. Gill (1975), Spin-up of a stratified ocean, with applications to up-

welling, Deep Sea Research and Oceanographic Abstracts, 22(9), 583 – 596.

Andres, M., J.-H. Park, M. Wimbush, X.-H. Zhu, K.-I. Chang, and H. Ichikawa (2008), Study

of the kuroshio/ryukyu current system based on satellite-altimeter and in situ measurements,

Journal of oceanography, 64(6), 937–950.

Azevedo, J. L., D. Nof, and M. M. Mata (2012), Eddy-train encounters with a continental

boundary: a south atlantic case study, Journal of Physical Oceanography, 42(9), 1548–1565.

Belo, W. C. (2011), A recirculação interna do giro subtropical do atlântico sul e a circulação

oceânica na região do pólo pré-sal da bacia de santos, Ph.D. thesis, Universidade de São

Paulo.

Biló, T. C. (2015), The changing brazil current system between 23 s-31 s: vertical structure and

mesoscale dynamics, Master’s thesis, Universidade de São Paulo.

Boebel, O., R. E. Davis, M. Ollitrault, R. G. Peterson, P. L. Richardson, C. Schmid, and W. Zenk

(1999), The Intermediate Depth Circulation of the Western South Atlantic, Geophys. Res.

Lett., 26(21), 3329–3332.

Bretherton, F. P., R. E. Davis, and C. B. Fandry (1976), A technique for objective analysis and

design of oceanographic experiments applied to MODE 73, Deep-Sea Res., 23, 559–582.

Calado, L., A. Gangopadhyay, and I. Da Silveira (2008), Feature-oriented regional modeling

and simulations (forms) for the western south atlantic: Southeastern brazil region, Ocean

Modelling, 25(1), 48–64.

Calado, L., I. Da Silveira, A. Gangopadhyay, and B. De Castro (2010), Eddy-induced upwelling

off cape são tomé (22 s, brazil), Continental Shelf Research, 30(10), 1181–1188.

67



Campos, E. J., and D. B. Olson (1991), Stationary rossby waves in western boundary current

extensions, Journal of Physical Oceanography, 21(8), 1202–1224.

Campos, E. J. D., J. E. Gonçalves, and Y. Ikeda (1995), Water mass characteristics and

geostrophic circulation in the South Brazil Bight: Summer of 1991, J. Geophys. Res.,

100(C9), 18,537–18,550.

Campos, E. J. D., Y. Ikeda, B. M. Castro, S. A. Gaeta, J. A. Lorenzzetti, and M. R. Stevenson

(1996), Experiment Studies Circulation in the Western South Atlantic, 77(27), 253–264.

Campos, E. J. D., D. Velhote, and I. C. A. Silveira (2000), Shelf break upwelling driven by the

Brazil Current meanders, Geophys. Res. Lett., 27(6), 751–754.

Carter, E. F., and A. R. Robinson (1987), Analysis models for the estimation of oceanic fields,

Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology, 4(1), 49–74.

Chaigneau, A., A. Gizolme, and C. Grados (2008), Mesoscale eddies off peru in altimeter

records: Identification algorithms and eddy spatio-temporal patterns, Progress in Oceanog-

raphy, 79(2), 106–119.

Chelton, D. B., M. G. Schlax, and R. M. Samelson (2011), Global observations of nonlinear

mesoscale eddies, Progress in Oceanography, 91(2), 167–216.

Chen, G., Y. Hou, X. Chu, P. Qi, and P. Hu (2009), The variability of eddy kinetic energy in

the south china sea deduced from satellite altimeter data, Chinese Journal of Oceanology and

Limnology, 27(4), 943–954.

da Silveira, I. C., L. B. Miranda, and W. S. Brown (1994), On the origins of the north brazil

current, Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans, 99(C11), 22,501–22,512.

da Silveira, I. C., G. R. Flierl, and W. S. Brown (1999), Dynamics of separating western bound-

ary currents, Journal of Physical Oceanography, 29(2), 119–144.

Early, J. J., R. Samelson, and D. B. Chelton (2011), The evolution and propagation of quasi-

geostrophic ocean eddies, J. Phys. Oceanogr., 41(8), 1535–1555.

Fernandes, A. M., I. C. A. da Silveira, L. Calado, E. J. D. Campos, and A. M. Paiva (2009), A

two-layer approximation to the Brazil Cirrent-Intermediate Western Boundary Current Sys-

tem between 20°S and 28°S, Ocean Modeling, 29, 154–158.

68



Firing, E., J. Ranada, and P. Caldwell (1995), Processing ADCP data with the CODAS software

system version 3.1, Tech. rep., Joint Inst. for Mar. and Atmos. Res./NODC, University of

Hawaii at Manoa, Honolulu.

Flierl, G. R. (1978), Models of vertical structure and the calibration of two-layer models, Dy-

namics of Atmospheres and Oceans, 2(4), 341 – 381.

Garfield, N. (1990), The Brazil Current at subtropical latitudes, Ph.D. thesis, University of

Rhode Island, Rhode Island.

Garzoli, S. L., S. Dong, R. Fine, C. S. Meinen, R. C. Perez, C. Schmid, E. Van Sebille, and

Q. Yao (2015), The fate of the deep western boundary current in the south atlantic, Deep Sea

Research Part I: Oceanographic Research Papers, 103, 125–136.

Gill, A. E. (2016), Atmosphere—ocean dynamics, Elsevier.

Goes, M., R. Molinari, I. da Silveira, and I. Wainer (2005), Retroflections of the north brazil

current during february 2002, Deep Sea Research Part I: Oceanographic Research Papers,

52(4), 647–667.

Gordon, A. L., and C. L. Greengrove (1986), Geostrophic circulation of the brazil-falkland

confluence, Deep Sea Research Part A. Oceanographic Research Papers, 33(5), 573–585.

Guerra, L. A. d. A. (2011), Vórtices das agulhas colidem com a corrente do brasil?, Ph.D. thesis,

Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro.

Hughes, C. W., and B. A. De Cuevas (2001), Why western boundary currents in realistic oceans

are inviscid: A link between form stress and bottom pressure torques, Journal of Physical

Oceanography, 31(10), 2871–2885.

Johns, W. E., T. N. Lee, F. A. Schott, R. J. Zantopp, and R. H. Evans (1990), The north brazil

current retroflection: Seasonal structure and eddy variability, Journal of Geophysical Re-

search: Oceans, 95(C12), 22,103–22,120.

Legeais, J.-F., M. Ollitrault, and M. Arhan (2013), Lagrangian observations in the Intermediate

Western Boundary Current of the South Atlantic, 85, 109–126.

69



Locarnini, R. A., A. V. Mishonov, J. I. Antonov, T. P. Boyer, H. E. Garcia, O. K. Baranova,

M. M. Zweng, C. R. Paver, J. R. Reagan, D. R. Johnson, M. Hamilton, and D. Seidov (2013),

World Ocean Atlas 2013, Volume 2: Temperature, Tech. rep., NOAA.

Lorenzzetti, J. A., J. L. Stech, W. L. M. Filho, and A. T. Assireu (2009), Satellite observation

of Brazil Current inshore thermal front in the SW South Atlantic: Space/time variability and

sea surface temperatures, Cont. Shelf Res., 29(17), 2061–2068.

Mano, M. F., A. M. Paiva, A. R. T. Jr., and A. L. G. A. Coutinho (2009), Energy Flux to a

Cyclonic Eddy off Cabo Frio, Brazil, J. Phys. Oceanogr., 39, 2999–3010.

Mata, M. M., S. Wijffels, J. A. Church, and M. Tomczak (2006), Statistical description of

the east australian current low-frequency variability from the woce pcm3 array, Marine and

freshwater research, 57(3), 273–290.

Meinen, C., A. Piola, R. Perez, and S. Garzoli (2012), Deep western boundary current transport

variability in the south atlantic: preliminary results from a pilot array at 34.5° s, Ocean

Science, 8(6), 1041–1054.

Mémery, L., M. Arhan, X. A. Alvarez-Salgado, M. J. Messias, H. Mercier, C. G. Castro, and

A. F. Rios (2000), The water masses along the western boundary of the south and equatorial

Atlantic, Prog. Oceanog., 47(1), 69–98.

Morten, A.-B. F. G., AJ (2017), Wavenumber-frequency analysis of single-layer shallow-water

beta-plane quasi-geostrophic turbulence.

Munk, W. H. (1950), On the wind-driven ocean circulation, Journal of meteorology, 7(2), 80–

93.

Oliveira, L. R., A. R. Piola, M. M. Mata, and I. D. Soares (2009), Brazil Current surface circu-

lation and energetics observed from drifiting buoys, J. Geophys. Res., 114(C10006).

Pedlosky, J. (2013), Ocean circulation theory, Springer Science &amp;amp; Business Media.

Polito, P. S., and W. T. Liu (2003), Global characterization of rossby waves at several spectral

bands, Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans, 108.

Polito, P. S., and O. T. Sato (2015), Do eddies ride on rossby waves?, Journal of Geophysical

Research: Oceans, 120(8), 5417–5435.

70



Rocha, C. B., I. C. A. da Silveira, B. M. Castro, and J. A. M. Lima (2014), Vertical structure,

energetics and dynamics of the Brazil Current System at 22°S-28°S, J. Geophys. Res-Oceans,

doi:10.1002/2013JC009143.

Rodrigues, R. R., L. M. Rothstein, and M. Wimbush (2007), Seasonal Variability of the

South Equatorial Current Bifurcation in the Atlantic Ocean: A Numerical Study, J. Phys.

Oceanogr., 37, 16–30.

Rodrigues, R. R., M. Wimbush, D. R. Watts, L. M. Rothstein, and M. Ollitrault (2010), South

atlantic mass transports obtained from subsurface float and hydrographic data, Journal of

Marine Research, 68(6), 819–850.

Samelson, R. (2010), An effective-? vector for linear planetary waves on a weak mean flow,

Ocean Modelling, 32(3), 170–174.

Schmid, C. (2014), Mean vertical and horizontal structure of the subtropical circulation in the

south atlantic from three-dimensional observed velocity fields, Deep Sea Research Part I:

Oceanographic Research Papers, 91, 50–71.

Schmid, C., H. Schäfer, W. Zenk, and G. Podestá (1995), The vitória eddy and its relation to

the brazil current, Journal of physical oceanography, 25(11), 2532–2546.

Schmitz, W. J. (1995), On the interbasin-scale thermohaline circulation, Reviews of Geophysics,

33(2), 151–173.

Silveira, I. C., J. A. M. Lima, A. C. K. Schimdt, W. Ceccopieri, A. Satori, C. P. F. Francisco,

and R. F. C. Fontes (2008), Is the meander growth in the Brazil Current System off Southeast

Brazil due to baroclinic instability?, Dynam. Atmos. Oceans, 45, 187–207.

Silveira, I. C. A., L. Calado, B. M. de Castro, M. Cirano, J. A. M. Lima, and A. S. Mascarenhas

(2004), On the Baroclinic Structure of the Brazil Current-Intermediate Western Boundary

Current at 22°-23°S, Geophys. Res. Lett., 31, 4308.

Silveira, I. C. d., W. S. Brown, and G. R. Flieri (2000), Dynamics of the north brazil cur-

rent retroflection region from the western tropical atlantic experiment observations (paper

2000jc900129), Journal of Geophysical Research-Part C-Oceans, 105(12), 28,559–28,584.

71



Soutelino, R., I. Da Silveira, A. Gangopadhyay, and J. Miranda (2011), Is the brazil current

eddy-dominated to the north of 20 s?, Geophysical Research Letters, 38(3).

Soutelino, R. G., A. Gangopadhyay, and I. C. A. da Silveira (2013), The roles of vertical shear

and topography on the eddy formation near the site of origin of the Brazil Current, Cont.

Shelf Res., 70, 46–60.

SSALTO/Duacs (2014), A new version of SSALTO/Duacs products available in April 2014.

Stommel, H. (1948), The westward intensification of wind-driven ocean currents, Eos, Trans-

actions American Geophysical Union, 29(2), 202–206.

Stommel, H. (1961), Thermohaline convection with two stable regimes of flow, Tellus, 13(2),

224–230.

Stommel, H. (1965), The Gulf Stream: A Physical and Dynamical Description, University of

California Press.

Stramma, L., and M. England (1999), On the wather masses and mean circulation of the South

Atlantic Ocean, J. Geophys. Res., 104(C9), 20,863–20,883.

Sverdrup, H. U. (1947), Wind-driven currents in a baroclinic ocean; with application to the

equatorial currents of the eastern pacific, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences,

33(11), 318–326.

Talley, L. D., G. L. Pickard, W. J. Emery, and J. H. Swift (2011), Descriptive Physical Oceanog-

raphy: An Introduction, sixth ed., Academic Press.

Tsuchiya, M. (1985), Evidence of a double-cell subtropical gyre in the south atlantic ocean,

Journal of Marine Research, 43(1), 57–65.

Vianna, M. L., V. V. Menezes, and D. P. Chambers (2007), A high resolution satellite-only

grace-based mean dynamic topography of the south atlantic ocean, Geophysical Research

Letters, 34(24).

Wortham, C., and C. Wunsch (2014), A multidimensional spectral description of ocean vari-

ability, Journal of Physical Oceanography, 44(3), 944–966.

72



Young, W. R., and P. Rhines (1982), A theory of the wind-driven circulation ii. gyres with

western boundary layers, J. Mar. Res, 40, 849–872.

Zemba, J. C. (1991), The structure and transport of the Brazil Current between 27°and

36°South, Ph.D. thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Woods Hole Oceano-

graphic Institution.

Zhang, D., T. N. Lee, W. E. Johns, C.-T. Liu, and R. Zantopp (2001), The kuroshio east of

taiwan: Modes of variability and relationship to interior ocean mesoscale eddies, Journal of

Physical Oceanography, 31(4), 1054–1074.

Zweng, M. M., J. R. Reagan, J. I. Antonov, R. A. Locarnini, A. V. Mishonov, T. P. Boyer, H. E.

Garcia, O. K. Baranova, D. R. Johnson, D. Seidov, and M. M. Biddle (2013), World Ocean

Atlas 2013, Volume 2: Salinity, Tech. rep., NOAA.

73


	List of Figures
	List of Tables
	List of Acronyms
	Abstract
	Resumo
	Introduction
	Large Scale Circulation
	Description
	Forcing

	The Study Area
	The BC mesoscale variability
	Thesis Hypothesis and Objectives
	Hypothesis
	Objectives


	Mesoscale Variability from Satellite Altimetry
	Datasets
	Altimetry
	Climatological hydrographic data

	Methods
	Annual signal removal
	Fast Fourier Transform
	Correlation field
	Radon Transform
	Explained variance

	Results and Discussion
	North of the Santos Bifurcation
	South of the Santos Bifurcation


	Quasi-Synoptic Observations
	Dataset
	In situ Quasi-Synoptic Velocity Measurements

	Methods: Objective Mapping
	Results and Discussion
	Near-Surface Streamfunction Fields
	Velocity Vertical Sections


	Summary and Conclusions
	Future work

	Bibliography

</field>
	</doc>
</add>