<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.18329</field>
		<field name="filename">25235_Tese_Zahra%20Abdollahnead_2016.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">
Z
ah

ra
 A

bd
ol

la
hn

ej
ad

July 2016U
M

in
ho

 |
 2

01
6

D
ev

el
op

m
en

t 
of

 F
oa

m
 O

ne
-P

ar
t 

G
eo

po
ly

m
er

s

Universidade do Minho
Escola de Engenharia

Zahra Abdollahnejad

Development of Foam One-Part Geopolymers



July 2016

Doctoral Thesis
Civil Engineering, Material

Work performed under the supervision of
Associate Professor Dr. José Luís Barroso de Aguiar

Co-Supervisor
Dr. Fernando Pacheco Torgal

Zahra Abdollahnejad

Development of Foam One-Part Geopolymers

Universidade do Minho
Escola de Engenharia



Zahara Abdollahnejad



Thesis chapters 

 

II 
 

 

 

 

 

 

Acknowledgments 

This thesis would not have been possible without the support of many 

people. Foremost, I would like to express my sincere gratitude to my 

supervisors Prof. Jose Barroso Aguiar for the continuous support of my PhD 

study and Investigator Pacheco-Torgal for his patience, motivation, 

enthusiasm, and immense knowledge. Their guidance helped me alot 

throughout writing this thesis. I could not have imagined having a better 

advisors and mentors for my PhD study.  

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

III 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

The author wishes to express her love and gratitude to her beloved father and 

mother; for their understanding and endless love, through the duration of her 

studies. 

Last but not the least; I would like to thank my supportive friend Mohammad 

Mastali throughout my PhD programme. 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

IV 
 

Resumo 

A produção de cimento Portland normal (CPN) o mais importante constituinte do betão requer 

uma elevada produção de energia com a consequente libertação para a atmosfera de dióxido de 

carbono e outros gases responsáveis por efeito de estufa (GEE). As preocupações ambientais 

relacionadas com as elevadas emissões de CO2 geradas durante a produção do CPN motivaram 

investigações para o desenvolvimento de novos materiais ligantes eco-eficientes. Os 

geopolímeros são ligantes alternativos ao CPN obtidos a partir de aluminosilicatos e activadores 

alcalinos. A geopolímerização é um processo quimico complexo que envolve a dissolução dos 

aluminosilicatos, o seu transporte, orientação e policondensação de produtos de reação. Contudo 

são reconhecidas algumas limitações aos geopolímeros correntes, bicomponentes (contendo 

soluções alcalinas e silicatos solúveis). A utilização de soluções alcalinas agressivas dificulta a 

aplicação dos geopolímeros. A utilização de silicato de sódio é responsável por uma elevada 

pegada carbónica dos geopolímeros. A durabilidade destes materiais é ainda tema controverso. 

Por exemplo os geopolímeros correntes (bicomponentes) estão associados à formação substancial 

de eflorescências pelo facto das soluções alcalinas e silicatos solúveis não reagirem totalmente 

durante o processo de geopolimerização. Este fenómeno é responsável por um aumento da 

permeabilidade dos geopolímeros e por uma redução da sua durabilidade. Consequentemente é 

necessário estudar novas e melhores misturas geopoliméricas. A descoberta dos geopolímeros 

monofásicos é considerada um importante acontecimento em termos de geopolímeros de baixas 

emissões de carbono aos quais basta juntar água, exactamente como sucede com o CPN. Contudo 

até ao presente momento estes novos ligantes tem estado associados a baixos valores de 

resistência à compressão. Alguns autores até referem uma perda de resistência ao longo do tempo 

em geopolímeros monofásicos à base de lamas vermelhas calcinadas e hidróxido de sódio. A 

presente tese pretende desenvolver novas misturas de geopolímeros monofásicos com um 

desempenho suficiente para poderem ser utilizadas pela indústria da construção. Na mesma foram 

estudadas as propriedades mecânicas e a durabilidade das novas misturas. Analisou-se a 

aplicabilidade de um modelo numérico para a previsão da resistência à compressão das novas 

misturas. Efetuou-se a caracterização dos produtos de reação através da análise da microestrutura 

e da espectroscopia de infravermelhos. Estudou-se a possibilidade da utilização dos geopolímeros 

monofásicos na produção de argamassas porosas leves com condutibilidade térmica melhorada. 

O seu desempenho foi comparado com o desempenho de argamassas porosas leves obtidas de 

geopolímeros correntes (bicomponentes) em termos de propriedades, custo e potencial de 

aquecimento global. 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

V 
 

Abstract 

The production of ordinary Portland cement (OPC) as the essential constituent of concrete 

requires considerable energy, releasing a significant amount of carbon dioxide and other 

greenhouse gases (GHGs) into atmosphere. Environmental concerns regarding the high 

CO2 emissions related to the production of OPC led to research efforts on the development 

of eco-efficient alternative binders. Geopolymers constitute promising inorganic binders 

alternative to OPC which are based on aluminosilicates by-products and alkali activators. The 

geopolymerization is a complex chemical process evolving dissolution of raw materials, 

transportation, orientation and polycondensation of the reaction products. However, there are 

still many drawbacks associated with traditional two part geopolymer mixes (containing 

alkaline species and soluble silicates). The caustic alkaline solutions make the handling and 

application of geopolymers difficult. The use of sodium silicate is responsible for a high 

carbon footprint of two part geopolymers. The durability of these binders is also subject of 

some controversy. For instance, current two part geopolymeric mixes can suffer from a high 

amount of efflorescence originated by the fact that alkaline or soluble silicates that are added 

during processing cannot be totally consumed during geopolymerisation. This phenomenon 

is responsible for an increase in geopolymer permeability and reduced durability. Therefore, 

the study of new and improved geopolymer mixes is needed. The discovery of one-part 

geopolymers is considered as a key event on the evolution of low carbon dioxide geopolymer 

technology in the “just add water” concept as it happens with OPC. However so far they were 

associated with very low compressive strength. Some authors even report a compressive 

strength decrease with time for one-part geopolymers based on calcined red mud and sodium 

hydroxide blends. The present thesis aimed to develop one part geopolymer mixtures with 

acceptable performance to be of some use for the construction industry. The mechanical 

properties and the durability performance of the new one-part geopolymer mixtures were 

studied. A numerical model to predict the compressive strength of one part-geopolymers was 

suggested. Hydration products results assessed with SEM/EDS and FTIR spectra were 

presented. The use of one part geopolymers for production of lightweight foam mortars with 

the improved thermal performance was studied. Comparisons to foam two part geopolymer 

mortars were made concerning properties, cost and global warming potential assessment. 

 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

VI 
 

Contents                                                                              Page 

CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

1.1 Justification                                                                                                  1 

1.2 Objectives                                                                                                     2 

1.3 Publications                                                                                                  3 

1.3.1.  International Journal Papers                                                                    3 

1.3.2. Conference Papers                                                                                    4 

1.3.3. Book Chapters                                                                                          4 

1.4 Thesis structure                                                                                             5 

 

CHAPTER 2-Literature review on two part geopolymers 

2.1 Two part geopolymers                                                                                    7                          

2.1.1 Alkali-activated binder                                                                                7 

2.2 Limitation of durability of geopolymer                                                         13 

2.2.1 Resistance to acid attack                                                                             14 

2.2.2 Alkali-silica reaction (ASR)                                                                       16 

2.2.3 Corrosion of steel reinforcement                                                                18 

2.2.4 Resistance to high temperatures                                                                 20 

2.2.5 Efflorescences                                                                                             21 

2.3 One part geopolymers                                                                                    25 

2.4 Conclusions                                                                                                    26 

 

CHAPTER 3-Experimental 

3. Experimental                                                                                                    29 

3.1 Materials                                                                                                         29 

3.1.1 Ordinary Portland Cement (OPC)                                                               29 

3.1.2 Superplasticizer (SP)                                                                                   29 

3.1.3 Fly ash                                                                                                         29 

3.1.4 Sand                                                                                                             30 

3.1.5 Kaolin                                                                                                          30 

3.1.6 Alkali activators                                                                                          31 

3.1.6.1 Sodium hydroxide                                                                                    32 

3.1.6.2 Sodium silicate                                                                                         32 

3.1.7 Foam agents                                                                                                   32 



Thesis chapters 

 

VII 
 

3.1.7.1 Hydrogen peroxide                                                                                     33 

3.1.7.2 Sodium perborate                                                                                        33 

3.1.7.3 Aluminum powder                                                                                      33 

3.4 Executed tests                                                                                                   33 

3.4.1 Water absorption by immersion                                                                    33 

3.4.2 Capillarity water absorption                                                                          34 

3.4.3 Compressive strength                                                                                    34 

3.4.4 Chloride diffusion                                                                                         34 

3.4.5 Carbonation resistance                                                                                  35 

3.4.6 Resistance to acid attack                                                                               35 

3.4.7 Bulk density                                                                                                  36 

3.4.8 Thermal conductivity                                                                                    36 

3.4.9 XRD                                                                                                              37 

3.4.10 SEM/EDS                                                                                                    37 

3.2.11 FTIR                                                                                                            38 

 

CHAPTER 4- Mix design, properties and durability 

4.1 Mechanical properties                                                                                      40 

4.1.1 Mix design                                                                                                     40 

4.1.2 Results and discussions                                                                                 42 

4.2. Compressive strength model                                                                           57 

4.3 Microstructure                                                                                                  57 

4.3.1 SEM                                                                                                               58 

4.3.2 EDS analysis                                                                                                  58 

4.4 FTIR                                                                                                                  58 

4.5 Mix proportioning                                                                                             60 

4.5.1 Compressive strength.                                                                                    60 

4.6 Durability                                                                                                          61 

4.6.1 Efflorescences                                                                                                61 

4.6.2 Water absorption by immersion                                                                     61 

4.6.3 Capillarity water absorption                                                                           62 

4.6.4 Chloride diffusion                                                                                          63 

4.6.5 Carbonation resistance                                                                                   64 

4.6.6 Resistance to acid attack                                                                                 65 



Thesis chapters 

 

VIII 
 

4.7 Conclusions                                                                                                        66 

 

 

CHAPTER 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

5.1 Introduction                                                                                                      69    

5.2 Two part foam geopolymers                                                                            70 

5.2.1 Properties                                                                                                      70 

5.2.2 Cost analysis                                                                                                 84 

5.3 One part foam geopolymers                                                                             88  

5.3.1 Properties                                                                                                      88 

5.3.2 Cost analysis                                                                                                 98 

5.3.3  Global warming potential                                                                           100 

5.4 Conclusions                                                                                                    100 

 

CHAPTER 6-Conclusions and suggestions for further investigations 

   6.1 Conclusions and suggestions for further investigations                                103 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

IX 
 

Figures Index                                                                                              Page 

Fig. 2.1 Summary of CO2-e for Grade 40 concrete mixtures with OPC and 

geopolymer binders                                                                                                                                                                                                10 

Fig. 2.2 Alkali-activated concrete after 10 months curing. (A) Reactive 

aggregate. (G) Alkali-silica gel                                                                                                             
17 

Fig 2.3 Ratios of the expansion relative to the limit proposed in the standard 

used for ASR test, for Portland cement and alkali-activated slag mixtures 

(Cyr and Pouhet,2014)                                                                                                                 
19 

Fig. 2.4 Transverse sections of carbonated alkali-activated slag concretes 

after 1000 h of exposure to a 1% CO2 environment, with the extent of 

carbonation revealed by a phenolphthalein indicator. Samples are 76.2 mm 

in diameter                                       

20 

Fig. 2.5 Geopolymer structure model                                                                            22 
Fig. 2.6 Alkali-activated mine waste mortars specimens after water 

immersion         
23 

Fig 2.7 High efflorescence after 50 days of partially-immersed Alkali 

activated fly ash 
24 

Fig 2.8 Efflorescence of the dense geopolymer TRSF0 and the foamed 

geopolymer TRSF2 specimens stored for times with the bottom in contact 

with water                              
25 

Fig 2.9 Compressive strengths of red mud-based one-part geopolymers 

produced with different activator doses as a function of the time of curing 

(Ke et al., 2015)             

26 

Fig. 3.1 Kaolin particle diameter obtained with and without a defloculation 

agent    
30 

Fig. 3.2 DTA/TGA curves for kaolin                                                                           31 

Fig. 3.3 Alambeta device                                                                                             36 

Fig. 3.4 Machine used to obtain XRD results                                                              37 

Fig. 3.5 Machine used to take SEM images                                                                 38 

Fig. 3.6  Device employed to obtain FTIR spectra                                                      38 

Fig. 4.1 Compressive strength: Phase A                                                                      43 

Fig. 4.2 Compressive strength: Phase B                                                                      44 

Fig. 4.3 Compressive strength: Phase C                                                                     44 

Fig. 4.4 Compressive strength: Phase D                                                                      45 

Fig. 4.5 Experimental and predicted compressive strength of mixtures a) 30 

OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, b) 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS and c) 18 

OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS                                                                                                                     

54 

Fig. 4.6 Plots for determining k and n in a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, 

b) 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS and c) 18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS                       
55 

Fig. 4.7 Compressive strength a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, b) 26 

OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS and c) 18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS in 

logarithmic scale                      

56 

Fig. 4.8 SEM micrograph of interfacial transition zone                                                    57 

Fig. 4.9 SEM micrograph of hybrid alkaline cement mortar                                            57 

Fig. 4.10  FTIR spectra                                                                                                      59 



Thesis chapters 

 

X 
 

Fig. 4.11 Compressive strength                                                                                         61 

Fig. 4.12 Water absorption by immersion                                                                         62 

Fig. 4.13 Water absorption capillarity coefficient                                                             63 

Fig. 4.14 Chloride diffusion coefficient                                                                            63 

Fig. 4.15 Carbonation depth                                                                                              64 

Fig. 4.16 Weight loss of specimens due to acid attack                                                     65 

Fig. 5.1 Water absorption by immersion according to activator/binder ratio 

and sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio:a) Activator/binder 

ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6                                                                               

72 

Fig. 5.2 Density according to activator/binder ratio and sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) 

Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6                                                                                                                            

73 

Fig. 5.3 Thermal conductivity according to activator/binder ratio and sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) 

Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6                                                                                

75 

Fig. 5.4 Thermal conductivity versus density: a) Hydrogen peroxide based 

geopolymers; b) Sodium perborate based geopolymers; c) both                                                                 
76 

Fig. 5.5 Compressive strength according to activator/binder ratio and sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) 

Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6                                                                                

78 

Fig. 5.6 Compressive strength versus density: a) Hydrogen peroxide based 

geopolymers; b) Sodium perborate based geopolymers; c) both                                                             
79 

Fig. 5.7 SEM mix FGA                                                                                                     80 

Fig. 5.8 SEM mix FGB                                                                                                     81 

Fig. 5.9 SEM mix FGC                                                                                                     82 

Fig. 5.10 IR bands of foam geopolymers: a) FGA; b) FGB; c) FGC                               84 

Fig. 5.11 Cost according to activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium 

hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder 

ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6                                                                                                                            

85 

Fig. 5.12 Cost to thermal resistance ratio                                                                         86 

Fig. 5.13 Cost to thermal resistance ratio                                                                    

a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder 

ratio=0.6 

87 

Fig. 5.14 XRD patterns of: a) 100 OPC (1.5% AL); b) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 

CS_7.7 CH (0.5% AL); c) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (5% H2O2); d) 30 

OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (3.5% H2O2); M-Mullite; Q-Quartz; C-Calcite; 

CA-Calcite silicate oxide                

89 

Fig. 5.15 SEM images of: a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (3.5% H2O2);  

b) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (5% H2O2); c) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 

CS_7.7 CH (0.5% AL); d) 100 OPC (1.5% AL);                                                                                            

90 

Fig. 5.16 Compressive strength                                                                                      91 

Fig. 5.17 Water absorption                                                                                             93 

Fig. 5.18 Bulk density                                                                                                    95 

Fig. 5.19 Thermal conductivity                                                                                      97 

Fig. 5.20 Cost of one-part geopolymer mixtures: Gray bars) Materials cost; 

Red bars) Materials cost for a carbon cost in scenario 1; Gree bars) Materials 

cost for a carbon cost in scenario 2                                                                                                                  

99 



Thesis chapters 

 

XI 
 

Fig. 5.21 Cost to thermal resistance ratio                                                                     99 

Fig. 5.22 Global warming potential to thermal resistance ratio                                   100 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 





Thesis chapters 

 

XII 
 

Tables Index                                                                                              Page 

Table 2.1 Bibliographic history of some important alkali-activated 

cement/geopolymer                                                                                                8 
 

Table 3.1 Chemical composition of the Portland cement                                      29  

Table 3.2 Chemical composition and physical properties of the fly ash               30  

Table 3.3 Characteristics of the sand                                                                     30  

Table 4.1 Mix proportions used in phase A                                                           40  

Table 4.2 Mix proportions used in phase B                                                           41  

Table 4.3 Mix proportions used in phase C                                                           41  

Table 4.4 Phase C-Volumetric ratios                                                                     41  

Table 4.5 Mix proportions used in phase D                                                           42 

Table 4.6 Phase D-Weight ratios                                                                           42                                                                            

Table 4.7 Composition of one part geopolymer mixes used for modeling 

compressive strength                                                                                              46 

 

Table 4.8 Constant, exponent and equation of compressive strength evolution for 

one part geopolymers                                                                                              53 
 

Table 4.9 Phase D-Weigth ratios                                                                            58                                                                        

Table 4.10 EDS Atomic ratio analysis                                                                   58 
 

 

Table 4.11 Mix composition [Kg/m3]                                                                     60  

Table 4.12 Resistance to chloride penetration                                                        64 

Table 5.1 EDS atomic ratios                                                                                   70                                                     
 

Table 5.2 EDS atomic ratios                                                                                    77  

Table 5.3 Content of geopolymer samples used for FTIR                                       83  

Table 5.4 Cost of the materials (euro/kg)                                                                85  

Table 5.5 Composition of one-part geopolymer mixtures                                       88  

Table 5.6 EDS atomic ratios                                                                                    89  

Table 5.7 Costs of the materials (euro/kg)                                                               98  

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Thesis chapters 

 

XIII 
 

 

Abbreviations and acronyms  

OPC – Ordinary Portland cement 

FA- Fly ash 

SP- Superplasticizer 

DTA- Differential thermal analysis 

TGA-Thermo gravimetric analysis  

SEM- Scanning Electron Microscopy 

FEG-Field Emission Gun  

EDS- Energy Dispersive Spectroscopy 

ITZ- Interfacial transition zone 

FTIR- Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy 

CSH- Calcium silicate hydrates 

Na-C-S-H-Sodium calcium silicate hydrates 

Na-A-S-H - Sodium aluminum silicate hydrates 

K-A-S-H - Potassium aluminum silicate hydrates 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

 

1 
 

1. Introduction  

This section presents a brief introduction and justifications on foam one-part geopolymer 

mortars. Then, the main objectives and finally published papers in this thesis are discussed.  

  

  1.1 Justifications 

The increasing worldwide demand for energy is a major cause of unsustainable development 

on our Planet. Between 2007 and 2030, energy demand will have risen around 40%, reaching 

a total of 16.8 billion tonnes of equivalent petroleum-TEP (Pacheco-Torgal &amp;amp; Jalali, 2011). 

The rise in energy consumption has two main causes, the increase in world population and the 

fact that there are an increasing number of people with access to electricity. In fact, currently, 

there are 1.5 billion people that still have no access to electricity (UN, 2010). Besides, since 

the urban human population will almost double, increasing from approximately 3.4 billion in 

2009 to 6.4 billion in 2050 (WHO, 2014), this will dramatically increase electricity demand. 

Since buildings consume throughout their life cycle, more than 40% of all energy produced 

(OECD, 2003), this subsector has a high potential for reducing carbon dioxide emissions. The 

European Union has been producing legislation in the field of building’s energy performance, 

which was materialised in the form of the European Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 

2002/91/EC (EPBD), which in turn, has been recast in the form of the 2010/ 31/ EU by the 

European Parliament on 19 May 2010. One of the new aspects of the EPBD that reflects an 

ambitious agenda on the reduction of the energy consumption is the introduction of the concept 

of nearly zero-energy building (Pacheco-Torgal, Cabeza, Mistretta, Kaklauskas, &amp;amp; Granqvist, 

2013). The use of thermal insulation materials constitutes the most effective way of mitigating 

heat loss in buildings, thus reducing heat energy needs, and therefore contributing to the nearly 

zero energy target. These materials are very important for the building material industry and 

represent a 21 billion € market share (Pacheco-Torgal, 2014). However, most current insulation 

materials are associated with negative impacts in terms of toxicity. Polystyrene, for example 

contains anti-oxidant additives and ignition retardants, additionally, its production involves the 

generation of benzene and chlorofluorocarbons. On the other hand, polyurethane is obtained 

from isocyanates, which are widely known for their tragic association with the Bhopal disaster. 

Besides, they release toxic fumes when subjected to fire (PachecoTorgal, Jalali, &amp;amp; Fucic, 

2012). In terms of legislation, the European Union recently approved the Regulation (EU) 

305/2011 (2011) related to the Construction Products. 



CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

 

2 
 

Regulation that will replace the current Directive 89/106/CEE, already amended by Directive 

1993/68/EEC, known as the Construction Products Directive. In the last years, several papers 

were published on foam alkali-activated cements with enhanced thermal conductivity (Feng et 

al., 2015; Hlavá?ek, Šmilauer, Škvára, Kopecký, &amp;amp; Šulc, 2015; Sanjayan, Nazari, Chen, &amp;amp; 

Nguyen, 2015; Zhang, Provis, Reid, &amp;amp; Wang, 2014). However, cost analysis was oddly 

avoided. Those authors strangely mentioned that low-cost alkali-activated cements materials 

could be produced.  

The discovery of one-part alkali-activated cements is considered a key event on the evolution 

of low-carbon alkali-activated cements technology in the “just add water” concept. Contrary to 

ordinary Portland cement (OPC)-based materials, alkali-activated cements use caustic 

activators that makes the handling and application of alkali-activated cements very difficult. 

That is why the alkali-activated cements based on the OPC concept of just add water to a 

powder are an important research line. However, investigations made so far on one-part alkali-

activated cements show that these materials are associated with very low compressive strength 

(Koloušek et al., 2007; Peng, Wan, Shen, &amp;amp; Xiao, 2014). Some authors even report a 

compressive strength decrease with time for one-part alkali-activated cements based on 

calcined red mud and sodium hydroxide blends (Ke, Bernal, Ye, Provis, &amp;amp; Yang, 2015). Since 

supply chain risks can limit the alkali-activated cements technology’s wider adoption, (Van 

Deventer, Provis, &amp;amp; Duxson, 2012) the use of minor volumes of OPC can help overcome this 

problem. Yang and Lee (2013) and Yang, Lee, Song, and Gong (2014) studied foam-ground 

granulated blast-furnace slag concrete produced with three alkali activators: Ca(OH)2 plus 

Mg(NO3)2, Ca(OH)2 plus 6.5% Na2SiO3, and 2.5% Ca(OH)2 plus Na2SiO3. These authors 

concluded that a unit binder content of approximately 400 kg/m3 is required to achieve the 

minimum quality requirements specified by the Korean Industrial Standard for floor heating 

systems. 

 

 1.2 Objectives 

 Developing a new composition of geopolymer to produce a mortar with higher level of 

efficiency and sustainability, is the main objective of this study. This aim can be decomposed 

into the following specific objectives: 

1. Developing mix composition of one-part geopolymers; 

2. Obtaining mechanical properties of one-part geopolymer; 

3. Microstructure study on the hydration products of one-part geopolymers; 



CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

 

3 
 

4. Development of an analytical model to predict the compressive strength of one-part 

geopolymers; 

5. Assessment of durability performance of one-part geopolymers; 

6. Development of mix compositions related to one-part foam geopolymers; 

7. Study the cost-efficiency performance of foam one-part geopolymers; 

8. Comparative study on the cost analysis of one-part geopolymers and two-part geopolymers; 

9. Compare the global warming potential of one-part foam geopolymers and two-part foam 

geopolymers 

 

 

1.3 Publications 

 

1.3.1 International Journal Papers 

   1. Abdollahnejad, Z., Nazari, A., Pacheco-Torgal, F., Sanjayan, J., Aguiar, J. Numerical 

modelling of the compressive strength of one-part geopolymers. Construction and Building 

Materials. 2015; Submitted. 

2. Abdollahnejad, Z., Miraldo, S., Pacheco-Torgal. F, Aguiar, J., Cost-efficient one-part 

geopolymers with low global warming potential for floor heating systems applications, 

Construction and Building Materials. 2015; Submitted. 

3. Abdollahnejad. Z., Pacheco-Torgal. F., Félix, T., Tahri, W. Aguiar, J., Mix design, 

properties and cost analysis of fly ash-based geopolymer foam, Construction and Building 

Materials. 2015; 80, 18-30. 

  4. Tahri, W., Abdollahnejad, Z., Mendes, J., Pacheco-Torgal. F., Barroso de Aguiar. J., “Fly 

Ash Geopolymeric Mortar for Coating of Ordinary Portland Cement Concrete Exposed to 

Harsh Chemical Environments. Advanced Materials Research. 2015; (accepted) 

5. Abdollahnejad, Z., Pacheco-Torgal. F., Aguiar, J., Jesus, C., Durability performance of 

fly ash based one-part geopolymer mortars, Key Engineering Materials, 2014; 634, 113-120. 

6. Abdollahnejad, Z., Hlavacek, P., Pacheco-Torgal, F., Aguiar, J., Compressive strength 

and microstructure of hybrid alkaline cements, Materials Research Ibero-American Journal of 

Materials. 2014; 17, Issue 4, 829- 837. 

7. Mastali M., Abdollahnejad M., Ghasemi Naghibdehi., M., Sharbatdar, M.K., Numerical 

Evaluations of Functionally Graded RC Slabs, Chinese Journal of Engineering. 2014. 

https://scholar.google.pt/scholar?oi=bibs&amp;amp;cluster=13795990819370274498&amp;amp;btnI=1&amp;amp;hl=en
https://scholar.google.pt/scholar?oi=bibs&amp;amp;cluster=13795990819370274498&amp;amp;btnI=1&amp;amp;hl=en
https://scholar.google.pt/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;hl=pt-PT&amp;amp;user=Tx13Qh4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Tx13Qh4AAAAJ:_FxGoFyzp5QC
https://scholar.google.pt/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;hl=pt-PT&amp;amp;user=Tx13Qh4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Tx13Qh4AAAAJ:_FxGoFyzp5QC


CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

 

4 
 

8. Pacheco-Torgal, F., Ding, Y., Miraldo, S., Abdollahnejad, Z., Labricha. J.A., Are 

geopolymers more suitable than Portland cement to produce high volume recycled aggregate 

HPC?, Construction and Building Material. 2012; 36, 1048-1052. 

9. Pacheco-Torgal, F., Abdollahnejad, Z., Miraldo, S., Baklouti, S., Ding, Y., An overview 

on the potential of geopolymer for concrete infrastructure rehabilitation, Construction and 

Building Materials.2012; 36, 1053-1058. 

10. Pacheco-Torgal, F., Abdollahnejad, Z., Camoes, A.F., Jamshidi, M, Ding, Y., Durability 

of alkali activated binders: A clear advantage over Portland cement or an unproven issue, 

Construction and Building Materials. 2012; 30, 400-405.  

 

1.3.2 Conference Papers 

1. Z. Abdollahnejad, A. Nazari, F. Pacheco-Torgal, J. Sanjayan, J.L Barroso Aguiar, 2015, 

“Prediction of the compressive strength of one-part geopolymers with the JMAK model”, 

ICEUBI2015, Covilha, Portugal. 

2. Z. Abdollahnejad, F. Pacheco-Torgal, J.L Barroso Aguiar, 2015, “Development of Foam 

One-Part Geopolymers with Enhanced Thermal Insulation Performance and Low Global 

Warming Potential”, ICPIC 2015, Singapore. 

3. W. Tahri, Z. Abdollahnejad, J. Mendes, F. Pacheco-Torgal, José Barroso de Aguiar, 2015, 

“Fly Ash Geopolymeric Mortar for Coating of Ordinary Portland Cement Concrete Exposed 

to Harsh Chemical Environments”, ICPIC 2015, Singapore. 

4. Z. Abdollahnejad, T. Félix, F. Pacheco Torgal, J.Barroso de Aguiar, 2015, “Preliminary 

experimental investigation on one-part geopolymer mixes”, European Mortar Summit 2015, 

Lisbon, Portugal. 

5. Z. Abdollahnejad, C. Jesus, F. Pacheco Torgal, J. L Barroso Aguiar, 2013, “One-part 

geopolymer mixes versus Ordinary Portland Cement (OPC): Durability assessment”, Braga, 

Portugal. 

6. Z. Abdollahnejad, P. Hlavacek, F. Pacheco Torgal, J. L Barroso Aguiar, 2012, “Preliminary 

experimental investigation on one-part geopolymer mixes”, Coimbra, Portugal.  

 

1.3.3 Book Chapters  

1. Pacheco-Torgal, F., Ding, Y., Miraldo, S., Abdollahnejad, Z., Labricha. J.A., Handbook of 

recycled concrete and demolition waste, Part 3, “The sustainability of concrete using recycled 



CHAPTER 1-Introduction 

 

5 
 

aggregate (RAs) for high performance concrete”, Woodhead Publishing series in Civil and 

Structural Engineering. 2013; 17, 424-438.  

2. Pacheco-Torgal, F.; Abdollahnejad, Z.; Camoes, A.F., Jamshidi, M, Ding, Y. (2016) Some 

durability shortcomings of geopolymers. In Handbook of low carbon concrete (Eds) Nazari, 

A.; Sanjayan, J., Elsevier, Waltham, US (in progress) 

 

1.4 Structure and content of the thesis 

This thesis is composed by six chapters. Its content can be summarized as follows: 

Chapter 1 presents the justification of this thesis along with its objectives. It also presents a list 

of publications in which the author of thesis participated during her PhD works. 

 

Chapter 2 reviews the state of the art of current two part geopolymers. Including some of its 

durability shortcomings namely the important problem of efflorescences that has received little 

attention by geopolymer researchers. This chapter also includes a brief review on one part 

geopolymers. 

 

Chapter 3 has a characterization of the materials used during the experimental work of this 

thesis along with a description of the tests. 

 

Chapter 4 addresses the study of the mix design of the one-part geopolymers. It also analyzes 

the mechanical properties and the durability of the new binders. Its hydration products are 

characterized and a model to predict the compressive strength is developed.  

 

Chapter 5 concerns the study of the mix design of one-part foam geopolymers. Its properties, 

cost efficiency and global warming impact its compared with the one of current two-part 

geopolymers. 

 

Chapter 6 presents the general conclusions of thesis along with suggestion for further 

investigation on the field of one part geopolymers. 

 

 



 

 

 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

6 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

CHAPTER TWO 

Literature Review 

 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

7 
 

2.1 Two part geopolymers 

In this part, the review of the relevant literature will be discussed. Presenting an overview of what 

has been done in previous researches. 

 

2.1.1 Alkali-activated binder 

   Research works carried out so far in developing alkali-activated binders show that this new 

material is likely to have enormous potential to become an alternative to Portland cement. The 

German cement chemist and engineer Kuhl made the first experiences on this field in 

1908 (Provis and Deventer, 2014). The bibliographic history of some important alkali-activated 

cement/geopolymer related events is presented in Table 2.1 although this table does not mention 

the contribution of Kuhl works. 

 

Alkali activated concrete have been receiving increased attention, due to the need of reducing 

greenhouse gas emissions generated by Portland cement and to the need of new binders with 

enhanced durability performance (Duxon et al., 2007; Pacheco-Torgal et al., 2008b). 

 

Research works carried out so far in the development of alkali-activated cements showed that 

much has already been  investigated and also that an  environmental friendly alternative to Portland 

cement is rising (Pacheco-Torgal et. al., 2008c; Li et. al., 2010; Davidovits et al., 1990).  

 

 

Davidovits et al. (1990) was the first author to address the carbon dioxide emissions of these 

binders stating that they generate just 0.184 tons of CO2 per ton of binder. Duxson et al. (2009) do 

not confirm these numbers; they stated that although the CO2 emissions generated during the 

production of Na2O are very high, still the production of alkali-activated binders is associated to a 

level of carbon dioxide emissions lower than the emissions generated in the production of OPC. 

According to those authors, the reductions can go from 50% to 100%. 

 

 

 

 

 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

8 
 

Table 2.1 Bibliographic history of some important alkali-activated cement/geopolymer related events (Li et 

al., 2010). 

Author Year Event 
Feret 1939 Slags used for cement. 

Purdon 1940 Alkali–slag combinations. 

Glukhovsky 1959 Theoretical basis and development of alkaline cements. 

Glukhovsky 1965 First called “alkaline cements”. 

Davidovits 1979 “Geopolymer” term. 

Malinowski 1979 Ancient aqueducts characterized. 

Forss 1983 F-cement (slag–alkali–superplasticizer). 

Langton and Roy 1984 Ancient building materials characterized. 

Davidovits and Sawyer 1985 Patent of “Pyrament” cement. 

Krivenko 1986 DSc thesis, R2O–RO–SiO2–H2O. 

Malolepsy and Petri 1986 Activation of synthetic melilite slags. 

Malek et al. 1986 Slag cement-low level radioactive wastes forms. 

Davidovits 1987 Ancient and modern concretes compared. 

Deja and Malolepsy 1989 Resistance to chlorides shown. 

Kaushal et al. 1989 Adiabatic cured nuclear wastes forms from alkaline mixtures. 

Roy and Langton 1989 Ancient concretes analogs. 

Majundar et al. 1989 C12A7–slag activation. 

Talling and Brandstetr 1989 Alkali-activated slag. 

Wu et al. 1990 Activation of slag cement. 

Roy et al. 1991 Rapid setting alkali-activated cements. 

Roy and Silsbee 1992 Alkali-activated cements: an overview. 

Palomo and Glasser 1992 CBC with metakaolin. 

Roy and Malek 1993 Slag cement. 

Glukhovsky 1994 Ancient, modern and future concretes. 

Krivenko 1994 Alkaline cements. 

Wang and Scivener 1995 Slag and alkali-activated microstructure. 

Shi 1996 Strength, pore structure and permeability of alkali-activated slag. 

Fernández-Jiménez and Puertas 1997 Kinetic studies of alkali-activated slag cements. 

Katz 1998 Microstructure of alkali-activated fly ash. 

Davidovits 1999 Chemistry of geopolymeric systems, technology. 

Roy 1999 Opportunities and challenges of alkali-activated cements. 

Palomo 1999 Alkali-activated fly ash — a cement for the future. 

Gong and Yang 2000 Alkali-activated red mud–slag cement. 

Puertas 2000 Alkali-activated fly ash/slag cement. 

Bakharev 2001–2002 Alkali-activated slag concrete. 

Palomo and Palacios 2003 Immobilization of hazardous wastes. 

Grutzeck 2004 Zeolite formation. 

Sun 2006 Sialite technology. 

Duxson 2007 Geopolymer technology: the current state of the art. 

Hajimohammadi, Provis and Deventer 2008 One-part geopolymer. 

Provis and Deventer 
2009 Geopolymers: structure, processing, properties and industrial 

applications. 
Note: According to Pacheco-Torgal (2014) this table should have credited the “one-part geopolymer” concept 

to Kolousek et al (2007) because their paper was submitted to review process in March 19 of 2007 and published 

online in 27 of July of 2007 while the paper of Hajimohammadi et al. (mentioned in the table) was submitted to review 

process on April 28 of 2008 and accepted by September 23 and published only by October 29 of 2008. 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

9 
 

Duxson and Van Deventer (2009) mention an independent study made by Zeobond Pty. Ltd. in 

which a low emissions Portland cement (0.67 ton/ton) and alkali-activated binders were compared, 

reporting that the latter had 80% lower CO2 emissions. Weil et al. (2009) mentioned that the 

sodium hydroxide and the sodium silicate are responsible for the majority of CO2 emissions in 

alkali-activated binders. These authors compared Portland cement concrete and alkali-activated 

concrete with similar durability reporting that the latter have 70% lower CO2 emissions, which 

confirmed the aforementioned reductions. McLellan et al. (2011) reported 44% to 64% reduction 

in greenhouse gas emissions of alkali-activated binders when compared to OPC.  

 

Habert et al. (2011) carried out a detailed environmental evaluation of alkali activated binders 

using the Life Cycle Assessment methodology confirming that they have a lower impact on global 

warming than OPC, but on the other side they have a higher environmental impact regarding other 

categories. More recently Turner and Collins (2013) showed that the CO2 footprint of a 40 MPa 

geopolymer concrete was approximately just 9% less than comparable concrete containing 100% 

OPC binder (328 kg/m3). Being that the major part was due to sodium silicate (Fig. 2.1). 

 

The high cost of alkali-activated binders is one of the major factors, which remain a severe 

disadvantage over Portland cement (Habert et al., 2011). Therefore, investigations about the 

replacement of water glass by sodic wastes are needed (Laldji et al., 2007). Currently alkali-

activated binders only becomes economic competitive for high performance structural purposes, 

because the cost of alkali-activated concretes is located midway between OPC concretes and high 

performance concretes. Since the average concrete class production lies between C25/30 and 

C30/37 and only 11% of the ready-mixed concrete production is above the strength class C35/45 

(ERMCO, 2011), this means that alkali-activated binders are targeting a small market share. 

 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

10 
 

 

Fig 2.1. Summary of CO2-emission for Grade 40 concrete mixtures with OPC and geopolymer 

binders (Turner and Collins, 2013) 

Therefore, in the short term the above cited disadvantage means that the study of alkali-activated 

applications should focus on high cost materials such as, commercial concrete repair mortars. 

Pacheco-Torgal (2008a and 2009) showed that alkali-activated mortars could be as much as 7 

times cheaper than current commercial repair mortars thus pointing available alternative for alkali-

activated binders. These materials are still at the beginning stages of development and hence need 

further research work in order to become technically and economically viable construction 

materials.  

 

Alkali activated materials is the broadest classification encompassing any binder derived by the 

reaction of an alkali metal source with a solid silicate powder while geopolymers is a subset of 

alkali activated materials where the binding phase is almost exclusively aluminosilicate and highly 

coordinated (Provis and Deventer, 2014). 

 

Research in this field has been published as ‘‘alkali-activated’’ binders, the term ‘‘geopolymer’’ 

is the generally accepted name for this technology. Investigations in the field of geopolymers had 

an exponential increase after the research results of Davidovits who developed and patented 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

11 
 

binders obtained from the alkali-activation of metakaolin, having named it with the term 

“geopolymer” in 1978. For the chemical designation of the geopolymer. Davidovits suggests the 

name “polysialates”, in which sialate is an abbreviation for aluminosilicate oxide. The sialate 

network is composed of tetrahedral anions [SiO4]
4- and [AlO4]

5- sharing the oxygen, which need 

positive ions such as (Na+, K
+

, Li
+

, Ca
++

, Na
+

, Ba
++

, NH4
+

, H3O
+) to compensate the electric charge 

of Al 3+ in tetrahedral coordination (after dehydroxilation the aluminum changes from coordination 

6 (octahedral) to coordination 4 (tetrahedral).  

 

The polysialate has the following empiric formulae: 

 

Mn{-( SiO2)z- AlO2}n, w H2O 

 

in which: n is the degree of polymerization, z is 1, 2 or 3, and M is an alkalication, such as 

potassium or sodium, generating different types of poly(sialates). According to Davidovits, 

geopolymers are polymers because they transform, polymerize and harden at low temperature.  

 

But they are also geopolymers, because they are inorganic, hard and stable at high temperature and 

also non inflammable. Over the last years several authors have reported research in a large number 

of aspects related to geopolymers such as:  dependence of the nature of source materials (alkali-

activated binders synthesized from calcined sources show a higher compressive strength than from 

raw materials) (Provis, 2009; Bakharev, 2005), immobilization of toxic metals  (Barbosa et al., 

2000; Vance et al., 2009; Vinsova et al., 2007), reaction mechanisms and hydration products 

(Provis et al., 2009; Bakharev, 2005; MacKenzi et al., 2005; Fernandez-Jimenez et al., 2005b), the 

role of calcium in geopolymerization (Weng et al., 2005; Yip et al., 2003; Yip et al., 2005) the 

development of lightweight building materials (Buchwald et al., 2005), durability issues (Hwai-

Chung and Peijang, 2005; Provis et al., 2008; Kani et al., 2011) and even LCA (Weil et al., 2009; 

Habert et al., 2011). 

 

According to those authors (Glukhovsky, 1981), an increase in the compressive strength of 4 MPa 

would require 24 h hydrothermal treatment at 100 ºC. The use of a much more intensive treatment 

(140 ºC) would increase compressive strength of 12-20 MPa. Some authors recently investigated 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

12 
 

these materials having reported a 28 days curing compressive strength of 27 MPa by using fly ash 

and 30% OPC (Abdollahnejad et al., 2014). 

 

So far investigations related to the geopolymerization of concentration and determination work are 

scarce (Lampris et al., 2009; Allahverdi and Najafi Kani, 2009), nevertheless, it seems that this 

binder has potential features to reuse recycled aggregates for the production of HPC. For the same 

water/binder ratio several authors reported that geopolymers present a higher mechanical strength 

than Portland cement.  

 

Wang in 1991 states a case of a geopolymeric concrete with 125 MPa compression strength. Other 

authors (Davidovits, 1994a) declare having obtained a 20 MPa strength just after 4 h increasing to 

70–100 MPa after 28 days curing. Fernandez-Jimenez et al. (2005a) studied mortars (w/b = 0.51) 

activated with NaOH and waterglass reporting 100 MPa for compressive strength. Fernandez-

Jimenez and Palomo in 2005a used slag/fly ashes mixtures activated with NaOH and waterglass 

(w/b = 0.35) announcing a 90 MPa compressive strength just after 20 h. Bakharev in 2005 studied 

fly ash pastes activated with NaOH and waterglass (w/b = 0.3) stating a 60 MPa compressive 

strength just after 2 days. Other authors (Pacheco-Torgal et al., 2007) report a compressive strength 

higher than 30 MPa after only one day, reaching almost 70 MPa after 28 days curing and 90 MPa 

at 90 days curing. In conventional concrete, the aggregates form a rigid skeleton of granular 

elements, which are responsible for compressive strength, in geopolymers most of the compressive 

strength is related to the matrix characteristics, therefore, this material does not rely in well-

proportioned aggregate mixtures. This makes geopolymer concrete more suitable to reuse recycled 

aggregates. 

 

These materials have another advantage over Portland cement concrete that is particularly 

interesting in the case of reusing contaminated recycled aggregates, a high immobilization 

capacity. According to Hermann et al. in 1999 the use of alkali-activated binders is a good way to 

immobilize a wide range of harmful constituents such as toxic metals, hydrocarbonates and even 

nuclear wastes in a final product with high durability and costing much less than the current 

vitrification process (Hermann et al., 1999). In 2007, Vinsova et al. refer that alkali-activated 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

13 
 

binders show a good performance in the immobilization of lead, cadmium and chromium, being 

less effective for immobilization of arsenic.  

 

Lancellotti et al. (2010) showed that metakaolin based geopolymers binders are able to immobilize 

toxic metals present in fly ash due to the incineration of municipal solid wastes. Immobilization 

of a municipal solid waste incineration residue using geopolymers was recently reported (Galiano, 

et al., 2010). Other authors (Hermann et al., 1999; Vinsova et al., 2007; Lancellotti, et al., 2010; 

Galiano, et al., 2010; Pacheco-Togal, et al., 2010; Garcia-Lodeiro, et al., 2007; Fu, et al., 2011; 

Zhang, et al., 2011) showed that geopolymeric binders can be used for the reuse of mine wastes. 

Besides geopolymeric concretes are associated to lower CO2 emissions than Portland cement 

concretes (Duxson, et al., 2007; Weil, et al., 2009; Habert, et al., 2011). This is a crucial advantage 

because Portland cement represents almost 80% of the total CO2 emissions of concrete, which in 

turn are about 6–7% of the Planet’s total CO2 emissions (Shi, et al., 2011; Pacheco-Torgal, et al., 

2012b).  

With a view to the large-scale adaptation of alkalin cement technology the world over, in 2007 a 

RILEM technical committee (TC 224 – AAM) began to compile and summarize experiences in 

connection with prime materials, cements, concretes, structures, output, test procedures, durability, 

envisaged use and so on. The ultimate aim is to develop basic recommendations for specifications 

designed to bring these cements to a market where they can compete on a level playing field with 

Portland cements. 

 

2.2 Limitation of durability of geopolymer 

   Besides the durability of alkali-activated binder is a subject of some controversy, while Duxson 

et al. (2009) state this is the most important determining the success of these new materials and 

other authors mention that the fact that samples from the former Soviet Union that have been 

exposed to service conditions for in excess of 30 years showing little degradation means that 

geopolymers do therefore appear to stand the test of time (Pacheco-Torgal F et al., 2012b).  

However, since those materials were of the (Si + Ca) type that conclusion cannot be extended to 

geopolymers defined as ‘‘alkali alumino silicate gel, with aluminium and silicon linked in a 

tetrahedral gel framework’’ (Weil M et al., 2009). On the other side Juenger et al. (2011) argue 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

14 
 

that ‘‘the key unsolved question in the development and application of alkali activation technology 

is the issue of durability’’ and more recently Van Deventer et al. (2012) recognized that ‘‘whether 

geopolymer concretes are durable remains the major obstacle to recognition in standards for 

structural concrete’’. 

Geopolymers as the alkali-actived binder have some properties which have advantages and 

disadvantages. Recently the following geopolymer properties were concerned by researchers 

which include: 

1. Resistance to acid attack; 

2. Alkali-silica reaction (ASR); 

3. Corrosion of steel reinforcement; 

4. Resistance to high temperatures;  

5. Efflorescence; 

 

2.2.1 Resistance to acid attack 

Concerning the resistance to acid attack, geopolymer performance is far better than that of 

Portland cement concretes because it does not contain Ca(OH)2, a soluble hydration product that 

constitutes the ‘‘Achilles’ heel’’ of Portland cement concrete.  Calcium hydroxide contributes 

slightly to the strength and impermeability of the paste, because it reduces the total pore volume 

by converting some of the liquid water into solid form. In this respect it is much less important 

than the C-S-H, however. CH is the most soluble of the hydration products, and thus is a weak link 

in cement and concrete from a durability point of view. If the paste is exposed to fresh water, the 

CH will leach out (dissolve), increasing the porosity and thus making the paste more vulnerable to 

further leaching and chemical attack. 

 

   Davidovits et al. (1990) reported mass losses of 6% and 7% for geopolymeric binders immersed 

in 5% concentration hydrochloric and sulfuric acids during 4 weeks. For the same conditions he 

also observed that Portland cement based concretes suffered mass losses between 78% and 95%. 

Other authors (Gourley and Johnson, 2005) mentioned that a Portland cement concrete with a 

service life of 50 years lost 25% of its mass after 80 immersions cycles in a sulfuric acid solution 

(pH = 1) while a geopolymeric concrete required 1400 immersions cycles to lose the same mass, 

thus meaning a service life of 900 years.  



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

15 
 

 

More recently Pacheco-Torgal et al. (2010) mentioned an average mass loss of just 2.6% after 

being submitted to the attack of (sulfuric, hydrochloric and nitric) acids during 28 days, while the 

mass loss for Portland cement concretes is more than twice that value.  

 

 

   Several authors reported that chemical resistance is one of the major advantages of alkali-

activated binders over Portland cement. In 1981,  Glukhovsky used alkali-activated slag mortars 

noticing that they showed increase tensile strength even after being immersed in lactic and 

hydrochloric acid solutions (pH = 3). Jiang (1997) studied the exposure of alkali- activated slag 

mortars during six months in 5% acid solution concentration, reporting that for citric acid changes 

were low, for nitric and hydrochloric acid changes were moderate although severe changes was 

noticed when sulphuric acid was used.  

 

Davidovits et al. (1990) reported mass losses of 6% and 7% for alkali-activated binders immersed 

in 5% concentration hydrochloric and sulphuric acids during 4 weeks. For the same conditions, he 

also reported that Portland cement based concretes suffered mass losses between 78% and 95% 

(1999 a),  Palomo et al. studied metakaolin mixtures activated with NaOH and water- glass when 

submitted to  sulphuric acid (pH = 3), sea water ported a minor flexural strength  decrease from 7 

to 28 days immersion, between 28 and 56 days flexural strength rises, decreasing again from 56 to 

90 days and rising from that day forward. They reported that the behavior was similar to the several 

acid solutions. According to these authors, unreacted sodium particles are not in the structure of 

the hardened material, remaining in a soluble condition thus when in contact with a solution they 

are leached increasing the binder porosity and lowering mechanical strength. On the other hand, 

strength increase after 3 months indicates that the reaction process is still evolving, with the 

formation of zeolitic precipitates thus lowering porosity and increasing strength.  

 

Shi and Stegmann (2000) compared the acid resistance of several binders; alkali-activated slags 

(AASs), OPC binders, fly ash/lime binders (FAL) and high alumina cement (AC), when immersed 

in nitric (pH = 3) and acetic (pH = 3 and 5) acid solutions. They reported that OPC binders 

presented higher mass losses than AAS and FAL binders while AC pastes were completely 

dissolved. According to these authors, OPC pastes are more porous than AAS but less porous than 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

16 
 

FAL pastes, so chemical attack is more influenced by the nature of hydration products than from 

porosity. They also reported that low pH acids are responsible for the highest chemical attack.  

 

Bakharev et al. (2002) also compared OPC and alkali-activated slag concrete resistance to sulphat 

attack, reporting that the former showed a lower strength reduction, that could be explained due to 

the binder structure chemical differences. Bakharev et al. (2002) studied OPC and slag concretes 

activated with NaOH and water glass, immersed in an acetic acid solution (pH = 4) during one 

year. They reported a 33% strength loss for the former and 47% for OPC concretes.  

 

   They claim that the strength loss is influenced by Ca content, 64% for OPC concretes and just 

39% for alkali-activated slag concretes. Besides slag compounds have lower Ca/Si molar ratio and 

are more stable in acid medium. As for OPC concrete calcium compounds, possess high Ca/Si 

molar ratios and react with acetic acid forming acetic calcium compounds which is very soluble.  

 

2.2.2 Alkali-silica reaction (ASR) 

The chance of ASR may take place in alkali-activated binders is an unknown subject. For OPC 

binders, however, the knowledge of ASR has been intensively studied; therefore, some 

explanations could be also applied to understand the possibility of ASR when alkali-activated 

binders are used. ASR was reported by the first time by Stanton (1940) and needs the simultaneous 

action of three elements in order to occur: (a) enough amorphous silica, (b) alkal ions and (c) water 

(Sims and Brown, 1998).  

 

The ASR begins when the reactive silica from the aggregates is attacked by the alkaline ions 

from cement forming an alkali–silica gel, which attracts water and starts to expand. The gel 

expansion leads to internal cracking, what have been confirmed by others (Wood and Johnson, 

1993) reporting 4 MPa pressures. Those internal tensions are higher than OPC concrete tensile 

strength, thus leading to cracking. However, some authors believe that ASR is not just a reaction 

between alkaline ions and amorphous silica but also requires the presence of Ca2+ ions (Davies, 

1998). In 1991, Davidovits compared alkali-activated binders and OPC binders when submitted to 

the ASTM C227 mortar-bar test, reporting a shrinkage behavior in the first case and a serious 

expansion for the OPC binder. Other authors (Fernandez-Jimenez and Puertas, 2002) reported 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

17 
 

some expansion behavior for alkali-activated binders although smaller than for OPC binders. 

However, Puertas (1995) believe ASR could occur for alkali-activated slag binders containing 

reactive opala aggregates. Bakharev et al. (2001) compared the expansion of OPC and alkali-

activated binders reporting that the first ones had higher expansion. This is clear from the 

microstructure analysis (Fig. 2.2).  

 

  Fig 2.2. Alkali-activated concrete after 10 months curing. (A)  

  Reactive aggregate. (G) Alkali-silica gel (Puertas F et al., 2009). 

 

   García-Lodeiro et al. (2007) showed that alkali-activated fly ash is less susceptible to generate 

expansion by alkali–silica reaction than OPC. They also showed that the calcium plays an essential 

role in the expansive nature of the gels. Recent investigations (Puertas et al., 2009) show that 

siliceous aggregates are more prone to ASR than calcareous aggregates in alkali-activated 

mixtures. Cyr and Pouhet (2014) reviewed the work of several authors concerning the expansion 

due to ASR (Fig. 2.3) noticing that some mixtures show an expansion above the limit proposed in 

the standard used for ASR tests. Therefore the study of ASR, in alkali-activated binders is not a 

closed subject, at least for the geopolymer mixtures containing calcium. 

 

2.2.3 Corrosion of steel reinforcement 

The corrosion of steel reinforcement is one of the causes that influences the structural capability 

of concrete elements. As concrete attack depends on its high volume and therefore is not of great 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

18 
 

concern, an attack to the steel reinforced bars is a serious threat eased by the fact that steel bars are 

very near of concrete surface and are very corrosion sensitive. In OPC binders, steel bars are 

protected by a passive layer, due to the high alkalinity of calcium hydroxide. The steel bars 

corrosion may happen if pH decreases thus destroying the passive layer, due to carbonation 

phenomenon or chloride ingress. The steel corrosion occurs due to an electrochemical action, when 

metals of different nature are in electrical contact in the presence of water and oxygen. The process 

consists in the anodic dissolution of iron when the positively charged iron ions pass into the 

solution and the excess of negatively charged electrons goes to steel through the cathode, where 

they are absorbed by the electrolyte constituents to form hydroxyl ions. These in turn combine 

with the iron ions to form ferric hydroxide, which then converts to rust. The volume increase 

associated with the formation of the corrosion products will lead to cracking and spalling of the 

concrete cover.  

 

For alkali-activated binders the literature is small about its capability to prevent reinforced steel 

corrosion. Torgal et.al investigated on the chloride diffusion, which clearly showed  alkali-

activated binders are able to prevent the ingress of harmful elements that could start steel corrosion.  

 

Roy et al. (2000) compared chloride diffusion for OPC and alkali-activated binders reporting that 

the former presented almost half of the diffusion values of the OPC binders. Saraswathy et al. 

(2003) studied alkali-activated fly ash mixtures reporting a steel corrosion resistance similar to the 

one of OPC binders.  

 

Miranda et al. (2005) even demonstrated that alkali-activated fly ash binders have superior pH 

conditions than OPC binders. They reported that pH decreased with hydration reaction 

development, however an alkaline condition remained even after 5 years, since carbonation 

phenomenon did not take place.  

 

 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

19 
 

 
 

 
 Reference Temperature Age of 

test 

Explanation of the different AAS 

mixtures 

A1, A2 Bakharev et al. (2001) 38°C 1 year A1: non-reactive aggregate 
A2: reactive aggregate 

B1 to B5 Gifford and Gillott (1996) 38°C 1 year B1: non-reactive aggregate 
B2: reactive (ASR) aggregate S1 
B3: reactive (ASR) aggregate S2 
B4: reactive (ASR) aggregate V 
B5: reactive (ASR) aggregate B 
AAS activated with Na2CO3 or Na2SiO3 

C1 to C3 Chen et al. (2002) 38°C 180 
days 

C1, C2 and C3: 2, 3.5 and 5% alkalis, 
respectively 
AAS activated with waterglass, NaOH, 
Na2CO3 or Na2SO4 

D1 to D3 Metso (1982) 40°C 70 days D1, D2 and D3: 3, 8 and 15% of opal, 
respectively 
Two types of slag, activated with 1.5 or 
2.4% Na 

E Al-Otaibi (2007) 60°C 1 year AAS activated with sodium silicate or 
sodium metasilicate, with Na2O content 
of 4 or 6%% 
Two OPC references: doped and non-
doped in alkalis 

F Fernandez-Jimenez A, 
Palomo A., Puertas F. (1999) 

80°C 16 days  

G Puertas et al. (2009) 80°C 14 days  
H Wang et al. (2010) 80°C 14 days  

 
Fig 2. 3 Ratios of the expansion relative to the limit proposed in the standard used for ASR test, for 

Portland cement and alkali-activated slag mixtures (Cyr and Pouhet, 2014) 

 

 

 

-0.5

0.0

0.5

1.0

1.5

2.0

2.5

3.0

3.5

4.0

A1 A2 B1 B2 B3 B4 B5 C1 C2 C3 D1 D2 D3 E F G H

E
x

p
a

n
s
io

n
 r

e
la

ti
v

e
 t

o
 t

h
e

 s
ta

n
d

a
rd

 l
im

it

Reference of the work

OPC AAS

e
x
p

a
n

s
io

n
 =

  
s
td

 l
im

it

6.6 ? ?4.8 4.6



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

20 
 

Aperador et al. (2009) mention that alkali-activated slag concrete is associated to poor 

carbonation resistance a major cause for corrosion of steel reinforcement. Bernal et al. (2010) 

shows that the activation of granulated blast furnace slag (GBFS)–metakaolin (MK) blends have 

low carbonation resistance. The same authors (Bernal et al., 2010) found that alkali-activated slag 

concretes present some susceptibility to carbonation, which depends on the binder content (Fig. 

2.4).  

 

Fig 2.4. Transverse sections of carbonated alkali-activated slag concretes after 1000 h of exposure to 

a 1% CO2 environment, with the extent of carbonation revealed by a phenolphthalein indicator. 

Samples are 76.2 mm in diameter (Bernal et al., 2010). 

 

Lloyd et al. (2010) show that geopolymer cement is prone to alkali leaching. This leads to a 

reduction in the pH and could cause steel corrosion. 

They also mention that the presence of calcium is crucial for having ‘‘durable steel-reinforced 

concrete’’ which is a setback for Si–Al geopolymers. Further research about reinforced steel 

corrosion is therefore needed, concerning alkalinity stability with curing time, as well as about 

chloride diffusion and carbonation resistance. 

 

 

2.2.4 Resistance to high temperatures and to fire 

Concretes based on Portland cement show a weak performance when subjected to a thermal 

treatment and when the temperature rises above 300 ºC they begin to disintegrate. As the alkali-

activated binders show a high stability when submitted to high temperatures even around 1000 ºC 

(Pawlasova et al., 2007). Other authors (Bortnovsky et al., 2007) studied the activation of 

metakaolin and shale wastes reporting a high mechanical performance after a thermal phase. The 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

21 
 

specimens show some slight strength loss between 600 ºC and 1000 ºC, however in some cases 

they show a strength increase at 1200 ºC. Kong et al. (2008) studied alkali-activated metakaolin 

binders observing that the residual strength after a thermal phase up to 800 ºC is influenced by the 

Si/Al ratio. The higher residual strength was obtained by the mixtures with a Si/Al ratio between 

1.5 and 1.7.  

 

Krivenko and Guziy (2007) found that alkali-activated binders show a high performance in the 

resistance to fire, thus suggesting that this material is suitable for use in works with a high fire risk 

like tunnels and tall buildings. Perná et al. (2007) confirmed that alkali-activated binders can be 

used as a 120 min anti-fire material in accordance with related standards of the Czech Republic. 

The anti-fire material must show a temperature lower than 120 ºC in the opposite side of the fire 

action.  

 

Temuujin et al. (2011) used alkali- activated binders as steel coatings stating that they maintained 

high structural integrity even after being submitted to a heat treatment by a gas torch. Zhao and 

Sanjayan (2011) compared the performance of OPC concrete and alkali activated concrete under 

the standard curve fire test mentioning that only the former exhibit spalling behavior. The internal 

pore structure of the latter allows a quick escape of the water vapor resulting in lower internal pore 

pressure. 

 

2.2.5 Efflorescences 

   Very few authors have investigated this serious limitation of geopolymers. Davidovits never 

mentioned and a search on the website of Geopolymer Institute show no paper about 

efflorescences. Also a search on Scopus about the words “geopolymers” and “efflorescences” 

show that only in 2007 was published the first paper where this problem is mentioned. 

Nevertheless, geopolymers suffer from severe efflorescence (Pacheco-Torgal and Jalali, 2010) 

because the bond between the sodium ions (Na+) and the aluminosilicate structure is weak which 

explains the leaching behavior (Skvara et al., 2008). According to those authors it is the presence 

of water that weakens the bond of sodium in the aluminosilicate polymers, a behavior that is 

confirmed by the geopolymer structure model (Fig. 2.5). 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

22 
 

 

Fig 2.5. Geopolymer structure model (Skvara et al., 2008). 

 

The subject of efflorescences in alkali-activated binders is relatively new, since very few authors 

have addressed this problem.  

Pacheco-Torgal and Jalali (2010) also found that sodium efflorecences are higher in alkali-

activated binders based aluminosilicate prime materials calcined at a temperature range below the 

dehydroxylation temperature with the addition of sodium carbonate as a source of sodium cations 

(Fig. 2.6). 

 

Temuujin et al. (2009) refer that although ambient cured fly ash alkali-activated binders exhibited 

efflorescences and that phenomena do not occur when the same alkali-activated binders are cured 

at elevated temperature which means the leach ate of sodium could be a sign of insufficient 

geopolymerisation. 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

23 
 

 

Fig 2.6. Alkali-activated mine waste mortars specimens after water immersion: Above mortars based 

on plain mine waste mud calcined at 950 ºC for 2 h; Below mortars based on mine waste  mud 

calcined at different temperatures with sodium carbonate (Pacheco-Torgal and Jalali, 2010) 

 

Van Deventer et al. (2010) recognized that current two part geopolymers suffer from severe 

efflorescence which is originated by the fact that ‘‘alkaline and/or soluble silicates that are added 

during processing cannot be totally consumed during geopolymerisation’’. Kani et al. (2011) 

showed that efflorescences can be reduced either by the addition of alumina-rich admixtures or by 

hydrothermal curing at temperatures of 65°C or higher. These authors found that the use of 8% of 

calcium aluminate cement greatly reduces the mobility of alkalis leading to minimum 

efflorescences (this cement has 28% of CaO). 

 

Recently Skvara et al. (2012) showed that Na, K is bounded only weakly in the nanostructure of 

the geopolymer (N, K)–A–S–H gel and is therefore leachable almost completely. This confirms 

that efflorescences is a worrying limitation of two part geopolymers when exposed to water or 

environments with RH above 30% (Fig. 2.7).  



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

24 
 

 

Fig 2.7. High efflorescence after 50 days of partially-immersed Alkali activated fly ash 

 

Zhang et al. (2014) also confirmed the presence of efflorescences in fly ash based geopolymers 

(Fig.2.8). Those authors recommended the use of hydrothermal treatments of geopolymers in order 

to reduce efflorescences formation. However this not only increases the cost of geopolymers but 

also increases its carbon dioxide footprint.  

There are many drawbacks associated with traditional two part mixes for the synthesis of 

geopolymers. The caustic alkaline solutions needed to form the geopolymers make the handling 

and application of geopolymers difficult. In addition, workability is generally poor and not easily 

adjustable due to a sticky and thick mortar that is generated during processing. The system is also 

sensitive to the ratio of alkaline and soluble silicate, which is difficult to control in practice.  



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

25 
 

 

Fig 2.8. Efflorescence of the dense geopolymer TRSF0 and the foamed geopolymer TRSF2 

specimens stored for times with the bottom in contact with water (Zhang et al., 2014) 

 

Additionally, using hydrothermal curing has serious limitations for on-site concrete placement 

operations. Most importantly, the alkaline soluble silicate that are added during processing cannot 

be totally consumed during geopolymerisation, even with curing at a raised temperature, due to 

the existence of dissolution equilibrium of raw aluminosilicate materials in alkaline silicate 

solutions. This causes severe efflorescences of the final geopolymer products and high 

permeability and water absorption due to the movement of alkali together with water to the 

geopolymer surfaces. This means that this subject merits further investigations.  

 

2.3 One part geopolymers 

One-part geopolymers represent a key event on geopolymer technology having been described by 

the first time in 2007 (Kolousek et al., 2007; Shi et al., 2011). The present invention provides an 

alternative to the conventional two part mixes and advantageously alleviates one or more of the 

disadvantages of prior part. The discovery of one-part geopolymers is considered as an important 

phenomena in the evolution of low carbon geopolymer technology in the “just add water” concept. 

However they were associated with low compressive strength (Koulosek et al., 2007). Recent 

investigations (Peng et al., 2015) confirm that one-part geopolymers show low mechanical 

strength. These authors noticed that the one part geopolymer mixtures show an increased reduced 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

26 
 

compressive strength after being immersed in water. This reduction being dependent on the kaolin 

thermal treatment. Higher calcination temperatures being responsible for higher compressive 

losses. Other authors (Ke et al., 2015) even reported a compressive strength decrease for one-part 

geopolymers based on calcined red mud and sodium hydroxide blends just after the first week of 

curing (Fig. 2.9). These limitations mean that further investigations are needed concerning the 

development of new and improved one part geopolymers. 

 
Fig. 2.9 Compressive strengths of red mud-based one-part geopolymers produced with different 

activator doses as a function of the time of curing (Ke et al., 2015) 

 

 

2.4 Conclusions 

Research on alkali-activated binders shows a broadest potential due to low CO2 emissions. These 

materials can be taken into account as an alternative to Portland cement, although various 

investigations need to be performed on the characteristics of these new materials. Many authors 

confirmed the reduction of CO2 emission when the alkali activated binder in compared to Portland 

cement, which leads to lower impact on global warming than OPC. Geopolymer is a subset of 

alkali activated materials with mostly binding phase of aluminosilicate and highly coordinated.  

New investigations are needed on the use of sodic wastes to replace sodium silicate in order to 

reduce the cost of this material; The new binders present higher chemical resistance, however it 

seems that depends more on the low content of soluble calcium compounds than their low 

permeability; although these binders contain a high level of alkali elements, they do not appear to 

be associated with the occurrence of ASR, which may be because the majority of alkali elements 



CHAPTER 2-Literature review 

 

27 
 

are associated with other reaction products. However, that explanation forgets the crucial role 

played by calcium in the ASR development meaning that although it is rather natural the absence 

of ASR in free calcium alkali-activated binders, that problem must be taken under consideration 

when calcium based binders were used. As the capability to keep an alkaline environment through 

time, which is crucial to maintain reinforced steel safe from corrosion, the current studies are not 

enough to prove it, as a matter of fact their resistance to carbonation is lower than OPC binders 

and recent investigation show that it is difficult to synthesize a low-Ca geopolymer capable of 

preserving the steel reinforcement passivation film; the use of calcium in alkali-activated binders 

is indispensable to keep a high pH but at the same time could be the responsible for triggering 

ASR; Contrary to standard OPC binders alkali-activated binders show a high stability when 

submitted to high temperatures which dependent on the Si/Al ratio. The investigations on the fire 

behavior of alkali-activated binders show that these materials are specially recommended for 

works with a high fire risk like tunnels and tall buildings; Alkali-activated binders are prone to the 

formation of efflorescences however this disadvantage can be greatly reduced when using 

hydrothermal curing treatments or calcium aluminate admixtures. Nevertheless, hydrothermal 

curing has limited applications for on situ concrete placement operations and the use of a calcium-

based admixture raises issues about its acid resistance. Furthermore, alkali-activated binders 

containing calcium-based admixture have a higher global warming impact than alkali-activated 

Si-Al mixtures. There are many drawbacks associated with the application of traditional two part 

mixes for the synthesis of geopolymers. One-part geopolymers ‘just add water concept’ represent 

a key event on geopolymer technology. The present invention provides an alternative to the 

conventional two part mixes and advantageously alleviates one or more of the disadvantages of 

prior part. 



























Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



39 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

CHAPTER FOUR 

Mechanical Properties, Microstructure and Durability 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

4.1 Mechanical properties 

After obtaining suitable values of materials for mortar, different specimens will be made with 

different mixtures and the properties of the fresh and hardened mortar will be evaluated.  

 

Mechanical properties and durability of hardened mortar will be assessed according to relevant 

standards such as ASTM and EN. Based on the results of the primary tests, new mixtures will be 

selected for assessment and the effect of constituent proportions will be evaluated.  

 

The SEM observations on these mixtures are also presented. The mixtures under investigation 

were based on the ones described in the international patent authored by Zheng et al. (2007). 

 

4.1.1 Mix design 

 Table 4.1 and 4.2 shows the mix proportion respectively used in phases A and B. In the mixes 7 

up to 12, potassium hydroxide were used instead of sodium hydroxide.   

Table 4.1 Mix proportions used in phase A 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 

 

 

 

Mix Calcined stuff**/Powder Fly ash/ 

Powder 

OPC/ 

Powder

* 

Ca(OH)2/

Powder 

Water/

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

 1-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5%   31%   ------        ------- 

 2-A       4 %     58.3 %     30 %   7.7 %   26%   ------        ------- 

 3-A       4 %     58.3 %     30 %   7.7 %   34%   ------        ------- 

 4-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   52%    

 

 

 

    80% 

 

       ------- 

 5-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   52%        ------- 

 6-A       4 %     58.3 %     30 %   7.7 %   31%        ------- 

 7-A       4 %     58.3 %     30 %   7.7 %   40%        ------- 

 8-A       4 %     58.3 %     30 %   7.7 %   35%        0.8% 

 9-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   37%        1.3% 

10-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   35%        2.5% 

11-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   31%        2.4% 

12-A       4 %     32.5 %     30 %   33.5 %   36%        1.5 % 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

Table 4.2 Mix proportions used in phase B 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 

 

The initial phases were meant to find out the mixtures with the highest compressive strength. 

Phases C (Table 4.3 and 4.4) and D (Tables 4.5 and 4.6) were meant to evaluate the influence of 

aggregate and calcium hydroxide. Tests were performed on 50×50×50 mm3 mortar specimens 

according to ASTM C109.  

Table 4.3 Mix proportions used in phase C 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 
 

 

Table 4.4 Phase C-Volumetric ratios 

Vs/Vp Vw/Vp Vsp/Vp 

1 0.77 0.023 

0.95 0.77 0.023 

0.9 0.77 0.023 

0.85 0.77 0.023 

                 -Vs/Vp=Sand volume/powder volume 

Mix Calcined stuff**/Powder Fly ash/ 

Powder 

OPC/ 

Powder

* 

Ca(OH)2

/Powder 

Water/

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

   1-B                 3.0% 33% 32.2%    33.5%     35% 35    35%    

 

 

      80% 

   

 

2.7% 

   2-B                3.0% 33% 32.2%    31.6%     35% 2.3% 

   3-B                 4% 32% 30%    33.5%     35% 1.5 

   4-B                 4% 32.5% 30%    33.5%     39%  1.5% 

   5-B                3.2% 60% 30%    6.8%     35% 1.0% 

   6-B                 4% 32.5% 30%    33.5%     34% 1.0% 

   7-B                 4% 58.3% 30%    7.7%     30% 0.5% 

   8-B                 4% 32.5% 30%    33.5%     35%    

 

      85% 

1% 

   9-B                 4% 58.3% 30%    7.7%     35% 1% 

  10-B                 4% 32.0% 30%    33.0%     30% 1% 

  11-B                 5% 32.0% 40%    23.0%     35% 1% 

  12-B                 5% 32.0% 30%    34.5%     35% 1% 

Mix 
Calcined 

stuff**/Powder 
Fly ash/ 

Powder 

OPC/Powder

* 
Ca(OH)2/

Powder 

Water/

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

1-C        

 

              5 % 

 

     

 

  32.0% 

     

 

    

 

       40 % 

     

 

   

 

  23.0% 

   

 

  34%     

 

      80% 

3% 

2-C   34% 2% 

3-C   29% 2% 

4-C   30% 3% 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

                 -Vw/Vp=Water volume/powder volume 

                 -Vsp/Vp=Superplasticizer volume/powder volume 

Table 4.5 Mix proportions used in phase D 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 

 

Table 4.6 Phase D-Weight ratios 

WCa/Wc      WCs/Wc WFA/Wc WSP/Wc 

      0.45         0.12        0.79      0.01 

       0.5         0.12         0.79      0.01 

      0.65         0.12        0.79      0.01 

       0.7         0.12        0.79      0.01 

                  -Ca= Calcium hydroxide         -SP= Superplasticizer                -Cs= Calcined stuff 

                   -FA=Fly ash                           - C=Cement 

 

 

4.1.2 Results and discussions 

The obtained results from casted samples in part A, B, C, and D under compression will be 

evaluated in this section. 

 

Fig. 4.1 shows the compressive strength of the mixtures tested in Phase A. The results show that 

the most promising mixture (8A) has a compressive strength around 27 MPa after 28 days curing.  

 

This mixture also has the eco-efficient advantage of containing a high content of an industrial by-

product. The mixture 2A shows a high compressive strength performance which is due to a low 

w/b ratio. The results also show that the curing days increase the compressive strength.  

 

This is a behaviour that is not observed in two part alkali-activated cements in which the 

compressive strength just after one day can reach 50% to 70% of the compressive strength after 

28 days curing (Pacheco-Torgal et al, 2007). However, while this behaviour is most evident for 

Mix 
Calcined 

stuff**/Powder 
Fly ash/ 

Powder 

OPC/Powder

* 
Ca(OH)2/

Powder 
Water/Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

1-D  

 

          5% 

   

 

 32.0 % 

    

 

    

 

        40 % 

 

  21.0%    

 

         29% 

   

 

 

 

    80% 

 2% 

2-D   24.0 %  1% 

3-D   27.0 %  1% 

4-D  19.0%  4% 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

mixture 8A, the one with the highest compressive strength at 14 days and at 28 days is not so 

evident for mixture 4A which as a lower fly ash content and a higher w/b. The use of a w/b=0.52 

leads to compressive strength results below 12 MPa after 28 days curing which is a very modest 

performance unsuitable to be used in future applications. The mixture with the lowest 1 day 

compressive strength (6A) is of difficult explanation because it has the same composition of the 

mixture with the highest 28 days compressive strength with the exception of the w/b content which 

is lower. 

 

Fig. 4.1 Variation of compressive strength with composition and curing days (Phase A) 

Mixtures based on calcined kaolin and sodium hydroxide revealed lower reactivity than the 

mixtures in which this last constituent was replaced by potassium hydroxide. This confirms the 

results obtained by other authors (Xu and Van Deventer, 2000; Diamond, 1976) who also found 

that geopolymers based on several alumino-silicate minerals had a high compressive strength in 

KOH than in NaOH. This fact is however independent of the extent of dissolution, being that those 

minerals show a higher dissolution when NaOH is used. Fig. 4.2 shows the compressive strength 

of the mixtures test in Phase B. The results indicate that a higher compressive strength mixture 

was obtained (11B) reaching 30 MPa after 28 days curing. Environmentally speaking since this 

mixture has more 10% OPC and more 15% of calcium hydroxide this mixture does seems as eco-

efficient as the previous mixture 8A. An interesting behaviour can be observed when comparing 

the mixture 11B with mixture 10B.  

0

5

10

15

20

25

30

1-A 2-A 3-A 4-A 5-A 6-A 7-A 8-A 9-A 10-A 11-A 12-A

1 day

7 days

14 days

28 days

C
c
C

o
m

p
re

s
s
iv

e
 s

tr
e

n
g

th
 (

M
P

a
)



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

 

 
Fig. 4.2 Variation of compressive strength with composition and curing days (Phase B) 

 

The differences between the two are the fact that mixture 10B includes less 10% of OPC but more 

10% in calcium hydroxide and also has a low w/b. As a consequence its compressive strength after 

28 days curing is almost 10 MPa apart from mixture 11B. And probably if the w/b was the same 

the compressive strength difference could be even higher. This show the existent of very reactive 

constituents existent in OPC. Again the mixtures where sodium hydroxide was replaced by 

potassium hydroxide show a higher compressive strength. Fig. 4.3 shows the compressive 

strength of the mixtures tested in Phase C.  

 
Fig. 4.3 Variation of compressive strength with the sand content and curing days (Mixture 11B) 

0

5

10

15

20

25

30

35

1-B 2-B 3-B 4-B 5-B 6-B 7-B 8-B 9-B 10-B 11-B 12-B

1 day

7 days

14 days

28 days

C
c
C

o
m

p
re

s
s
iv

e
  
s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

0

5

10

15

20

25

30

35

1 Day 7 days 14 Days 28 Days

(Vs/Vp)=1

(Vs/vp)=0.95

(Vs/vp)=0.9

(Vs/Vp)=0.85

C
c
C

o
m

p
re

s
s
iv

e
  
s
tr

e
n

g
th

 
(M

P
a

)



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

In this phase the mixture 11B was used as reference in order to evaluate the compressive strength 

variation due to aggregate content. Vs relates to the volume of sand and Vp for the volume of 

powder (OPC, FA, Kaolin, Potassium hydroxide and Ca (OH) 2). Increasing the sand content leads 

to lower compressive strength because the w/b ratio has also increased in order to maintain the 

workability. Fig. 4.4 shows the compressive strength of the mixtures tested in Phase D. In this 

phase the mixture 11B was used as reference in order to evaluate the compressive strength 

variation due to calcium hydroxide content. The calcium hydroxide is presented as a function of 

the Portland cement percentage.  

 

 

Fig. 4.4 Variation of compressive strength with the Ca(OH)2 content and curing days (Mixture 11B) 

 

The results show that there is not a direct linear relationship between the calcium hydroxide content 

and the compressive strength. The use of calcium hydroxide as much as 50% of Portland cement 

leads to the highest compressive strength. Increasing the Ca(OH)2 percentage beyond that 

percentage can lead to a decrease in the compressive strength. Concerning the efflorescences no 

relevant presence was observed. This confirmed the observations included in the international 

related patent. 

 

 

 

0

5

10

15

20

25

30

35

40

45

1 Day 7 days 14 Days 28 Days

(WCa(OH)2)/Wc=0.4

(WCa(OH)2)/Wc=0.5

(WCa(OH)2)/Wc=0.65

(WCa(OH)2)/Wc=0.7

C
c
C

o
m

p
re

s
s
iv

e
  
s
tr

e
n

g
th

(M
P

a
)



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

4.2 Compressive strength modelling 

Arshad and Maaroufi (2015) recently applyed the Johnson–Mehl–Avrami–Kolmogorov (JMAK) 

model to the kinetics of crystallization in amorphous materials. Therefore this section discloses 

results regarding the modelling the compressive strength of one part-geopolymers with the JMAK 

model. 

Table 4.7 shows the compositions of the one part geopolymer mixtures used in the present study. 

After demoulding, the specimens were submitted for a thermal treatment during 24 h at different 

temperatures (40ºC, 60ºC and 80ºC). The specimens were also placed in the chamber room, with 

relative humidity of 58 %, during the curing time.  

Table 4.7- Composition of one part geopolymer mixes used for modeling compressive strength 

Mix OPC/Powder* Fly ash/ 

Powder 

Ca(OH)2

/Powder 
Calcined 

stuff**/Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

Water/

Powder 

OPC 30-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 4 30% 

58.3% 7.7% 

  4% 

80% 0.08% 35% OPC 26-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 8 26%        8% 

OPC 18-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 16 18%   16% 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 
 

Figure 4.5 shows compressive strengths of one part geopolymers according to curing time. It also 

includes the predicted values according to the JMAK model. The equation of this model is as 

follows: 

)exp(1)(
n

kttf ???                           (1) 

Where f(t) is degree of reaction, t is time of reaction, k is a constant and n is the exponent.  

 

According to Fig. 4.5 the degree of reaction in cementitious systems is related directly to 

compressive strength. Therefore, Eq. (1) can be adopted for compressive strength of geopolymers 

as follows:  

))exp(1(
n

c
ktf ??? ?                           (2) 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

where f c is the compressive strength and ? is a constant. Eq. (1) is solved for degree of reaction 

varying between 0 and 1. In Eq. (2), fc is greater than 1 and hence for our case where strengths are 

below100MPa, we divide the strengths by 100. This normalized number can be included in the 

constant ?. For specimens with higher strengths, one can divide them by a reference number. To 

determine k and n, Eq. (3) can be written in the following form: 

)()())1(( tLnnkLnfLnLn
c

????                      (3) 

k and n can be easily found from intercept and slope of the line plotted in the form of ln (1-ln(1-

fc)) versus ln t respectively. These lines for the whole considered geopolymeric systems considered 

in this study have been plotted in Fig. 4.5. Calculated k and n and their corresponding equations 

have been given in Table 4.8. The predicted compressive strengths for one part geopolymeric 

mixtures was presented in Fig. 4.6 The results are influenced not only by the one part geopolymer 

mixture but also by the temperature treatment. 

 

Compressive strength evolution vs. time plotted in logarithmic scale is presented in Fig. 4.7 The 

results are influenced not only by the one part geopolymer mixture but also by the temperature 

treatment. Traditional ? shape diagrams where found only for 30-OPC-58.3FA_7.7CH_4CS 

treated at 40 ºC. 

 

 

 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

Table 4.8 Constant, exponent and equation of compressive strength evolution for one part geopolymers 

 

Curing 

temperature 

(oC) 

30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16 CS 

       

k n Equation k n Equation k n Equation 

40 0.0805 0.2305 ?? = 100[1 ?

??0.0805?
0.2305

]  

0.0717 0.1393 ?? = 100[1 ? ?
?0.07178?0.1393] 0.0942 0.0481 ?? = 100[1 ? ?

?0.0942?0.0481] 

60 0.1288 0.1198 ?? = 100[1 ?

??0.1288?
0.1198

]  

0.0773 0.1321 ?? = 100[1 ? ?
?0.0773?0.1321] 0.1014 0.017 ?? = 100[1 ? ?

?0.1014?0.017] 

80 0.1075 0.0651 ?? = 100[1 ?

??0.1075?
0.0651

]  

0.0580 0.1201 ?? = 100[1 ? ?
?0.085?0.1201] 0.1002 0.0145 ?? = 100[1 ? ?

?0.1002??0.0145] 

 

 

 

  



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

 
(a) 

 
(b) 

 
(c) 

Figure 4.5. Experimental and predicted compressive strength of mixtures a) 30 OPC_58.3 

FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, b) 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS and c) 18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS 

8

10

12

14

16

18

20

22

0 20 40 60

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of Curing (Days)

30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS

Predicted at 40 oC

Predicted at 60 oC

Predicted at 80 oC

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC

6

8

10

12

14

16

0 20 40 60

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of Curing (Days)

26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS

Predicted at 40 oC

Predicted at 60 oC

Predicted at 80 oC

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC

6

7

8

9

10

11

12

0 20 40 60

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of Curing (Days)

18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16 CS

Predicted at 40 oC

Predicted at 60 oC

Predicted at 80 oC

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

  

(a) 

 
(b) 

 
(c) 

Figure 4.6. Plots for determining k and n in a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, b) 26 OPC_58.3 

FA_7.7 CH_8 CS and c) 18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS 

 

1.4

1.6

1.8

2

2.2

2.4

0.08 0.1 0.12 0.14 0.16 0.18 0.2

-l
n

(l
n

-(
1

-f
'c

))

ln(t)

30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS

40 oC

70 oC

90 oC

1.8

2

2.2

2.4

2.6

2.8

0.08 0.1 0.12 0.14 0.16 0.18 0.2

-l
n

(l
n

-(
1

-f
'c

))

ln(t)

26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS

40 oC

70 oC

90 oC

1.8

1.9

2

2.1

2.2

2.3

2.4

2.5

2.6

0.08 0.1 0.12 0.14 0.16 0.18 0.2

-l
n

(l
n

-(
1

-f
'c

))

ln(t)

18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16 CS

40 oC

70 oC

90 oC



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 
(a) 

 
(b) 

 
(c) 

Figure 4.7. Compressive strength a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS, b) 26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 

CH_8 CS and c) 18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16CS in logarithmic scale 

 

8

10

12

14

16

18

20

22

1 10 100

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of curing (Days)

30 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_4 CS

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC

6

8

10

12

14

16

1 10 100

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of curing (Days)

26 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_8 CS

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC

6

7

8

9

10

11

12

1 10 100

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

Age of curing (Days)

18 OPC_58.3 FA_7.7 CH_16 CS

40 oC

60 oC

80 oC



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

4.3 Microstructure 

The results of Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) and chemical analyses of samples which 

were performed with the Energy Dispersive Spectroscopy (EDS) technique will be discussed in 

the following paragraphs.  

 

4.3.1 SEM 

 Figs. 4.8 and 4.9 shows two SEM micrographs taken from 28 days cured specimens. In contrast 

with the porous typical interfacial transition zone of Portland cement mixtures, one part 

geopolymers present a very dense and uniform ITZ. 

 

Fig. 4.8 SEM micrograph of interfacial transition zone 

 

Fig. 4.9 SEM micrograph of hybrid alkaline cement mortar 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 4.3.2 EDS analysis 

 The molar ratios of the analyses carried out by EDS are displayed in table 4.9 and 4.10.  

 
Table 4.9 Phase D-Weight ratios 

WCa(OH)2/Wc WCa/Wc WFA/Wc WSP/Wc 

0.45 0.12 0.79 0.01 

0.5 0.12 0.79 0.01 

0.65 0.12 0.79 0.01 

0.7 0.12 0.79 0.01 

 

Table 4.10 EDS Atomic ratio analysis 

Atomic ratio 
Zone 

Z2 Z3 

SiO2/Al2 O3 25.6 2.89 

Al2O3/ Na2O 2.15 5.44 

CaO / SiO2 0.13 0.5 

Na2O / CaO 0.13 0.12 

MgO/Al2O3 - 0.15 

 

   Typical C/S ratios in CSH of traditional OPC systems go between 1.5 to 2.0 (Diamond, 1976; 

Richardson, 2000). However, the areas Z2 and Z3, have a much lower C/S ratio which means it 

has some sodium replacing Ca2+ in CSH. Some authors have already demonstrated that sodium 

incorporation in CSH phase increased as C/S ratio decreases, and therefore they name it as Na-C-

S-H (Macphee, 1989). The areas marked as Z2 and Z3 are identified as some form of calcium 

silicate with traces of some sodium and aluminum in its composition which could be associated to 

a (N, C)-A-S-H gel. According to Garcia-Lodeiro et al. (2013), these gels usually evolve into 

compositions with higher calcium and lower aluminum content. Those authors also mention that 

this is a blank field and that almost nothing has been published concerning the interaction between 

aluminosilicate materials containing sodium (or potassium or sulphates) in the formation of N-A-

S-H or K-A-S-H type cementitious gels. 

 

4.4 FTIR 

The FTIR spectra are presented in Fig. 4.10. The mix compositions are presented in Table 4.11. 

The strong peak band 965 cm-1 is characterized as asymmetric Si-O-Si or Al-O-Si stretching, 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

which is typical of the polymerization of the silicate group with the formation of CSH (Garcia 

Lodeiro et al,. 2008; Garcia Lodeiro et al,. 2009). 

 

A shift to a high wave number occurs when the different spectra are compared. Usually this 

indicates an increase in the Si content of the gel.  

 

   The carbonate bands C-O at around 1415 cm_1 and 850 cm_1 arise from the reactions of 

atmospheric CO2 with calcium hydroxide. This peak intensity changes with the amount of calcium 

hydroxide.  

 

   The broad bands in the region of 1648–3000 cm-1 characterized the spectrum of stretching and 

deformation vibrations of O-H and H–O–H groups from the weakly bound water molecules. 

 

 

 
 

Fig. 4.10 FTIR spectra 

3000.0 2000 1500 1000 550.0

c m-1

%R 

R 1

R 2

R 3

R 4

R 5



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

4.5 Mix proportioning  

For the further investigations by utilizing the obtained results in the previous step 4, new mixes 

are added in this phase. In addition to the 4 new mixes, one has been selected from the previous 

part. Based on what were concluded until now, the research will be continued by testing the 5 

mixes for obtaining higher compressive results and a high eco-efficient performance. To expand 

the obtained results, durabilty tests will also be performed. The compositions of the dry mixes 

contain the following materials: kaolin, fly ash, ordinary Portland cement (OPC), sodium 

hydroxide, calcium hydroxide (Ca(OH)2), water and superplasticizer. These are adapted from the 

ones presented in the international patent WO 2007/109862 A1 (Zheng et al, 2007). 

 

 

Table 4.11 Mix composition  

Mix 
OPC/ 

Powder* 

Fly ash/ 

Powder 

Ca(OH)2/

Powder 

Calcined 

stuff**/ 

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

Water/ 

Powder 

OPC 100 (R1) 100 - - - 

0.8 0.08 0.35 

OPC 70 – FL 30 (R2) 70 30 - - 

OPC 30-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 4   (R3) 30 58.3 7.7 4 

OPC 26-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 8   (R4) 26 58.3 7.7   8 

OPC 18-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 16  (R5) 18 58.3 7.7 16 

*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Ca(OH)2 + Calcined stuff 
*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 ratio. 

 
 

4.5.1 Compressive strength 

Fig. 4.11 shows the compressive strength results. The reduction of OPC content leads to a high 

reduction on the compressive strength of the mortars. The slow hydration characteristics of fly ash 

contribute to explain that reduction. The mixture with just 30% OPC (and 58.3 fly ash, 7.7 calcium 

hydroxide and 4% calcined stuff) shows an almost 40% reduction in compressive strength when 

compared to the reference mixture. Since this mixture has a higher percentage reduction on OPC 

content this could mean that the addition of fly ash and calcined stuff could have compensated that 

reduction. However, the use of increase content in calcined stuff does not seem to compensate the 

OPC reduction. Thus meaning that the use of 4% calcined stuff seems to be an optimum content. 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

Fig. 4.11 Variation of compressive strength with composition and curing age. 

 

4.6 Durability 

Experimental results will be continued on the durability performance of one-part geopolymers 

concerning penetration of chloride, carbonation resistance and resistance to acid attack.  

 

4.6.1 Efflorescences 

Concerning the occurrence of efflorescences, no presence was observed. This confirmed the 

observations included in the international related patent. The explanations for that can be related 

to the low amount of (sodium/potassium) as well as to the fact that some sodium/potassium 

replaced Ca2+ in CSH hydration products. Another factor that influences efflorescences is pore 

volume and permeability. In Portland cement, the water participates in the hydration products so, 

as the hydration progresses, the pore volume decreases over time. However, two part alkali-

activated binders do not have the same pore volume reduction benefit through the conversion of 

water into a solid via its incorporation into reaction products (Van Deventer et al., 2012), thus 

needing a very low w/b ratio to ensure low permeability. 

 

4.6.2 Water absorption by immersion 

The results of water absorption by immersion are presented in Fig. 4.12. Since all the mixtures 

have the same w/b ratio they should present a similar open porosity. So the differences between 

0

10

20

30

40

50

60

70

80

90

OPC 100 OPC 70 – FL 30 OPC 30-FL 58.3-
CH 7.7-CS 4

OPC 26-FL 58.3-
CH 7.7-CS 8

OPC 18-FL 58.3-
CH 7.7-CS 16

C
o

m
p

re
ss

iv
e

 s
tr

e
n

g
th

 (
M

P
a

)

14 28



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

the several mixtures could be explained by the scatter data because they are small enough for that. 

Of course the different hydration products present in the different mixtures may contribute for the 

porosity differences but only in a very slight manner. That is why the mixture already mention in 

the previous section as having a good compressive strength performance shows the lower open 

porosity. 

 
 

Fig. 4.12 Variation of water absorption by immersion with composition.  

 

4.6.3 Capillarity water absorption 

The water absorption capillarity coefficients are showed in Fig. 4.13. The reference mixture 

shows the best performance. On the opposite side the mixture with 26% OPC 58.3 fly ash, 7.7 

calcium hydroxide and 8% calcined stuff clearly shows a very high water absorption by capillarity 

even at early ages. Such performance is typical of a microstructure with a high amount of capillary 

pores. Three remaining mixtures show a similar capillary water absorption coefficient indicating 

a similar internal capillary pore network. 

 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

 

Fig. 4.13 Variation of Water absorption capillarity coefficient with composition 

 

4.6.4 Chloride diffusion 

Fig. 4.14 shows the results of the chloride diffusion coefficient. The results are in accordance 

with the water absorption (open porosity) results. They show that all the mixtures have in the worst 

case a moderate resistance to chloride diffusion when a comparison is made to the performance of 

Table 4.12. With the exception of the mixture with 18% OPC 58.3 fly ash, 7.7 calcium hydroxide 

and 16% calcined stuff. All the other three mixtures in which OPC was partially replaced by fly 

ash showed a high resistance to chloride diffusion. 

 

Fig. 4.14 Chloride diffusion coefficient 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

Table 4.12 Resistance to chloride penetration (Gjorv, 1996) 

×10-12 (m2/s) Concrete resistance 

&gt;15 Low 

10-15 Moderate 

5-10 High 

2.5-5 Very high 

&lt;2.5 Ultra high 

 

 

4.6.5 Carbonation resistance 

Fig. 4.15 shows the results of the carbonation resistance. The 100% OPC based mortar showed 

the lowest carbonation depth. Replacing 30% OPC by fly ash leads to a higher carbonation depth. 

Part of the explanation is related to the higher capillarity coefficient of the latter and the other part 

to the different hydration products.  

 

 

Fig. 4.15 Carbonation depth 

   Previous investigations (Khunthongkeaw et al,. 1996) have already reported an increase in 

concrete carbonation when fly-ash (FA) is used. The mixture with 30% OPC, 58.3 FA, 4% 

calcined stuff and 7.7% Ca(OH)2 shows a much higher carbonation depth than the second mixture 

with 30% FA. Since both mixtures have the same capillarity coefficient this means that the 

carbonation behaviour is related exclusively to the different hydration products. Thus meaning that 

the new hydration products are proper to carbonation. The mixture with 26% OPC, 58.3 FA, 8% 

0

5

10

15

20

25

30

0 10 20 30 40 50 60

C
a

rb
o

n
a

ti
o

n
 d

e
p

th
 (

m
m

)

Time (days)

OPC 100 OPC 70 – FL 30

OPC 30-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 4 OPC 26-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 8

OPC 18-FL 58.3-CH 7.7-CS 16



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

calcined stuff and 7.7% Ca(OH)2 shows the highest carbonation depth. This result is not a surprise 

because this mixture has also the highest water absorption capillarity. The mixture with 18% OPC, 

58.3 FA, 16% calcined stuff and 7.7% Ca(OH)2 shows almost the same carbonation depth as the 

mixture with 30%OPC and just 4% calcined stuff meaning that difference in composition has 

little influence on carbonation depth. 

 

4.6.6 Resistance to acid attack 

The results of mass loss for specimens immersed in 10% sulphuric acid solutions are shown in 

Fig. 4.16.  

 

Fig. 4.16 Weight loss of specimens due to acid attack 

After 1 day of immersion the best results are shown by the reference mixture and also by the 

mixture in which 30% OPC was replaced by fly ash. Since the reference mixture has much lower 

capillary water absorption than the other mixes, this means that in a short term the rate of acid 

ingress contributes to explain the observed results. However, this is not the case of the one part 

geopolymeric mixture with 8% calcined stuff because since it has the highest capillarity coefficient 

it should have a higher weight loss than the other geopolymeric mixtures.  

 

After 3 days of immersion in acid solution, one can confirm that the weight loss is proportional to 

the OPC content in the mixtures. A higher OPC content is associated to a lower weight loss. High 

pozzolan content mixtures showed lower resistance to acid attack this results do not confirm 

previous findings about the fact that the presence of pozzolanic admixtures was found to lower the 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

detrimental effect of acid attack on concrete (Beddoe and Schmidt, 2009; Goyal et al,. 2009) 

Probably because a denser microstructure typical of pozzolanic based mixtures were not yet 

formed by the time this mixtures were tested (28 days).  

 

 4.7 Conclusions 

   The investigations concerning mix design, properties and durability of one part geopolymer 

mixtures allowed for the following conclusions: 

Several one part geopolymer mixtures were developed some having a high compressive strength 

suitable for construction purposes. The results show that there is not a direct linear relationship 

between the calcium hydroxide content and the compressive strength. Still a general trend was 

observed linking compressive strength evolution with curing age, which is typical of OPC 

chemistry. Geopolymeric mixtures with 4% calcined stuff seems to correspond to a good 

compromise between a low OPC content and an acceptable compressive strength. A reduction of 

OPC content leads to a reduction on the compressive strength of the mixtures being that the 

addition of fly ash is not enough to compensate the OPC reduction due to its slow hydration 

characteristics. Further investigations on mixture composition will be needed in order to select 

mixtures with a high compressive strength and a high eco-efficient performance. The applicability 

of the Johnson–Mehl–Avrami–Kolmogorov model to predict the compressive strength of one part-

geopolymers was analysed. The degree of reaction of geopolymers was supposed to be related 

directly to compressive strength and then Avrami constants and exponents were found for all one 

part geopolymers. It was shown that compressive strength evolution of some one part geopolymers 

can be found by the proposed equations. The microstructure of one part geopolymers mortars 

present a very dense and uniform ITZ different of the porous typical interfacial transition zone of 

Portland cement mixtures. C/S ratio results show that some sodium is replacing Ca2+ in CSH 

which is typical of Na-C-S-H hydration products. FTIR spectra, strong peak band around 965 cm-

1 was characterized in the one part geopolymers that attributed stretching vibrations Si-O-Si or Al-

O-Si mode. No efflorescences, were observed. This may be due to the low amount of alkaline 

species used as well as to the fact that some sodium replaced Ca2+ in CSH hydration products. The 

durability of OPC mortars and one part geopolymer mortars was assessed by water absorption by 

immersion, water absorption by capillarity and resistance to acid attack. The results of water 



Chapter 4-Mix design, properties and durability 

 

absorption by immersion are very similar for all the mixtures which is due to the fact that they 

have the same w/b ratio. The capillary water absorption is very high for the one part geopolymeric 

mixtures with 8% calcined stuff indicating a microstructure with very high amount of capillary 

pores. The results of resistance to acid attack show that the weight loss is inversely proportional to 

the OPC content in the mixtures. 

 



 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

68 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

CHAPTER FIVE  

 Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

69 

 

5.1 Introduction 

This chapter compares the performance of two part foam geopolymers with the 

performance of one part geopolymers. The reason for such comparison as to do with the 

fact that foam geopolymer constitutes a recent research field with high potential in the 

development of low toxicity thermal insulators and with low thermal conductivity 

(Prud´homme et al, 2010; Shi et al., 2012, Zhang et al., 2012). Most important the 

development of materials for energy building related applications is a crucial issue 

because the increasing demand for worldwide energy, is a major cause for the 

unsustainable development of our Planet. Between 2007 and 2030 energy demand will 

grow about 40% reaching 16.8 billion tonnes of equivalent petroleum-TEP (Pacheco-

Torgal and Jalali, 2011). The rise in energy consumption has two main reasons, the 

increase in world population and the fact that there are an increasing number of people 

with access to electricity. Currently, 1.5 billion people still have no access to electricity 

(UN, 2010). Besides since urban human population will almost double, increasing from 

approximately 3.4 billion in 2009 to 6.4 billion in 2050 (WHO, 2014) this will 

dramatically increase electricity demand. Beyond what energy consumption means in 

terms of using non-renewable fossil materials, the highest environmental impact of energy 

consumption has to do with carbon dioxide emissions, generated during the burning of 

coal and gas for electricity generation in power stations. Given that buildings consume 

throughout their life cycle, more than 40% of all energy produced (OCDE, 2003), we can 

easily see the high energy saving potential that this subsector may represent in terms of 

reducing carbon dioxide emissions. Energy efficiency is the most cost effective way to 

reduce emissions, improve competitiveness and create employment. The Energy Road 

Map 2050 (COM 885, 2011) confirmed that higher energy efficiency in new and existing 

buildings is key for the transformation of the EU’s energy system. COM 815 (2011) 

mentions that the Union's energy efficiency target of saving 20% of energy by 2020 could 

cut consumers’ bills by up to €1000 per household a year and improving Europe’s 

industrial competitiveness and creating up to 2 million new jobs by 2020. The European 

Energy Performance of Buildings Directive 2002/91/EC (EPBD) has been recast in the 

form of the 2010/31/ EU by the European Parliament on 19 May 2010.  One of the new 

aspects of the EPBD that reflects an ambitious agenda on the reduction of the energy 

consumption is the introduction of the concept of nearly zero-energy building (Pacheco-



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

70 

 

Torgal et al., 2013). The use of thermal insulation materials constitutes the most effective 

way of reducing heat losses in buildings thus reducing heat energy needs. These materials 

are very important for the building material industry representing a 21 billion € market 

share (Pacheco-Torgal, 2014). With the exception of expanded cork, which is based on a 

renewable and completely recyclable material, all the other current insulation materials 

are associated with negative impacts in terms of toxicity. Polystyrene, for example 

contains anti-oxidant additives and ignition retardants, additionally, its production 

involves the generation of benzene and chlorofluorocarbons. On the other hand, 

polyurethane is obtained from isocyanates, which are widely known for their tragic 

association with the Bhopal disaster. Besides, they release toxic fumes when subjected to 

fire (Pacheco-Torgal et al., 2012b). Besides recently the European Union approved the 

Regulation (EU) 305/2011 related to the Construction Products Regulation (CPR) that 

replaced the current Directive 89/106/CEE, already amended by Directive 1993/68/EEC, 

known as the Construction Products Directive (CPD). A crucial aspect of the new 

regulation relates to the information regarding hazardous substances.  

 

5.2 Two part foam geopolymers 

The mix parameters were analysed through a laboratory experiment of 54 different two 

part geopolymeric mortar mixes were, sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio (2.5, 

3.5, 4.5), activator/binder mass ratio (0.6, 0.8, 1.0), chemical foaming agent type 

(hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) and sodium perborate (NaBO3)) and foaming agent mass ratio 

content (1%, 2%, 3%). 

Table 5.1 Mix compositions (%) 

Mix 
Fly ash/ 

Powder* 

Ca(OH)2/ 

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

Sodium silicate/ 

Sodium hydroxide 

Activator/ 

Binder 
H2O2

**
 NaBO3 

FL 90-CH 10 90 10 80 

2.5 

3.5 

4.5 

0.6 

0.8 

1.0 

1 

2 

3 

1 

2 

3 

*Powder: Fly ash + Ca(OH)2  

**Foam agent to powder 

5.2.1 Properties  

The results of water absorption by immersion are showed in Fig. 5.1. The lowest water 

absorption by immersion (11.2%) was in a mixture with an activator/binder ratio of 0.8 a 

sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 4.5 and 3% hydrogen peroxide content. Very similar 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

71 

 

and low water absorption values (12.7%) were found for mixtures with 1% hydrogen 

peroxide and a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5. One with an activator/binder 

ratio of 0.8 and the other with an activator/binder ratio of 1.0. The highest water 

absorption by immersion (27%) were found in a mixture with an activator/binder ratio of 

1.0 a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5 and 3% hydrogen peroxide content. A 

similar high water absorption (27%) was found in a mixture with an activator/binder ratio 

of 1.0 a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 3.5 and 3% sodium perborate content and 

also in a mixture with an activator/binder ratio of 0.6 a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide 

of 4.5 and 3% hydrogen peroxide content. This means that concerning water absorption 

both foaming agents allow for high porosity mixtures depending on their content and on 

the ratios activator/binder and sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide.  

 

The results of density are presented in Fig. 5.2. The lowest density results were found in 

mixtures with an activator/binder ratio of 0.6 and 3% hydrogen peroxide content. One 

with a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 4.5 (734 kg/m3) and other with a sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5 (749 kg/m3). As a general trend the increase of foaming 

agent leads to a lower density. However, the opposite can also take place. That is the case 

of hydrogen peroxide based mixtures with an activator/binder ratio of 1.0 a sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide of 3.5. 

 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

72 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.1 Water absorption by immersion according to activator/binder ratio and sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder 

ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

73 

 

 

  

 

 

Fig. 5.2 Density according to activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass 

ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

74 

 

Fig. 5.3 shows the results of the thermal conductivity. Thermal conductivity was executed 

on specimens, which had low density (lower than 900 kg/m3) and compressive strength 

above 3 MPa. The missing values are related to high density mixtures. The lowest thermal 

conductivity performance was achieved (0.113 W/m.ºK) in a mixture with an 

activator/binder ratio of 0.8 a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5 and 3% sodium 

perborate content. A similar thermal conductivity was obtain in a mixture with the same 

activator/binder ratio, the same sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide ratio and 1% sodium 

perborate content (0.1195 W/m.ºK). A mixture with the same sodium silicate/sodium 

hydroxide of 2.5 with an activator/binder ratio of 0.6 and 2% hydrogen peroxide content 

also lead to a low thermal conductivity (0.1293 W/m.ºK).  

 

   Another sodium perborate based mixtures with an activator/binder ratio of 1.0 and a 

sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 4.5 also led to a low thermal conductivity (0.1187 

W/m.ºK). These results outperform the thermal conductivity of commercial autoclaved 

aerated concrete masonry blocks (Ytong) of around (0.17 W/m.ºK). No valid statistic 

correlation was found between thermal conductivity and density (Fig. 5.4). Different 

sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide ratios and different activator/binder ratios could explain 

this. 

 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

75 

 

  

 

  

Fig. 5.3 Thermal conductivity according to activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium 

hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; 

Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

76 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.4 Thermal conductivity versus density: a) Hydrogen peroxide based geopolymers; 

b) Sodium perborate based geopolymers; c) both 

b) 

c) 

a) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

77 

 

Fig. 5.5 shows the results of the compressive strength. Low compressive strength results 

(below 3 MPa) were found in hydrogen peroxide mixtures (2 and 3%) with an 

activator/binder ratio of 0.8 and a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5. It is important 

to mention that the mixtures with a low thermal conductivity previously mentioned 

showed a compressive strength in the range of 4.5-6.0 MPa while commercial autoclaved 

aerated concrete masonry blocks have an average compressive strength above 4,5 MPa.  

No valid statistic correlation was found between compressive strength and density due to 

the variation of the results and the limited number of test samples (Fig. 5.6).  

Figs. 5.7-5.9 show the microstructure of three foam geopolymer mixtures. Their 

composition is shown in table 5.1 while the EDS atomic ratios of two points for each 

mixture are presented also in table 5.2.  

Table 5.2 EDS atomic ratios 

 

   The microstructure of the three samples shows different level of unreacted fly ash 

particles. This is consistent with their compressive strength respectively 4.6 MPa, 5.36 

MPa and 6.89 MPa. All EDS atomic ratios show a low C/S ratio. Typical C/S ratios in 

CSH of traditional OPC systems are situated from 1.5 to 2.0 (Diamond, 1976). Meaning 

there has been some sodium replacing Ca2+ in CSH. Some authors have already 

demonstrated that sodium incorporation in the CSH phase increases as C/S ratio decreases 

(Macphee, 1989).  

All EDS analysis show hydration products with a SiO2/Al2O3 higher than the original 

SiO2/Al2O3 fly ash ratio which is explained by the Si species added through the used of 

the sodium silicate. FG B and FG C show similar SiO2/Al2O3 atomic ratios although they 

used very different sodium silicate contents in their composition. This could mean that the 

extra Si species have not contributed to the formation of the hardened alkaline 

aluminosilicate structure and that an optimum sodium silicate content exists. 

 

 Fly ash                                                             FG A FG B FG C 

Z1 Z2 Z1 Z2 Z1 Z2 

SiO2/Al2O3 3.05 19.57 10.33 9.86 9.78 9.92 8.24 

Al2O3/Na2O 16.75 0.13 0.14 0.30 0.15 0.45 0.63 

CaO/SiO2 0.05 0.47 0.1 0.27 0.14 0.28 0.28 

Na2O/CaO 0.38 0.78 6.49 1.22 4.35 0.75 0.67 

MgO/Al2O3 0.13 0.57 0.29 0.27 0.44 0.31 0.38 

Fe2O3/Al2O3 0.19 0.30 0.09 0.14 0.08 0.24 0.16 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

78 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.5 Compressive strength according to activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium 

hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; 

Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

79 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.6 Compressive strength versus density: a) Hydrogen peroxide based geopolymers; 

b) Sodium perborate based geopolymers; c) both 

c) 

a) 

b) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

80 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.7 SEM mix FGA 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

81 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.8 SEM mix FGB  

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

82 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.9 SEM mix FGC  

   The FTIR spectra of the three hardened foam geopolymer mixtures (table 5.3) are 

presented in Fig. 5.10. Strong vibration typical of alluminosilicates can be seen. The peak 

centered around 959 and 965 cm-1 is characteristic of a geopolymerization reaction 

corresponding to the Si–O–Al and Si–O–Si vibration bands. The band at about 864 cm-1 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

83 

 

(Fig. 5.10 c) is assigned to Si– OH bending vibration. This mixture had a sodium 

silicate/sodium hydroxide of 4.5. The absorption band around 1394, 1396 and 1405 cm-1 

is attributed to stretching vibrations of CO3
2- ions confirming the existence of carbonate 

species (Fernandez-Jimenez and Palomo, 2005). Atmospheric CO2 enter in geopolymer to 

reacting with unhydrated sodium to form sodium carbonate.  

 
Table 5.3 Content of geopolymer samples used for FTIR  

 

 

4000.0 3000 2000 1500 1000 552.0

50.0

60

70

80

90

100.0

c m-1

%T  

3340.31

1651.44

1394.30

959.73

 

Sample Activator/ 

Binder 

Sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass 

ratio (SS/SH) 

Foam Agent 

type 

Foam 

agent 

content 

FG A 1 2.5 

 

NaBO3 1% 

FG B 
0.6 H2O2 3% 

FG C 4.5 

a) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

84 

 

4000.0 3000 2000 1500 1000 552.0

50.0

60

70

80

90

100.0

c m-1

%T  

3291.59

1649.56

1396.09

965.68

 

4000.0 3000 2000 1500 1000 552.0

50.0

60

70

80

90

100.0

c m-1

%T  

3274.68
1649.99

1433.54

1405.91

965.22

864.60

 

Fig. 5.10 FTIR bands of foam geopolymers: a) FGA; b) FGB; c) FGC  

 

 

5.2.2 Cost analysis 

Since the sodium perborate has a cost 50% higher than the hydrogen peroxide it is 

important to assess how can this influence the overall cost performance of the different 

mixtures. Fig. 5.11 shows the cost of the foam geopolymer mixtures according to the 

activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio. The lower the 

activator/binder ratio, the lower the cost. This is because the cost percentage of foaming 

agents is just around 10% the total cost (Table 5.4).  

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

85 

 

Table 5.4 Cost of the materials (euro/kg) 

Calcium 

hydroxide 

Fly ash Sodium  

silicate 

Sodium 

hydroxide 

Water H2O2 NaBO3 

0.3 0.03 0.53 0.85 0.001 0.98 1.5 

 

 

 

         

Fig. 5.11 Cost according to activator/binder ratio and sodium silicate/sodium 

hydroxide mass ratio: a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; 

Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

86 

 

   Alkaline activators being responsible for 80% of the cost. Current investigations aiming 

to replace sodium silicate by low cost waste glass (Puertas et al., 2014) will increase the 

cost efficiency of foam geopolymer mixtures. Fig. 5.12 shows the cost to thermal 

resistance ratio. Fig. 5.13 shows the cost to thermal resistance ratio for several 

activator/binder ratios. The mixture with the higher performance uses sodium perborate 

with a activator/binder ratio of 1.0 and sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio of 

4.5.   

 

Hydrogen peroxide based mixtures (3% and 2% content) with and activator/binder ratio of 

0.8 and a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide mass ratio of 2.5 and 3.5 also present a low 

cost to thermal resistance ratio. 

 

 

Fig. 5.12 Cost to thermal resistance ratio 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

87 

 

 

 

 

 

Fig. 5.13 Cost to thermal resistance ratio: 

a) Activator/binder ratio=1; b) Activator/binder ratio=0.8; Activator/binder ratio=0.6 

a) 

b) 

c) 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

88 

 

5.3 One part foam geopolymers 

The one part geopolymer mixtures used to produce the foam geopolymer are presented 

in table 5.5. The influence of three foaming agents namely aluminium powder (0.5% -

1.5%), NaBO3 (3%-5%) and H2O2 (3%-5%) was analysed. 

 

Table 5.5 Composition of one-part geopolymer mixtures    

Mix 
OPC/ 

Powder* 

Fly ash/ 

Powder 
Calcined /Powder 

Ca(OH)2/ 

Powder 

Sand/ 

Powder 

SP/ 

OPC 

W/ 

Powder 

100 OPC 100% - - - 

80% 0.8% 35%  

30 OPC_70 FA 30% 70% - - 

30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH 30% 58.3% 4% 7.7% 

26 OPC_58.3 FA_8 CS_7.7 CH 26% 58.3% 8% 7.7% 

18 OPC_58.3 FA_16 CS_7.7 CH 18% 58.3% 16% 7.7% 
*Powder: OPC + Fly ash + Calcined kaolin and sodium hydroxide + Ca(OH)2 

*Calcined stuff has been prepared by mixing kaolin and sodium hydroxide with 2.5/1 

ratio. 
 

5.3.1 Properties  

The results of X-ray diffraction are presented in Fig. 5.14. A small mullite crystalline 

phase is detected in all the calcined kaolin based mixtures. A clear calcite peak is common 

to the calcined kaolin mixtures. The clear crystalline structure in these mixtures contrasts 

with the amorphous structures of traditional two part geopolymers. The different foaming 

agents (aluminum powder and hydrogen peroxide) seems not to have altered the 

crystalline phases of the hardened material. The exception being the clear calcite silicate 

oxide in the mixture containing 5% oxygen peroxide. Results of SEM are presented in 

Fig. 5.15 Also the mixtures have the following compressive strength after 28 days curing 

(2.3, 2.2, 7 and 8.7). The mixtures associated to lower compressive strength show lesser 

dense microstructure. This is clearer in the mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (5% 

H2O2) with 5% hydrogen peroxide foaming agent. Concerning the EDS molar ratios 

(Table 5.6). Several areas (Z2 e Z3 in mixture with 3.5% H2O2 and Z2 in mixture with 

0.5% aluminum powder) in the one-part geopolymer mixture show lower C/S ratio typical 

of sodium incorporation in the CSH phase into Na-C-S-H gel. That usually evolve into 

compositions with higher calcium and lower aluminum content (with the C–A–S–H gel 

proposed to be more stable than N–A–S–H, at high pH) (Garcia-Lodeiro et al., 2013). 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

89 

 

 
Fig. 5.14 XRD patterns of: a) 100 OPC (1.5% AL); b) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (0.5% 

AL); c) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (5% H2O2); d) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (3.5% 

H2O2); M-Mullite; Q-Quartz; C-Calcite; CA-Calcite silicate oxide 

 
                                             Table 5.6 EDS atomic ratios  

 
100 OPC 

 

30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH 

 

 

 

1.5% AL 3.5% H2O2 

 

5% H2O2 
 

 

0.5% AL 

 Z1 Z2 Z1 Z2 Z3 Z1 Z1 Z2 

SiO2/Al2O3 1.41 3.96 8.81 6.08 4.41 5.86 2.08 5.84 

Al2O3/ Na2O --- --- 0.47 2.73 4.53 --- 6.20 6.66 

CaO / SiO2 6.57 3.32 5.08 0.46 0.08 6.55 2.40 0.42 

Na2O / CaO --- --- 0.04 0.13 0.61 --- 0.03 0.06 

MgO/Al2O3 0.57 3.84 2.32 0.54 --- --- --- --- 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

90 

 

 

Fig. 5.15 SEM images of: a) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (3.5% H2O2);  

b) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (5% H2O2); c) 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH (0.5% AL); 

d) 100 OPC (1.5% AL);  
 

Results of compressive strength of one-part geopolymer mortars are shown in Fig. 5.16. 

For mortars based only in Portland cement, increase of the aluminium content leads to a 

decrease in compressive strength.  



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

91 

 

 
Fig. 5.16 Compressive strength 

   Except when the aluminium content increases from 1.2% to 1.5% which leads to 

increase of compressive strength. The reaction of aluminium powder in the alkaline 

environment liberates Al2O
- and hydrogen gas (H2) according to the equation 1 (Arellano 

et al., 2010): 

 

8Al+2OH-+ 2H2O   ?  4Al2O
-+3H2                                                                      (1) 

 

   When the NaBO3 is used as foaming agent in Portland cement mortars a trend on 

compressive strength decreased with foaming agent increased. Although one exception is 

detected when NaBO3 increased from 3% to 3.5% that leads to an increase in compressive 

strength. Concerning the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent shows a minor 

increase in the compressive strength but when the foaming agent is increased 4% to 4.5% 

compressive strength decreased. Comparing the performance of the different foaming 

agents on Portland cement mortars it is observed that the higher compressive strength 

(20.24 MPa) was recorded for a 0.5% AL content. Concerning the mixture 30 OPC_70 

FA, the increase of the aluminium content results in a decrease in compressive strength.  

 

   Except when it increased from 1% to 1.2% lead to slight compressive strength increase. 

When the NaBO3 is used a trend on compressive strength decrease with foaming agent 

increase can be found. In respect to the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent from 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

92 

 

3%-3.5% leads to decrease the compressive strength. In an alkaline environment oxygen 

peroxide decomposes into water and oxygen.  

 

  In general, it can be stated that the results gathered for compressive strength of the 

mixture 30 OPC_70 FA with different foam agents are taken place in a lower range in 

compare to other compressive strengths of one-part geopolymer mortars. Regarding the 

mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH an increase of the aluminium content results in a 

reduction for compressive strength. Increasing NaBO3 from 1% to 5% reduced the 

compressive strength with some exceptions. The exceptions were found when the NaBO3 

content increased from 1% to 2% and 4.5% to 5%. Since, no specific trend was observed 

in compressive strength of the mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH that used H2O2.  

 

   Comparing the performance of the different foaming agents the higher compressive 

strength (7 MPa) took place for a 0.5% AL content. Additionally, two similar compressive 

strength recorded for this mixture with 1% AL (6 MPa) and 1.2% AL (6.04 MPa). Results 

of compressive strength in mixture 26 OPC_58.3 FA_8 CS_7.7 CH show that there is an 

increase in compressive strength when the Al content increased. The increase in density 

can related to pore collapses as suggested by these authors (Masi et al., 2014). Those 

authors also confirm that aluminium powder is very reactive requiring a much less amount 

than hydrogen peroxide to obtain similar densities. However since the former costs 33 

more than the later (section 5.3.2) it is important to compare the economic performance of 

the different mixtures. Although an exception discovered when the aluminium content 

increased from 0.5% to 1%. Since, no specific trend was observed in compressive strength 

of the mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH that used NaBO3. Concerning the use of 

H2O2 result in constant trend in compressive strength with an exception. An increase of 

H2O2 content between 3% to 3.5% lead to a slight increase in the compressive strength. 

The higher compressive strength (6.99 MPa) registered for a 4% NaBO3 content.  

   Concerning the mixture 18 OPC_58.3 FA_16 CS_7.7 CH, an increase in the aluminium 

content leads to a decrease in compressive strength. When the NaBO3 is used as foaming 

agent a trend on compressive strength increase with foaming agent increase can be 

noticed. Except when the NaBO3 increased from 4% to 4.5% lead to a compressive 

strength reduction. Respect to the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent results in 

reduction of compressive strength. By comparing the performance of the different 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

93 

 

foaming agents it can be concluded that the higher compressive strength (6.11 MPa) was 

measured for a 5% NaBO3 content. The overall results show that several mixtures show a 

compressive strength similar to the one of commercial cellular concrete blocks (6.5 MPa).  

 

   However most mixtures comply with the compressive strength requirement (?1.4 MPa) 

of the grades 4 and 5 of the Korean Industrial Standard code for foam concrete for floor 

heating systems (Yang et al., 2014). 

 

   Results of water absorption of one-part geopolymer mortars are shown in Fig. 5.17. For 

mortars based on Portland cement, the increase of the aluminium content does not leads to 

a relevant change in water absorption. When it increases from 1.2% to 1.5% leads to the 

slight water absorption decrease. When the NaBO3 is used as foaming agent in Portland 

cement mortars a trend on water absorption increase with foaming agent increase can be 

noticed. However, some exceptions are detected. The increase from 3% to 3.5% and the 

increase from 4% to 4.5% that lead to a water absorption reduction. Concerning the use of 

H2O2 the increase of foaming agent from 3% to 3.5% shows a minor increase in the water 

absorption but when the foaming agent is increased above 3.5% no water absorption is 

detected. Comparing the performance of the different foaming agents on Portland cement 

mortars it is seen that the highest water absorption (62%) took place for a 5% 

NaBO3 content.  

 
Fig. 5.17 Water absorption 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

94 

 

   However, this mixture shows a foaming efficiency (water absorption/foaming agent 

content= 12) that is lower than other mixtures based on aluminium foaming agent that 

show higher water absorption levels with just 0.5% content (efficiency= 90). Concerning 

the mixtures 30 OPC_70 FA, the increase of the aluminium content leads to a slight 

increase in water absorption. When the aluminium increases from 1.2% to 1.5% a slight 

water absorption decrease was detected. When the NaBO3 is used as foaming agent in this 

mixture a trend on water absorption decrease with foaming agent increase registered.  

 

   However, there was an exception. When the NaBO3 increased from 4% to 4.5% leads to 

a water absorption reduction. Regarding the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent 

depicts a minor decrease in the water absorption but when the foaming agent is increased 

above 4% slight increase in water absorption is detected. Comparing the performance of 

the different foaming agents on the mixture 30 OPC_70 FA it is revealed that the higher 

water absorption (50.53%) recorded for 1.5% Al content. In respect to the mixtures 30 

OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH, an increase of the aluminium content leads to an increase of 

water absorption. The increase from 0.8% to 1% and 1.2%to 1.5% decrease the water 

absorption. When the NaBO3 is used as foaming agent, a decrease was detected by 

increasing foam agent content. Although some exceptions were detected from 1% to 2% 

and 4% to 5% which lead to water absorption increase.  

 

   Concerning the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent leads to reduce in water 

absorption with one exception. The exception was monitored in an increase of foam agent 

from 4% to 4.5% which leads to increase in water absorption. Comparing the performance 

of the different foaming agents it is found that the higher water absorption (81.07%) took 

place for a 4.5% H2O2 content. This corresponds to an efficiency of (81.07/4.5= 18) while 

Al mixtures show high efficiencies (40/1.2=33.3).Concerning the mixtures 26 OPC_58.3 

FA_8 CS_7.7 CH, an increase of the aluminium content leads to a slight decrease in water 

absorption with one exception. The exception was measured when the use of 

AL increased from 0.5% to 1% and a minor increase in the water absorption was detected.  

 

   When the NaBO3 is used as foaming agent a trend on water absorption is almost 

constant with no increase, regardless increasing foam agent content. In respect to the use 

of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent shows no change in the water absorption. The 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

95 

 

performance of different foaming agents on this mixture showed that the higher water 

absorption (72.72%) was registered for a 3% NaBO3 content. Additionally, some similar 

high water absorptions observed for this mixture with 1.2% Al (72.31%), 1.5% AL 

(72.22%), 3.5% NaBO3 (72.27%), and 5% NaBO3 (72.70%). Concerning the mixture 30 

OPC_58.3 FA_16 CS_7.7 CH, an increase of the aluminium content leads to an increase 

in water absorption. When the NaBO3 is used a trend on water absorption reduction with 

foaming agent content increase can be noticed. However, some exceptions are acquired.  

 

   The increase of NaBO3 from 3% to 3.5% and the increase of NaBO3 from 4.5% to 5% 

lead to a water absorption increase. Regarding the use of H2O2, by increasing foam agent 

content no increase in water absorption is discovered. Comparing the performance of the 

different foaming agents on the mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_16 CS_7.7 CA it is seen that 

the higher water absorption (81.48%) took place for a 5% NaBO3 content.  

 

   The results of bulk density of one-part geopolymer mortars are shown in Fig. 5.18. For 

mortars based on Portland cement an increment in the aluminium content leads to a 

decrease in bulk density. When the NaBO3 is employed in Portland cement mortars a 

trend on bulk density decrease with foaming agent content increase can be noticed.  

 
Fig. 5.18 Bulk density 

   Concerning the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent show a minor increase in the 

bulk density but when the foaming agent is increased between 4% to 4.5% slight decrease 

in bulk density was detected. Regarding the performance of the different foaming agents 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

96 

 

on Portland cement mortars it is revealed that the lowest bulk density (1067 kg/m3) 

recorded for a 3% H2O2 content. Concerning the mixture 30 OPC_70 FA the increase of 

the aluminium content leads to decrease in bulk density. Except when it increases from 

1% to 1.2% lead to the slight bulk density increase. When the NaBO3 is used a trend can 

be noticed on bulk density increase. Regarding the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming 

agent from 3% to 4% show a decrease in the bulk density but when the foaming agent is 

increased above 4% an increase in the bulk density were registered. The lowest bulk 

density (785 kg/m3) took place for a 4.5% H2O2 content. In respect to results of bulk 

density for mixture 30 OPC_58.3 FA_4 CS_7.7 CH increasing the aluminium content 

leads to reduce bulk density. Except when it increases from 0.8% to 1% which lead to the 

slight bulk density increase. Increasing the NaBO3 content results in increasing bulk 

density, except when it increases from 4% to 4.5% which leads to the slight bulk density 

decrease. Concerning the use of H2O2 the increase of foaming agent show a constant trend 

in bulk density results. Comparing the obtained results by using different foaming agents 

it is observed that the lowest bulk density (821 kg/m3) took place for a 1.2% Al content.  

 

   Concerning the mixture 26 OPC_58.3 FA_8 CS_7.7 CH an increasing the aluminium 

content from 0.5% to 1% leads to slight increase in bulk density. By increasing Al content 

more than 0.8% results in constant trend in bulk density and no increase was detected.  

 

   Respect to the increase in NaBO3 content as foam agent, no change was observed. When 

NaBO3 content increased from 4% to 4.5% a slight increase in bulk density was noticed.  

 

   The use of H2O2 shows a slight decrease from 3% to 3.5%. Increasing H2O2 content 

more than 3.5% did not show any change in bulk density. Comparing the results obtained 

from using different foaming agents, it is revealed that the lowest bulk density (980 

kg/m3) measured for a 4% H2O2 content. Concerning the mixture 18 OPC_58.3 FA_16 

CS_7.7 CH. the increase of the aluminium content leads to reduce of bulk density. 

Increasing of NaBo3 content, results in reduction of bulk density. However some 

exceptions were detected. Increasing NaBO3 from 3% to 3.5% and 4% to 4.5% lead to 

slight increase in bulk density.  The increase of H2O2  foam agent content leads to 

decrease of bulk density. Except from 4.5% to 5% which show an increase in the bulk 

density. The lowest bulk density (654 kg/m3) recorded for a 4.5% H2O2 content. 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

97 

 

   Fig. 5.19 presents the results of thermal conductivity performance of some one part 

foam geopolymer mixtures. Thermal conductivity test was not carried out on all one-part 

geopolymer mixtures. Instead, two criteria were considered to select the mixtures for 

thermal conductivity testing, a) Mixtures with compressive strength greater than 2 MPa; 

b) Mixtures with bulk density lower than 1100 kg/m3. The lowest thermal conductivity 

performance (0.132 W/m.K) was recorded for one-part geopolymer mortars, in mix 30 

OPC+58.3 FA+4 CS_7.7 CH and 1.2% Al. Furthermore, a close value of thermal 

conductivity was measured for the same mixture with 1.5% aluminium powder. As the 

thermal conductivity of commercial autoclaved aerated concrete masonry blocks (Ytong) 

is around (0.17 W/m.K), similar thermal conductivity performances can be considered 

acceptable for thermal insulator like cementitious materials.  The mixture 26 OPC+58.3 

FA+8 CS_7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide shows an acceptable thermal 

conductivity of 0.16 W/m.K because it fits the threshold of the grades 4 and 5 of the 

Korean Industrial Standard code for foam concrete for floor heating systems (Yang et al., 

2014). 

 
Fig. 5.19 Thermal conductivity 

 

 

 

 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

98 

 

5.3.2 Cost analysis 

The cost of materials are listed in Table 5.7 which shows that the Al powder foaming 

agent has a much higher cost than the other two foaming agents. The cost of mixtures is 

presented in Fig. 5. 20.  

Table 5.7 Costs of the materials (euro/kg) 

Sand OPC 
Ca (OH)2 Fly 

ash 
Kaolin 

Sodium 

hydroxide 
Water SP H2O2 NaBO3 AL 

0.02 0.1 0.3 0.03 0.29 0.85 0.1 0.82 0.98 1.5 32.4 

 

   The results show that using Al powder leads to a significant increase of the cost of 

geopolymers mixtures. The most cost-efficient mixtures (67 euro/m3) were obtained for 

26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide foaming agent. The use of 

mixtures based on aluminium powder is not feasible because they are not cost-efficient at 

all. The mixture based on aluminium powder foaming agent with the lowest cost (30 

OPC+58.3 FA+4 CS+7.7 CH) costs more than 200 euro/m3. This represents more than 

twice the cost of Ytong masonry blocks (70-80 euro/m3). It is worth remember that foam 

mortars based on classical two part geopolymers have a cost above 300 euro/m3 

(Abdollahnejad et al., 2015). Fig. 5.20 also includes cost simulations for two scenarios: a) 

Carbon social cost of 34.7 euro/ton as per US study (Standford, 2015); b) Carbon social 

cost of 206.3 euro/ton (Moore and Diaz, 2015). When the cost of the mixtures includes the 

cost of carbon dioxide emissions mixtures based on hydrogen peroxide show a high 

increase in its cost. A minor increase is noticed in aluminium powder based mixtures. The 

results confirm that in both scenarios the mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 

3.5% hydrogen peroxide foaming agent is still the most cost-efficient. The results of the 

cost to thermal resistance ratio are presented in Fig. 5.21 The best ratio was detected for 

the mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH around 10 euro/(m.K/W).  



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

99 

 

Fig. 5.20 Cost of one-part geopolymer mixtures: Gray bars) Materials cost; Red bars) 

Materials cost for a carbon cost in scenario 1; Green bars) Materials cost for a carbon cost in 

scenario 2  

 
Fig. 5.21 Cost to thermal resistance ratio 

30 OPC_58.5 FA_4CS_7.7CH 

100 OPC 

 

30 OPC_ 

70 FA 
26 OPC_ 

58.5 FA_ 

8CS_ 

7.7CH 

18 OPC_ 

58.5 FA_ 

16CS_ 

7.7CH 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

100 

 

5.3.3 Global warming potential 

The global warming potential GWP (KgCO2e) was assessed using EcoInvent database. 

Fig. 5.22 presents the global warming potential to thermal resistance ratio. The results 

show that mixtures with similar thermal conductivity performance have a much different 

global warming potential to thermal resistance ratio. This parameter is influenced by the 

percentage of Portland cement. Higher percentages are associated with higher ratios of 

global warming potential to thermal resistance ratios. Even the mixtures containing 

sodium hydroxide have a lower ratio because although the GWP of NaOH is 2.65 higher 

than the GWP of Portland cement the amount of OPC used in those mixtures is much 

higher. The mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide 

foaming has a global warming potential of 443 KgCO2eq/m
3. 

 

Fig. 5.22 Global warming potential to thermal resistance ratio  

 

 

5.4 Conclusions 

The results of two part foam geopolymers show that the sodium perborate over performs 

hydrogen peroxide leading to a lower overall thermal conductibility of foam geopolymers. 



Chapter 5 – Performance of foam geopolymers: Two part versus one part 

101 

 

The use of an activator/binder ratio of 0.8 and a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5 

led to the lowest thermal conductivity. Mixtures with a low thermal conductivity of 

around 0.1 W/(m.ºK) and a compressive strength of around 6 MPa were achieved. The 

cost analysis show the foaming agents are responsible for a small percentage of foam 

geopolymers total cost (less than 10%) being that the alkaline activators are responsible 

for more than 80%.  

 

   Concerning foam one part geopolymer mixtures the results show that the use of 

aluminium powder is very effective in obtaining foam materials with low thermal 

conductivity. An increase of bulk density with aluminium powder content was noticed 

that could be related to pore collapses. Aluminium powder allows the production of 

mortar mixtures with a compressive strength above 6MPa however, its high cost means 

they are commercially useless when facing the competition of commercial cellular 

concrete. The mortar mixture based on aluminium powder mortar with the lowest cost (30 

OPC+58.3 FA+4 CS+7.7 CH) costs more than 200 euro/m3. This represents more than 

twice the cost of Ytong masonry blocks (70-80 euro/m3). It is worth remember that foam 

mortars based on classical two part geopolymers have a cost above 300 euro/m3 which 

shows that two part geopolymers are not a cost-effective solution for thermal insulation 

materials. The mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide 

shows an acceptable compressive strength and thermal conductivity complying with the 

requirements of the grades 4 and 5 of the Korean Industrial Standard code for foam 

concrete for floor heating systems (?1.4 MPa and ?0.16 W/m.K). This mixture is cost 

efficient (67 euro/m3) and has a low global warming potential of 443 KgCO2eq/m
3. When 

the cost of the mixtures includes the cost of carbon dioxide emissions mixtures based on 

hydrogen peroxide show a high increase in its cost. A minor increase is noticed in 

aluminium powder based mixtures. The results confirm that in both carbon dioxide social 

cost scenarios the mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide 

foaming agent is still the most cost-efficient. 

 

 

 

 

 

 



103 
 

6.1 Conclusions and suggestions for further investigations 

 
   The production of Portland cement as the essential constituent of concrete requires considerable 

energy, releasing a significant amount of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases (GHGs) into 

atmosphere. Environmental concerns regarding the high CO2 emissions related to the production 

of ordinary Portland cement (OPC) led to research efforts on the development of eco-efficient 

alternative binders.  

 

Geopolymers constitute promising inorganic binders alternative to OPC which are based on 

aluminosilicates by-products and alkali activators. The geopolymerization technology is a 

complex chemical process evolving dissolution of raw materials, transportation, orientation and 

polycondensation of the reaction products. However, there are still many drawbacks associated 

with traditional two part geopolymer mixes. The caustic alkaline solutions needed to form the 

geopolymers make the handling and application of geopolymers difficult. Also, workability is 

generally poor and not easily adjustable due to a sticky and thick mortar that is generated during 

processing. The system is also sensitive to the ratio of alkaline and soluble silicate, which is 

difficult to control in practice. Also two part geopolymers carbon footprint is dependent on the 

fact that sodium silicate usage is avoided. The durability of two part geopolymers is also subject 

of some controversy. Some authors state that the durability of these materials constitutes the most 

important advantage over Portland cement others argue that it is an unproven issue. For instance 

current two part geopolymeric mixes can suffer from efflorescence originated by the fact that 

alkaline or soluble silicates that are added during processing cannot be totally consumed during 

geopolymerisation. This leads to high permeability and water absorption due to the movement of 

alkali together with water to the geopolymer surfaces. Therefore, new and improved geopolymer 

mixes are needed. 

 

The discovery of one-part geopolymers is considered as a key event on the evolution of low 

carbon geopolymer technology in the “just add water” concept. However they were associated 

with very low compressive strength. Some authors even report a compressive strength decrease 

with time for one-part geopolymers based on calcined red mud and sodium hydroxide blends. The 

present thesis aimed to develop some one part geopolymer mixtures that could be of some use for 

the construction industry. The experimental and numerical results allows for the following 

conclusions 



104 
 

Several one part geopolymer mixtures were developed some having a high compressive strength 

suitable for construction purposes. The results show that there is not a direct linear relationship 

between the calcium hydroxide content and the compressive strength. Still a general trend was 

observed linking compressive strength evolution with curing age, which is typical of OPC 

chemistry. The applicability of the Johnson–Mehl–Avrami–Kolmogorov model to predict the 

compressive strength of one part-geopolymers was analysed. The degree of reaction of 

geopolymers was supposed to be related directly to compressive strength and then Avrami 

constants and exponents were found for all one part geopolymers. It was shown that compressive 

strength evolution of some one part geopolymers can be found by the proposed equations. The 

microstructure of one part geopolymers mortars present a very dense and uniform ITZ different of 

the porous typical interfacial transition zone of Portland cement mixtures.C/S ratio results show 

that some sodium is replacing Ca2+ in CSH which is typical of Na-C-S-H hydration products. No 

efflorescences, no presence was observed. This may be due to the low amount of alkaline species 

used as well as to the fact that some sodium replaced Ca2+ in CSH hydration products.  

 

The investigations on foam geopolymers show that in two part mixtures the sodium perborate 

over performs hydrogen peroxide leading to a lower overall thermal conductibility. The use of an 

activator/binder ratio of 0.8 and a sodium silicate/sodium hydroxide of 2.5 led to the lowest 

thermal conductivity. Mixtures with a low thermal conductivity of around 0.1 W/(m.ºK) and a 

compressive strength of around 6 MPa were achieved. The cost analysis show the foaming agents 

are responsible for a small percentage of foam geopolymers total cost (less than 10%) being that 

the alkaline activators are responsible for more than 80%. Concerning one part geopolymers the 

results show that the use of aluminium powder is very effective in obtaining foam materials with 

low thermal conductivity. An increase of bulk density with aluminium powder content was 

noticed that can be related to pore collapses. Aluminium powder allows the production of mortar 

mixtures with a compressive strength above 6MPa however its high cost means they are 

commercially useless when facing the competition of commercial cellular concrete. The mixture 

26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen peroxide shows an acceptable compressive 

strength and thermal conductivity complying with the requirements for foam concrete for floor 

heating systems (?1.4 MPa and ?0.16 W/m.K). This mixture is cost efficient (67 euro/m3) and has 

a low global warming potential of 443 kg CO2eq/m
3. The results confirm that in both carbon 

dioxide social cost scenarios the mixture 26 OPC+58.3 FA+8 CS+7.7 CH with 3.5% hydrogen 

peroxide foaming agent is still the most cost-efficient. 

 



105 
 

Concerning applications foam one part geopolymers could also be used in the production of 

lightweight masonry units an issue that should merit future investigations.  Other issues that 

should be investigated include the assessment of alkali-silica reaction not only because of its 

alkali components but also because of the presence of calcium. The study of the pH conditions of 

these materials is needed because this is crucial to prevent the corrosion of steel reinforcement. 

The study of one part geopolymer mixtures based on other by products and industrial wastes with 

pozzolanic properties will also be needed to enhance the body of knowledge of these materials.  



 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 106 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

                                                           REFERENCES 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 107 
 

Abdollahnejad Z., Pacheco-Torgal F., Aguiar A., “Mix design, properties and cost analysis of fly ash-based 

geopolymer”, Construction and Building Materials, 2015; 8: 18-30. 

 

Abdollahnejad Z., Hlavacek P., Miraldo S., Pacheco-Torgal F., Aguiar J., “Compressive strength, 

microstructure and hydration products of hybrid alkaline cements”, Materials Research. 2014; 17:221-227. 

 

Allahverdi A., Najafi Kani E., “Construction wastes as raw materials for geopolymer binders”, International 

Journal of Civil Engeneering. 2009; 7:154–60. 

 

Allahverdi A., Škvára F., “Nitric acid attack on hardened paste of geopolymeric cements- Part 1”, Ceramics-

Silikaty, 2001; 45:81–8. 

 

Allahverdi A., Škvára F., “Sulfuric acid attack on hardened paste of geopolymer cements- Part 2”, Corrosion 

mechanism at mild and  relatively low concentrations  – Part 2. Ceramics-Silikaty, 2005; 45:1–4. 

 

Allahverdi A., Škvára F., “Sulfuric acid attack on hardened paste of geopolymer cements- Part 1”, Mechanism 

of corrosion at relatively high concentrations. Ceramics-Silikaty. 2005; 49:225–9. 

 

Al-Otaibi S., “Durability of concrete incorporating GGBS activated by water-glass”, Construction and Building 

Materials, 2007; 22(10): 2059–2067. 

 

Aperador W.,  de Gutiérrez R., Bastidas D., “Steel corrosion behavior in carbonated alkali-activated slag 

concrete”, Corrosion Science. 2009; 51:2027–33. 

 

Arshad M., MaaroufiA., “Relationship between Johnson–Mehl–Avrami and Šesták–Berggren models in the 

kinetics of crystallization in amorphous materials”, Journal of Non-Crystalline Solids. 2015; 413:53–58. 

 

Arellano Aguilar R.; Burciaga Díaz O., Escalante García J.I., “Lightweight concretes of activated metakaolin-

fly ash binders, with blast furnace slag aggregates”, Construction and Building Materials, 2010; 24: 1166–1175. 

 

ASTM C373-14a, Standard Test Method for Water Absorption, Bulk Density, Apparent Porosity, and Apparent 

Specific Gravity of Fired White ware Products, Ceramic Tiles, and Glass Tiles, ASTM International, West 

Conshohocken, PA, 2014. 

 

Bakharev T.,“Geopolymeric materials prepared using class F fly ash and elevated temperature curing”, Cement 

and Concrete Research, 2005; 3: 1224 – 1232. 

 

Bakharev T., Sanjayan JG., Cheng YB., “Resistance of alkali-activated slag to alkali–aggregate reaction”, 

Cement and Concrete Research, 2001; 31:331–4. 

 

Bakharev T., Sanjayan J G., Cheng Y B., “Resistance of alkali-activated slag concrete to alkali–aggregate 

reaction”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2000; 31(2): 331–334. 

 

Bakharev T., Sanjayan JG., Cheng YB., “Resistance of alkali-activated slag concreteto acid attack”, Cement  

and Concrete Research,  2003; 33:1607–11. 

 

Bakharev T., Sanjayan J.G., Cheng Y.B., “Sulfate attack on alkali-activated slagconcrete”, Cement and 

Concrete Research,  2002; 31:211–6. 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 108 
 

Boron J.B., Inorganic Chemistry Encyclopedia of Inorganic Chemistry, 1994,  Ed. R. Bruce King, John Wiley 

&amp;amp; Sons ISBN 0-471-93620-0 

 

Bernal S., de Gutiérrez R., Pedraza A., Provis J., Rodriguez E., Delvasto S., “Effect of binder content on the 

performance of alkali-activated slag concretes”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2011; 41:1–8. 

 

Bernal S., de Gutiérrez R., Pedraza A., Provis J., Rose V., “Effect of silicate modulus and metakaolin 

incorporation on the carbonation of alkali silicate-activated slags”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2010; 

40:898–907. 

 

Bortnovsky O., Dvorakova K., Roubicek P., Bousek J., Prudkova Z., Baxa P.Barbosa., Valeria F., MacKenzie, 

K. J. D., Thaumaturgo C., “Synthesis and characterization of materials based on inorganic polymers of alumina 

and silica: Sodium polysialate polymers”, International Journal of Inorganic Polymers, 2000; 3: 309-317. 

 

Bortnovsky O., Dvorakova K., Roubicek P., Pousek J., Prudkova Z., Baxa P., “Development, properties and 

production of geopolymers based on secondary raw materials”, In: Alkali activated materials – research, 

production and utilization 3rd conference, Prague, Czech Republic. 2007; 83–96. 

 

Buchwald A., Dombrowski K., Weil, M. “The influence of calcium content on the performance of 

geopolymeric binder especially the resistance against acids”, Proceedings of the World Geopolymer, 

Geopolymer Green Chemistry and Sustainable Development Solutions, 2005; 35-39. 

 

Buchwald A., Kaps Ch., Hohmann M., “Alkali-activated binders and pozzolan cemeent binders-compete binder 

reaction or two sides of the same story?”, In proceeding of 11 International conference on the Chemistry of 

cement, Durban, South Africa, 2003; 1238-1246.  

 

Brooks R., Bahadory M., Tovia F., Rostami H., “Properties of alkali-activated fly ash: high performance to 

lightweight”, International Journal of Sustainable Engineering,  2010; 3:211–8. 

 

BS EN 1015-18. Methods of test for mortar for masonry. Determination of water absorption coefficient due to 

capillary action of hardened mortar, 2002. 

 

Chen Y., Pu X., Yang C., Ding Q., “Alkali aggregate reaction in alkali slag cement mortars”, Wuhan University 

of Technology-Mater, Sci. Ed. 2002; 17(3): 60–62. 

 

Cyr, M., Pouhet R., “Resistance to alkali-aggregate reaction (AAR) of alkali-activated binders.In Handbook of 

Alkali-Activated Cements, Mortars and Concretes”, 397-422 (Eds) Pacheco-Torgal, F.; Labrincha, J.; Palomo, 

A.; Leonelli, C.; Chindaprasirt, P., WoddHead Publishing, 2014, Cambridge, UK. 

 

COM (2011) 885/2. Energy Roadmap 2050. 

 

COM 815 (2011) Progress report on the Europe 2020 strategy 

 

Damtoft J., Lukasik J., Herfort D., Sorrentino D., Gartner E., “Sustainable development and climate change 

initiatives”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2008; 38:115–27. 

 

Davidovits J., “Properties of geopolymers cements. In: Proc of the 1st international conference on alkaline 

cements and concretes”, Ukraine: Scientific Research Institute on Binders and Materials Kiev, 1994a; 131–49. 

 

 

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0471936200


                                                                                                                                                                                 109 
 

Davidovits J., High-alkali cements for 21st century concretes. In Concrete Technology, Past, Present and 

Future. Metha, P.K, American Concrete Institute, Farmington Hills, MI. Ed. 1994b; 383–397. 

 

Davidovits J., Geopolymers: inorganic polymeric new materials. J Therm Anal. 1991; 37:1633–56. 

 

Davidovits J, Comrie DC, Paterson JH, Ritcey DJ., “Geopolymeric concretes for environmental protection”, 

ACI ConcrInt, 1990; 12:30–40. 

 

Davidovits J., “Synthesis of new high temperature geo-polymers for reinforced plastics/composites”, SPE 

PACTEC 79 Society of Plastic Engineers, Brookfield Center, 1979; 151-154. 

 

Davies D., Oberholster RE., “Alkali–silica reaction products and their development”, Cement and Concrete 

Research, 1988; 18:621–35. 

 

Development, properties and production of geopolymers based on secondary raw materials. In: Alkali activated 

materials – research, production and utilization 3rd conference, Prague, Czech Republic. 2007; 83–96. 

 

Duxson P., Van Deventer J., In: Provis J., Van Deventer J., editor. Geopolymers, structure, processing, 

properties and applications. Cambridge, UK: Woodhead  Publishing Limited Abington Hall; 2009 [ISBN -13: 

978 1 84569 449 4]. 

 

Duxson P., Provis J., Lukey G., Van Deventer J., “The role of inorganic polymer technology in thedevelopment 

of green concrete”, Cement and Concrete Research. 2007; 37:1590–7. 

 

Dolezal J., Skvara F., Svoboda P., Sulc R., Kopecky L., Pavlasova S., Myskova L., Lucuk M.,  Dvoracek K., 

“Concrete based on fly ash geopolymers. In: Alkali activated materials – research”, production and utilization 

3rd conference, Prague, Czech Republic, 2007; 185–97. 

 

Diamond S.,  C/S mole ratio of CSH gel in a mature C3S paste as determined by EDXA. Cement and concrete 

Research 6, 1976; 413-416.  

 

Damjanovic A., Genshaw M.,  Bockris J., “Hydrogen peroxide formation in oxygen reduction at gold 

electrodes: II”, Alkaline Solution, J.Electroanalytical Chem. Interfacial Electrochem 15. 1967; 173–180. 

 

Diamond S.,  “C/S mole ratio of CSH gel in a mature C3S paste as determined by EDXA”, Cement and 

Concrete Research, 1976; 6: 413-416. 

 

ERMCO Statistics of the year 2010. Boulevard du Souverain 68, B-1170, Brussels, Belgium; 2011. 

 

Feng J., Zhang R., Gong L., Li Y., Cao W., Cheng X., “Development of porous fly ash based geopolymer with 

low thermal conductivity”, Materials and Design, 2015; 65: 529–533. 

Fernandez-Jimenez A., Palomo A., “Composition and microstructure of alkali activated fly ash binder: Effect of 

the activator”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2005a; 35: 1984-1992. 

 

Fernandez-Jimenez A., Palomo A., “Mid-infrared spectroscopic studies of alkali activated fly ash structure”, 

Microporous Mesoporous, 2005b; 86: 207–14. 

 

Fernandez-Jimenez A, Puertas F., “The alkali–silica reaction in alkali-activated slag mortars with reactive 

aggregate”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2002; 32: 1019–24. 



                                                                                                                                                                                 110 
 

 

Fernandez-Jimenez A., Palomo A., Puertas F., “Alkali activated slag mortars. Mechanical strength behaviour”,  

Cement and Concrete Research, 1999; 29: 1313–21. 

 

Fu Y., Cai L., Wu Y., “Freeze–thaw cycle test and damage mechanics models of alkali-activated slag concrete”,  

Construction and Building Materials, 2011; 25:3144–8. 

 

Flatt R., Roussel R., Cheeseman C.R., “Concrete: An eco-material that needs to be improved”, Journal of the 

European Ceramic Society, 2012;32: 2787-2798. 

 

Galiano Y., Pereira C., Vale J., “Stabilization/solidification of a municipal solid waste incineration residue 

using fly ash-based geopolymers”, Hazard Mater, 2011; 185: 373–81. 

 

García-Lodeiro I., Palomo A., Fernández-Jiménez A., “Alkali – aggregate reaction in activated fly ash 

systems”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2007; 3: 175–83. 

 

Garcia Lodeiro I., Fernandez-Jimenez A., Blanco  M.T., Palomo A., “FTIR study of sol-gel Synthesis of 

cementitious gels: CSH and NASH.”, Journal of Sol–Gel Science Technology, 2008;45: 63–72. 

 

Garcia Lodeiro I., Macphee D., Palomo A., Fernandez-Jimenez A., “Effect of alkalis on fresh CSH gels. FTIR 

analysis”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2009;39: 147–53.  

 

Lodeiro G., Fernandez-Jimenez A., Palomo A., “Alkali-activated based concrete”, ISBN 978-0-85709-424-7,In 

Eco-efficient concrete. Geopolymers, Ed. F.Pacheco-Torgal, S.Jalali, J. Labrincha &amp;amp; V.M. John, Woodhead 

Publishing Limited Abington Hall, Cambridge, UK. 2013; 439-487.  

 

Gartner E., “Industrially interesting approaches to low-CO2 cements”, Cement and Concrete Research 2004. 

;34:1489–98. 

 

Gifford P.M., Gillott J.E., “Alkali-silica reaction (ASR) and alkali-carbonate reaction (ACR) in activated blast 

furnace slag cement (ABFSC) concrete”, Cement and Concrete Research, 1996;26(1): 21–26. 

 

Glukhovsky V.D., “Slag-alkali concretes produced from fine-grained aggregate”, Kiev: VishchaShkolay; 1981.  

 

Gourley J.T., Johnson G.B., “Evelopments in geopolymer precast concrete”, In: Quentin S, editor. Proc of 

geopolymer 2005 world congress. France: Geopolymer Green Chemistry and Sustainable Development 

Solutions, 2005; 139–43. 

 

Goyal S., Kumar M., Sidhu D.S., Bhattacharjee B., “Resistance of mineral admixture concrete to acid attack”, 

Journal of Advanced Concrete Technology, 2009;7: 273–83. 

 

 

 

Gjørv O.E., “Performance and serviceability of concrete structures in the marine environment”, Proceedings, 

Odd E. Gjørv Symposium on Concrete for Marine Structures, Ed. por P.K. Mehta, CANMET/ACI, 1996; 259-

279.  

 

Habert G., de Lacaillerie J., Roussel N., “An environmental evaluation of geopolymer based concrete 

production: reviewing current research trends”, Journal of Cleaner Production, 2011; 11:1229–38. 



                                                                                                                                                                                 111 
 

 

Hermann E., Kunze C., Gatzweiler R., Kiebig G., Davidovits J., “Solidification of various radioactive residues 

by geopolymer with special emphasis on long term stability”, In: Proc of 1999 geopolymere conference; 1999; 

211–28. 

 

Hill C. N. A., “Vertical Empire: The History of the UK Rocket and Space Programme”, 1950–1971. Imperial 

College Press. 2001;[ISBN 978-1-86094-268-6]. 

 

IUPAC. Compendium of Chemical Terminology, 2nd ed. (the "Gold Book"). Compiled by A. D. McNaught 

and A. Wilkinson. Blackwell Scientific Publications, Oxford, 1997.  

 

IPCC, Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. 4th Assessment report. In:Parry ML, editor. Assessment of 

observed changes and responses in natural and managed systems. Climate change: impacts, adaptation and 

vulnerability. Contribution of working group II to the 4th assessment report of the Intergovernmental Panel on 

Climate Change. Cambridge Univ. Press; 2007; 79–131. 

 

Jiang W., Silsbee M.R., Breval E., Roy M.D., “Alkali-activated cementitious materials in chemically aggressive 

environments”, In: Young JF, editor. Mechanisms of chemically degradation of cement-based systems.E&amp;amp;FN 

SPON London. 1997; 289–96. 

 

Juenger M., Winnefeld F., Provis J., Ideker J., “Advances in alternative cementitious binders”, Cement and 

Concrete Research, 2011;41:1232–43. 

 

Keawpapasson P., Tippayasam C., Ruangjan S., Thavorniti P., Panyathanmaporn T., Fontaine A., Leonelli C., 

Chayasuwa D., “ Metakaolin-Based Porous Geopolymer with Aluminium Powder”, Key Engineering Materials. 

2014; 608: 132-138. 

 

Kolousek ,. Brus J., Urbanova M.,  Andertova J., Hulinsky V., Vorel J., “Preparation, structure and 

hydrothermal stability of alternative (sodium silicate-free) geopolymers”, Journal of Materials Science, 

2007;42:9267-9275. 

 

Kani E., Allahverdi A., Provis J., “Efflorescence control in geopolymer binders based on natural pozzolan”, 

Cement and Concrete Composites, 2011; 34: 25-33. 

 

Kolousek D., Brus J., Urbanova M., Andertova J., Hulinsky V., Vorel J., “Preparation, structure and 

hydrothermal stability of alternative (sodium silicate free) geopolymers”, Journal of Materials Science. 2007; 

42, 9267-9275. http://dx.doi. org/10.1007/s10853-007-1910-5 

 

Ke, X., Bernal S., Ye, N., Provis J., Yang J., “One-part geopolymers based on thermally treated red mud/NaOh 

blends”, Journal of American Ceramic Society, 2015; 98: 5-11. 

 

Kong D., Sanjayan J., Sagoe-Cretensil K., “Factors affecting the performance of metakaolin geopolymers 

exposed to elevated temperatures”, Journal of Matererial Science, 2008; 43:824–31.  

 

 

Krivenko P., Guziy S., “Fire resistant alkaline Portland cements”, In: Alkali activated materials – research, 

production and utilization 3rd conference, Prague, Czech Republic, 2007; 333–47. 

 

Khunthongkeaw K., Tangtermsirikul S., Leelawat T., A study on carbonation depth prediction for fly ash 

concrete, Journal of Construction and Building Materials. 1996; 20: 744–753. 

http://books.google.com/?id=AzoCJfTmRDsC
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/978-1-86094-268-6
http://www.scientific.net/KEM


                                                                                                                                                                                 112 
 

 

Laldji S., Tagnit-Hamou A., “Glass frit for concrete structures: a new alternative cementitious material”, 

Canadian Journal of Civil Engineering, 2007; 34:793–802.  

 

Lampris C., Lupo R., Cheeseman C., “Geopolymerization of silt generated from construction and demolition 

waste washing plants”, Waste Management, 2009; 29:368–73. 

 

Lancellotti I., Kamseu E., Michelazzi M., Barbieri B., Corradi A., Leonelli C., “Chemical stability of 

geopolymers containing municipal solid waste incinerator fly ash”, Waste managment, 2010; 30: 673-679.  

 

Li C., Sun H., Li L., “A review: The comparison between alkali-activated slag (Si+Ca) and metakaolin (Si+Al) 

cements”, Cement and Concrete Research. 2010; 40:1341-1349. http:// dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cemconres. 

2010.03.020 

 

Lloyd R., Provis J., Van Deventer S.J.S., “Pore solution composition and alkali diffusion in inorganic polymer 

cement”,  Cement and Concrete Research, 2010; 40: 1386–92. 

 

Lloyd R., “Accelerated ageing of geopolymers. In Provis and Van Deventer (Ed.) Geopolymers: Structure, 

processing, properties and industrial applications”, CRC Press, 2009; 139–166. 

 

LNEC E 463 - Concrete: Calculation of the chloride coefficient by migration test under nonstationary 

conditions (in Portuguese), LNEC, Lisboa; 2004. 

 

Macphee D.E., “Solubility and aging of calcium silicate hydrates in alkaline solutions at 25º C”, Journal of 

American Ceramic Society.1989; 72: 646-654. 

 

MacKenzie K.J. D., Brew D., Fletcher R., Nicholson C.L., Vagana R., Schmucker Masi G., Rickard W., 

Vickers l., Bignozzi M., Van Riessen A., “A comparison between different foaming methods for the synthesis 

of light weight geopolymers”, Ceramics International 40, 2014; 13891-13902. 

 

Material Safety Data Sheet, Solid sodium hydroxide, Link address: http://www.certified-lye.com/  access date 

(6/9/2015) 

 

McLellan B., Williams R., Lay J., Van Riessen A., Corder G., “Costs and carbon emissions for geopolymer 

pastes in comparison to ordinary Portland cement”, Journal of Cleaner Production, 2011; 19:1080–90. 

 

Metso J., “The Alkali Reaction of Alkali-activated Finnish Blast Furnace Slag. Silicates industriels”, 1982; 4-5: 

123–127. 

 

Miranda J.M., Fernandez-Jimenez A., Gonzalez A., Palomo A., “Corrosion resistance in activated fly ash 

mortars”, Cement and Concrete Research, 2005; 35:1210–7. 

 

Moore F., Diaz D., “Temperature impacts on economic growth warrant stringent mitigation policy”, Nature 

Climate Change, 2015; 5: 127-131. 

 

Toward M., “An understanding of the synthesis mechanisms of geopolymer materials”, Proceedings of the 

World Geopolymer, Geopolymer Green Chemistry and Sustainable Development Solutions. 2005; 41-44. 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 113 
 

Norman G., Earnshaw A., “Chemistry of the Elements” (2nd ed.), Butterworth-Heinemann, 1997. 

[ISBN 0080379419]. 

 

NP EN 450-1, Fly ash for concrete – Part 1: Definition, specifications and conformity criteria, 2005.  

 

NP EN 206-1: 2007, Concrete: Part 1. Specification, performance, production and conformity, 2007.  

 

OCDE Environmental sustainable building—challenges and policies, 2003; Paris. 

 

Patent US7691198 B2, Jan Stephanus Jakob Van Deventer, Dingwu Feng, Peter Duxson, “Dry mix cement 

composition, methods and systems involving same”, 2010.  

 

Pacheco-Torgal, F., Introduction. In Handbook of Alkali-Activated Cements, Mortars and Concretes, 1-16 

(Eds) Pacheco-Torgal, F.; Labrincha, J.; Palomo, A.; Leonelli, C.; Chindaprasirt, P., WoddHead Publishing, 

Cambridge, UK, 2014. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal, F., “Eco-efficient construction and building materials research under the EU Framework 

Programme Horizon 2020”, Construction and Building Materials. 2014; 51: 151-162. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal, F., Cabeza, L., Mistretta, M., Kaklauskas, A., Granqvist, G., “Nearly zero energy building 

refurbishment. A multidisciplinary approach”, Springer Verlag, London, UK, 2013. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F, Fucic A., Jalali S., “Toxicity of Building Materials”, Woodhead Publishing Limited 

Abington Hall, Cambridge, UK, 2012a 

 

Pacheco -Torgal, F., Abdollahnejad Z., Camões A.F., Jamshidi, M., Ding Y., “Durability of alkali-activated 

binders. A clear advantage over Portland cement or an unproven issue”, Construction and Building Materials. 

2012b; 30: 400-405. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal, F.,  Jalali, S., “Eco-efficient construction and building materials”, Springer Verlag, London, 

UK. 2011. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Gomes J., Jalali S., “Durability and environmental performance of alkali-activated tungsten 

mine waste mud mortars”, Journal of Materials in Civil Engineering, 2010; 22:897–904. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Gomes J., Jalali S., “Adhesion characterization of tungsten mine waste geopolymeric 

binder. Influence of OPC concrete substrate surface treatment”, Construction and Building Materials, 2008a; 

22:154–61. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Gomes J., Jalali S., “Alkali – activated binders: a review Part 2: About materials and binders 

manufacture”, Construction and Building Materials, 2008b; 22:1315–22. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Gomes J.P., Jalali S., “Properties of tungsten mine waste geopolymeric binder”, 

Construction and Building Materials, 2008c; 22:1201–11. 

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Gomes J.P., Jalali S., “Investigations on mix design of tungsten mine waste geopolymeric 

binders”, Construction and Building Materials, 2008d; 22:1939–49.  

 

Pacheco-Torgal F., Castro-Gomes J.P., Jalali S., “Investigations about the effect of aggregates on strength and 

microstructure of geopolymeric  mine waste mud binders”, Cement and Concrete Research,  2007; 37: 933-941.  

 

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterworth-Heinemann
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0080379419
http://www.google.com/search?tbo=p&amp;amp;tbm=pts&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;q=ininventor:%22Jan+Stephanus+Jakob+Van+Deventer%22
http://www.google.com/search?tbo=p&amp;amp;tbm=pts&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;q=ininventor:%22Dingwu+Feng%22
http://www.google.com/search?tbo=p&amp;amp;tbm=pts&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;q=ininventor:%22Peter+Duxson%22


                                                                                                                                                                                 114 
 

Palomo A., Blanco-Varela M.T., Granizo M.L., Puertas F., Vasquez T., Grutzeck M.W., “Chemical stability of 

cementitious materials based on metakaolin”,  Cement and Concrete Research, 1999a; 29:997–1004. 

 

Palomo A., Grutzek M.W., Blanco M.T., “Alkali-activated fly ashes. A cement for the future”, Cement and 

Concrete Research, 1999b; 29(8): 1323-1329. 

 

Peng M.X., Wan Z.H., Shen S.H., Xiao Q.G., “Synthesis, characterization and mechanisms of one-part 

geopolymeric cement by calcining low-quality kaolin with alkali”, Materials and Structures, 2014; 48: 699-708. 

 

Provis J.L., Van Deventer J.S.J., “Alkali-activated materials”, State-of-the-Art Report, RILEM TC 224-

AAM.Springer/RILEM, Berlin, 2014. 

Provis, J.L., “Geopolymers and other alkali activated materials: why, how, and what?”, Materials and 

Structures. 2014; 47: 11-25. 

Provis J, Van Deventer J., editor. “Geopolymers, structure, processing, properties and applications”, Woodhead 

Publishing Limited Abington Hall, Cambridge, UK; 2009: 194–210. 

 

Provis, J. “Immobilisation of toxic wastes in geopolymers. In Geopolymers, Structure, Processing, Properties 

and Applications”, ISBN -13: 978 1 84569 449 4, Ed. J. Provis&amp;amp; J. Van Deventer, Woodhead Publishing 

Limited Abington Hall, Cambridge, UK, 2009; 421-440. 

 

Provis, J.L., Muntingh, Y., Lloyd R.R., Xu H., Keyte L.M., Lorenzen L., Krivenko P.V., Van Deventer J.S.J. 

“Will geopolymers stand the test of time?”, Ceramic Engineering and Science Proceedings, 2008; 28: 235-248.  

 

Pawlasova S., Skavara F., “High-temperature properties of geopolymer materials. In: Alkali activated materials 

– research, production and utilization”, 3rd conference, Prague, Czech Republic, 2007; 523–4. 

 

Perná I, Hanzlicek T, Straka P, Steinerova M. “Utilization of fluidized bed ashes in thermal resistance 

applications. In: Alkali activated materials – research, production and utilization”, 3rd conference, Prague, 

Czech Republic, 2007; 527–37. 

 

Prud’homme E., Michaud P., Joussein E., Peyratout C., Smith A., Arrii-Clacens S., Clacen J.M., Rossignol S., 

“Silica fume as porogent agent in geo-materials at low temperature”, Journal of the European Ceramic Society, 

2010; 30: 1641-1648.  

 

Puertas F., “Cementos de escórias activadas alcalinamente”, Situacion actual y perpectivas de futuro. Materials 

Construction, 1995; 45:53–64. 

 

Puertas F., Palacios M., Gil-Maroto A., Vázquez T., “Alkali–aggregate behavior of alkali-activated slag 

mortars: effect of aggregate type”, Cement and Concrete Composition, 2009; 31:277–284.  

 

Beddoe R.E., Schmidt K., “Acid attack on concrete – effect of concrete composition. Part 1”, Centrum 

Baustoffe und Materialprüfung, 2009; 7:88–94. 

 

Regulation (EU) 305/2011- Construction Products Regulation 

 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 115 
 

Richardson I.G., “The nature of the hydration products in hardened cement pastes”, Cement and Concrete 

Composites. 2000; 22: 97-113.  

 

Roy D.M., Jiang W., Silsbee M.R., “Chloride diffusion in ordinary blended and alkali-activated cement pastes”, 

Cement and Concret Research, 2000; 30:1879–84. 

 

Saraswathy V., Muralidharan S., Thangavel K., Srinivasan S., “Influence of activated fly ash on corrosion 

resistance and strength of concrete”,  Cement and Concret Research. 2003; 25:673–80. 

 

Shi D., Shi L., Zhang J., Cheng J., “Preparation and properties of a novel non-flammable thermal insulation 

material”, Advanced Materials Research, 2012, 1504-1512 

 

Shi C., Fernández Jiménez A., Palomo A., “New cements for the 21st century: the pursuit of an alternative to 

Portland cement”, Cement and Concret Research. 2011; 41:750–63. 

 

Shi C., Krivenko P.V., Roy D.M., “Alkali-activated cements and concretes”, Taylor and Francis, Abingdon, 

2006.  

 

Shi C., Stegmann J.A., “Acid corrosion resistance of different cementingmaterials”, Cement and Concret 

Research,  2000; 30:803–8. 

 

Sims I., Brown B., “Concrete aggregates. In: Hewlett PC, editor. Lea´ s chemistry ofcement and concrete”, 4th 

ed. London; 1998: 903–89. 

 

Skvara F., Kopecky L., Smilauer V., Alberovska L., Vinsova L., “Aluminosilicate polymers – influence of 

elevated temperatures, efflorescence”, Ceramics – Silikaty, 2009; 53:276–82. 

 

Skvara F,, Kopecky L,, Smilauer V,, Alberovska L,, Bittner Z., “Material and structural characterization of 

alkali activated low-calcium brown coal fly ash”, Journal of Hazardous Material, 2008; 168:711–20. 

 

Slavik R., Bednarik V., Vondruska M., Nemec A., “Preparation of geopolymer from fluidized bed combustion 

bottom ash”,. Journal of Material Processing Technology, 2008; 200:265–70. 

 

Stern N., “Stern review on economics of climate change”, Cambridge University Press; 2006. 

 

Stanford Report Estimated social cost of climate change not accurate, Stanford scientists say. 

http://news.stanford.edu/news/2015/january/emissions-social-costs-011215.html 

 

Stanton T.E., “Influence of cement and aggregate on concrete expansion”, EngNews Record 1940; 1:50–61. 

 

Temuujin J., Rickard W., Lee M., Van Riessen A., “Preparation and thermal properties of fire resistant 

metakaolin-based geopolymer-type coatings”, Journal of Non-Cryst Solids,  2011; 357:1399–404. 

 

Temuujin J., Van Riessen A., Williams R., “Influence of calcium compounds on the mechanical properties of 

fly ash geopolymer pastes”, Journal of Hazard Material, 2009; 167:82–8. 

 

UN Energy for a sustainable future. The Secretary-General’s Advisory Group on energy and climate change, 

2010; New York 

 



                                                                                                                                                                                 116 
 

Van Deventer J.S.J., Provis J., Duxson P., “Technical and commercial progress in the adoption of geopolymer” 

cement. Miner Eng. 2012; 29: 89–104. 

 

Van Deventer J.S.J, Feng D., Duxson P., “Dry mix cement composition, methods and systems involving same”, 

US Patent 7691,198 B2; 2010. 

 

Vance e., Perera D., “Geopolymers for nuclear waste immobilisation. In Geopolymers, Structure,Processing, 

Properties and Applications”, Ed. J. Provis&amp;amp; J. Van Deventer, Woodhead Publishing Limited Abington Hall, 

Cambridge, UK. 2009; 401-420. 

 

Vinsova H., Jedinakova K., Gric L., Sussmilch J., “Immobilization of toxic contaminants into aluminosilicate 

matrixes. In: Proceedings of the 2007 – alkali activated materials – research, production and utilization 3rd 

conference. Prague: Czech Republic, 2007;735–6. 

 

Vijaya R., “Low-Calcium Fly-Ash-Based Geopolymer Concrete. Faculty of Engineering”, Curtin University of 

Technology, Perth, Australia, 2008; Chapter 26:1-19. 

 

Wang S., “Review of recent research on alkali-activated concrete in china”, Magazine of Concret Research 

1991; 5154:29–35. 

 

Weng L., Sagoe-Crentsil K., Brown, T., Song S.,  “Effects of aluminates on the formation of geopolymers”, 

Materials Science &amp;amp; Engineering, 2005;117: 163-168. 

 

Wang Q., Ding Z.Y., Li L., Zhang C.Y., Sui Z.T., “Effect of Alkali-Activateor on Alkali-Aggregate Reaction of 

Slag-Based Geopolymer.”, First International Conference on Advances in Chemically-activated Marterials, 

2010;131–138. 

 

WHO (2014) Urban population growth. Global health observatory. 

http://www.who.int/gho/urban_health/situation_trends/urban_population_growth_text/en/ 

 

Wood J.G., Johnson R.A., “The appraisal and maintenance of structures with akali–silica reaction”, Journal of 

Structural Engineering, 1993; 71(2). 

 

Hwai-Chung W., Sun P., “New building materials from fly ash-based lightweight inorganic polymer”, 

Construction and Building Materials, 2005; 21: 211-217. 

 

Xu H., Van Deventer S.J., “The geopolymerisation of alumino-silicate minerals”, International Journal of 

Mineral Processing, 2000; 59: 247-266.  

 

Xu H., “The geopolymerisation of alumino-silicate minerals”, PhD Thesis, University of Melbourne. 2002. 

 

Yang K.-H., Lee K.-H., “Tests on alkali-activated slag foamed concrete with various water-binder ratios and 

substitution levels of fly ash”, Building Construction and Planning Research: 1, 8–14. 

 

Yang, K.H., Lee J.K., Song M.H., “Properties and sustainability of alkali-activated slag foamed concrete”, 

Journal of Cleaner Production, 2014; 68: 226-233. 

 

http://www.who.int/gho/urban_health/situation_trends/urban_population_growth_text/en/
http://www.scopus.com.scopeesprx.elsevier.com/record/display.url?eid=2-s2.0-0033740501&amp;amp;origin=resultslist&amp;amp;sort=plf-f&amp;amp;cite=2-s2.0-0033740501&amp;amp;src=s&amp;amp;imp=t&amp;amp;sid=rFXANjrCZRQsFS6B-iqgIQ9%3a100&amp;amp;sot=cite&amp;amp;sdt=a&amp;amp;sl=0


                                                                                                                                                                                 117 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 

Yip C.K., Van Deventer S.J.S., “Microanalysis of calcium silicate hydrate gel formed within a geopolymeric 

binder”, Journal of Materials Science 38, 2003; 3851-3860. 

 

Yip C.K., Lukey G.C., Van Deventer S.J.S., “The coexistence of geopolymeric gel and calcium silicate hydrate 

gel at the early stage of alkaline activation’, Cement and Concrete Research,  2005;35: 1688-1697. 

 

Yunsheng Z., Wei S.,  “Fly ash based geopolymer concrete”, Indian Concrete Journal, 2006; 80:20–4. 

 

Zhang, Z., Provis J., Reid A., Wang H., “Geopolymer foam concrete: An emerging material for sustainable 

construction”, Construction and Building Materials, 2014;56: 113-127. 

 

Zhang L., Ahmari S., Zhang J., “Synthesis and characterization of fly ash modified mine tailings-based 

geopolymers”, Construction and Building Materials, 2011; 25:3773–81. 

 

Zhang M., Wruck B.A., Graeme – Barber E., Salje M., Carpenter, “Phonon-spectroscopy on alkali-feldspar: 

phase transitions and solid solutions”, American Mineralogist 81; 1996: 92-104.   

 

Zhao R., Sanjayan J.G., “Geopolymer and Portland cement concretes in simulated fire”, Magazine Concrete 

Research, 2011; 63(3):163–73. 

 

Zheng D., Van Deventer J.S.J., Duxson P., “The dry mix cement composition, methods and systems involving 

same”, International Patent WO 2007/109862 A1, 2007.  

 

 


	Capa_Esc_Engenharia
	int
	Thesis-final



</field>
	</doc>
</add>