<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<add>
	<doc>
		<field name="docid">BR-TU.08920</field>
		<field name="filename">13813_Paula_Eneidade_D.pdf</field>
		<field name="filetype">PDF</field>
		<field name="text">f SECRETARIA ' DE PÓS-GRADUAÇÃO &amp;lt;IB. j
"Isolamento e caracterização de membranas eritrocitárias resistentes a detergentes"
Orientadora: Profa. Dra. Eneida de Paula
Campinas, 2009
UNIVERSIDADE ESTADUAL DE CAMPINAS
Cleyton Crepaldi Domingues
INSTITUTO DE BIOLOGIA
Tese apresentada ao Instituto de Biologia para obtenção do Título de Doutor em Biologia Funcional e Molecular, na área de Bioquímica.	-
Este exemplar corresponde à redação finai da tese defendida pelo(a) candidato (a)	
	. a - ..■- y- - i
e aprovac	aúpela Comissão Julgadora.
FICHA CATALOGRAFICA ELABORADA PELA BIBLIOTECA DO INSTITUTO DE BIOLOGIA - UNICAMP
Domingues, Cleyton Crepaldi
D713i	Isolamento e caracterização de membranas eritrocitárias
resistentes a detergentes / Cleyton Crepaldi Domingues. -Campinas, SP: [s.n.], 2009.
Orientadora: Eneida de Paula.
Tese (doutorado) - Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Instituto de Biologia.
1. Eritrócitos. 2. Detergentes. 3. Membranas (Biologia). 4. Lipid rafts. 5. Flotilina. I. Paula, Eneida de. II. Universidade Estadual de Campinas. Instituto de Biologia. III. Título.
(scs/ib)
Título em inglês: Isolation and characterization of detergent-reistant membranes from erythrocytes.
Palavras-chave em inglês: Erythrocytes; Detergent; Membranes (Biology); Lipid rafts; Flotillin. Área de concentração: Bioquímica.
Titulação: Doutorem Biologia Funcional e Molecular.
Banca examinadora: Eneida de Paula, Pietro Ciancaglini, Anita Hilda Straus Takahashi, Karin do Amaral Riske, Monica Andréa Pickholz.
Data da defesa: 23/01/2009.
Programa de Pós-Graduação: Biologia Funcional e Molecular.
isslnatuq.
Assinati
Campinas, 23 de Janeiro de 2009
BANCA EXAMINADORA
Profa. Dra. Eneida de Paula (Orientadora)
Prof. Dr. Pietro Ciancaglini
Profa. Dra. Anita Hilda Straus Takahashi
Profa. Dra. Karin do Amaral Riske
Profa. Dra. Monica Andrea Pickholz
Prof. Dr. Leonardo Fernandes Fraceto
Profa. Dra. Fernanda Ramos Gadelha
Profa. Dra. Denise Vaz de Macedo
Assinatura
Assinatura
Assinatura
Assinatura
Assinatura
AGRADECIMENTOS
Ao meu Deus que sempre me iluminou.
À minha família que sempre me apoiou e esteve sempre ao meu lado, mesmo nos momentos em que eu estava distante fisicamente. Mãe (Odete) a você minha eterna gratidão... te amo. Meire e Camila (minhas irmãs queridas), Matheus (meu sobrinho sapeca) e Marcelo (cunhado) a vocês meu carinho especial.
À Profa. Dra. Eneida de Paula pela orientação, profissionalismo e amizade ao longo desses anos. Obrigado pela confiança em meu trabalho e por aceitar esse desafio.
Ao Prof. Dr. Giampaolo Minetti (Itália) pela orientação, colaboração, dedicação e discussões. Obrigado por me deixar fazer parte da sua equipe.
À Dra. Annarita Ciana (Itália) por todo seu conhecimento e experiência compartilhados e pelos nossos momentos de "brainstorms".
Às Profas Dra. Eneida de Paula e Dra. Sônia V. P. Malheiros pelos momentos didáticos e oportunidades na área de ensino.
À grande família Biomembranas. Nesse laboratório aprendi com cada um de vocês muito mais do que ciência. Durante esses anos tive o privilégio de conviver com pessoas maravilhosas que passaram ou ainda estão no grupo: Allan, Ana Cláudia, Angélica, Beth, Bispo, Bruna, Camila, Carol, Cintia, Dani (Murango), Dani (Japipa), Dona Cidinha, Eneida, Elisa, Fernanda, Gi Tófoli, Giovana, Hayda, Jú, Léo Fraceto, Léo (Vinícius), Luciana, Marcio, Maribel, Monica, Natalie, Nilce, Nonis, Paulinho (Pô), Raquel, Roberta, Sheila, Simone, Sônia, Thais.
Ao meu amigo Bispo (Claudio) especialmente por esse último ano de convivência diária (casa e trabalho). Amigo, cozinheiro, "expert" em informática, parceiro de basquete e tênis... Valeu Bispão!
À Cintia pela nossa cumplicidade no trabalho e pela convivência e atividades dentro e fora da UNICAMP.
À minha amiga Muranguese (agora Profa. Dra. Daniele) especialmente pelos bons momentos que vivemos na Itália. Quantos passeios e quantas histórias vivemos em 2007... Momentos inesquecíveis.
Aos meus amigos Paulinho Baldasso e Juliana Mattoso pelo apoio técnico, piadas, desabafos, e muitos bandejões.
Às secretárias Marina e Andréia pelo profissionalismo e amizade.
Ao Giovanni, pela amizade, companheirismo, respeito e incentivo. Ti ringrazio tantissimo!
Aos professores, alunos e técnicos dos laboratórios do departamento de Bioquímica. Com certeza já precisei da ajuda de todos vocês.
Aos professores, alunos e funcionários do departamento de Bioquímica de Pavia. Em especial meus agradecimentos a Ilária, Annarita, Alessandra, Christian, Isa, Gianni, Mari, Alessandro, Stefano, Lina e Paolo que fizeram das duras horas de trabalhos momentos prazerosos.
Aos amigos que conquistei na Itália fora do mundo acadêmico: Gio, Manu, Panda, Ila, Mauro, Giaggia, Chiara Bendi, Paola, Chiara Piovella, Silvia, Giulio, Stefi, Dome, Balda, Francesca, Marco, Gigi, Marcello, Filippo, Iada, Andrea... Muitos jogos, passeios, festas, e claro muito vinho e pizza. Grazie a tutti!
Rodrigo, Pedro e Paulo, obrigado por tudo, sei que sempre posso contar com vocês (e vice-versa).
Aos meus amigos de Salto, Campinas e região que sempre torceram por mim e que me traziam para o "mundo real" (churrasquinho, cinema, balada, etc.). São tantos amigos que se eu fosse citar o nome de todos daria uma segunda tese.
Ao CNPq e CAPES por todo apoio financeiro.
Esta tese está de acordo com a deliberação da Comissão Central de Pós-Graduação (CCPG) da Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP) n° 0001/98, que regulamenta o formato alternativo para dissertação e tese, permitindo a inserção de artigos científicos de autoria ou co-autoria do candidato.
“Não se mede o estudo pelo número de páginas lidas numa noite ou pela quantidade de livros lidos num semestre. Estudar não é um ato de consumir idéias, mas de criá-las e recriá-las."
Paulo Freire
INDICE
LISTA DE ABREVIATURAS...............................................................1
Resumo............................................................................2
ABSTRACT............................................................................4
INTRODUÇÃO..........................................................................6
Membranas biológicas..............................................................6
Lipid rafts e membranas resistentes a detergentes.................................9
Membrana eritrocitária...........................................................19
DRMs de eritrócitos..............................................................28
Solubilização e resistência de membranas a detergentes...........................33
OBJETIVOS..........................................................................40
RESULTADOS E DISCUSSÃO ............................................................42
Parte 1- artigo: Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents.43
Parte 2- DRMs de eritrócitos obtidas com uso de Triton X-100 e C12E8 .............51
Artigo 1: Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8...51
Artigo 2: Detergent-resistant membranes from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes using
Triton X-100 and C12E8...........................................................62
Parte 3: Variações metodológicas no preparo de DRMs..............................87
Efeito de diferentes detergentes no isolamento de DRMs..........................87
Efeito da temperatura no isolamento de DRMs.....................................89
Efeito de anestésicos locais em DRMs............................................93
CONSIDERAÇÕES FINAIS...............................................................97
CONCLUSÕES........................................................................100
REFERÊNCIAS BIBLIOGRÁFICAS........................................................103
PRODUÇÕES CIENTÍFICAS.............................................................117
LISTA DE ABREVIATURAS
DRMs - detergent-resistant membranes; membranas resistentes a detergentes
C12E8 - octaetilenoglicol mono lauril éter
Triton X-100 - terc-octilfenoxi polietoxietanol
ASB-14 - tetradecanoil amidopropil dimetilamônio propanosulfonato
ASB-16 - hexadecanoil amidopropil dimetilamônio propanosulfonato
CHAPS - 3-[(3-colamidopropil)-dimetilamônio]-1-propanosulfonato
lo - fase líquido ordenada
ld - fase líquido desordenada
EDTA - ácido etilenodiamino tetracético
TNE - tris/HCl, NaCl, EDTA
TERF - transferência de energia de ressonância de fluorescência
MFA - microscopia de força atômica
RPE - ressonância paramagnética eletrônica
RMN - ressonância magnética nuclear
CMC - concentração micelar crítica
Re - razão molar efetiva detergente/lipídio
Resat - razão molar efetiva detergente/lipídio para início da solubilização
ResQl - razão molar efetiva detergente/lipídio para completa solubilização
SDS-PAGE - sodium dodecyl sulfate-poliacrylamide gel electrophoresis; eletroforese em gel de poliacrilamida-dodecil sulfato de sódio
RESUMO
Detergentes constituem uma das ferramentas mais importantes no estudo de membranas biológicas. A eficiência de um detergente em solubilizar biomembranas e suas proteínas depende de suas propriedades físico-químicas e a solubilização parcial pode resultar em membranas resistentes a detergentes (DRMs). A resistência a detergentes dessas frações membranares constituídas principalmente de colesterol, esfingolipídios e proteínas específicas foi analisada nesse trabalho, usando membranas de eritrócitos humanos. Embora não haja evidências experimentais suficientes pra afirmar que DRMs correspondam aos microdomínios naturais existentes em biomembranas, conhecidos como lipid rafts e que também são enriquecidos em colesterol e esfingolipídios, DRMs são bons modelos para o estudo daqueles. A obtenção de DRMs com uso do detergente octaetilenoglicol mono lauril éter (C12E8) a baixa temperatura (4oC) é descrita pela primeira vez. Os detergentes zwiteriônicos ASB-14, ASB-16 e CHAPS também foram testados, mas falharam no isolamento de DRMs com baixa densidade. DRMs obtidas com C12E8 e com Triton X-100 apresentaram um aumento da razão colesterol/proteína de pelo menos três vezes em relação à membrana original. A proteína flotilina-2, considerada um marcador de lipid rafts, foi detectada em DRMs isoladas com Triton X-100 e em DRMs com C12E8 isoladas a partir de células depletadas de colesterol. Proteínas do citoesqueleto também foram encontradas em DRMs, exceto quando as células foram previamente depletadas de colesterol. Resultados de ressonância paramagnética eletrônica com uso de marcadores de spin do tipo doxil-estearato revelaram maior grau de organização das cadeias acila dos lipídios de DRMs em relação à membrana original, independentemente do detergente utilizado. Nossos resultados também mostraram que DRMs de eritrócitos podem ser também obtidos na temperatura fisiológica (37°C) com
o mesmo conteúdo de colesterol presente em DRMs isoladas a 4°C. A necessidade do uso de carbonato de sódio no protocolo para obtenção de DRMs sugere fortemente a existência de uma associação eletrostática entre DRMs e o citoesqueleto eritrocitário.
ABSTRACT
Detergents constitute an important tool for the study of cell membranes. The solubilization efficiency of a specific detergent depends upon its physicochemical properties so that detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) can be obtained as a result of the partial solubilization of biological membranes. In this study DRMs which are structures enriched in cholesterol, sphingolipids and specific proteins, were isolated and characterized from human erythrocyte membranes. Although there are no evidences to support that DRMs correspond to the natural existing microdomains of natural membranes, known as lipid rafts which are also cholesterol and sphingolipid-enriched structures, DRMs are good models for the study of rafts. DRMs from erythrocytes obtained with 8 polyoxyethylene lauryl ether (C12E8) at low temperature (4oC) are described here for the first time. The zwitterionic detergents ASB-14, ASB-16 and CHAPS failed to isolate these low buoyant density fractions. Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs presented a cholesterol/protein mass ratio 3 times higher than in the whole membrane. Flotillin-2, a marker of lipid rafts, was confined within the DRM fractions obtained with Triton X-100 and it was partially associated with C12E8 DRMs when erythrocyte cells were previously cholesterol-depleted. Association of membrane-skeleton proteins with DRMs was also observed, except when DRMs were prepared from cholesterol-depleted cells. Results of electron paramagnetic resonance through the use of doxyl stearate spin labels revealed that DRMs are highly ordered structures in respect to the original membrane and that their acyl chain packing is not different if prepared with either Triton X-100 or C12E8. We have also found that DRMs from erythrocytes can be isolated at physiological temperature (37°C), presenting the same cholesterol content as in DRMs prepared at 4°C. The fact that we were only able to prepare DRMs when sodium carbonate was used strongly
suggests the existence of an electrostatic association between DRMs and the membrane-skeleton.
INTRODUÇÃO
Membranas biológicas
As membranas biológicas são essenciais para a vida. Elas definem os limites celulares, dividem as células em compartimentos discretos, organizam seqüências de reações complexas e atuam na recepção de sinais e nas transformações de energia. Segundo Warren (1987) a formação da membrana foi um pré-requisito para a evolução da vida, preservando a integridade da célula e protegendo-a das forças de ruptura, físicas ou químicas do ambiente.
Membranas biológicas são estruturas fluidas e dinâmicas constituídas de proteínas e lipídios orientados (Berg et al., 2007), em combinações variáveis que são específicas para cada espécie, tipo celular e organela (Nelson &amp;amp; Cox, 2006). As membranas possuem ainda uma porção de carboidratos, que aparecem em menor quantidade em relação aos outros componentes e são encontrados na forma de glicoproteínas e glicolipídios. Os componentes lipídicos das membranas formam a barreira de permeabilidade e suas proteínas agem como um sistema de bombas e canais que conferem à membrana a permeabilidade seletiva (Berg et al., 2007). A passagem da água pela membrana, por exemplo, é facilitada por uma família de proteínas conhecida como aquaporinas. Mais de dez aquaporinas diferentes de mamíferos já foram identificadas, sendo a aquaporina-1 de eritrócitos humanos a primeira a ser descoberta e provavelmente a mais estudada (Benga, 2006).
Em 1972, Singer &amp;amp; Nicolson propuseram o modelo do "mosaico fluido" para explicar a estrutura da membrana plasmática. Segundo esse modelo, aceito até os dias de hoje, as moléculas protéicas encontram-se ancoradas
ou inseridas entre os lipídios que estão distribuídos em bicamadas, constituindo um arranjo extremamente dinâmico (Singer e Nicolson, 1972; Singer, 2004). Várias destas proteínas têm função de transporte enquanto outras atuam como receptores necessários ao funcionamento da célula. Algumas proteínas associadas à membrana pelo lado citoplasmático formam uma malha rígida, o citoesqueleto, que ajuda a manter a integridade da célula. A remoção das proteínas integrais ou intrínsecas, que estão fortemente associadas com a membrana, só ocorre por agentes capazes de romper interações hidrofóbicas entre proteínas e lipídios, como os detergentes, solventes orgânicos ou outros agentes desnaturantes. Já as proteínas periféricas ou extrínsecas por estarem associadas com a membrana através de interações eletrostáticas ou ligações de hidrogênio podem ser removidas por tratamentos moderados como alterações no pH, na força iônica e ainda pela adição de uréia ou carbonato (Santos &amp;amp; Ciancaglini, 2000; Yeagle, 2005). Singer (2004) revê o modelo proposto em 1972 (Singer &amp;amp; Nicolson, 1972) e demonstra sua acertividade, em relação às proteínas de membrana.
Os glicerofosfolipídios e esfingolipídios são os principais componentes lipídicos das biomembranas, além do colesterol que é uma das moléculas mais importantes na organização das membranas como uma barreira física. Esses lipídios expõem seus grupos polares ao meio aquoso, enquanto as cadeias de ácidos graxos e o núcleo da molécula do colesterol estão orientados para o interior de cada uma das monocamadas lipídicas, formando uma lamela de caráter hidrofóbico. Os lipídios e a maioria das proteínas são livres para se difundirem lateralmente dentro da membrana enquanto a difusão transversal (flip-flop) é menos freqüente nos lipídios e inexistente nas proteínas. O comprimento e o grau de insaturações dos ácidos graxos são os principais determinantes da fluidez ou compactação da
bicamada lipídica, seguidos pelo teor de colesterol, interações entre as cabeças polares de lipídios e associação com proteínas específicas (Gennis, 1989; Yeagle, 2005).
Os lipídios que constituem as membranas apresentam uma grande variedade de cadeias acila e grupos polares, em várias combinações. Além disso, a composição diferencial de lipídios e proteínas nas monocamadas interna e externa intensifica a assimetria das membranas, que é fundamental para que as mesmas exerçam seus papéis estruturais e funcionais.
Estima-se a presença de 500 a 1000 lipídios diferentes numa simples membrana biológica. Essa imensa variedade lipídica seria desnecessária se as membranas atuassem apenas como uma barreira hidrofóbica, mas se justifica ao considerarmos as recentes atribuições propostas para esses lipídios, como o envolvimento na transdução de sinal e em interações específicas célula-célula. Mas ainda pouco se sabe sobre os lipídios que interagem com elementos do citoesqueleto ou com enzimas e proteínas que ativamente translocam-se entre o citosol e a membrana plasmática (Yavin &amp;amp; Brand, 2005).
Segundo Edidin (2003), evidências acumuladas nas últimas décadas requerem uma reavaliação do clássico modelo do "mosaico fluido" de membranas (Singer &amp;amp; Nicolson, 1972), de modo que haja uma completa compreensão da dinâmica membranar. As membranas não deveriam ser apenas consideradas como barreiras seletivas contendo proteínas integrais, mas sim uma dispersão contínua de grupos funcionais formados por lipídios e proteínas que atuam conjuntamente num processo de sinalização celular (Edidin 2003; Yavin &amp;amp; Brand, 2005). Alterações na composição lipídica bem como da sua assimetria podem resultar em falhas na associação entre lipídios e proteínas, causando diversas conseqüências celulares e patologias severas.
Muitos desses problemas podem ser originados por mudanças na regulação da expressão gênica devido a um desequilíbrio na dieta lipídica; já que grande parte dos lipídios que compõem as membranas provém da dieta (Price et al., 2000; Yavin &amp;amp; Brand, 2005).
Lipid rafts e membranas resistentes a detergentes
Devido à mistura de lipídios e também ao fato de a maioria dos fosfolipídios de membrana apresentar baixa temperatura de transição de fases, as membranas biológicas se encontram principalmente na fase líquido desordenada (ld), onde as cadeias acila em conformação trans-gauche movimentam-se com alto coeficiente de difusão e alta amplitude de rotação ao redor destas ligações, conferindo caráter fluido e desordenado (Brown &amp;amp; London, 1998). No entanto, as membranas também apresentam microdomínios denominados lipid rafts ou simplesmente rafts que se encontram na fase líquido ordenada (lo), que é caracterizada por um alto grau de ordem das cadeias acila saturadas (Brown &amp;amp; London, 1998). Estes microdomínios são constituídos fundamentalmente por esfingolipídios, colesterol e proteínas específicas (Simons &amp;amp; Ikonen, 1997; Brown &amp;amp; London, 1998; Simons &amp;amp; Vaz, 2004; Pike, 2004; Lichtenberg et al., 2005).
A tendência de certos lipídios (particularmente esfingolipídios) em formar domínios em bicamadas de fosfatidilcolina foi postulado na década de 80 (Thompson &amp;amp; Tillack, 1985). Desde então, muitos estudos têm sido feitos para caracterizar esses domínios e tentar relacioná-los com os rafts de membranas biológicas. Embora o colesterol não seja essencial para formação de domínios de esfingolipídios (Brown, 1998), a fase lo é dependente de esterol. Além disso, os domínios na fase lo possuem características intermediárias entre as
fases gel (fase em que os lipídios estão altamente condensados e essencialmente com restrição de movimentos) e ld, ou seja, ao mesmo tempo em que as cadeias acila apresentam um alto grau de empacotamento na fase lo, as moléculas dos lipídios apresentam, individualmente, um alto grau de difusão lateral pela bicamada como ocorre na fase ld (Veatch &amp;amp; Keller, 2005; Brown, 2006). Em membranas modelo, domínios na fase lo podem coexistir com domínios na fase ld e com domínios na fase gel (onde os lipídios apresentam as cadeias acila extremamente ordenadas e são praticamente estáticos) (Brown, 2006). Assim, a hipótese dos rafts propõe a formação de domínios na fase lo em membranas biológicas ricas em colesterol (particularmente na membrana plasmática) coexistindo com domínios de membrana na fase ld (figura 1) (Lagerholm et al., 2005; Brown, 2006). Embora o colesterol e fosfolipídios saturados, como a esfingomielina, sejam cruciais para a formação de domínios na fase lo e, portanto, para formação e estabilidade de rafts, ainda não está elucidada a natureza de interação física entre esses lipídios. Resultados de modelagem computacional revelaram que numa mistura ternária composta de colesterol, 1,2-dioleilfosfatidilcolina e esfingomielina, ocorre uma localização preferencial do colesterol na interface entre os domínios formados pelos outros dois lipídios (Pandit et al., 2004).
Entre as proteínas que se associam aos rafts destacam-se as proteínas ancoradas ao glicosilfosfatidilinositol, estomatinas, flotilinas e aquaporina-1 (Schnitzer &amp;amp; Oh, 1996; Pike, 2004, Luna et al., 2005). Essas e outras proteínas apresentam, portanto, alta afinidade a ambientes organizados como os domínios na fase lo da membrana.
Estudos demonstraram que os rafts estão envolvidos no processo de tráfego intracelular de proteínas e lipídios, endocitose e que atuam principalmente na transdução de sinal (Simons &amp;amp; Ikonen, 1997; Brown &amp;amp; London, 1998; Ikonen, 2001, Samuel et al., 2001, Pike, 2004, 2006). Além
disso, nos últimos anos, o envolvimento de rafts com processos desencadeados por diversos patógenos, bactérias, príons, vírus e parasitas (Scheiffele et al., 1997; Nguyen &amp;amp; Hildreth, 2000; van der Goot &amp;amp; Harder, 2001; Simons &amp;amp; Ehehalt, 2002; Murphy et al., 2007) tem sido postulado.
colesterol
AB	C
Figura 1 - Modelo de distribuição de proteínas transmembranares entre as fases líquido ordenada (lo) e líquido desordenada (ld) da membrana. Evidências experimentais sugerem que diferentemente do que se postula, proteínas que possuem longos domínios transmembranares não se inserem em rafts. Domínios protéicos transmembranares curtos (B) ou longos (C) se localizam preferencialmente na fase líquido desordenada. Proteínas palmitoiladas (A) se localizam nas bordas dos rafts com o domínio transmembranar voltado para os lipídios da fase líquido desordenada, enquanto as cadeias de palmitato posicionam-se adjacentes aos domínios na fase líquido ordenada (adaptado de Brown, 2006).
Estudos com membranas modelo em que as fases ld e lo coexistem, demonstraram a insolubilidade a detergentes com moderado poder de solubilização (como, por exemplo, o não iônico Triton X-100) de domínios na fase lo. Esta resistência à solubilização seria dada pelo alto grau de empacotamento das cadeias acila presentes na fase lo. Domínios insolúveis obtidos desta forma - por ação de detergentes e a baixa temperatura - são
chamados de membranas resistentes a detergente (Brown &amp;amp; London, 1998; Pike, 2004; Brown, 2007). Por uma questão de praticidade e devido ao uso extensivo na literatura, o termo DRMs (detergent-resistant membranes) será utilizado aqui.
Há duas décadas DRMs também têm sido obtidas a partir de membranas biológicas. Assim como os rafts, DRMs são estruturas enriquecidas em esfingolipídios e colesterol, além de proteínas com afinidade a ambientes organizados (Brown &amp;amp; Rose, 1992). Assim, a presença dessas moléculas em DRMs sugere que domínios na fase lo e ld podem coexistir também em membranas biológicas, o que permitiria definir operacionalmente os DRMs como microdomínios (rafts) obtidos em condições controladas (a baixa temperatura). O isolamento de DRMs se tornou um método bastante utilizado para estudo de rafts, particularmente para determinação da sua composição protéica (Brown, 2007).
A metodologia de isolamento de DRMs consiste no tratamento de células ou membranas biológicas isoladas com Triton X-100, a baixa temperatura (4°C), seguido por flotação dos complexos lipoprotéicos insolúveis em gradiente de sacarose. Essas frações, por apresentarem baixa densidade (aproximadamente 1,09-1,12 g/mL), são encontradas em regiões do gradiente que correspondem a 10-30% (m/v) de sacarose (Brown &amp;amp; Rose, 1992; Hope &amp;amp; Pike, 1996). DRMs são geralmente depletadas de proteínas transmembranares que apresentam alfa-hélices hidrofóbicas e são enriquecidas de proteínas organizadoras de rafts, que se associam ao colesterol e proteínas modificadas por ácidos graxos de cadeias longas (ex. ácido mirístico e ácido palmítico) (Luna et al., 2005).
Entre as proteínas comumente presentes em DRMs destacam-se as proteínas aciladas, proteínas ancoradas ao glicosilfosfatidilinositol, alguns
receptores transmembranares e canais (Benting et al., 1999; Moffett et al., 2000; Ridyard &amp;amp; Robbins, 2003). Portanto, flotilinas que são proteínas miristoiladas e multiplamente palmitoiladas (Neumann-Giesen et al., 2004) são freqüentemente encontradas em DRMs de diferentes membranas plasmáticas (Ciana et al., 2005; Delaunay et al., 2007). Já entre as proteínas transmembranares comumente excluídas estão algumas tirosina fosfatases (Janes et al., 1999; Young et al., 2005).
Estudos com membranas modelo demonstraram que a detecção de domínios na fase lo após tratamento de determinadas misturas de lipídios ricas em colesterol com Triton X-100 somente é possível quando essas misturas já apresentavam domínios na fase lo, antes da ação do detergente (Ahmed et al., 1997). Já o tratamento de bicamadas lipídicas compostas de fosfolipídios, colesterol e esfingomielina, contendo domínios nas fases ld e lo, com Triton X-100 resultou na solubilização seletiva dos domínios na fase ld e relativa preservação dos domínios na fase lo (Dietrich et al., 2001). Outros estudos revelaram ainda que a separação de fase lo e ld pode ocorrer a 37°C, em misturas lipídicas com níveis fisiológicos dos tipos de lipídios que formam essas fases (colesterol, fosfolipídios insaturados e esfingolipídios), de modo que a separação de fases seria plausível também em membranas biológicas (Silvius, 2003). Juntamente, esses resultados sugerem que DRMs isoladas de membranas biológicas poderiam, também, ser formados a partir de domínios (rafts) pré-existentes (Brown, 2006). Além disso, a presença de proteínas em DRMs sugere que as mesmas encontram-se concentradas em microdomínios naturais das membranas biológicas conferindo um importante papel funcional aos rafts (Brown, 2006).
Baseado na importância que tem o colesterol na formação da fase lo e na estabilidade de proteínas ali contidas, experimentos têm sido realizados com membranas depletadas de colesterol, como meio de desorganizar
estruturas na fase lo presentes em rafts de membranas biológicas (Hancock,
2006). Mudanças no conteúdo de colesterol podem resultar em alterações no ambiente físico dos rafts remanescentes e, conseqüentemente, nos tipos de lipídios que podem particionar nesses domínios (Pike, 2004).
Embora muitos trabalhos utilizem a detecção de proteínas específicas em frações de DRMs para avaliar sua afinidade por rafts de membranas biológicas, ainda há muitas controvérsias sobre a relação existente entre rafts e DRMs. Umas das principais críticas apontadas é o fato de que a extração com detergente pode induzir, sob condições específicas, a separação de fase e levar à formação de domínios na fase lo em membranas modelo que inicialmente se apresentavam como uma fase homogênea (Heerklotz, 2002). Mais recentemente, Lichtenberg e cols. (2005) descreveram aspectos sobre o fenômeno da resistência de componentes da membrana a detergentes e concluíram que DRMs não podem ser identificadas como entidades in vivo (rafts), presentes nas membranas biológicas. De acordo com aqueles autores DRMs é apenas o resultado da solubilização incompleta de membranas por detergentes e essa resistência seria determinada por fatores termodinâmicos e cinéticos; já rafts foram definidos como microdomínios transientes de membrana existentes in vivo constituídos principalmente de esfingolipídios e colesterol. Dessa forma a presença de uma molécula em DRMs não necessariamente significa sua localização em rafts. A tendência de uma molécula em se inserir em DRMs pode ocorrer por diversas razões: ela pode preferir um ambiente da membrana mais organizado; pode interagir preferencialmente com colesterol ou glicolipídios; ou pode ainda favorecer a formação de uma região de maior compactação na membrana (Lichtenberg et al., 2005). Outras limitações relacionadas às DRMs se baseiam na definição do tamanho, propriedades e dinâmica de microdomínios existentes nas membranas biológicas, uma vez
que para a formação das DRMs se emprega a ruptura da membrana (McIntosch, 2007) e, sob condições determinadas (baixa temperatura).
Devido às diversas críticas apontadas ao uso de detergentes para isolamento de rafts, outros métodos têm sido relatados. Para isolar microdomínios de membranas ricos em caveolina na ausência de detergentes, Song et al. (1996) descreveram o uso de carbonato de sódio em suas preparações com células renais de cães - MDCK (Madin-Darby canine kidney)-, enquanto Smart et al. (1995), a partir de células de fibroblatos humano, utilizaram um método de preparação consistindo em um processo de purificação em duas etapas, baseado na densidade dessas estruturas em gradiente de OptiPrep (solução de iodixanol - relativamente inerte do ponto de vista osmótico e empregado na separação de organelas celulares) em substituição ao gradiente de sacarose; em ambos os processos as membranas foram sonicadas para obtenção de pequenos fragmentos, antes da separação por centrifugação em gradiente de densidade. Curiosamente, as frações de baixa densidade (supostamente rafts) obtidas por esses métodos revelaram também ser enriquecidas em esfingolipídios e colesterol, em relação às membranas originais. No entanto, diferentemente das frações obtidas com uso de detergentes, essas frações não se mostraram depletadas de glicerofosfolipídios (Pike, 2004). Um método mais simples e que também utiliza OptiPrep na ausência de detergente foi descrito recentemente por Macdonald &amp;amp; Pike (2005) para membranas de diferentes tipos celulares (células de ovário de hamster chinês, células HeLa, e células tumorais MDA-231 de mama). De acordo com esses autores, o ponto crítico da preparação foi a remoção do quelante de cálcio EDTA e a inclusão de cátions de sódio e magnésio nos tampões de lavagem e lise das membranas. Outra técnica alternativa, sem uso de detergentes é a de imunoisolamento,
que se caracteriza pelo uso de anticorpos na fase de preparação da amostra (Shah &amp;amp; Sehgal, 2007).
Segundo Pike (2004), os rafts devem ser definidos pelas suas funções e não pelo método pelo qual são isolados das membranas biológicas, deixando de lado a sua definição operacional (DRMs). Dessa forma os rafts de membranas são pequenos domínios (10-200 nm), heterogêneos, altamente dinâmicos, enriquecidos em esfingolipídios e esteróis que compartimentalizam processos celulares. Pequenos rafts podem, algumas vezes, ser estáveis para formar grandes agregados através de interações proteína-proteína e proteína-lipídio (Pike, 2006).
Considerando a diversidade de definições para rafts e as limitações existentes nas metodologias empregadas para seu isolamento e identificação, fica difícil estabelecer uma correlação entre os microdomínios detectados por diferentes técnicas. Dessa forma, aspectos bioquímicos e biofísicos destes microdomínios têm sido alvo de muitos debates na literatura. No campo da biofísica, as técnicas espectroscópicas mais utilizadas para estudo dos rafts são: fluorescência (supressão, microscopia, transferência de energia de ressonância de fluorescência-TERF, espectroscopia de correlação de fluorescência) (London, 2002; Glebov &amp;amp; Nichols, 2004; Kahya, 2006), ressonância paramagnética eletrônica (RPE) (Subczynsky &amp;amp; Kusumi, 2003), ressonância magnética nuclear (RMN) (Veatch et al., 2004; Polozov &amp;amp; Gawrisch, 2006), microscopia de força atômica (MFA) (Kirat &amp;amp; Morandat, 2007), single-particle tracking (SPT) (Jacobson &amp;amp; Dietrich, 1999; Jin &amp;amp; Verkman, 2007) e optical trapping (Pralle,
2000).
Em membranas modelo, uma separação macroscópica das fases lo e ld em domínios maiores que 200 nm é claramente visível com uso de
marcadores de fluorescência que particionam diferentemente nas duas fases; mas, domínios com essas dimensões (&gt; 200 nm) não são observados em membranas biológicas. Por outro lado, o uso de técnicas como TERF e MFA, que não se limitam aos problemas de difração e resolução da microscopia de luz, evidenciaram a existência de domínios lo muito menores do que 200 nm (Hancock, 2006). A partir do tamanho de domínios lo obtidos por imagens de TERF foi possível demonstrar que a concentração local de colesterol está diretamente relacionada ao tamanho do domínio lo; aumentos na fração molar de colesterol (de 10% a 35%) em membranas em que as fases lo e ld coexistem, mostraram um aumento progressivo no tamanho de domínios lo: pequenos (&amp;lt;20 nm), médios (20-75 nm) e grandes (&gt; 100 nm) domínios (Hancock, 2006). No entanto, devido às grandes variações de tamanhos de rafts detectados em membranas intactas por diferentes ferramentas bioquímicas e biofísicas (tabela 1), muitos estudos ainda estão em andamento para elucidar as características de rafts como tamanho, forma e localização.
Subczynsky &amp;amp; Kusumi (2003) propuseram a existência de pelo menos três tipos de rafts, na membrana: 1) pequenos e instáveis, consistindo de poucas moléculas e com tempo de vida menor que 1 ms; 2) formados por oligômeros de proteínas ancoradas ao glicosilfosfatidilinositol ou receptores transmembranares induzidos pelo ligante, com um tempo de vida na ordem de minutos; 3) maiores e com um tempo de vida da ordem de um segundo, que se formam ao redor dos rafts descritos no segundo tipo devido a segregação de moléculas sinalizadoras, resultante da fusão de pequenos rafts instáveis que as contém. A figura 2 ilustra a dinâmica de formação de rafts em membranas plasmáticas em quatro etapas em que os três tipos de rafts propostos por Subczynsky &amp;amp; Kusumi (2003) estão presentes. A rápida interconversão dos microdomínios seria regulada por fatores extras e
intracelulares, além de fatores intrínsecos da própria membrana (Matkó &amp;amp; Szollósi, 2005).
Tabela 1 - Distribuição de tamanhos de rafts determinados por várias
técnicas bioquímicas e biofísicas biológicas.		em diferentes membranas modelo e	
Membrana	Método de detecção	Tamanho (nm)	Referência
Modelo	RPE pulsada	&gt; 5	Subczynsky &amp;amp; Kusumi, 2003
Modelo	MFA	50 - 200	Yuan &amp;amp; Johnston, 2000
Biológica	TERF baseado em anisotropia	70	Varma &amp;amp; Mayor, 1998
Biológica	SPT	40 - 600	Dietrich et al., 2002
Biológica	microscopia confocal	300 -1500	Vereb et al., 2000
Figura 2 - Dinâmica dos domínios (rafts) em membrana plasmática: 1. Complexo condensado de colesterol e esfingolipídios; 2. Pequenos rafts instáveis na monocamada externa ou interna; 3. Domínios da monocamada externa estabilizados por ligantes (L) ou anticorpos (Ab); 4. Rafts de
sinalização, que podem coexistir na membrana, de forma dinâmica (adaptado de Matkó &amp;amp; Szollosi, 2005).
Além do tamanho, a estabilidade dos rafts também é bastante questionável. No trabalho de Harder (2003), a formação e modulação dos microdomínios com capacidade de sinalização são interpretadas como dependentes do equilíbrio raft/não raft dos constituintes da membrana plasmática.
Membrana eritrocitária
A membrana do eritrócito, dada sua facilidade de obtenção e isolamento e por permitir o monitoramento da desestabilização de sua estrutura (hemólise) tem sido extensivamente estudada e é uma das membranas mais conhecidas em termos de estrutura, função e genética (Laurialt &amp;amp; O'Brien, 1991, Malheiros et al., 2004; Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007). De fato, os primeiros relatos do uso de eritrócitos para estudo das propriedades de inchamento e plasmólise de membranas datam da segunda metade do séc. XIX. Em 1899, usando eritrócitos humanos, Overton demonstrou que a permeabilidade de não eletrólitos através da membrana se relacionava com a solubilidade destes em lipídios. Outro exemplo importante a mencionar é o trabalho de Gorter &amp;amp; Grendel (1925) que, ao medir área de uma monocamada de lipídios extraídos de eritrócitos e dividi-la pela área da superfície dos eritrócitos (calculada como 2.diâmetro2 = 1,82,2) concluíram que as membranas eram formadas por uma camada bimolecular de lipídios (Datta, 1987).
Embora a membrana eritrocitária seja um modelo relativamente simples para o estudo de membranas plasmáticas (pelo fato de o eritrócito não apresentar outras membranas, já que é desprovido de núcleo e organelas), sua distribuição de proteínas e lipídios é bastante complexa. Esta membrana tem sido muito empregada para estudos de solubilização, com surfatantes clássicos e não clássicos (Hargestrand &amp;amp; Isomaa, 1989; Malheiros et al., 2000, 2004; Preté et al., 2002a,b; Rodi et al., 2006; Domingues et al., 2007; Domingues et al., 2008a).
A composição da membrana eritrocitária é fundamental para sua capacidade de deformação e estabilidade (Chasis &amp;amp; Shohet, 1987; Yawata,
2003)	e lhe permite desempenhar suas funções, como ao passar por capilares sinusóides de diâmetro inferior ao seu. Ela isola o conteúdo celular do meio exterior, regula concentrações intracelulares de íons e interage com o ambiente via receptores de membrana (Low et al., 2002). Devido a sua resistência mecânica e flexibilidade, a membrana plasmática permite ao eritrócito percorrer o sistema vascular enquanto mantém sua forma bicôncava, que propicia máxima troca gasosa. O nível intracelular de ATP regula propriedades dinâmicas da membrana (Mosior et al., 1990; Murray, 2007; Salzer et al., 2008) e sabe-se que, durante os 120 dias (em média) na circulação a membrana eritrocitária sofre alterações no seu conteúdo lipídico e protéico, o que modifica sua fluidez, atividade enzimática, permeabilidade iônica e tamanho (Jain, 1988; Hollan, 1996; Salzer et al., 2008).
A membrana eritrocitária é constituída de uma bicamada lipídica que contém várias proteínas integrais, uma rede protéica (citoesqueleto) e uma pequena porção de carboidratos ligados às proteínas e aos lipídios. A proporção, em peso, de proteínas:lipídios:carboidratos na membrana eritrocitária é 49:43:8 (Montgomery, 1994). Fosfolipídios compõem a principal classe de lipídios da membrana eritrocitária, englobando glicero e
esfingolipídios (65%), além de glicolipídios (10%) e colesterol (25%) (Storch &amp;amp; Kleinfeld, 1985). Dentre os fosfolipídios, os mais encontrados na membrana eritrocitária são fosfatidiletanolamina (30%), fosfatidilcolina (27%), esfingomielina (23%), fosfatidilserina (15%) e fosfatidilinositol (5%) (Zachowski, 1993). Esses fosfolipídios se arranjam assimetricamente pela bicamada lipídica. A distribuição assimétrica nas duas monocamadas (interna e externa) da membrana eritrocitária é absoluta para a fosfatidilserina (PS) com todas suas moléculas localizadas na camada interna; de maneira semelhante, a maioria das moléculas de fosfatidiletanolamina (PE) se situa preferencialmente na monocamada interna. Por outro lado a fosfatidilcolina (PC) e a esfingomielina localizam-se, preferencialmente, na monocamada externa (Connor et al., 1990, Yawata, 2003).
As proteínas representam cerca de 50% da massa total das membranas de eritrócito (Cooper, 1997). Entre os 500 spots protéicos já detectados por eletroforese bidimensional em membranas de eritrócitos, 59 polipeptídios diferentes já foram identificados ao lado de suas 43 isoformas (Low et al., 2002). Essas proteínas juntamente com aquelas identificadas exclusivamente por eletroforese monodimensional (SDS-PAGE) totalizam um número estimado em 84 proteínas associadas à membrana do eritrócito (Low et al., 2002). As características de algumas dessas proteínas estão descritas na tabela 2.
Tabela 2- Características das proteínas integráis e periféricas (citoesqueleto) da membrana eritrocitária.
Proteína	PM aproximado (kDa)	pI	Tipo: Integral (I)/Periférica (P)	Acesso ao NCBI/SWISS- PROT
Espectrina a	240	4,96	P	P02549
Espectrina p	220	5,13	P	P11277
Anquirina	210	5,65	P	P16157
Banda 3	95	5,07	I	P02730
Proteína 4.1	80	5,41	P	P11171
Proteína 4.2	79	-	P	P16452
p55	55	9,06	P	Q00013
Dematina	46	9,01	P	Q08495
Actina	43	5,29	P	P02570
Gliceraldeído 3-	35	8,57	P	P04406
fosfato				
desidrogenase				
Tropomiosina	32	4,75	P	P12324
Estomatina	31	7,71	I	P27105
Glicoforinas:	36, 20,32	-	I	CAC85280,
A, B, C				CAC83876,
				P04921
As proteínas integrais interagem com os lipídios da membrana através de suas porções hidrofóbicas que penetram ou atravessam a bicamada lipídica. Entre as proteínas integrais do eritrócito se destacam: a banda 3 (proteína transportadora de íons) e as glicoforinas, que possuem receptores de membrana e antígenos e que participam do reconhecimento célula-célula
na face externa da membrana. Já as proteínas periféricas (principalmente espectrina, actina, proteína 4.1 e 4.9) formam um extenso retículo submembranar, o citoesqueleto eritrocitário, que é responsável pela forma bicôncava do eritrócito e que representa 60% da massa protéica de toda a membrana (Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007). As proteínas que compõem o citoesqueleto interagem entre si e com certas proteínas integrais da membrana do eritrócito, como esquematizado na figura 3.
interação
interação espectrina-l ¡pidió
interação espectrina-anquirina-banda 3
¡nteraçao
Interação Horizontal
glicoforina
_		
	GP	1
		
	X x X X \ \ &gt;,
	3 espectrina \\xxx\\\
interação dímero-dimero da espectrina
interação espectrina-proteína 4.1-glicoforina
	n	
	Op	?? ü
		
		
Figura 3 - Representação da membrana plasmática e do citoesqueleto em eritrócitos. GP = glicoforina C; 4.1 = proteína 4.1; 2.1 = anquirina (Adaptado de Gallagher &amp;amp; Forget, 2001).
Abaixo segue uma descrição sucinta das proteínas clássicas que constituem a membrana eritrocitária e normalmente são observadas em SDS-PAGE:
Proteínas integrais
•	Banda 3: é a proteína integral mais abundante, representando 25-30% de
todas as proteínas da membrana com 106 cópias por célula. Seu nome vem da separação eletroforética em SDS-PAGE (figura 4) e sua função principal é mediar a troca de íons cloreto e bicarbonato através da membrana, além de contribuir na manutenção da morfologia eritrocitária. Seu domínio transmembranar de 52 kDa atravessa de 12 a 13 vezes a bicamada lipídica (Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007). Outro domínio importante da banda 3 é o citoplasmático, que é responsável pela interação desta proteína com outras (especialmente proteína 4.1, 4.2 e anquirina) através de seus resíduos carregados negativamente. Este segmento citoplasmático tem forte afinidade pela hemoglobina,	aldolases, gliceraldeído 3-fosfato
desidrogenase e fosfofrutoquinase. Além disso, estes sítios têm significado fisiológico na regulação da glicólise e auxiliam a formação de complexos multienzimáticos (Mandal et al., 2003).
•	Glicoforinas: são glicoproteínas que atravessam uma única vez a membrana e são divididas em 4 tipos, designadas pelas abreviações GPA, GPB, GPC e GPD. Elas apresentam um domínio externo, onde estão os oligossacarídeos, um segmento incluído no interior da bicamada e um segmento interno citoplasmático. A GPA, a forma principal, é a maior sialoglicoproteína e corresponde a 2-4% das proteínas dessa membrana, além de ser a segunda proteína integral mais abundante. Sua alta concentração nos eritrócitos é responsável por 80% da carga negativa destas células, devida ao ácido siálico presente em sua constituição. Essa superfície externa negativa ajuda a minimizar a interação célula-célula e a prevenir a aglutinação eritrocitária (Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007). A GPC é responsável por um dos pontos de ancoramento do citoesqueleto com a membrana plasmática. As outras
glicoforinas se encontram em pequenas quantidades e não possuem uma caracterização bem definida.
Além da banda 3 e das glicoforinas, outras proteínas integrais como receptores hormonais como o da insulina e o transportador da glicose (banda 4.5) estão presentes em concentração significativa na membrana eritrocitária (Low et al., 2002; Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007).
Proteínas periféricas (citoesqueleto)
•	Espectrina: é a proteína mais importante do citoesqueleto apresentando 105 cópias por célula. A espectrina apresenta papel fundamental no formato e deformabilidade do eritrócito. É uma proteína longa e fibrilar constituída por duas cadeias polipeptídicas (alfa e beta). Fisiologicamente a espectrina se encontra na forma de tetrâmero sendo que a zona de interação dos dímeros ocorre pela região N-terminal de uma cadeia alfa que faceia a região C-terminal de uma cadeia beta do dímero oposto (figura 3) (Mandal et al., 2003; Murray, 2007). A espectrina também interage direta e independentemente com domínios lipídicos, contribuindo para a conexão entre citoesqueleto e bicamada (Diakowski et al., 2003; Ray &amp;amp; Chakrabarti,
2004). Recentes estudos demonstraram que interações diretas entre espectrina e fosfolipídios, em particular fosfatidilserina, ocorrem através de múltiplos sítios de ligação existentes nas subunidades alfa e beta da espectrina. No entanto, o significado fisiológico dessas interações ainda permanece obscuro (An et al., 2004, 2005; Diakowski et al., 2006). Outras proteínas do citoesqueleto como a anquirina, actina e proteína 4.1 se associam à espectrina.
•	Anquirina: também conhecida por sindeína, a anquirina representa a banda
2.1	no perfil eletroforético (figura 4) e apresenta o mesmo número de
cópias que a espectrina (105 cópias por célula). Possui três domínios estruturais, sendo um domínio ligado à subunidade beta da espectrina, um segundo domínio que interage com a banda 3 e um domínio regulador que controla a função dos outros dois domínios (Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007). Dessa forma, a ligação à espectrina e a forte ligação à banda 3, favorece a ligação da espectrina à membrana.
•	Proteína 4.1: está presente numericamente em 2 x 105 cópias por célula. O maior ponto de ligação da proteína 4.1 na membrana eritrocitária é com a GPC e GPD. Uma das principais proteínas do citoesqueleto, essa proteína contribui na manutenção e modulação da morfologia do eritrócito, bem como nas propriedades mecânicas da membrana, através das suas múltiplas ligações com outras proteínas do citoesqueleto (espectrina, actina, p55) e proteínas transmembranares (banda 3 e GPC) (An et al., 2006). Tanto a interação da proteína 4.1 com a p55 quanto a desta com GPC/D são de alta afinidade (Mandal et al., 2003). As interações espectrina-actina são facilitadas pela proteína 4.1. Além disso, a proteína 4.1 pode interagir com alguns fosfolipídios da membrana e, dessa forma, conectar a bicamada lipídica ao citoesqueleto (Murray, 2007).
•	Proteína 4.2: também chamada de palidina, apresenta 100 mil cópias em cada eritrócito. Liga-se com a banda 3 e com anquirina, desempenhando um papel organizacional na membrana. É muito importante para a regulação da estabilidade e flexibilidade dos eritrócitos (Karacay &amp;amp; Chang, 1999; Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007).
•	Actina: essa proteína corresponde à banda 5 no perfil eletroforético (figura
4)	e se encontra ligada à espectrina e à proteína 4.1. Forma um complexo juncional com proteína 4.1, aducina e tropomiosina, favorecendo a ligação da actina com a espectrina.
Figura 4 - Esquema do perfil eletroforético monodimensional (SDS-PAGE) das proteínas da membrana eritrocitária. G3PDH = gliceraldeido 3-fosfato desidrogenase (adaptado de Murador &amp;amp; Deffune, 2007).
Há mais de duas décadas sabe-se que o citoesqueleto do eritrócito está conectado com a bicamada lipídica através das proteínas banda 3 e glicoforina C, por intermédio da anquirina e proteína 4.1, respectivamente. No entanto, outra possibilidade de conexão envolvendo Rh, RhAG, CD47, proteína 4.2 e/ou anquirina foi recentemente descrita (Mauro-Chanteloup et al., 2003; Nicolas et al., 2003).
DRMs de eritrocitos
Nos últimos anos, DRMs de eritrócitos foram isoladas e caracterizadas, embora ainda haja divergências sobre a composição protéica e lipídica dessas estruturas (Salzer &amp;amp; Prohaska, 2001; Nagao et al., 2002; Murphy et al., 2004; Ciana et al., 2005; Wilkinson et al., 2007; Kamata et al., 2008).
Composição protéica em DRMs de eritrócitos
Salzer &amp;amp; Prohaska (2001), demonstraram que a flotilina-1 e 2 e estomatina são as principais proteínas integrais em DRMs de eritrócitos, enquanto outras proteínas como espectrina, actina, proteína 4.1 e proteína 4.2 foram encontradas parcialmente associadas às DRMs. De fato, as proteínas flotilina, estomatina, Gsa, proteínas ligadas ao glicosilfosfatidilinositol, além do gangliosídeo GM1 têm sido usados como marcadores da presença de rafts/DRMs em eritrócitos (Salzer &amp;amp; Prohaska, 2001; Ciana et al., 2005; Wilkinson et al., 2007; Kamata et al., 2008). No entanto, vários estudos demonstraram que a concentração e o tipo de detergente utilizado resultam em variações qualitativas e quantitativas nas proteínas de DRMs (Schuck et al., 2003; Murphy et al., 2004).
Embora a espectrina seja observada em DRMs de eritrócitos e de outros tipos celulares, sua presença em DRMs ainda é bastante discutida. Particularmente para eritrócitos, sua associação a DRMs pode depender da concentração do detergente empregado, do pH e da concentração de proteína na amostra inicial (Murphy et al., 2004; Ciana et al., 2005). Ciana et al. (2005) caracterizaram DRMs isoladas de membranas eritrocitárias utilizando diferentes metodologias e verificaram que, qualitativa e quantitativamente, diferentes frações de DRMs são obtidas de acordo com as condições adotadas durante o isolamento. De acordo com seus resultados, grande parte das
frações de DRMs enriquecidas pelos marcadores de lipid rafts, como flotilina-2 e GM1, está ancorada ao citoesqueleto eritrocitário através de interações eletrostáticas que podem ser rompidas pelo aumento simultâneo de pH e força iônica do meio de solubilização. No entanto, nenhum modelo experimental mais consistente foi proposto ainda para explicar essa associação de DRMs e/ou rafts com o citoesqueleto. Dessa forma, proteínas que são freqüentemente encontradas em DRMs poderiam estar envolvidas nessa associação e nesse caso, as proteínas flotilina e estomatina seriam fortes candidatas. A seguir encontra-se uma breve descrição dessas duas proteínas.
• Flotilinas: flotilina-1 e -2 são também conhecidas por reggie-2 e -1, respectivamente. Possuindo um peso molecular de 47 kDa, essas proteínas pertencem à família das proteínas SPFH (S = Stomatin; P = Prohibiting; F = Flotillin; H = HflK/C - proteínas bacterianas) e apresentam um domínio de seqüência comum (SPFH) na região N-terminal (Tavernarakis et al., 1999). Encontradas principalmente na membrana plasmática, essas proteínas não possuem domínio transmembranar e tanto a região C- quanto a N-terminal faceiam o citosol (Morrow et al., 2002). A inserção das flotilinas na monocamada interna das membranas se dá através de acilação nos seus N-terminais. Enquanto a flotilina-2 é miristoilada e palmitoilada, a flotilina-1 é apenas palmitoilada (Morrow et al., 2002; Neumann-Giesen et al., 2004). A estrutura trimensional do domínio SPFH da flotilina-2, encontrada no banco de dados PDB (Protein Data Bank) - código de acesso = 1win - revela uma estrutura compacta e elipsóide-globular. Em relação à região C-terminal da flotilina-2 sabe-se que ela é essencial para a formação de homo e hetero-oligômeros (Neumann-Giesen et al., 2004). Devido ao fato de a flotilina-2 ser irreversivelmente miristoilada e, portanto, apresentar menor mobilidade em relação à flotilina-1 que é reversivelmente palmitoilada e mais versátil em termos de transição entre a membrana plasmática e várias organelas
intracelulares, ela tem sido mais utilizada como um marcador de rafts do que a sua análoga flotilina-1 (Langhorst et al., 2005). Embora as flotilinas tenham sido descobertas há uma década, o papel biológico dessas proteínas ainda não está completamente estabelecido. Alguns estudos indicam o envolvimento dessas proteínas em várias vias de transdução de sinal, no tráfego de vesículas e no rearranjo do citoesqueleto. Além disso, muitas proteínas interagem com as flotilinas (Langhorst et al., 2005, 2008). Em eritrócito, particularmente, a função dessas proteínas é desconhecida.
• Estomatina: assim como as flotilinas, a estomatina não está presente exclusivamente em eritrócitos como se pensava no início dos anos 90. Estomatina é uma proteína integral (100.000 cópias/célula), possui peso molecular de 31 kDa e compõe a banda 7 (7.2b) de acordo com sua mobilidade eletroforética em amostras de membranas isoladas de eritrócitos (código de acesso ao PDB = 3bk6). Essa proteína possui as regiões N- e C-terminal faceando o citoplasma, enquanto sua palmitoilação favorece sua associação na membrana. Além disso, o domínio hidrofóbico da estomatina está inserido apenas na monocamada interna da membrana (Umlauf et al., 2004; Umlauf et al., 2006). A formação de complexos homo-oligoméricos na membrana, característico desta proteína, é dependente da composição da sua região C-terminal (resíduos 264-272) (Snyers et al., 1999; Umlauf et al., 2006). No entanto, apenas três resíduos hidrofóbicos da região C-terminal são necessários para associação da estomatina em DRMs (resíduos 266-268). Já os resíduos 269-272 que são fundamentais para oligomerização, não são essenciais para associação em DRMs. Dessa forma, a oligomerização da flotilina não está diretamente relacionada à sua associação em DRMs e possivelmente em rafts (Umlauf, 2006). Embora a função dessa proteína seja ainda alvo de investigação, estudos
demonstraram seu envolvimento no controle da permeabilidade de canais iônicos e organização de domínios lipídicos (Wang &amp;amp; Morrow, 2000).
Composição lipídica em DRMs de eritrócitos
Como observado também em DRMs preparadas de outras membranas biológicas, o colesterol e os esfingolipídios são, quantitativamente, os principais componentes encontrados nas DRMs dos eritrócitos (Ciana et al., 2005; Koumanov et al., 2005; Rodi et al., 2006) e que seriam responsáveis pela segregação lateral de fases, i.e., pela formação desses domínios (Rietveld &amp;amp; Simons, 1998). Além desses, o gangliosídeo GM1 também é considerado um marcador de DRMs em eritrócitos (Ciana et al., 2005), embora seja encontrado em concentrações bem inferiores ao colesterol e esfingolipídios. Esse alto conteúdo lipídico presente em DRMs é, portanto, responsável pela baixa densidade dessas frações obtidas em gradiente de sacarose.
Num trabalho interessante Rivas &amp;amp; Gennaro (2003), usando ressonância paramagnética eletrônica, demonstraram claramente que a matriz lipídica de DRMs de eritrócitos ainda permanece, mesmo após uma depleção de 40% do colesterol daquela membrana, embora proteínas marcadoras de rafts como a flotilina-1 e -2 e a estomatina, não sejam mais detectadas (Rivas &amp;amp; Gennaro,
2003).
O uso de seqüestradores de colesterol da membrana como a metil-beta-ciclodextrina tem sido grandemente empregado em estudos de DRMs. Assim como observado por Rivas &amp;amp; Gennaro (2003), outros estudos indicam alterações na composição protéica e lipídica (colesterol) em DRMs formadas a partir de eritrócitos depletados de colesterol (Samuel et al. 2001; Kamata et al., 2008).
A contribuição do colesterol e dos esfingolipídios na organização e estabilização de DRMs/rafts ainda não está totalmente elucidada (Fielding,
2006)	. Segundo Rodi et al. (2006) existe uma alta relação entre restrições na mobilidade de cadeias lipídicas e o conteúdo de esfingomielina nestas estruturas lipídicas, demonstrando o importante papel da esfingomielina em determinar a organização de cadeias acila. No entanto, diversas proteínas presentes em DRMs são facilmente extraídas quando células são depletadas de colesterol (Simons &amp;amp; Ehehalt, 2002; Chamberlain, 2004). De acordo com Samuel et al. (2001) a depleção de colesterol em eritrócitos não resulta em alterações na assimetria, deformabilidade ou propriedades da membrana, indicando que embora o colesterol seja crítico para a organização de proteínas em DRMs, estes domínios parecem ter pouca influência em diversas funções eritrocitárias analisadas. No entanto, foi observada diminuição da infecção pelo parasita causador da malária em eritrócitos depletados de colesterol e, cujas DRMs apresentaram conteúdo reduzido deste lipídio (Samuel et al., 2001). O envolvimento de DRMs pode ser entendido considerando-se a remodelagem citoplasmática dos componentes da membrana de eritrócitos, envolvendo a exclusão da estomatina, espectrina, actina e fosfatidilinositol 4,5-bisfosfato no vacúolo parasitário, durante a infecção pelo Plasmodium (Murphy et al.,
2007)	.
Outra forma de induzir alterações na estrutura de DRMs sem alterar o conteúdo de colesterol foi recentemente postulada por Kamata et al. (2008) através do uso de anestésicos locais; nesse estudo os autores mostraram um efeito reversível da lidocaína na desorganização de rafts e conseqüente alteração na transdução de sinal dependente de Gsa, em eritrócitos. Os efeitos de anestésicos locais sobre a fase lipídica das membranas incluem diminuição da temperatura de transição de fase, desorganização das cadeias acilas (de
Paula &amp;amp; Schreier, 1996) e alteração na segregação lateral de fases induzida por cálcio (Cullis &amp;amp; Verkleij, 1979; Soares, 2001).
Solubilização e resistência de membranas a detergentes
Detergentes, surfatantes ou tensoativos são moléculas anfifílicas que se agregam em meio aquoso. A maior parte das moléculas de detergente tem uma estrutura cônica, apresentando uma curvatura espontânea positiva que lhes confere a tendência a formar agregados do tipo micelar (Helfrich, 1973; Israelachvili et al., 1980). O uso de detergentes tem sido uma das ferramentas mais importantes no estudo de lipídios e proteínas de membranas biológicas. Geralmente, os detergentes não iônicos como os polioxietilenos são utilizados como agentes solubilizadores de membrana para evitar grandes alterações estruturais das proteínas, uma vez que possuem um baixo efeito desnaturante (le Maire et al., 2000). Baseado na existência de uma íntima relação entre formação de micelas, partição e ruptura de membrana (Lichtenberg, 1985; Lichtenberg et al., 2000), o produto entre a constante de ligação e a concentração micelar crítica (Kb . CMC) é utilizado para classificar os detergentes em relação ao potencial de ruptura da membrana (Heerklotz &amp;amp; Seelig, 2000), tal que: Kb . CMC &amp;lt;1 indica um forte agente solubilizador, enquanto que Kb . CMC &gt; 1 indica um fraco agente solubilizador. Outra forma de classificar os detergentes em relação ao potencial de ruptura da membrana, proposta por nosso grupo, seria o uso da razão molar detergente:lipídio (Re) necessária para solubilizar a membrana (Preté et al., 2006), como será descrito a seguir.
Em misturas contendo detergente e fosfolipídios, não ocorre a coexistência de micelas puras de detergente e bicamadas puras de fosfolipídio,
por uma questão entrópica (Lichtenberg et al., 2005). De fato, a mistura desses compostos anfifílicos leva à solubilização da membrana modelo, o que pode ser descrito como um processo de transição membrana-micela, em que:
1)	inicialmente monômeros do detergente particionam na bicamada; 2) membranas mistas, i.e., saturadas pela incorporação dos monômeros de detergente, coexistem em equilíbrio termodinâmico com micelas mistas (detergente-fosfolipídios/proteínas); 3) componentes da membrana são totalmente solubilizados nas micelas do detergente (Lichtenberg et al., 2000). Dessa forma, o processo de solubilização por detergentes depende da razão molar efetiva detergente/lipídio (Re) alcançada na membrana. Considerando que Resat e Resol correspondem às razões críticas que descrevem o início e a completa solubilização da membrana, respectivamente, estes parâmetros representam o limite para a coexistência de membranas mistas e micelas mistas (Lichtenberg, 1985; Lichtenberg et al.,2000). Além da composição da membrana e do detergente utilizado, os valores de Resat e Resol dependem também de outros fatores como a composição da fase aquosa e a temperatura (Lichtenberg et al., 2005). Os valores de Resat e ResQl também dependem da CMC do detergente e da sua partição na membrana, como demonstraram Heerklotz &amp;amp; Seelig (2000) e podem também ser usados para a classificação de seu efeito solubilizador, tal que detergentes com Resat &amp;lt;1 seriam considerados fortes e com Resat &gt;1 fracos (Preté, 2006).
Esta abordagem aplica-se também à solubilização de membranas biológicas (Preté et al., 2002a,b; Domingues et al., 2008a) e, como mostra a figura 5 (Schreier et al., 2000) vários equilíbrios entre o detergente (monomérico ou micelar) e componentes da membrana coexistem, durante o processo.
Efeitos da intercalação da droga na membrana:
-	mudança na organização da bicamada (efeito na permeabilidade, estrutura e função de proteína)
-	"flip-flop" de lipídios ou droga
-	mudança na forma (eritrocitos)
-	endo/exovesiculação
-domínio droga-lipidio fora da bicamada
-	interd ig itação
-	ruptura (solubilização de membrana)
Figura 5 - Esquema de possíveis eventos envolvidos na interação de detergente com membrana biológica. Os processos correspondem à: 1-solubilização do anfifílico; 2- equilíbrios entre monômero-agregado; 3- ligação do monômero à membrana; 4- equilíbrios do anfifílico entre micela-membrana. Após a saturação da membrana, moléculas do detergente saem da membrana carregando componentes da membrana (lipídios e proteínas). As constantes representam cada processo. Os prováveis eventos resultantes da interação detergente-membrana estão listados no esquema (adaptado de Schreier et al., 2000).
No entanto, em algumas condições experimentais, mesmo em altas concentrações de detergente uma fração da membrana pode permanecer na forma não solubilizada, isto é, fragmentos da membrana resistentes a detergente não são convertidos em micelas mistas. As razões pelas quais
ocorre essa solubilização incompleta podem ser de natureza termodinâmica ou cinética.
Evidências experimentais revelaram que uma das possibilidades para a resistência a detergente pela membrana (incompleta solubilização) resulta da interação esfingomielina-colesterol. Embora ainda questionada, a interação entre esfingomielina e colesterol em bicamadas parece ocorrer devido à ligação de hidrogênio entre o grupo hidroxila (30OH) do colesterol e o grupo carbonila da ligação amida da esfingomielina (Rietveld &amp;amp; Simons, 1998; Veiga et al., 2001). No estudo feito por Sot et al. (2002), DRMs ricas em esfingomielina e colesterol foram obtidas a partir de misturas de Triton X-100 e vesículas feitas de fosfatidilcolina, esfingomielina e colesterol. Assim, experimentalmente, a presença desses lipídios pode resultar em bicamadas resistentes à solubilização por Triton X-100, em uma grande faixa de temperatura (Lichtenberg, 2005). Outros estudos têm sugerido que a resistência de certas membranas a detergentes não ocorre nem devido à alta viscosidade, nem devido à presença de colesterol ou esfingolipídios per se; sendo o efeito do colesterol e esfingolipídios dependente (em uma maneira complexa) tanto da temperatura quanto da composição das bicamadas (Heerklotz et al., 1997; Schnitzer et al., 2003; Lichtenberg et al., 2005).
Se a resistência a detergentes é um fenômeno em equilíbrio (transição bicamada-micela), este fato estaria relacionado à baixa afinidade do lipídio em particionar em micelas mistas, ou seja, uma forte preferência do lipídio pela fase lamelar. Isso significa que, para a membrana não solubilizada, Resol será diretamente relacionada à afinidade do lipídio para com a membrana em oposição às micelas mistas, descrita pela constante de associação KLb/m. Neste caso, se a resistência termodinâmica de um lipídio na bicamada é devida a um alto valor de KLb/m, ela independe da presença ou ausência de um outro lipídio facilmente solubilizado (Lichtenberg et al., 2005). Esses fatos poderiam,
então, explicar a resistência a detergentes por certas misturas contendo esfingomielina e colesterol. Além da transição da esfingomielina de bicamadas para micelas ser desfavorável em termos de curvatura interfacial, a ruptura das ligações de hidrogênio intermolecular com concomitante diminuição na ordem das cadeias acila dos lipídios também é uma barreira para ocorrência dessa transição (Lichtenberg et al., 2005).
A eficiência de um detergente em solubilizar a membrana ou de formar microdomínios na fase lo pode resultar em DRMs com diferentes composições. Assim, detergentes fracos que agem de maneira menos eficiente e com menor seletividade (para proteínas e lipídios), podem resultar em DRMs formadas devido a uma inadequada solubilização. Da mesma maneira, a diminuição na concentração de um detergente forte diminui sua seletividade e aumenta a proporção dos componentes de DRMs. Por outro lado, uma solubilização eficiente pode resultar na ruptura de interações fracas entre proteínas e rafts (Lingwood &amp;amp; Simons, 2007). No entanto, o que essas frações resistentes a detergente refletem, realmente, na membrana ainda é alvo de investigação.
Por outro lado, as diferentes composições protéicas e lipídicas encontradas em DRMs são consideradas como resultado da heterogeneidade dos rafts nas membranas biológicas e do modo com que estes microdomínios seriam diferentemente solubilizados, de acordo com o detergente empregado ou do método de isolamento (Pike, 2004). Três modelos de estrutura de rafts foram propostos por Pike (2004): 1) rafts são compostos por camadas concêntricas de lipídios contendo uma região central bem organizada, rica em colesterol e esfingolipídios e uma região menos organizada na periferia dessas camadas; 2) rafts são domínios homogêneos bem organizados cercados por uma fase desordenada que compreende o restante da membrana. As frações de baixa densidade, apresentando diferentes composições lipídicas e protéicas e resultantes da extração com diferentes detergentes, dependem da
habilidade dos detergentes em extrair seletivamente lipídios e proteínas desses rafts homogêneos; 3) rafts com diferentes composições lipídicas e protéicas existem na membrana e são seletivamente solubilizados de acordo com o detergente utilizado.
Em resumo, embora seja inequívoco que interações intermoleculares entre componentes lipídicos da membrana sejam responsáveis pela segregação em domínios (rafts), a existência e estrutura desses domínios bem como sua(s) função(ões) nas membranas biológicas ainda é motivo de debate.
Em estudos prévios de nosso grupo de pesquisa analisamos o efeito hemolítico de diferentes detergentes sobre membranas de eritrócitos humano (Galembeck et al., 1998; Preté et al., 2002a,b; Domingues, 2004; Preté, 2006; Domingues et al., 2008a), o que nos permitiu, através das razões detergente:lipídio para solubilização da membrana (Re), classificá-los como fracos ou fortes agentes solubilizadores e correlacionar seu efeito sobre a membrana com sua capacidade de rompê-las e formar micelas mistas (Preté, 2006). O Triton X-100 e o C12E8 se mostraram fortes agentes solubilizadores, com valores de Resat iguais a 1,6 e 0,2, respectivamente, e constante de ligação à membrana semelhantes, estimada em 6000 M-1 (Preté et al., 2002b). Ainda com membranas de eritrócitos humano, analisamos através de eletroforese bidimensional a solubilização diferencial de proteínas desta membrana, induzida por detergentes, com destaque para os zwiteriônicos ASB-14 e ASB-16, da família das amidosulfobetaínas, capazes de solubilizar seletivamente proteínas não visualizadas em géis bidimensionais com o uso dos clássicos CHAPS e Triton X-100 (Domingues, 2004; Domingues et al., 2007). Com essas duas abordagens procuramos obter informações relacionadas à solubilização induzida por detergentes na fase lipídica (ensaios hemolíticos) ou protéica (eletroforese bidimensional) da
membrana, separadamente. No entanto, o processo de solubilização de membranas biológicas por detergentes é extremamente complexo, envolve diferentes lipídios e proteínas e pode ser incompleto, levando a formação de DRMs. A caracterização dessas frações ricas em colesterol, esfingolipídios e proteínas específicas, obtidas por solubilização incompleta das membranas biológicas com uso de detergentes (DRMs) foi a motivação desta investigação. As propriedades físico-químicas dos detergentes utilizados neste estudo estão descritas na tabela 3.
Tabela 3- Propriedades físico-químicas e estruturas dos detergentes: Triton X-100, C12E8, ASB-14, ASB-16 e CHAPS.
Detergente MMa CMC (mM) N° Agregaçãoa
H3C
Estrutura
CH3
Triton X-100	625	0,2-0,9
C12E8	538,8	0,11a
ASB-14	434,7	0,1b
ASB-16	462,7	0,01b
CHAPS	614,9	6-10a
a
100-155
123
H3C
H3C—C—CH2—C
O(CH2CH2O)9,10H
CH3
CH3(CH2)10CH2O(CH2CH2O)8H
CH
3
H
N
SO
ade acordo com Bhairi (2001).
bde acordo com Domingues et al. (2008a).
OBJETIVOS
Este trabalho teve como objetivo preparar e caracterizar, quanto a composição e organização lipídica/protéica, frações de membrana eritrocitária resistentes aos detergentes não iônicos Triton X-100 e C12E8, a fim de obter informações sobre os mecanismos de interação proteína-proteína e proteína-lipídio existentes nas membranas biológicas.
Objetivos específicos:
1)	Preparar DRMs de eritrócitos através do uso de C12E8 e compará-las com as obtidas por Triton X-100.
2)	Comparar DRMs obtidas de eritrócitos íntegros e de ghosts (membranas isoladas) de eritrócitos com Triton X-100 e C12E8.
3)	Caracterizar, quanto ao conteúdo lipídico (de colesterol) e protéico (total e específico), DRMs preparadas a partir de Triton X-100 e C12E8.
4)	Através da depleção de colesterol dos eritrócitos, verificar o papel deste lipídio esteroídico na manutenção/organização de DRMs obtidas com Triton X-100 e C12E8.
5)	Caracterizar a estrutura de DRMs obtidas com Triton X-100 e C12E8, quanto à organização da bicamada lipídica (ordem) medida por Ressonância Paramagnética Eletrônica, com marcadores de spin.
6)	Preparar DRMs de eritrócitos através do uso de detergentes zwiteriônicos (ASB-14, ASB-16 e CHAPS).
7)	Avaliar o efeito de variações metodológicas (temperatura, presença ou não de carbonato de sódio e EDTA, tratamento das células com anestésicos locais) na obtenção de DRMs.
RESULTADOS E DISCUSSÃO
Os resultados e discussão deste trabalho estão apresentados em três partes, sendo as duas primeiras na forma de artigos.
PARTE 1
Artigo:
Domingues CC, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E (2008) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents. Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res. 41:758764.
Neste artigo além de apresentarmos o efeito hemolítico de novos detergentes zwiteriônicos (ASB-14 e ASB-16) e descrevermos suas CMC através de EPR, destacamos o grande potencial desses detergentes na solubilização de diferentes componentes da membrana (colesterol e proteínas) que nos levaram a questionar se DRMs seriam ou não obtidas através do uso de ASB (ver parte 3).
PARTE 2
DRMs de eritrócitos obtidas com uso de Triton X-100 e Ci2E8
Artigo 1:
Domingues CC, Ciana A, Buttafava A, Balduini C, de Paula E, Minetti G (2008) Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8. J. Membr. Biol. DOI 10.1007/s00232-008-9142-4.
Artigo 2:
Domingues CC, Ciana A, Balduini C, de Paula E, Minetti G. Detergentresistant membranes from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes using Triton X-100 and C12E8. (a ser submetido)
PARTE 3
Variações metodológicas no preparo de DRMs
PARTE 1
Artigo:
Domingues CC, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E (2008) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents. Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res. 41:758764.
Brazilian Journal of Medical and Biological Research (2008) 41: 758-764
ISSN 0100-879X	'
Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents
C.C. Domingues1, S.V.P. Malheiros1 2 and E. de Paula1
'Departamento de Bioquímica, Instituto de Biología, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas, SP, Brasil
'Departamento de Biología e Fisiología, Faculdade de Medicina de Jundiaí, Jundiaí, SP, Brasil
Correspondence to: E. de Paula, Departamento de Bioquímica, Instituto de Biología, UNICAMP, Caixa Postal 6109, 13083-970 Campinas, SP, Brasil Fax: +55-19-3521-6129. E-mail: depaula@unicamp.br
Understanding the membrane solubilization process and finding effective solubilizing agents are crucial challenges in biochemical research. Here we report results on the interaction of the novel linear alkylamido propyl dimethyl amino propanosulfonate detergents, ASB-14 and ASB-16, with human erythrocyte membranes. An estimation of the critical micelle concentration of these zwitterionic detergents (ASB-14 =100 pM and ASB-16 = 10 pM) was obtained using electron paramagnetic resonance. The amount of proteins and cholesterol solubilized from erythrocytes by these detergents was then determined. The hemolytic activities of the ASB detergents were assayed and the detergent/lipid molar ratios for the onset of hemolysis (Re5a’) and total lysis (ReMl) were calculated, allowing the determination of the membrane binding constants (Kb). ASB-14 presented lower membrane affinity (Kb = 7050 M'1) than ASB-16 (Kb = 15610 M'1). The amount of proteins and cholesterol solubilized by both ASB detergents was higher while Resat values (0.22 and 0.08 detergent/lipid for ASB-14 and ASB-16, respectively) were smaller than those observed with the classic detergents CHAPS and Triton X-100. These results reveal that, besides their well-known use as membrane protein solubilizers to enhance the resolution of two dimensional electrophoresis/ mass spectrometry, ASB-14 and ASB-16 are strong hemolytic agents. We propose that the physicochemical properties of ASB detergents determine their membrane disruption efficiency and can help to explain the improvement in the solubilization of membrane proteins, as reported in the literature.
Key words: Hemolysis; Protein solubilization; Erythrocyte; Zwitterionic detergents; Critical micelle concentration; Cholesterol solubilization
Research supported by FAPESP (#03/02394-4). C.C. Domingues was the recipient of fellowships from CAPES (Master program) and CNPq (#141618/2005-1).
Received March 4, 2008. Accepted August 25, 2008
Introduction
The solubilization of biological membranes by detergents has been investigated for many years (1-6). Detergents are amphiphilic compounds that solubilize membrane proteins and lipids, leading to disruption of cell membranes at high enough concentrations. According to their physicochemical properties - such as charge, critical micelle concentration (CMC), aggregation number and hydrophilic-lipophilic balance (HLB) - different interactions occur and membrane proteins are denatured or not (4,7). As for the lipids, quantitative studies of membrane solubi
lization show a strong correlation between these physicochemical properties of detergents (2,8-10) and their lytic effect.
In the last decades, new detergents have appeared, being designed to improve the solubilization of membrane proteins. The zwitterionic amidosulfobetaine detergents ASB-14 and ASB-16 (linear alkylamido propyl dimethyl amino propanosulfonates) with 14 and 16 atoms of carbon in the acyl chain, respectively, were synthesized by Chevallet et al. (11). They have contributed to the advance of two-dimensional gel electrophoresis analysis, improving the solubilization of many hydrophobic proteins such
Erythrocyte solubilization by ASB detergents
as erythrocyte band III (12,13) and others (11,14-16).
Despite the contribution of ASB detergents to the pro-teomic sciences, their role in the membrane solubilization process still remains unclear. In the present article, we studied the interaction of ASB-14 and ASB-16 with human erythrocyte membranes, using the quantitative approach described by Lichtenberg (2) to describe cell disruption and membrane solubilization.
Material and Methods
The alkylamido propyl dimethyl amino propanosul-fonate detergents ASB-14 and ASB-16 were obtained from Calbiochem (USA). CHAPS and 5-doxyl stearic acid (5-SASL) were purchased from Sigma Chemical Co. (USA). All other reagents were of analytical grade.
Determination of critical micelle concentration
5-SASL films were prepared by evaporating stock chloroform solution of the spin label, under a stream of N2. PBS (147 mM NaCI, 5 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.4) was added and the samples were vortexed for about 5 min. Aliquots of ASB-14 or ASB-16, prepared in PBS, were added to the tubes to produce 1 -5000 pM of each detergent and 50 pM of 5-SASL. Electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectra were recorded in 0.2-mL flat quartz cells, at room temperature, in a Bruker EMS spectrometer, operating at 9 GHz and 3.4 kG.
Isotonic hemolytic assay
Freshly obtained human blood from healthy donors was collected into a stock solution containing 26.3 g/L trisodic citrate, 3.27 g/L citric acid, 31.9 g/L dextrose, 2.2 g/ L sodium phosphate, and 0.275 g/L adenine, and the cell were washed three times in 5 mM PBS buffer, pH 7.4, by centrifugation.
ASB-14 (10-100 pM) or ASB-16 (1-20 pM), prepared in isotonic PBS, pH 7.4, were added to the erythrocyte suspensions (0.15-0.60% hematocrit, diluted in PBS), and the samples were kept for 15 min at 37°C. After centrifugation at 260 g for 3 min, membrane disruption, reported as hemolysis percentage, was measured by the hemoglobin released in the supernatant, as described by Malheiros et al. (17). Each triplicate measurement was carried out on at least two different blood samples.
Solubilization of protein and cholesterol
Blood was collected and cells washed as described above. Packed cells suspended in PBS were filtered through «-cellulose/microcrystalline-cellulose. Ghost membranes were prepared by hypotonic hemolysis, resus-www.bjournal.com.br
759 pending erythrocytes in lysis buffer (5 mM sodium phosphate, 0.5 mM EDTA, 5 mM diisopropyl fluorophosphate, pH 8.0) at 4°C, followed by centrifugation at 26,000 g for 20 min and repeated washings with the same buffer, according to Dodge et al. (18). Protein concentration was determined with bicinchoninic acid (Pierce Biotechnology, USA), using bovine serum albumin as standard.
Purified ghost membranes (1 mg/mL, final protein concentration) were mixed with ASB, CHAPS or Triton X-100, prepared in PBS, for 30 min at 37''C. The samples were then centrifuged at 15,000 g, for 30 min at room temperature and the supernatant solution was used for the measurement of solubilized protein and cholesterol. Cholesterol was measured using a colorimetric assay kit (R-Biopharm Italia srl, Italy; #10139050035) for Iutidine-dye (3,5-diacetyl-1,4-dihydrolutidine), which has a stoichiometric relationship with the amount of cholesterol in the sample and is produced after enzymatic reactions catalyzed by cholesterol oxidase and catalase. Untreated samples of ghosts in PBS were used as control. Triplicate measurements on at least two different blood samples were carried out. The 100% values in Figure 2A,B correspond to the total protein and cholesterol concentrations, respectively, of the untreated ghosts in PBS.
Results and Discussion
Electron paramagnetic resonance experiments and CMC determination
Figure 1 presents the EPR spectra of 5-SASL in PBS buffer (0 ASB-14) and in the presence of increasing concentrations of ASB-14. At low ASB-14 concentrations (up to 75 pM), the isotropic 5-SASL signal refers to the probe in the aqueous phase. Once the CMC of ASB-14 is reached, the spin label increasingly enters the newly formed micelles, giving rise to: 1) spin-spin interactions (mainly visible as changes in the baseline of the spectra at 100 to 150 pM ASB-14), and 2) broad lines and highly anisotropic signals of 5-SASL inside the micelles, easily observed at ASB-14 concentrations greater than 150 pM. In addition, the spin probe signal (area under the peaks) is increased, due to the increased solubility of 5-SASL in the micelles. We have determined the CMC of ASB-14 to be 100 pM. the lowest concentration of detergent in which a spectrum with motional restricted spin label was observed. Similar results were found for ASB-16, but micelle formation was registered at concentrations about 10 times lower (CMC = 10 pM) than that of ASB-14. This is the first report in the literature of the CMC of ASB-14 and ASB-16. The values reported here, in PBS buffer, are quite reasonable compared with the CMC determined for other sulfobetaine
760
zwitterionic homologues, Zwit 3-14 and Zwit 3-16, with equivalent acyl chains: CMC = 121 and 11.3 pM, respectively, in water (19) and 140 and 14 pM, respectively, in 0.1-0.2 M NaCI (20).
HLB is a parameter frequently used to describe the physicochemical properties of non-ionic detergents. Here we have calculated HLB values for ASB-14 and ASB-16, from the ratio of mass between the hydrophilic/hydropho-bic groups on the molecules, according to Griffin (21). Intermediate values (11.6 and 10.9, respectively) reveal the well-balanced amphiphile character of these detergents, the smaller HLB of ASB-16 being due to the contribution of its longer hydrophobic tail.
Solubilization of membrane components
Figure 2A shows that the total amount of proteins solubilized from erythrocyte ghosts by ASB-14 and ASB-16 is higher than that obtained with CHAPS or Triton X100, even at the highest concentrations of detergents tested. This result agrees well with the two dimensional electrophoresis data in the literature that show an improvement in the resolution of many integral membrane proteins (11-16) with ASB-14 and ASB-16 compared with classic detergents such as Triton and CHAPS (22,23). We have tested both detergents in the sample buffer used for twodimensional gel electrophoresis of red blood cells, and the results indicate that different proteins were solubilized by using these detergents, and therefore ASB detergents are useful to achieve a more detailed assignment of the proteins (24).
Figure 2B reports the amount of cholesterol released in the supernatant after treatment of red blood cell membranes with the detergents. It is interesting to note that, under the experimental conditions (starting material containing 1 mg/mL membrane proteins or ca. 1.3 mM total lipids), the maximum amounts of cholesterol solubilized after treatment with ASB-14 or ASB-16 were reached when the detergentJipid molar ratio was approximately 4:1, while for Triton X-100 and CHAPS the ratios were higher (20:1 and 40:1, respectively), indicating that ASB detergents are stronger cholesterol solubilizers.
The higher amounts of cholesterol in the supernatant indicate that ASB detergents did not induce the formation of detergent-resistant membrane (DRM), known to be enriched in cholesterol and sphingolipids, as described for Triton X-100 (25-27), possibly explaining the improved solubilization of proteins eventually involved in DRM (Figure 2A). In addition, preliminary results from our laboratory indicate that a low buoyant density fraction in sucrose gradient was not formed when ASB detergents were used to solubilize erythrocyte membranes at low temperature
C.C. Domingues et al
Figure 1. EPR spectra cf 5-SASL in 5 mM PBS buffer, pH 7.4 (0 ASB-14), and in the presence of increasing ASB-14 concentrations. Line broadening and anisotropic spectra (beyond 150 pM - see text) indicate the critical micelle concentration. Abscissa = 100 gauss windows around the magnetic field center (3.4 kG).
Erythrocyte solubilization by ASB detergents
761
a ■■■■ CHAPS
	f	T	*	*		
	¥	 A		1			
I			
1			
j *			
L-	Í		ASB-14 -■O- •• ASB-16 CHAPS —A-- Triton X-100
Detergent (mM)	Detergent (mM)
Figure 2. Protein (A) and cholesterol (B) content solubilized from erythrocyte ghosts by detergents ASB-14, ASB-16, CHAPS, and Triton X-100. Samples of ghosts containing 1 mg/mL of protein were incubated with the detergents in 5 mM PBS buffer for 30 min at37°C and centrifuged at 15,000 gfor 30 min, at room temperature. Untreated samples of ghosts in PBS were used as control. The 100% values in panels A and B correspond to the total protein and cholesterol concentrations, respectively, in the untreated ghosts’ samples, in PBS.
erythrocytes in 5 mM PBS buffer, pH 7.4, 37°C (15 min) at hematocrits 0.15% (squares), 0.30% (circles), 0.45% (triangles), and 0.60% (inverted triangles). Effective detergent/lipid molar ratios for erythrocyte membranes saturation and solubilization by ASB-14 (C) and ASB-16 (D). The inset in A shows the Csat and Cso1 determination from the hemolytic curve at 0.15% hematocrit. Csat = concentration required to induce membrane saturation (onset of hemolysis); Cso1 = detergent concentration required for total membrane solubilization (100% lysis).
762
C.C. Domingues et al.
(4C'C), indicating their greater power to disrupt the membrane compared with Triton X-100 (Domingues CC, Ciana A, de Paula E, Minetti G, unpublished results).
To further understand the membrane solubilization process, we have applied the quantitative approach proposed by Lichtenberg (2) to analyze ASB-lnduced erythrocyte hemolysis, as follows.
Hemolytic experiments
The hemolytic curves obtained with increasing concentrations of ASB-14 and ASB-16 in erythrocyte suspensions are shown in Figure 3A,B. Membrane disruption, reported as % hemolysis, was determined from the amount of hemoglobin released in the supernatant solution, as previously described (17).
The quantitative analysis of the membrane solubilization process proposed by Lichtenberg (2) was applied to the hemolytic curves, considering Csat and CSD| (inset in Figure 3A) to be the detergent concentration required to
ASB-14, ASB-16 and CHAPS, a classic detergent of identical polar head group but with a steroidic hydrophobic portion (30). The small Csat and Csal values found for ASB-14 and ASB-16 reflect their high capacity to solubilize erythrocyte membranes, being more potent hemolytic agents than CHAPS. The differences in Csal and C5D| values observed between ASB-14 and ASB-16 are consistent with the results reported by Prete et al. (10) within a homologue series of detergents, In which Csat and Cso1 decreased with CxEg polyoxyethylene alkyl ethers of longer hydrocarbon chains. The smaller Csat and Cso1 values found for ASB-16 show that hydrophobic interactions between the detergent acyl chains and the erythrocyte membrane components are strongly involved In the solubilization process.
The hemolytic process induced by detergents could be described as a bllayer-to-mlcelle transition in which, according to Lichtenberg et al. (31), Resat and Resal determine the limits for the coexistence of mixed-membranes and
induce membrane saturation (the onset of hemolysis) and total membrane solubilization (100% lysis), respectively (2,6,10,17,28).
Plots of Csat and Cso1 as a function of membrane lipid concentration (Figure 3C,D) allowed the determination of Re, the effective detergent/lipid molar ratio for initial (Resal) and total hemolysis (Reso1). The straight line obtained in each case is predicted by Equation 1 (8.9):	'
D, = Re[L+1 / Kb(Rs+1)] (Equation 1)
where, Dt is the total detergent concentration (Csat, CSQ|) and L is the lipid concentration in the membrane (28). Re values were calculated from the slope of the resulting straightlines while the y-intercept corresponds to Dw, the concentration of free detergent in water (2,29). Kb (M_1), the molar binding constant of the detergent to the erythrocyte membrane, was derived from Re5at and Dw5at values, according to Equation 2 (2,29):
Re = KbDw/(1-KbDw) (Equation 2)
Table 1 lists the Csat and C5D| values obtained from the hemolytic curves of
Table 1. Hemolytic effect on human erythrocytes induced by ASB-14, ASB-16 and CHAPS.
Ht(L)	Csat			CSO		
	ASB-14 (pM)	ASB-16 (t*M)	CHAPS (mM)	ASB-14 (t*M)	ASB-16 (pM)	CHAPS (mM)
0.15% (13 pM)	27.6	6.0	4.3	45.3	7.8	7.4
0.30% (26 pM)	32.3	7.0	5.6	47.6	10.4	8.4
0.45% (39 pM)	34.7	8.3	5.8	50.7	12.4	8.7
0.60% (52 pM)	36.3	9.1	6.0	57.9	14.0	9.2
Experimental condition as in Figure 3. L = lipid concentration in erythrocyte membranes corresponding to each hematocrit (Ht), calculated according to Malheiros et al. (28). Qsai - concentration required to induce membrane saturation (onset of hemolysis); Cs° = detergent concentration required for total membrane solubilization (100% lysis).
Table 2. Effective detergent/lipid molar ratios and related parameters in the hemolysis of erythrocytes by ASB-14, ASB-16, CHAPS, and Triton X-100.
	ASB-14	ASB-16	CHAPS	Triton X-100b
Re5at	0.22	0.08	40.62	1.58
Re5tjl	0.31	0.16	43.77	2.15
dwse"	25.6 pM	4.9 pM	4.1 mM	0.10 mM
DwsqI	40.2 pM	6.0 pM	7.0 mM	0 18 mM
Kb (M"1)a	7050	15610	236	5900
Experimental conditions as in Figure 3. Re5at = detergent/lipid molar ratio for the onset of hemolysis; Reso1 = detergent/lipid molar ratio for the total lysis; DwSBt = concentration of free detergent in water at the onset of hemolysis: Dwso1 = concentration of free detergent in water at total lysis; K-, = molar binding constant of the detergent to the erythrocyte membrane. aTaken from the saturation curves in Figure 3C,D bData from Prete et al. (6).
Erythrocyte solubilization by ASB detergents mixed-micelles. Table 2 reports the quantitative parameters calculated from the hemolytic curves in Figure 3C,D. The Re values smaller than unit determined for ASB-14 and ASB-16 (Table 2) confirm that these detergents present stronger lytic effects than CHAPS (Re = 40.62; Table 2) or the non-ionic Triton X-100 (Re = 1.58; Ref. 6). In fact, the Re values herein described for the ASB detergents are similar to those reported by Prete et al. (10) for alkyl ether (CXE8) homologues of equivalent acyl chains, but higher HLB.
The binding constants of ASB-14 (7050 M_1) and ASB-16 (15610 M'1) in Table 2 show the different affinities of these detergents to the erythrocyte membrane, explaining their distinct lytic effects (ASB-16 &gt; ASB-14). These results are in good agreement with those previously reported for the CxE8 homologues (10), when a straight relationship between the Kb value and lytic effect was observed.
Moreover, the CMC values found for ASB-14 and ASB-16 disclosed the correlation between the solubilization and the aggregative properties of these detergents (1,4,5,32). Lichtenberg et al. (31) demonstrated that Dw values, the concentration of free detergent in water, are related but always smaller than the CMC values, since the membrane lipids offer an additional driving force for detergent aggregation, decreasing the concentration for micelle formation. By the same reasoning, to have an estimation of the CMC, the values of D,/al are preferable to those of DWSQ|, which may be influenced by the mixed micelles formed at higher detergent concentrations (33). Thus, the Dw values found for ASB-14 and ASB-16 (25.6 and 4.9 pM, respectively; Table 2), are consistent with the CMC values determined from the EPR data. The determined Dw value for CHAPS (4.14 mM) was also smaller than its CMC (6-10 mM; Ref. 34).
According to Heerklotz and Seelig (33), the membrane disruption potency of detergents can be assessed by the relationship between their CMC and binding constants, in which strong detergents (Kb x CMC&amp;lt;1) are able to solubilize lipid membranes at detergent-to-lipid molar ratios smaller than 1. Thus, by applying the product Kb x CMC to classify detergents according to their membrane disruption potency (33), ASB-14 and ASB-16 can be designated as strong detergents, and their Re values (Table 2) smaller than 1 corroborate this classification.
This research shows that ASB-14 and ASB-16 present a high affinity to the erythrocyte membrane, being a useful tool for the solubilization of its components (both proteins and lipids), compared to classic detergents such as CHAPS or Triton X-100. Our results suggest that the relationship between membrane disruption efficiency (Table 2) and the physicochemical properties of ASB detergents (CMC, HLB) can explain the improvement in the solubilization of membrane proteins, as described in proteomic research papers (11-16,22,23).
To further understand their role in the specific solubilization of membrane proteins and lipids, other experiments are being conducted by our group to evaluate the effect of ASB-14 and ASB-16 on the formation/disruption of DRM from erythrocyte membranes, using specific lipid raft markers.
Acknowledgments
We thank Dr. S. Schreier for the use of the EPR facilities and Dr. G. Minetti for kindly supplying the kits used for cholesterol and protein measurement.
References
1.	Helenius A, Simons K. Solubilization of membranes by detergents. Biochim Biophys Acta 1975; 415: 29-79.
2.	Lichtenberg D. Characterization of the solubilization of lipid bilayers by surfactants. Biochim Biophys Acta 1985; 821: 470-478.
3.	Lasch J. Interaction of detergents with lipid vesicles. Biochim Biophys Acta 1995; 1241: 269-292.
4.	Jones MN. Surfactants in membrane solubilisation. Int J Pharm 1999; 177: 137-159.
5.	Schreier S, Malheiros SV, de Paula E. Surface active drugs: self-association and Interaction with membranes and surfactants. Physicochemical and biological aspects. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000; 1508: 210-234.
6.	Prete PS, Malheiros SV, Meirelles NC, de Paula E. Quantitative assessment of human erythrocyte membrane solubilization by Triton X-100. Biophys Chem 2002; 97: 1-5.
7.	le Maire M, Champeil P. Moller JV. Interaction of membrane proteins and lipids with solubilizing detergents. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000: 1 508: 86-111
8.	Partearroyo MA. Urbaneja MA, Goni FM. Effective deter-gent/lipid ratios in the solubilization of phosphatidylcholine vesicles by Triton X-100. FEBS Lett 1992; 302: 138-140
9.	Requero MA, Goni FM, Alonso A. The membrane-perturbing properties of palmitoyl-coenzyme A and palmitoylcarnitine. A comparative study. Biochemistry 1995; 34: 1040010405.
10.	Prete PS, Gomes K. Malheiros SV, Meirelles NC, de Paula E. Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by nonionic surfactants of the polyoxyethylene alkyl ethers series. Biophys Chem 2002; 97: 45-54.
11.	Chevallet M, Santoni V, Poinas A. Rouquie D, Fuchs A, Kieffer S, et al. New zwitterionic detergents improve the
764
C.C. Domingues et al
analysis of membrane proteins by two-dimensional electrophoresis. Electrophoresis 1998; 19: 1901-1909.
12.	Rabilloud T, Blisnick T, Heller M, Luche S, Aebersold R. Lunardi J, et al. Analysis of membrane proteins by twodimensional electrophoresis: comparison of the proteins extracted from normal or Plasmodium falciparum-mfected erythrocyte ghosts. Electrophoresis 1999; 20: 3603-3610.
13.	Starita-Geribaldi M, Thebault P, Taffin de Givenchy E, Guittard F, Geribaldi S. 2-DE using hemi-fluorinated surfactants. Electrophoresis 2007; 28: 2489-2497.
14.	Molloy MP, Herbert BR. Williams KL, Gooley AA. Extraction of Escherichia coli proteins with organic solvents prior to two-dimensional electrophoresis. Electrophoresis 1999; 20: 701-704.
15.	Hennlngsen R, Gale BL, Straub KM, DeNagel DC. Application of zwitterionic detergents to the solubilization of integral membrane proteins for two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and mass spectrometry. Proteomics 2002; 2: 1479-1488.
16.	He J, Liu Y, He S. Wang Q, Pu H, Ji J. Proteomic analysis of a membrane skeleton fraction from human liver. JProteome Res 2007; 6: 3509-3518.
17.	Malheiros SV, de Paula E, Meirelles NC. Contribution of trifluoperazine/lipid ratio and drug ionization to hemolysis. Biochim Biophys Acta 1998: 1373: 332-340.
18.	Dodge JT. Mitchell C, Hanahan DJ. The preparation and chemical characteristics of hemogicbln-free ghosts of human erythrocytes. Arch Biochem Biophys 1963; 100: 119130.
19.	Walter A, Kuehl G, Barnes K, VanderWaerdt G. The vesicle-to-micelle transition of phosphatidylcholine vesicles induced by nonionic detergents: effects of sodium chloride, sucrose and urea. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000; 1508: 20-33.
20.	Brito RM, Vaz WL. Determination of the critical micelle concentration of surfactants using the fluorescent probe N-phenyl-1 -naphthylamine. Anal Biochem 1986; 152: 250-255.
21.	Griffin WC. Classification of surface-active agents by HLB. J Soc Cosmet Chem 1949: 1: 311 -326.
22.	Martins D, Oliveira BM, Farias AS, Horiuchi RSO, Domingues CC, de Paula E, et al. The use of ASB-14 in combination with CHAPS is the best for solubilization of human brain proteins for two-dimensional gel electrophoresis. Brief Fund Genomic Proteomic 2007 6: 70-75.
23.	Di Cero L, Bellato CM, Meinhardt LW, Ferrari F, Castellari RR, Marangoni S, et al. Assessment of four different detergents used to extract membrane proteins from Xylella fastidiosa by two-dimensional electrophoresis. Braz J Microbiol 2004; 35: 269-274.
24.	Domingues CC, Cunha ES. Winck FV, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E. Avaliação de detergentes na solubilização de proteínas de membrana eritrocitária humana em eletroforese bidimensional. Rev Ciências Biol Saúde 2007; 2: 38-46.
25.	Pike LJ. Lipid rafts: heterogeneity on the high seas. Biochem J 2004; 378: 281 -292.	'
26.	Ciana A, Balduini C, Minetti G. Detergent-resistant membranes in human erythrocytes and their connection to the membrane-skeleton. J Biosci 2005; 30: 317-328.
27.	Kamata K, Manno S, Ozaki M, Takakuwa Y. Functicna evidence for presence of lipid rafts in erythrocyte membranes: Gsalpha in rafts is essential for signal transduction. Am J Hematol 2008: 83: 371-375.
28.	Malheiros SV, Meirelles NC, de Paula E. Pathways involved in trifluoperazine-, dibucaine- and praziquantel-induced hemolysis. Biophys Chem 2000; 83: 89-100.
29.	Lichtenberg D. Micelles and liposomes. In: Shimitzky M (Editor), Book review: Biomembranes. Physical aspects. Weinheim: VCH; 1993. p 63-96.
30.	Attwood D, Florence AT. Surfactant systems: Their chemistry. pharmacy and biology. 2nd edn. London: Chapman and Hall; 1983.
31.	Lichtenberg □, Opatowski E, Kozlov MM. Phase boundaries in mixtures of membrane-forming amphiphiles and micelle-forming amphiphiles. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000; 1508: 1-19.
32.	Tragner D. Csordas A. Biphasic interaction of Triton deter-
gents with the erythrocyte membrane. Biochem J 1987; 244: 605-609.	'
33.	Heerklotz H, Seelig J. Correlation of membrane/water partition coefficients of detergents with the critical micelle concentration. Biophys J 2000; 78: 2435-2440.
34.	Chattopadhyay A. Harikumar KG. Dependence of critica micelle concentration of a zwitterionic detergent on ionic strength: implications in receptor solubilization. FEBS Lett 1996: 391: 199-202.
Parte 2: DRMs de eritrocitos obtidas com uso de Triton X-100 e C12E8
Artigo 1:
Domingues CC, Ciana A, Buttafava A, Balduini C, de Paula E, Minetti G (2008) Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8. J. Membr. Biol. DOI 10.1007/s00232-008-9142-4.
Resistance of Human Erythrocyte Membranes to Triton X-100 and Ci2E8
Cleyton Crepaldi Domingues • Annarita Ciana •
Armando Buttafava * Cesare Balduini •
Eneida de Paula • Giampaolo Minetti
Received: 12 September 2008/Accepted: 11 November 2008 © Springer Science+Business Media, LLC 2008
Abstract Lipid rafts are microdomains enriched in cholesterol and sphingolipids that contain specific membrane proteins. The resistance of domains to extraction by nonionic detergents at 4°C is the commonly used method to characterize these structures that are operationally defined as detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs). Because the selectivity of different detergents in defining membrane rafts has been questioned, we have compared DRMs from human erythrocytes prepared with two detergents: Triton X-100 and Cj2E8. The DRMs obtained presented a cholesterol/protein mass ratio three times higher than in the whole membrane. Flotillin-2 was revealed in trace amounts in DRMs obtained with C12E8, but it was almost completely confined within the DRM fraction with Triton X100. Differently, stomatin was found distributed in DRM and non-DRM fractions for both detergents. We have also measured the order parameter (5) of nitroxide spin labels inserted into DRMs by means of electron paramagnetic resonance. The 5- and 16-stearic acid spin label revealed significantly higher S' values for DRMs obtained with either Triton X-100 or C12E8 in comparison to intact cells, while the difference in the 5 values between Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs was not statistically significant. Our results
C. Crepaldi Domingues ■ E. de Paula
Departamento de Bioquímica, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas, SP, Brazil
A. Ciana • C. Balduini • G. Minetti (El)
Dipartimento di Biochimica “A. Castellani”, Università di Pavia, Via Bassi, 21, 27100 Pavia, Italy e-mail: minetti@unipv.it
A. Buttafava
Dipartimento di Chimica Generale, Università di Pavia, Pavia, Italy
suggest that although the acyl chain packing is similar in DRMs prepared with either Triton X-100 or Cj2E8 detergent, protein content is dissimilar, with flotillin-2 being selectively enriched in Triton X-100 DRMs.
Keywords Detergent-resistant membrane • Lipid raft • Membrane-skeleton ■ EPR • Nitroxide spin label • Flotillin
Introduction
Lipid rafts are transient membrane microdomains observed in vivo that are rich in cholesterol, sphingolipids, and specific membrane proteins (Simons and Ikonen 1997; Brown and London 1998; Simons and Vaz 2004; Pike 2004; Lichtenberg et al. 2005). These membrane rafts, which exist in a liquid-ordered phase (Lichtenberg et al. 2005; Delaunay et al. 2007), have been implicated in numerous cellular functions, such as signal transduction, endocytosis, parasite or virus infection, and vesicular and cholesterol trafficking (Samuel et al. 2001; Haidar et al. 2002; de Gassart et al. 2003; Pike 2004, 2006).
In the last few years, different techniques have been suggested to study lipid rafts, but the vast majority of reports describing the properties of these structures are based on methods that involve their extraction with nonionic detergents at 4°C (Brown and Rose 1992; Schuck et al. 2003; Pike 2004). In this way, the operational definition for rafts as detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) has been widely accepted. While, on the one hand, the detergent-soluble membrane fraction obtained by this treatment is enriched in phospholipids containing unsaturated acyl chains, on the other, DRMs are enriched in sphingolipids that, because of their saturated acyl chains,
strongly contribute to a more organized bi layer environment.
Although different studies with DRMs from erythrocyte cells have been reported (Samuel et al. 2001; Salzer and Prohaska 2001; Nagao et al. 2002; Salzer et al. 2002; Murphy et al. 2004, 2007; Ciana et al. 2005), the association of rafts with membrane-skeletal proteins, the cholesterol regulation of the raft’s protein content, and the role of rafts in erythrocyte function are topics that remain unclear (Grzybek et al. 2006). An optimized method to prepare DRMs from ghost membranes has been described by our group (Ciana et al. 2005), and these results strongly suggest the association of DRMs to the erythrocyte membrane-skeleton. More recently, the contribution of rafts to Gsa-mediated signal transduction in erythrocyte membranes has been evidenced (Kamata et al. 2008).
Qualitative and quantitative differences in the properties of DRMs are observed by the use of different detergents (Schuck et al. 2003; Pike 2004). Nonionic detergents are very useful in membrane studies because of their capacity to solubilize the lipid bilayer without affecting important structural features, and Triton X-100 is a classical nonionic detergent used in the majority of DRM studies so far. In the present study, we have isolated, characterized, and compared DRMs obtained from human erythrocytes with two nonionic detergents, Triton X-100 and Ci2E8. The use of CJ2E8, in particular, is very common for the solubilization, crystallization, and reconstitution of membrane proteins (Rigaud et al. 1995; le Maire et al. 2000; Santos et al. 2002). It has been used for extracting erythrocytes’ band 3 because of its capacity to preserve the in vivo oligomeric state of the protein (Casey and Reithmeier 1991). Furthermore, the lytic effect of the Ci2E8 occurs in the same range of that of Triton X-100 because their physicochemical properties, such as molecular weight, critical micellar concentration, and hydrophilic/lipophilic balance, are very similar (Prete et al. 2002). We show here that flotillin-2 was found only in the DRMs obtained with Triton X-100.
Moreover, to our knowledge, for the first time, electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) was used to characterize purified DRMs (isolated in a sucrose gradient) obtained from erythrocytes. The results indicate that the acyl chain packing is similar in DRMs prepared with the two detergents.
Methods
Preparation of Erythrocyte Membranes
Blood was collected from normal human donors after informed consent was obtained. Blood was mixed with 0.1 volumes of 3.8% (w/v) sodium citrate. After centrifugation
at 1000g, the plasma was removed and the packed cells were suspended in an equal volume of phosphate-buffered saline (5 m.\i Na-phosphate, 154.5 mM NaCl, 4.5 mM KC1, 300 mOsmol/kg H2O, pH 7.4). The suspension was then filtered through a-cellulose/microcrystalline cellulose to isolate erythrocytes from platelets and leukocytes (Beutler et al. 1976). The purified erythrocyte suspension was washed three times in phosphate-buffered saline, and the packed cells were used to prepare DRMs. For the preparation of ghost membranes, the purified erythrocytes were mixed with 10 volumes of hypotonic phosphate buffer (5 mM Na-phosphate, 0.5 mM EDTA, 5 mM di-isopropyl fluorophosphate, pH 8.0) at 4°C, followed by centrifugation at 26,000g; the supernatant was discharged and the washing repeated four times with the same buffer, according to Dodge et al. (1963).
Preparation of DRMs
DRMs were prepared either from intact erythrocytes or ghost membranes following a previously detailed protocol (Ciana et al. 2005). Briefly, the packed cells (approximately 1.25 x 109 cells) were incubated with TNE buffer (25 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.4) containing Triton X-100 or Ci2E8, so that the final volume was 0.625 ml and the final detergent concentration 16 mM, and the detergent/lipid molar ratio approximately 12. After 30 min, the sample was mixed with an equal volume of 80% sucrose solution in TNE containing 0.3 m Na2CO8. The sample was then transferred to ultracentrifuge tubes, and 2.5 ml of a 30% sucrose solution in TNE was gently layered on top of the sample, followed by 1.25 ml of a 5% sucrose solution in TNE. All procedures were conducted at 4°C, and the samples were subjected to ultracentrifugation in a bench-top ultracentrifuge (Optima Max, equipped with a swinging-arm MLS50 rotor, Beckman Coulter, Milan, Italy) at 225,000gmax for 16 h at 4°C. The top 1 ml was collected as the first fraction. Proceeding down the gradient, fractions 2-6 were collected as 0.8-ml aliquots and saved for subsequent characterization. Fractions 2 and 3 contain the low-density material corresponding to DRMs. DRMs from ghost membranes were prepared by using the same protocol; samples of ghost membranes were treated with the detergent so that the final protein concentration was set to 1.0 mg/ml.
Cholesterol was quantified with a colorimetric assay kit (N. 10139050035, R-Biopharm Italia Sri, Milan, Italy), directly on a suitable dilution of ghost membranes and DRMs, and after lipid extraction of whole erythrocytes (Rose and Oklander 1965). Protein content was determined with bicinchoninic acid (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, IL) with bovine serum albumin used as a standard.
Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate-Polyacrylamide Gel Electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and Western Blot Testing
Samples were separated in 10% SDS-PAGE gels according to Laemmli (1970). The gels were either stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue or electrophoretically transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes. Membranes were blocked for 1 h in TNE containing 5% skim milk and 0.05% Tween-20, then incubated with the relevant primary antibody: mouse monoclonal anti-flotillin-2 (BD Italia, Milan, Italy), goat polyclonal anti-human stomatin and mouse monoclonal (BRIC 10) anti-human glycophorin C (GPC) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, Germany), mouse monoclonal anti-human band 3 (Sigma-Aldrich, Milan, Italy), and mouse polyclonal antiprotein 4.1 (Abnova Corporation, Taipei, Taiwan). The membranes were then washed and incubated with the appropriate peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody; proteins were revealed with the Amersham ECL Western blotting kit (GE Healthcare, Milan, Italy). For the quantitative Western blot technique described in Fig. 5, densitometric quantification of the protein bands on digital images of the photographic films was performed by the software Scion Image (Scion Corporation, Frederick, MD).
EPR Experiments
The 7?-doxyl-stearic acid spin labels, SASL probes (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO) with n = 5 or 16, were incorporated up to approximately 2 mol% of lipids into the DRM fractions by 30-min incubation at room temperature. The EPR spectra were recorded at 20-25°C and 9.4 GHz in a Broker EMX (X band) spectrometer. For the SASL probes, whose long molecular axis is approximately parallel to the bilayer normal, the order parameter (5) was calculated according to Eq. 1:
S =______2A// — 2A-L______
2[A=- (A„+Avv)/2]
where A// and A± are the hyperfine splittings corresponding to spin labels whose long molecular axes are oriented approximately parallel or perpendicular, respectively, to the external magnetic field. From oriented SASL spectra (as in the membrane), the hyperfine splittings can be directly determined as half the separation between the outer and the inner extrema, respectively (Hubbel and McConnel 1971), as exemplified in Fig. 6. Axx, Ayy (6.0 G each), and Azz (32.0 G) are the values of the principal components of the hyperfine tensor (Griffith and Jost 1976), determined in a rightly oriented sample. The order parameter is related to the tilt angle of the acyl chains and to trans-gauche distribution of chain dihedrals, but the
relationship is indirect. The larger the value of 5, the smaller the amplitude of motion and the more ordered the lipid chains (Schreier et al. 1978).
Results
Characterization of Cholesterol and Protein Content of DRMs Obtained from Whole Erythrocytes with Triton X-100 and C12E8
To compare DRMs obtained with the two different detergents, the purified insoluble materials were prepared using the same detergent/lipid molar ratio (12:1) as described in Materials and Methods.
Figure 1 shows the DRM material (interface between 5% and 30% sucrose) obtained from ghost membranes (tubes 1 and 2) and intact cells (tubes 3 and 4) with each detergent. Visually, one can observe that a more diffuse band was formed when C^Eg was used, revealing density differences in comparison to that obtained with Triton X100. In spite of this difference, the DRM bands from ghosts and intact erythrocytes were very similar when the same detergent was used. Furthermore, as opposed to what may be observed in Fig. 1, DRMs did not float to the 5-30% sucrose interface when sodium carbonate was not present after the treatment with the detergent (data not shown).
The cholesterol and protein contents of the isolated low-density material (Fig. 1) were determined, and the results
Fig. 1 Sucrose density gradients after centrifugation of detergent-treated ghost membranes (tubes 1 and 2) and whole erythrocytes (tubes 3 and 4). Tubes 1 and 3 contain samples treated with Triton X100; tubes 2 and 4 contain samples treated with C12E8. The arrow indicates the position of the DRMs. The percentages to the right indicate the sucrose concentration of the various layers. The dark color present in the bottom (40% sucrose) of the tubes 3 and 4 is due to the presence of hemoglobin released after detergent treatment. The image is representative of at least five independent experiments with similar results
Fig. 2 Quantification of cholesterol content (a) and cholesterol/ protein ratio (b) of DRM fractions 2 and 3, obtained with Triton X-100 and C12E8. The cholesterol in (a) was quantified in 1.25 x 109 intact erythrocytes or in a volume of ghost membranes corresponding to 0.625 mg protein (control), and in the DRMs obtained after centrifugation of the given amounts of starting material. Error bars revealed that for both detergents, approximately 30% of total cholesterol of the original samples (ghosts or intact cells) was recovered in the DRM fractions 2 and 3 (Fig. 2a). No differences were detected when DRMs were prepared with Triton X-100 or Ci2Eg.
A remarkable feature of the DRMs is their increased cholesterol-to-protein mass ratio with respect to the parent cell membrane. When DRMs were obtained from ghost membranes, there was no significant difference in the cholesterol-to-protein mass ratio of the DRM fractions between the detergents used (Fig. 2b). Although the cho-lesterol-to-protein mass ratio is smaller in Ci2E8 DRMs prepared with intact cells, we observed a 3-fold increase in this ratio for all DRM fractions obtained with that detergent, in comparison to intact cells or ghost membranes (controls, Fig. 2b).
Figure 3 shows the distribution of different proteins in Triton X-100 and CJ2E8 DRMs from whole erythrocytes; no differences were observed when ghosts or intact cells were treated with the same detergent (data not shown). The distribution of the raft markers flotillin-2 and stomatin was very different: whereas stomatin was recovered in both soluble and insoluble (Triton X-100 and Ci2E8 DRMs) fractions, flotillin-2 was highly enriched in Triton X-100 DRMs and poorly detected in Cj2E8 DRMs. Band 3 and GPC show up as a barely visible signal in Western blots of DRMs obtained with Triton X-100, and are not detected when C12Eg is used (Fig. 3). A more quantitative estimation of the band 3 and GPC content in DRMs obtained with Triton X-100 was carried out here by quantitative Western blot testing using carefully prepared purified ghost membranes as a standard for building calibration curves. As shown in Fig. 4, band 3 content in DRMs is approximately 2% and GPC content 3%, with respect to the content of each protein in the intact cell membrane. The same
represent the standard deviation (n = 3). The amount of membrane proteins present in intact erythrocytes in B (control) was estimated according to the lipid:membrane-protein mass ratio (1:1.2) and the total membrane lipid concentration, according to Dodge et al. (1963) and Malheiros et al. (2000)
Fig. 3 Distribution of flotillin-2 (flot-2), stomatin (stom), band 3, GPC, and protein 4.1 (4.1) in different sucrose density fractions numbered from top to bottom. Fractions 2 and 3 correspond to DRMs obtained from whole erythrocytes with Triton X-100 (left) and Cj2E8 (right). Results are representative of five independent experiments
quantification for DRMs obtained with CJ2Eg was not conducted because of the much lower band 3 and GPC content in these samples (see Fig. 3).
Interestingly, we found that membrane-skeletal proteins, such as spectrin, actin and protein 4.1, were present in both Triton X-100 and Cj2Eg DRMs (Figs. 3 and 5). The presence of these proteins in erythrocyte DRMs is also a matter of debate in the literature. It was previously observed by others (Murphy et al. 2004) that membrane-skeletal proteins tend to associate to the DRMs when a relatively low detergent-to-protein ratio is used during the solubilization of erythrocyte ghosts with Triton X-100. However, in our hands, membrane-skeletal proteins are detected in variable amounts depending on the blood sample, even when DRMs are extracted by a relatively high detergent-to-protein ratio,
ghosts (%)
Fig. 5 SDS-PAGE of proteins present in the DRM fractions 2 and 3 prepared from whole erythrocytes with Triton X-100 (lanes 2 and 3) and C12E8 (lanes 4 and 5). Lane 1 corresponds to an amount of ghost sample proportional to the total amount loaded for the DRM fractions 2 and 3. Results are representative of three independent experiments
ghosts (%)
Fig. 4 Quantification by Western blotting of band 3 and GPC in DRMs obtained from whole erythrocytes with Triton X-100. Purified ghost membranes were prepared from an aliquot of erythrocytes with particular attention to avoid loss of cells during the preparation, so that the final suspension of white ghosts contained the same amount of cells. DRMs were prepared from whole erythrocytes. In the SDS-PAGE gels, appropriate amounts of ghost membranes were loaded as calibration curves suitably chosen to comprise the intensity signal of the unknown DRM samples, as determined in preliminary tests. The calibration curves are labeled in percent, meaning the percentage of protein with respect to that present in the whole cell membrane. After transfer to PVDF membranes, the protein of interest was revealed by immunodetection with chemiluminescence. The integrated densities of the corresponding bands in the photographic films were measured and the calibration curves were used to extrapolate the amount of protein in the unknown samples. In the images shown, for band 3, two calibration curves and two different DRM samples (two replicate lanes for each experiment) are shown from independent experiments loaded in the same gel; for GPC, one calibration curve and two lanes loaded with DRMs from the same experiment are shown. The image is representative of four independent experiments for band 3, and three independent experiments for GPC. The mean ± SD of the values obtained for the protein content in DRMs, expressed as the percentage of the content in the original cell membrane, were band 3,
at which Murphy et al. (2004) did not observe membrane-skeletal proteins in DRMs (Ciana et al. 2005).
EPR Spectroscopy of DRMs Obtained from Whole
Erythrocytes with Triton X-100 and C^Eg
To investigate the acyl chain packing in the DRMs, we have monitored two different regions of the bi layer by means of the spin probes 5- and 16-SASL.
Figure 6 shows the EPR spectra of 5-SASL in erythrocyte membranes, as well as in Triton X-100 and Ci2Eg DRMs disclosing the measure of the outer and inner extrema (2A/7 and 2A±). 5-SASL sensed a highly ordered region of the membrane, with S control values around 0.76. There is no significant difference in 5 values between whole erythrocytes and purified ghost membranes, nor between the DRMs obtained from them, when Triton X100 was used (Table 1). The 5 values in DRMs were significantly higher (&gt;0.82) than those from intact membranes (P &amp;lt;0.001), showing an increase in the orientation of the
acyl chains (increased order) consistent with the liquid-ordered state of the DRMs. Furthermore, no significant difference (P &gt; 0.05; n = 5) was observed between S values of DRMs obtained from intact cells extracted by Triton X-100 and by Ci2E8 (Table 1).
As Table 1 shows, 16-SASL monitored a less organized region of the membrane so that 5 values lower than those obtained with 5-SASL were found for control samples and their respective DRMs obtained with either Triton X-100 or Ci2Eg. The small order parameters reflect the increased trans-gauche isomerization of the acyl chain at deeper acyl chain positions, as expected from the profile of acyl chain
Fig. 6 EPR spectra of 5-SASL in whole erythrocytes (a), Triton X100 DRMs (b), and C12E8 DRMs (c). Results are representative of five independent experiments
Table 1 Order parameters (S) obtained from electron paramagnetic resonance spectra of the spin labels 5- and 16-SASL in ghost membranes, intact erythrocytes, and their respective detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) prepared with Triton X-100 or C12E8a
Sample	c '-’control	SDRM Triton X-100	Sdrm C12E8
5-SASL			
Ghosts	0.759 ± 0.016	0.823 ± 0.014**	ND
Intact cells 16-SASL	0.762 ± 0.009	0.836 ± 0.005**	0.827 ± 0.017**
Ghosts	0.277 ± 0.009	0.321 ± 0.004*	ND
Intact cells	0.268 ± 0.001	0.319 ± 0.001**	0.302 ± 0.002*
* P &amp;lt;0.01, ** P &amp;lt;0.001 (paired Student’s i-test, n = 3-5)
a Data are expressed as mean ± SD. Statistical differences are between DRMs versus control samples (ghosts or intact cells). ND, not determined
order (Seelig 1977). As for 5-SASL, an increase in the orientation of the acyl chains sensed by 16-SASL was observed in the DRMs obtained with both detergents, as reflected by higher S' values measured in DRMs with respect to the parent cell membrane (Table 1).
Discussion
Studies with DRMs from human erythrocytes have been reported, showing that variations in the protocols and/or some maneuvers result in DRMs with different properties. For other cell types, the use of different detergents has been suggested to produce differences in the properties of DRMs (Schuck et al. 2003; Pike 2004). To isolate DRMs from human erythrocytes, Triton X-100 has been the only detergent tested so far. In the present study, we compare DRMs obtained with Triton X-100 and C^Eg, which are strongly lytic nonionic detergents (Prete et al. 2002).
The use of sodium carbonate in addition to the nonionic detergent for the isolation of DRMs from erythrocytes has only been described by Nagao et al. (2002) and by our group (Ciana et al. 2005), and it has been shown to aid in isolating DRMs containing only integral membrane proteins (Salzer and Prohaska 2001) as an alternative to otherwise effective methods not requiring carbonate in addition to the detergent (Samuel et al. 2001; Murphy et al. 2004; Wilkinson et al. 2007; Kamata et al. 2008). The isolation of DRMs from rabbit erythrocytes has also been described to require carbonate (Motoyama et al. 2006). The inclusion of EDTA in the solubilization buffers has been suggested as a possible cause for the failure in isolating DRMs without carbonate (Wilkinson et al. 2007). However, some of the published methods that do not involve carbonate also include EDTA in their buffers (Samuel et al. 2001; Murphy et al. 2004; Kamata et al. 2008). Moreover, in our hands, the simple omission of EDTA does not permit to isolate DRMs in the low-density region of the gradient without carbonate (not shown). The question as to why some methods do allow isolating DRMs without the use of carbonate is thus still open. Our results strongly suggest that both for intact erythrocytes and ghost membranes, sodium carbonate helps to disrupt possible electrostatic interactions between DRMs and the mem brane-skeleton.
Approximately 30% of total cholesterol of the original samples (ghosts or intact cells) was recovered in the isolated DRMs (Fig. 2a), a finding that agrees well with previous reports (Murphy et al. 2004; Ciana et al. 2005). Moreover, a remarkable increase in the cholesterol-toprotein mass ratio (Fig. 2b) was observed in DRMs obtained from both detergent treatments. These results show that DRMs are cholesterol enriched relative to intact
membranes, thus exhibiting characteristics consistent with the properties of membrane rafts.
DRMs from erythrocytes have been reported as enriched in proteins such as flotillin-1, flotillin-2, stomatin, Gsa, a number of glycosyl-phosphatidyl-inositol (GPI)-linked proteins and the ganglioside GM 1 (Salzer and Prohaska 2001; Ciana et al. 2005; Wilkinson et al. 2007; Kamata et al. 2008). Although the cholesterol results presented here revealed no differences between Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs, we wondered whether integral and/or membrane-skeletal proteins would be differentially solubilized by each detergent.
One of the remarkable results of the application of the solubilization at 4°C with nonionic detergents of the erythrocyte membrane is the almost complete exclusion of band 3 protein from the DRMs (Ciana et al. 2005). Although the presence of band 3 as a significant component of DRM fractions has only been reported by Murphy et al. (2004), our evidence is in good agreement with that of other groups (Salzer and Prohaska 2001; Wilkinson et al. 2007), and we observed the same results with CJ2E8, which better preserves the oligomeric state of band 3 (Casey and Reithmeier 1991) (Figs. 3 and 4). This evidence is striking in view of the fact that band 3 is the most abundant integral protein of the erythrocyte membrane, and a significant portion of the membrane itself is detergent resistant (when considering that DRMs contain approximately 30% of the whole membrane cholesterol), yet DRMs remain virtually band 3-free. GPC is also strongly depleted in DRMs. We concluded provisionally from our previous work (Ciana et al. 2005) that band 3 is only present in trace amounts in DRMs obtained from ghosts with Triton X-100, and that it is therefore unlikely that band 3 could significantly contribute to the anchoring of DRMs to the membraneskeleton. Although it could be reconsidered, after the results of the quantification presented here, the possibility that a low but significant percent of band 3 and GPC in DRMs could be responsible for their carbonate-sensitive linkage to the membrane-skeleton, the fact that DRMs obtained with CJ2E8 lack band 3 and GPC and yet can be obtained in similar amounts (expressed as cholesterol content) as with Triton X-100 only when carbonate is used, seems to rule out this possibility.
Three models for the structure of rafts have been proposed by Pike (2004) to account for the observed experimental results. In model I, a lipid raft has a layered structure with a central core (enriched in cholesterol and sphingolipids) surrounded by layers of decreasing lipid order. The detergents act on this type of raft by solubilizing the layers, eventually leaving an insoluble portion that is more or less enriched in cholesterol/sphingolipids depending on the detergent. In model II, rafts have a homogeneous composition and detergents act by selectively
extracting some components (lipids and proteins) and leaving others as insoluble material. In model III, rafts are heterogeneous, i.e. different populations of rafts, with distinct lipid and protein composition, coexist in the membrane. The detergents, according to their strength and selectivity, solubilize some populations while leaving others as insoluble membranes.
The data presented here on the differential distribution of flotillin, stomatin, band 3, and GPC in DRMs obtained with Triton X-100 and Cj2E8, can be discussed within the tripartite modelization described above. Thus, if layered domains (model I) or homogeneous domains (model II) existed in the erythrocyte membrane, then CJ2E8 would seem more powerful than Triton X-100 in solubilizing those layers where the above-cited proteins should be preferentially located (or to selectively extract lipids and proteins in the model of homogeneous domains), leaving a detergent-resistant portion that is depleted of those proteins. If heterogeneous microdomains existed in the membrane (model III), represented by flotillin-containing and flotillin-free domains, then Triton X-100 would seem less selective than Ci2E8 in solubilizing them, as it leaves, as detergent-resistant material, populations of DRMs that contain the mentioned protein, which is instead solubilized by Cj2E8. On the other hand, within model III, if C12E8 permitted the solubilization of only a subset of heterogeneous rafts (those which contain flotillin), then the amount of DRMs obtained should be less with Cj2E8 than with Triton X-100, which is not the case here, as approximately 30% of the cell membrane cholesterol is isolated as DRMs, with both detergents. Therefore, from this evidence it is not possible to propend for one of the models proposed to represent the lipid microdomains in the membrane, except, possibly, for model III. Further studies are needed to better understand the nature of these entities—for example, through immunological separation of DRMs obtained with a single detergent using antibodies against different protein species.
Recently, Wilkinson et al. (2007) have suggested that stomatin and actin are associated in rafts from erythrocytes, having a regulatory function in Ca2+-induced vesiculation. In this way, the presence of actin in the DRM fractions prepared here (Fig. 5) is quite reasonable. The residual, variable content of membrane-skeletal proteins in our samples is difficult to explain, mainly in view of the fact that the supposed electrostatic interactions between them and the DRMs should be disrupted by the inclusion of carbonate in the solubilization medium. Moreover, high donor-to-donor variability has been observed in this respect during our study. What is invariant, however, in our experience, is the requirement of carbonate for the reproducible isolation of DRMs, which has led us to propose that DRMs in the erythrocyte interact electrostatically with the
membrane-skeleton (Ciana et al. 2005). One of the variables that has been suggested to modulate the interaction of DRMs with submembranous structures is the presence of the divalent cations Ca2+ and Mg2+ (Macdonald and Pike 2005; Parkin et al. 1996). However, a systematic investigation of the impact of the intracellular ionic composition on the interaction between the lipid bilayer and the underlying cytoskeleton, has not been conducted, so far. Thus, it would be possible that a subtle mechanism, regulating the supramolecular structure of the membraneskeleton, on the one hand, and its interaction with domains of the lipid bilayer on the other, involved intracellular divalent cations and be at the basis of the observed variability in the amount of DRM-associated membrane-skeletal proteins. The importance of intracellular cations would be even more relevant for this cell type, where oscillations in the concentration of free magnesium ions occur at each oxygenation/deoxygenation cycle of hemoglobin. This aspect is now under study in our laboratory.
In order to further characterize the DRMs obtained from erythrocytes, we have used EPR spectroscopy with spin-labeled lipid molecules, an approach widely used to probe the order and dynamics of lipid bi layers and biological membranes (Cassera et al. 2002; Sulkowski et al. 2006; Rivas and Gennaro 2003; Rodi et al. 2006).
We have shown before in model membranes that S values measured at 22°C from the 5-SASL spectra in egg phosphatidylcholine (PC) liposomes (S = 0.66) (de Paula and Schreier 1995) increased (S = 0.78) in the presence of cholesterol (4:3 mol% egg PC:cholesterol) (Cereda et al. 2004), what is expected from the cholesterol effect in the liquid crystalline phase (McMullen et al. 1993). The order parameter of intact erythrocyte membranes ghosts, measured with 5-SASL (S' = 0.76, Table 1) is in good agreement with previous reports in the literature (Rivas and Gennaro 2003). Thus, although the lipid packing in erythrocyte membranes could be comparable to that of egg PC:cholesterol liposomes, the high cholesterol content of the DRMs (as shown in Fig. 2) and the saturated acyl chains of the sphingolipids justify the higher molecular orientation of the detergent resistant fragments (Table 1), in the liquid ordered phase. Our EPR results with spin labels at different membrane depths revealed significantly higher 5 values in DRMs purified in a sucrose gradient with either Triton X-100 or CJ2E8, in comparison to intact cells. Other works have also reported increased 5 and Amax (2A//) values in EPR spectra from 5- and 16-SASL incorporated in insoluble pellets prepared from erythrocytes treated with cold Triton X-100 (Rivas and Gennaro 2003; Rodi et al. 2006). However, those authors did not use a sucrose gradient to isolate DRMs, so that their insoluble pellets could be contaminated by other possible insoluble (nonraft) components, which would present high density.
Curiously, EPR spectra did not reveal any difference in the DRMs obtained from intact erythrocyte membranes with Triton X-100 and Cj2E8 treatments. The similar 5 values found for Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs, both for 5- and 16-SASL, clearly show that the acyl chain packing is similar in these DRMs, as expected from their comparable cholesterol content (Fig. 2).
In summary, our results show that flotillin-2, a marker of lipid rafts, is selectivity enriched in Triton X-100 DRMs from erythrocytes, but it is solubilized by treatment with Cj2E8. On the other hand, the acyl chain packing of the lipids in these domains is not different, after treatment with Triton X-100 or C12E8. Thus, the absence of flotillin-2 from DRMs does not affect the order of the structures involved in those domains.
Atomic force microscopy and fluorescence correlation spectroscopy studies with model membranes have clearly shown the spontaneous formation of laterally segregated domains within lipid bilayers as well as the selective protein incorporation into such domains (Saslowsky et al. 2002; Bacia et al. 2004; Salamon et al. 2007). The association of certain membrane proteins with DRMs may depend on the concentration and the type of detergent (I-langumaran et al. 1999; Matko and Szollosi 2005). Yet, from the point of view of membrane-protein extraction, the specific solubilization induced by detergents has been widely explored, CJ2E8 and Triton X-100 being powerful solubilizers for Na,K-ATPase and other eukaryote and prokaryote membrane proteins (Santos et al. 2002; Berger et al. 2005).
The types of proteins enriched in DRMs include acylated proteins, GPI-anchored proteins and certain membrane receptors and channels. However, many transmembrane proteins with hydrophobic alpha-helices, including specific tyrosine phosphatases, are largely excluded from membrane microdomains or DRMs (Moffet et al. 2000; Ridyard and Robbins 2003; Wong and Schlichter 2004; McIntosh 2007). Furthermore, the diversity observed among lipid rafts may be also explained by compartmentalization of raft-associated proteins by the underlying cytoskeleton (Munro 2003).
Flotillin is a well-known lipid-raft marker that is colocalized at the caveolae associated proteins, including GPI-linked receptors (Bickel et al. 1997; Glebov et al. 2006). It is myristoylated and multiply palmitoylated, and these lipid modifications are responsible for its membrane insertion because it does not have any intramembrane domain (Neumann-Giesen et al. 2004). Moreover, disruption or stabilization of the actin cytoskeleton modulate the lateral mobility of flotillin microdomains, as shown by fluorescence recovery after photobleaching, by Langhorst et al. (2007), showing flotillin intrinsic relation to the cytoskeleton. On the basis of cytoskeleton rupture, which also
depends on the solubilization of other proteins, it is not surprising that flotillin content in Ci2E8 and Triton X-100 DRMs is different because these detergents could have different selectivities in solubilizing other membrane proteins that are involved in the cytoskeleton.
Although the organization of DRM components in the bilayer is unclear, our results support the connection of DRMs to the membrane-skeleton, as we have suggested previously (Ciana et al. 2005). In this work, we also provide results that support the use of different detergents to improve the knowledge about the structures of DRMs from erythrocytes and their possible involvement in rafts in the plasma membrane in vivo.
Acknowledgments This work was supported by a research grant from FAPESP (Proc. 03/02394-4), Brazil, and by PRIN funds of the “Ministero dell’Universita e della Ricerca,” Italy. C.C.D. acknowledges a fellowship from CAPES (Proc. 3597/06-7) and CNPq (Proc. 141618/2005-1), Brazil.
References
Bacia K, Scherfeld D, Kahya N, Schwille P (2004) Fluorescence correlation spectroscopy relates rafts in model and native membranes. Biophys J 87:1034-1043
Berger BW, Garcia RY, Lenhoff AM, Kaier EW, Robinson CR (2005) Relating surfactant properties to activity and solubilization of the human adenosine A3 receptor. Biophys J 89: 452^464	’
Beutler E, West C, Blume KG (1976) The removal of leukocytes and platelets from whole blood. J Lab Clin Med 88:328-333
Bickel PE, Scherer PE, Schnitzer JE, Oh P, Lisanti MP, Lodish HF (1997) Flotillin and epidermal surface antigen define a new family of caveolae-associated integral membrane proteins. J Biol Chem 272:13793-13802
Brown DA, London E (1998) Functions of lipid rafts in biological membranes. Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol 14:111-136
Brown DA, Rose JK (1992) Sorting of GPI-anchored proteins to glycolipid-enriched membrane subdomains during transport to the apical cell surface. Cell 68:533-544
Casey JR, Reithmeier RAF (1991) Analysis of the oligomeric state of band 3, the anion transport protein of the human erythrocyte membrane, by size exclusion high performance liquid chromatography. J Biol Chem 266:15726-15737
Cassera MB, Silber AM, Gennaro AM (2002) Differential effects of cholesterol on acyl chain order in erythrocyte membranes as a function of depth from the surface. An electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spin label study. Biophys Chem 99:117-127
Cereda CM, de Araujo DR, Brunetto GB, de Paula E (2004) Liposomal prilocaine: preparation, characterization, and in vivo evaluation. J Pharm Sci 7:235-240
Ciana A, Baidu ini C, Minetti G (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes in human erythrocytes and their connection to the membrane-skeleton. J Biosci 30:317-328
de Gassart A, Geminard C, Fevrier B, Raposo G, Vidal M (2003) Lipid raft-associated protein sorting in exosomes. Blood 102: 4336-4344
Delaunay JL, Breton M, Godine JW, Trugnan G, Maurice M (2007) Differential detergent resistance of the apical and basolateral NPPases: relationship with polarized targeting. J Cell Sci 120: 1009-1016
de Paula E, Schreier S (1995) Use of a novel method for determination of partition coefficients to compare the effect of local anesthetics on membrane structure. Biochim Bhiophys Acta 1240:25-33	'
Dodge JT, Mitchell C, Hanahan DJ (1963) The preparation and chemical characteristics of hemoglobin-free ghosts of human erythrocytes. Arch Biochem Biophys 100:119-130
Glebov OO, Bright NA, Nichols BJ (2006) Flotillin-1 defines a clathrin-independent endocytic pathway in mammalian cells. Nat Cell Biol 8:46-54
Griffith OH, Jost OP (1976) Spin labels in biological membranes. In: Berliner LJ (ed) Spin labeling: theory and applications. Academic Press, New York, pp 454-523
Grzybek M, Chorzalska A, Bok E, Hryniewicz-Jankowska A, Czogalla A, Diakowski W, Sikorski AF (2006) Spectrinphospholipid interactions. Existence of multiple kinds of binding sites? Chem Phys Lipids 141:133-141
Haidar K, Mohandas N, Samuel BU, Harrison T. Hiller NL, Akompong T, Cheresh P (2002) Protein and lipid trafficking induced in erythrocytes infected by malaria parasites. Cell Microbiol 4:383-395
Hubbel WL, McConnel HM (1971) Molecular motion in spin-labeled phospholipids and membranes. J Am Chem Soc 93:314-326
Ilangumaran S, Arni S, van Echten-Decker G, Borisch B, Hoessli DC (1999) Microdomain-dependent regulation of Lek and Fyn protein-tyrosine kinases in T lymphocyte plasma membranes. Mol Biol Cell 10:891-905
Kamata K, Manno S, Ozaki M, Takakuwa Y (2008) Functional evidence for presence of lipid rafts in erythrocyte membranes: Gsa in rafts is essential for signal transduction. Am J Hematol 83:371-375
Laemmli UK (1970) Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4. Nature (London) 227:680-685
Langhorst MF, Solis GP, Hannbeck S, Plattner H, Stuermer CA (2007) Linking membrane microdomains to the cytoskeleton: regulation of the lateral mobility of reggie-l/flotillin-2 by interaction with actin. FEBS Lett 581:4697^4703
le Maire M, Champed P, Moller JV (2000) Interaction of membrane proteins and lipids with solubilizing detergents. Biochim Biophys Acta 1508:86-111
Lichtenberg D, Goni FM, Heerklotz H (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes should not be identified with membrane rafts. Trends Biochem Sci 30:430-436
Macdonald JL, Pike LJ (2005) A simplified method for the preparation of detergent-free lipid rafts. J Lipid Res 46:1061-1067
Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2000) Pathways involved in trifluoperazine-, dibucaine- and praziquantel-induced hemolysis. Biophys Chem 83:89-100
Matko J, Szollosi J (2005) Regulatory aspects of membrane microdomain (raft) dynamics in live cells. In: Mattson MP (ed) Membrane microdomain signaling. Lipid rafts in biology and medicine. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 15^16
McIntosh TJ (2007) Overview of membrane rafts. In: McIntosh TJ (ed) Methods in molecular biology: lipid rafts. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 1-7
McMullen TPW, Lewis RNAH, McElhaney RN (1993) Differential scanning calorimetric study of the effect of cholesterol on the thermotropic phase behavior of a homologous series of linear saturated phosphatidylcholines. Biochemistry 32:516-522
Moffet S, Brown DA, Linder ME (2000) Lipid-dependent targeting of G proteins into rafts. J Biol Chem 275:2191-2198
Motoyama K, Arima H, Toyodome H, Irie T, Hirayama F, Uekama K (2006) Effect of 2,6-di-D-methyl-alpha-cyclodextrin on hemolysis and morphological change in rabbit’s red blood cells. Eur J Pharm Sci 29:111-119
Munro S (2003) Lipid rafts: elusive or illusive? Cell 115:377-388
Murphy SC, Samuel BU, Harrison T, Speicher KD, Speicher DW, Reid ME, Prohaska R, Low PS, Tanner MJ, Mohandas N, Haidar K (2004) Erythrocyte detergent-resistant membrane proteins: their characterization and selective uptake during malaria infection. Blood 103:1920-1928
Murphy SC, Fernandez-Pol S, Chung PH, Murthy SNP, Milne SB, Salomao M, Brown HA, Lomasney JW, Mohandas N, Haidar K (2007) Cytoplasmic remodeling of erythrocyte raft lipids infection by the human malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum. Blood 110:2132-2139
Nagao E, Seydel KB, Dvorak JA (2002) Detergent-resistant erythrocyte membrane rafts are modified by a Plasmodium falciparum infection. Exp Parasitol 102:57-59
Neumann-Giesen C, Falkenbach B, Beicht P, Claasen S, Liiers G, Stuermer CA, Herzog V, Tikkanen R (2004) Membrane and raft association of reggie-l/flotillin-2: role of myristoylation, palm-itoylation and oligomerization and induction of filopodia by overexpression. Biochem J 378:509-518
Parkin ET, Turner AJ, Hooper NM (1996) Isolation and characterization of two distinct low-density, Triton-insoluble, complexes from porcine lung membranes. Biochem J 319:887-896
Pike LJ (2004) Lipid rafts: heterogeneity on the high seas. Biochem J 378:281-292
Pike LJ (2006) Rafts defined: a report on the keystone symposium on lipid rafts and cell function. J Lipid Res 47:1597-1598
Prete PSC, Gomes K, Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2002) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by nonionic surfactants of the polyoxyethylene alkyl ethers series. Biophys Chem 97:45-54
Ridyard MS, Robbins SM (2003) Fibroblast growth factor-2-induced signaling through lipid raft-associated fibroblast growth factor receptor substrate 2 (FRS2). J Biol Chem 278:13803-13809
Rigaud J-L, Pitard B, Levy D (1995) Reconstituition of membrane proteins into liposomes: application to energy-transducing membrane proteins. Biochim Biophys Acta 1231:223-246
Rivas MG, Gennaro AM (2003) Detergent resistant domains in erythrocyte membranes survive after cell cholesterol depletion: an EPR spin label study. Chem Phys Lipids 122:165-169
Rodi PM, Cabeza MS, Gennaro AM (2006) Detergent solubilization of bovine erythrocytes. Comparison between the insoluble material and the intact membrane. Biophys Chem 122:114-122
Rose HG, Oklander M (1965) Improved procedure for the extraction of lipids from human erythrocytes. J Lipid Res 6:428-431
Salamon Z, Devanathan S, Tollin G (2007) Plasmon-waveguide resonance spectroscopy studies of lateral segregation in solid-supported proteolipid bilayers. In: McIntosh TJ (ed) Methods in molecular biology: lipid rafts. Human Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 159-178
Salzer U, Prohaska R (2001) Stomatin, flotillin-1, and flotillin-2 are major integral proteins of erythrocyte lipid rafts. Blood 97:1141-1143
Salzer U, Hinterdorfer P, Hunger U, Bor ken C, Prohaska R (2002) Ca++-dependent vesicle release from erythrocytes involves stomatin-specific lipid rafts, synexin (annexin VII), and sorcin. Blood 99:2569-2577
Samuel BU, Mohandas N, Harrison T, McManus H. Rosse W, Reid M, Haidar K (2001) The role of cholesterol and glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored proteins of erythrocyte rafts in regulating raft protein content and malarial infection. J Biol Chem 276:29319-29329
Santos HL, Lamas RP, Ciancaglini P (2002) Solubilization of Na,K-ATPase from rabbit kidney outer medulla using only C12E8. Braz J Med Biol Res 35:277-288
Saslowsky DE, Lawrence J, Ren X, Brown DA, Henderson RM, Edwards JM (2002) Placental alkaline phosphatase is efficiently targeted to rafts in support lipid bilayer. J Biol Chem 277:2696626970
Schreier S, Polnaszek CF, Smith ICP (1978) Spin labels in membranes. Biochim Biophys Acta 515:375—436
Schuck S, Honsho M, Ekroos K, Shevchenko A, Simons K (2003) Resistance of cell membranes to different detergents. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 100:5795-5800
Seelig J (1977) Deuterium magnetic resonance: theory and application to lipid membranes. Q Rev Biophys 10:353^-18
Simons K, Ikonen E (1997) Functional rafts in cell membranes. Nature 387:569-572
Simons K, Vaz WL (2004) Model systems, lipid rafts, and cell membranes. Annu Rev Biophys Biomol Struc 33:269-295
Sulkowski WW, Pentak D, Nowak K, Sulkowska A (2006) The influence of temperature and pH on the structure of liposomes formed from DMPC. J Mol Struct 792-793:257-264
Wilkinson DK, Turner EJ, Parkin ET, Gamer AE, Harrison PJ, Crawford M, Stewart GW, Hooper NM (2007) Membrane raft actin deficiency and altered Ca2+-induced vesiculation in stomatin-deficient overhydrated hereditary stomatocytosis. Biochim Biophys Acta 1778:125-132
Wong W, Schlichter LC (2004) Differential recruitment of Kvl.4 and Kv4.2 to lipid rafts by PSD-95. J Biol Chem 279:444^152
Artigo 2:
Domingues CC, Ciana A, Balduini C, de Paula E, Minetti G. Detergentresistant membranes from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes using Triton X-100 and Ci2E8 (a ser submetido).
Detergent-resistant membranes from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes using Triton X-100 and C12E8
Cleyton Crepaldi Domingues1, Annarita Ciana2, Cesare Balduini2, Eneida de Paula1, Giampaolo Minetti2 *
1Departamento de Bioquímica, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas, SP, Brazil
2	Università di Pavia, Dipartimento di Biochimica ’’A Castellani", Pavia, Italy
Corresponding author:
Giampaolo Minetti
Dipartimento di Biochimica ’’A Castellani"
Via Bassi, 21, 27100, Pavia, Italy
Tel: +39 0382 987236
Fax: +39 0382 987240
E-mail: minetti@unipv.it
Abstract
Transient lateral microdomains or lipid rafts are believed to play a fundamental role in many physiologic membrane-mediated cell processes. Detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) have been shown to be a good model for the study of lipid rafts. Here we have prepared DRMs from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes, using the nonionic detergents Triton X-100 and C12E8. The order parameters (S) from cholesterol-depleted DRMs measured by means of electron paramagnetic resonance at different depths of the membrane were increased in comparison to either the intact membrane or their respective DRMs. Flotillin-2, a protein marker of lipid rafts, sensitively increased in C12E8 DRMs when the cells were previously cholesterol-depleted while the cytoskeleton proteins spectrin and actin were excluded from Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs. The role of cholesterol in DRMs formation is discussed and the results presented here provide further support for the use of C12E8 to the study of DRMs.
Keywords: cholesterol, lipid raft, erythrocyte, electron paramagnetic resonance, flotillin, membrane-skeleton
Introduction
Lipid rafts are transient liquid-ordered (lo) phase microdomains observed in biological membranes which are rich in cholesterol, sphingolipids and membrane proteins, such as acylated and glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored proteins (Simons and Ikonen, 1997; Brown and London, 1998a; Simons and Vaz, 2004; Lichtenberg et al., 2005) and lack glycerophospholipids, mainly the unsaturated ones. Rafts are thought to be small (10-200 nm) and heterogeneous structures, but they can be stabilized to form larger platforms through protein-protein and protein-lipid interactions (Pike, 2006). The driving force for rafts formation is phase separation caused by the favored association between cholesterol and sphingolipid, as shown by the induction of phase when cholesterol was added to liposomes of phospholipids and sphingolipids (Brown and London 1998b, 2000) or by the spontaneous formation of cholesterol and sphingolipid-rich domains observed in monolayers composed by phospholipids, sphingolipids and cholesterol (Dietrich et al., 2001, 2002).
Detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) obtained from the low density fractions of sucrose gradients (5-30%) are also formed by cholesterol and sphingolipids in the lo phase (Brown and Rose, 1992; Schroeder et al., 1994) and have been used as a powerful tool in the lipid rafts research. Specific proteins associate to DRMs due to their inherent affinity for the ordered membrane state of those lipid domains. Furthermore, raft-targeting signals identified by DRMs analysis are often required for protein function, implicating rafts in a variety of cell process (Brown, 2006, 2007). Mild detergents such as the nonionic Triton X-100, Brij, Lubrow WX and the zwitterionic CHAPS have been reported to isolate DRMs (Schuck et al., 2003; Delaunay et al., 2007) in varied cell types, with detectable differences in their protein composition (Pike, 2004). In a recent work, we have reported
the isolation of Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs from human erythrocytes with a 3 fold increase in the cholesterol/protein mass ratio and high lipid order, compatible with the lo phase. Despite the specific proteins distribution in those DRMs, flotillin-2 was found to be different, being selectivity enriched in Triton X-100 DRMs but poorly detected in C12E8 DRMs obtained by the same protocol (Domingues et al., 2008).
Different treatments can affect the affinity and association of a particular protein to the DRMs (Ilangumaran &amp;amp; Hoessli, 1998). Cholesterol seems to play a central role in stabilizing the sphingolipid/glicosphingolipid domains and its depletion or enrichment in biological membranes has resulted in destabilized membrane rafts (Ilangumaran et al., 1999; Xu &amp;amp; London, 2000; Matkó et al., 2002). Methyl-beta-cyclodextrin (MBCD) has been a very helpful tool for disrupting rafts' integrity, by selectively extracting membrane cholesterol. Unlike other cholesterol-binding agents, MBCD neither binds nor inserts into the plasma membrane (Ohtani et al., 1989). Methylated cyclodextrin is strictly surface-acting and is able to form inclusion complexes with cholesterol (Nishijo et al., 2003). Here we report results on the role played by cholesterol depletion of human erythrocytes in determining integral and membrane-skeletal proteins association to DRMs prepared with Triton X-100 and C12E8. Moreover, the acyl chain packing in the DRMs obtained from cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes were determined by means of electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR).
Materials and Methods
Preparation of erythrocytes
Blood was collected from normal human donors after informed consent was obtained. Blood was mixed with 0.1 volumes of 3.8 % (w/v) sodium citrate and after centrifugation at 1000g, the plasma was removed and the packed cells were suspended in an equal volume of PBS buffer (5 mM Na-phosphate, 154.5 mM NaCl, 4.5 mM KCl, 300 mOsmol/kg H2O, pH 7.4). The suspension was then filtered through a-cellulose/microcrystalline cellulose to isolate erythrocytes from platelets and leukocytes (Beutler et al., 1976). The purified erythrocyte suspension was washed three times in PBS and the packed cells were used to prepare DRMs. Cholesterol depletion was performed using MBCD (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO): purified packed erythrocytes were suspended in 5 mM MBCD in PBS buffer (20% hematocrit) and incubated for 30 min at 37°C; cells were then washed three times with PBS by centrifugation at 1000g to remove MBCD-cholesterol complexes. After that, treated and control whole erythrocytes were lysed and subjected to lipid extraction (Rose and Oklander, 1965). Cholesterol was quantified using a colorimetric assay kit (N. 10139050035, R-Biopharm Italia Srl, Milan, Italy).
To prepare ghost membranes, the purified erythrocytes were mixed with 10 volumes of hypotonic phosphate buffer (5 mM Na-phosphate, 0.5 mM EDTA, 5 mM di-isopropylfluorophosphate, pH 8.0) at 4 °C, followed by centrifugation at 26000 g; the supernatant was discharged and the washing repeated at least 4 times with the same buffer, in order to obtain white ghost membranes, according to Dodge et al. (1963). Protein concentration was determined with bicinchoninic acid (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, IL), using bovine serum albumin as standard.
Solubilization of protein, cholesterol and phospholipids
Purified ghost membranes (1 mg/mL, final protein concentration) were mixed with PBS containing Triton X-100 or C12E8 and incubated for 30 min at 4°C. The samples were then centrifuged at 15000g, for 30 min at 4°C and the supernatant solution was used for the measurement of solubilized protein, cholesterol and phospholipids. Cholesterol and proteins were measured as described above and the phospholipid concentration in the supernatant was determined as inorganic phosphate according to Chen et al. (1956). Untreated samples of ghosts in PBS were used as control, corresponding to total protein, cholesterol and phospholipid concentrations. Triplicate measurements on at least two different blood samples were carried out.
Preparation of DRMs
DRMs were prepared from either intact or cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes, following a previously detailed protocol (Ciana et al., 2005; Domingues et al., 2008). Briefly, the packed cells (approximately 1.25 x 109 cells) were incubated with TNE buffer (25 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.4) containing either Triton X-100 or C12E8, so that the final volume was 0.625 mL and the ultimate detergent concentration 16 mM, giving a detergent/lipid molar ratio ca 12. After 30 min the samples were mixed with an equal volume of 80 % sucrose solution in TNE containing 0.3 M Na2CO3. The sample was then transferred to ultracentrifuge tubes and
2.5	mL of a 30 % sucrose solution in TNE was gently layered on top of the sample, followed by 1.25 mL of a 5 % sucrose solution in TNE. All procedures were conducted at 4 °C and the samples were subjected to ultracentrifugation in a bench-top ultracentrifuge (Optima Max, equipped with a swinging-arm MLS50 rotor, Beckman Coulter, Milan, Italy) at
225000gmax, for 16 h at 4 °C. The top 1 mL was collected as the first fraction. Proceeding down the gradient, fractions 2-6 were collected as 0.8 mL aliquots and saved for subsequent characterization. Fractions 2 and 3 contain the low-density material corresponding to DRMs.
SDS-PAGE and western blotting
Samples were separated using either 10% or 12.5% SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) according to Laemmli (1970). The gels were either stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue or electrophoretically transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes. Membranes were blocked for 1 h in TNE containing 5 % skimmed milk, 0.05 % Tween 20 and then incubated with the relevant primary antibody: mouse monoclonal anti flotillin-2 (BD Italia, Milan, Italy), goat polyclonal anti human stomatin and mouse monoclonal (BRIC 10) anti human glycophorin C (GPC) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, Germany), mouse monoclonal anti human band 3 (Sigma-Aldrich, Milan, Italy). The membranes were then washed and incubated with the appropriate peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody and the proteins were revealed with the Amersham ECL western blotting kit (GE Healthcare, Milan, Italy).
EPR experiments
The n-doxyl-stearic acid spin labels, SASL probes (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO) with n = 5 or 16, were incorporated up to 2 mole% of lipids into the DRM fractions by 30 min incubation at room temperature. The spectra were recorded at 20-25 °C and 9.4 GHz in a Bruker EMX (X band) spectrometer. The order parameter (S) was calculated from the hyperfine splittings of the spin label spectra, as described previously (Domingues et al,
2008). The order parameter is directly related to the tilt angle of the acyl
chains and (indirectly) to the trans-gauche distribution of chain dihedrals. The larger the value of S (~unity), the smaller the amplitude of motion and the more ordered the lipid chains (Schreier at al., 1978).
Results and Discussion
Triton X-100 is a widely used detergent to isolate DRMs from model and biological membranes, especially from erythrocytes. Recently, we have reported the characterization of DRMs from human erythrocytes prepared with either Triton X-100 or octaethylene glycol monododecyl ether, C12E8. These nonionic detergents of equivalent hemolytic activity (Preté et al., 2002) lead to DRMs of different protein composition and lipid packing compatible with the lo phase (Domingues et al., 2008).
To further investigate the solubilization induced by Triton X-100 and C12E8 we have analyzed the total amount of proteins, cholesterol and phospholipids in the soluble fraction obtained from ghost membranes (Fig. 1) after incubation with both detergents. Instead of intact cells, only ghost membranes were used to avoid the interference of hemoglobin in the total protein quantification. Overall the solubilization profile of these membrane components was similar, reflecting the equivalent affinity of Triton X-100 and C12E8 for the erythrocyte membranes (binding constants = 5900 and 6000 M1, respectively) (Preté et al., 2002). Solubilization of proteins and lipids were very similar up to 5 mM (20 and 50 times CMC of Triton X-100 and C12E8, respectively) but at high detergent concentrations (above 15 mM) Triton X100 was more efficient in the solubilization of cholesterol (mainly) and phospholipids (Fig. 1B). As expected, phospholipids were the most solubilized lipids (&gt; 80% at 50 mM detergents), while protein and cholesterol are more resistant to detergents. Besides, almost 50% of the ghost membrane
proteins remained insoluble (Fig. 1A) what could not be accounted just for the (presumed) insolubility of cytoskeletal proteins in nonionic detergents, evidencing proteins associated to DRMs.
Since cholesterol has been shown to play an important role in the formation of lipid raft (London and Brown, 2000; Matko et al., 2002, Pike et al, 2004) and DRMs are cholesterol-enriched (approximately 30 - 40% of the total erythrocyte membrane cholesterol remains in the insoluble detergent fraction according to Koumanov et al., 2005; Ciana et al, 2005; Domingues et al., 2008) we have investigated the composition and organization of DRMs from cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes. As described in "Materials and Methods" we have incubated erythrocytes with non-lytic amount of MBCD (5 mM) so that approximately 40% of total cholesterol was removed from the intact membranes, in very good agreement with the results from Vazquez et al. (2002). Although visually slight differences could be observed in the low buoyant density fraction (interface between 5 % and 30 % sucrose gradient) from cholesterol-depleted and normal erythrocytes samples, DRMs were obtained with either Triton X-100 or C12E8.
Figure 2 shows the distribution of specific proteins in Triton X-100 and C12E8 DRMs from control (untreated) and cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes isolated as fractions 2 and 3 in the sucrose gradient; the proteins revealed in the fractions 4, 5 and 6 correspond to soluble fractions.
Two of the cholesterol-binding, raft-organizing proteins are flotillin and stomatin. Rivas &amp;amp; Gennaro (2003) and Samuel et al. (2001) have suggested that Triton X-100 is able to solubilize these two proteins in cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes, indicating that cholesterol is critical for protein assembly into DRMs. In our hands, stomatin association into DRMs was essentially unaffected by MBCD treatment (Fig. 2) while flotillin-2, which has
been shown to be selectivity confined in Triton X-100 DRMs but almost completely solubilized by C12E8 (Domingues et al., 2008), got enriched in C12E8 DRMs (Fig. 2).
After MBCD treatment, if a reduction in the association of a protein to DRMs is observed we can easily deduce its preferential binding to domains in the lo phase, weakened by the decreased cholesterol content. On the other hand if no changes in protein association is found, no conclusions can be drawn, because the remaining cholesterol in the DRMs could be enough to keep such domains intact (Schuck et al. 2003). As shown in Fig. 2, after MBCD treatment we found a redistribution of flotillin-2 and its presence was increased in DRM fractions when C12E8 was used.
As cholesterol has been shown to modulate attractive forces between reversibly palmitoylated signaling proteins and lipids in rafts (Fragoso et al., 2003) herein it might have modulated flotillin-2, which is a multiply palmitoylated protein with no transmembranar domains but acyl-anchored to the internal leaflet of the membrane and that tends to form oligomers (Neumann-Giessen et al., 2004; Delaunay et al., 2007). As proposed by Pike (2004), the heterogeneity found in DRMs isolated by different detergents reflects the existence of heterogeneous domains before extraction to detergent. Thus, the formation of heterogeneous subset domains that contain flotillin-2, after MBCD treatment could explain the presence of insoluble flotillin-2 in those C12E8 DRMs. In this way, subset of domains, less resistant to Triton X-100, could be formed as suggested by the presence of flotillin-2 in the (soluble) fraction 6 (Fig. 2). Furthermore, the different membrane lipid composition and/or distribution obtained after MBCD treatment could give rise to differential sensitivity to extraction by detergent.
As evidenced in Fig. 2, almost all band 3 and Glycophorin C are found in the soluble fractions (5 and 6), irrespective of cholesterol depletion, for any detergent used. These results suggest that the environment of these proteins is not affected by cholesterol removal.
Since no great differences were found in the solubilized material (Fig.
1)	after Triton X-100 and C12E8 treatment, one should expect the same or similar composition in the DRMs prepared with both detergents. Indeed, we have shown before that the increase in the cholesterol content of the DRM fractions (3-fold increase in the cholesterol/protein mass ratio in comparison to intact cell membrane) as well as the increase in the lipid packing of these DRMs, sensed by nitroxide spin labels inserted in-between the lipids and measured by EPR, were the same no matter what detergent, Triton X-100 or C12E8, was used (Domingues et al., 2008).
Koumanov et al. (2005) have reported that the sphingomyelin:cholesterol molar ratio in DRMs from human erythrocyte ghosts is approximately 1:1 and it does not change in erythrocytes DRMs from various other animal species, regardless of differences in the cholesterol content of the respective erythrocyte membranes. To further understand the effect of cholesterol depletion in the DRMs formation we have monitored the lipid packing of these structures, using EPR spectroscopy with spin-labeled probes (5- and 16-doxyl stearic acid) positioned at different membrane depths (Table 1). The order parameters (S) of cholesterol-depleted erythrocyte membranes (0.774 ± 0.008 with 5-SASL and 0.258 ± 0.001 with 16-SASL) were not found to be different from those of intact membranes, showing that cholesterol extraction was partial.
Modified cyclodextrin such as MBCD has been extensively used for cholesterol trapping (Ilangumaran and Hoessli 1998; Cassera et al. 2002;
Schuck et al. 2003). However, it is known that side effects of MBCD, as releasing of some small cholesterol-binding proteins from the membrane can occur (Ilangumaran and Hoessli, 1998) and it must be considered in the DRMs preparation, since the organization of such domains in vivo are likely to be controlled by cholesterol-binding proteins (Anderson and Jacobson, 2002; Pike, 2003). On the other hand, Schuck et al. (2003) found no changes in DRM association of several proteins tested when they treated intact MDCK (Madin-Darby canine kidney) cells with MBCD to extract more than 70% of the membrane cholesterol. These different results show that the question whether association of a particular protein with DRMs (and extrapolating with rafts) reflects its ability to bind to cholesterol is still opened.
Table 1 shows the high S values found in DRMs from cholesterol-depleted cells obtained with Triton X-100 and C12E8 detergents, revealing that lipids are in the lo phase, as reported before for DRMs prepared from intact red blood cells (Domingues et al, 2008). More interestingly, the S values measured with 5-SASL in the DRMs obtained from cholesterol-depleted cells were still higher (p &amp;lt;0.001) than those in the DRMs from untreated cells, both for Triton X-100 and C12E8. The higher order milieu is imposed by the sphingomyelin/cholesterol increased, since sphingolipids are composed of long and unsaturated acyl chains (Rietveld and Simons, 1998) resulting in a more tight packing of these structures. The increased acyl chain order sensed by 5-SASL in Triton X-100 DRMs from cholesterol-depleted membranes has not been observed by Rivas and Gennaro (2003), probably because insoluble pellet reported by those authors was obtained by centrifugation after detergent extraction, instead of a purified material isolated in a sucrose gradient. For 16-SASL, that monitor a deeper bilayer region, no significant differences were found between DRMs from intact and
cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes, probably because of the lower order of the membrane core decreasing the sensitivity of the probe (Godici and Ladsberger, 1974) to monitor changes in the acyl chain orientation, as well as to the upper insertion of cholesterol (Kessel, 2001). Nevertheless, our EPR results confirm that cholesterol depletion is not enough to weaken the interactions responsible for the characteristic liquid-ordered state of DRMs, indicating that DRMs stability is influenced, but not only dependent on the cholesterol content.
The highly ordered DRMs obtained when cholesterol was previously extracted from the erythrocytes (Table 1) seems to favor the association of flotillin-2, at least in the case of C12E8, increasing the amount of these lipid raft protein marker in the DRM fraction (Fig. 2). In this way, the model proposed by Pike (2004) for the formation of heterogeneous subset of domains, more or less detergent resistant is quite plausible to explain our results.
In spite of association of cytoskeleton proteins with DRMs no consensus is found in the literature. We and other authors have shown the presence of such cytoskeletal proteins as actin, spectrin, tropomodulin, protein 4.1 and
4.2,	in DRMs from human erythrocytes (Salzer &amp;amp; Prohaska, 2001; Murphy et al., 2004; Ciana et al., 2005; Wilkinson et al., 2007; Domingues et al., 2008). However, the physiological relevance of cytoskeletal association with DRMs remains unclear. The effects of cholesterol removal on membrane-skeletal proteins are illustrated in Fig. 3. Interestingly, spectrin and actin were virtually absent only in DRMs from cholesterol-depleted membrane, indicating that the membrane-skeleton association with DRMs depends on cholesterol. Actually, cholesterol depletion has global effects on membrane and cell properties. Perturbation of the cytoskeleton would explain the results in Fig. 3 and this hypothesis is based on the modulation of the
cytoskeleton/membrane interaction by phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP2). When cholesterol is depleted it reduces lateral mobility of membrane proteins because it disrupts the highly regulated interactions of PIP2 with molecules controlling the state and organization of the actin cytoskeleton (Kwik et al., 2003). Thus, since a regulated PIP2 activity depends on cholesterol domains, its depletion results in failed regulation of the cell cytoskeleton facilitating a release of spectrin and/or actin from DRMs. Besides cholesterol removal, other strategies to study the cytoskeleton association with DRMs are under investigation in our laboratory.
We have previously suggested the connection of DRMs to the membrane-skeleton (Ciana et al., 2005; Domingues et al., 2008). In this study, our findings indicate that cholesterol contribute for this connection. Our results are also supported by Diakowski et al. (2006) whose data have also evidenced that erythrocyte spectrin interacts with model membranes prepared from a raft-like mixture of lipids. Moreover, those authors have shown that besides cholesterol content, the chemical structure of the membrane lipids would contribute for that interaction so that the cholesterol depletion mainly from the outer leaflet of the bilayer should have an effect on the lipid distribution in the inner leaflet, leading to the disruption of spectrin interaction to DRMs.
In conclusion, our data indicate that cholesterol depletion can affect the distribution of proteins in DRMs because it can induce the formation of more ordered domains. Organization of flotillin-2 domains seems to be strongly dependent on cholesterol, while stomatin domains are practically unaffected. Our results also suggest the use of both Triton X-100 and C12E8 as a good tool to study association of a specific protein with DRMs.
Acknowledgments
We thank Dr. A. Buttafava for the access to EPR facilities. This work was supported by PRIN funds of the "Ministero dell'Universita e della Ricerca", Italy. C.C.D. acknowledges the fellowships from CAPES (Proc. 3597/06-7) and CNPq (Proc. 141618/2005-1), Brazil.
References
Anderson RG, Jacobson K (2002) A role for lipid shells in targeting proteins to caveolae, rafts and others lipid domains. Science 296:1821-1825
Beutler E, West C, Blume KG (1976) The removal of leukocytes and platelets from whole blood. J. Lab. Clin. Med. 88:328-333
Brown DA (2006) Lipid rafts, detergent-resistant membranes, and raft targeting signals. Physiology 21:430-439
Brown DA (2007) Analysis of raft affinity of membrane proteins by detergent-insolubility. In: McIntosh, T.J. (ed.), Methods in molecular biology. Lipid rafts. Humana Press, Totowa NJ, pp. 1-7
Brown DA, London E (1998a) Functions of lipid rafts in biological membranes. Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol. 14:111-136
Brown DA, London E (1998b) Structure and origin of ordered lipid domains in biological membranes. J. Membr. Biol. 164, 103-114
Brown DA, London E (2000) Structure and function of sphingolipid- and cholesterol-rich membrane rafts. J. Biol. Chem. 275, 17221-17224
Brown DA, Rose JK (1992) Sorting of GPI-anchored proteins to glycolipid-enriched membrane subdomains during transport to the apical cell surface. Cell 68:533-544
Chen PS, Toribara TYjr, Warner H (1956) Microdetermination of phosphorus. Anal. Chem. 28:1756-1758
Ciana A, Balduini C, Minetti G (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes in human erythrocytes and their connection to the membrane-skeleton. J. Biosci. 30:317-328
Delaunay JL, Breton M, Godine JW, Trugnan G, Maurice M (2007) Differential detergent resistance of the apical and basolateral NPPases: relationship with polarized targeting. J. Cell Sci. 120:1009-1016
Diakowski W, Ozimek E, Bielska E, Bem S, Langner M, Sikorski AF (2006) Cholesterol affects spectrin-phospholipid interactions in a manner different from changes resulting from alterations in membrane fluidity due to fatty acyl chain composition. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1758:4-12
Dietrich C, Volovyk ZN, Levi M, Thompson NL, Jacobson K (2001) Partitioning of Thy-1, GM1 and crosslinked phospholipid analogs into lipid rafts reconstituted in supported model membrane monolayers. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 98:10642-10647
Dietrich C, Yang B, Fujiwara T, Kusumi A, Jacobson K (2002) Relationship of lipid rafts to transient confinement zones detected by single particle tracking. Biophys. J. 82:274-284
Dodge JT, Mitchell C, Hanahan DJ (1963) The preparation and chemical characteristics of hemoglobin-free ghosts of human erythrocytes. Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 100:119-130
Domingues CC, Ciana A, de Paula E, Faucitano A, Minetti G (2008) Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8. J. Membr. Biol. DOI 10.1007/s00232-008-9142-4
Fragoso R, Ren D, Zhang X, Su MW, Burakoff SJ, Jin YJ (2003) Lipid raft distribution of CD4 depends on its palmitoylation and association with Lck, and evidence for CD4-induced lipid raft aggregation as an additional mechanism to enhanced CD3 signaling. J. Immunol. 170:913-921
Godici PE, Landsberger FR (1974) Dynamics structure of lipid-membranes— C13 nuclear magnetic resonance study using spin labels. Biochemistry 13 (1974) 362-368
Ilangumaran S, Arni S, van Echten-Decker G, Borisch B, Hoessli DC (1999) Microdomain-dependent regulation of Lck and Fyn protein-tyrosine kinases in T lymphocyte plasma membranes. Mol. Biol. Cell 10:891-905
Ilangumaran S, Hoessli DC (1998) Effects of cholesterol depletion by cyclodextrin on the sphingolipid microdomains of the plasma membrane. Biochem. J. 335:433-440
Kwik J, Boyle S, Fooksman D, Margolis L, Sheetz MP, Edidin M (2003) Membrane cholesterol, lateral mobility, and the phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate-dependent organization of cell actin. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 100:13964-13969
Koumanov KS, Tessier C, Momchilova AB, Rainteau D, Wolf C, Quinn PJ (2005) Comparative lipid analysis and structures of detergent-resistant membrane raft fractions isolated from human and ruminant erythrocytes. Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 434:150-158
Laemmli UK (1970) Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4. Nature (London) 227:680-685
Lichtenberg D, Goni FM, Heerklotz H (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes should not be identified with membrane rafts. Trends Biochem. Sci. 30:430436
London E, Brown DA (2000) Insolubility of lipids in triton X-100: physical origin and relationship to sphingolipid/cholesterol membrane domains (rafts). Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1508:182-195
Matko J, Bodnar A, Vereb G, Bene L, Vamosi G, Szentesi G, Szollosi J, Gaspar R, Horejsi V, Waldmann TA, Damjanovich S (2002) GPI-microdomains (membrane rafts) and signaling of the multi-chain interleukin-2 receptor in human lymphoma/leukemia T cell lines. Eur. J. Biochem. 269:1199-2008.
Murphy SC, Samuel BU, Harrison T, Speicher KD, Speicher DW, Reid ME, Prohaska R, Low PS, Tanner MJ, Mohandas N, Haldar K (2004) Erythrocyte detergent-resistant membrane proteins: their characterization and selective uptake during malaria infection. Blood 103:1920-1928
Neumann-Giesen C, Falkenbach B, Beicht P, Claasen S, Luers G, Stuermer CA, Herzog V, Tikkanen R (2004) Membrane and raft association of reggie-1/flotillin-2: role of myristoylation, palmitoylation and oligomerization and induction of filopodia by overexpression. Biochem. J. 378:509-518
Nishijo J, Moriyama S, Shiota S (2003) Interactions of cholesterol with cyclodextrins in aqueous solution. Chem. Pharm. Bull. 51:1253-1257
Ohtani Y, Irie T, Uekama K, Fukunaga K, Pitha J (1989) Differential effects of a-, p- and y-cyclodextrins on human erythrocytes. Eur. J. Biochem. 186:1722
Pike LJ (2003) Lipid rafts: bringing order to chaos. J. Lipid Res. 44:655:667
Pike LJ (2004) Lipid rafts: heterogeneity on the high seas. Biochem. J. 378:281-292
Pike LJ (2006) Rafts defined: a report on the keystone symposium on lipid rafts and cell function. J. Lipid Res. 47:1597-1598
Preté PSC, Gomes K, Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2002) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by non-ionic surfactants of the polyoxyethylene alkyl ethers series. Biophys. Chem. 97: 45-54
Rivas MG, Gennaro AM (2003) Detergent resistant domains in erythrocyte membranes survive after cell cholesterol depletion: an EPR spin label study. Chem. Phys. Lipids 122:165-169
Rose HG, Oklander M (1965) Improved procedure for the extraction of lipids from human erythrocytes. J. Lipid Res. 6:428-431
Salzer U, Prohaska R (2001) Stomatin, flotillin-1, and flotillin-2 are major integral proteins of erythrocyte lipid rafts. Blood 97:1141-1143
Samuel BU, Mohandas N, Harrison T, McManus H, Rosse W, Reid M, Haldar K (2001) The role of cholesterol and glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored proteins of erythrocyte rafts in regulating raft protein content and malarial infection. J. Biol. Chem. 276:29319-29329
Schroeder R, London E, Brown DA (1994) Interactions between saturated acyl chains confer detergent resistance on lipids and GPI-anchored proteins: GPI-anchored proteins in liposomes and cells show similar behavior. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 91:12130-12134
Schuck S, Honsho M, Ekroos K, Shevchenko A, Simons K (2003) Resistance of cell membranes to different detergents. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 100:5795-5800
Simons K, Ikonen E (1997) Functional rafts in cell membranes. Nature 387:569-572
Simons K, Vaz WL (2004) Model systems, lipid rafts, and cell membranes. Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struc. 33:269-295
Vazquez MJ, Rivas MG, Gennaro AM (2002) Modification of cholesterol content in human red cell membranes by using methyl-p-cyclodextrin: time evolution and cell shape changes. Revista FABICIB 6:121-127
Wilkinson DK, Turner EJ, Parkin ET, Garner AE, Harrison PJ, Crawford M, Stewart GW, Hooper NM (2007) Membrane raft actin deficiency and altered Ca2+-induced vesiculation in stomatin-deficient overhydrated hereditary stomatocytosis. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1778:125:132
Xu X, London E (2000) The effect of sterol structure on membrane lipid domains reveals how cholesterol can induce lipid domain formation. Biochemistry 39:843-849
Table 1 - Order parameters S obtained from EPR spectra of the spin labels 5 and 16-SASL in intact erythrocytes, cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes and their respective DRMs prepared with Triton X-100 or C12E8.
Sample
5-SASL
16-SASL
Scontrol	SDRM	SDRM	SDRM	SDRM
			Scontrol	
	Triton X-100	C12E8	Triton X-100	C12E8
Intact cellsa
0.762
± 0.009
0.836
± 0.005*
0.827
± 0.017*
0.268
± 0.001
0.319
± 0.001*
0.302
± 0.002**
Cholesterol-depleted cells
0.774
± 0.008
0.878
± 0.011*- #
0.872
± 0.004*-##
0.258
± 0.001
0.318 ±
0.003*
0.304
± 0.002**
Note: data expressed as mean ± S.D. Statistical differences between DRMs vs. control samples: * p &amp;lt;0.001; ** p &amp;lt;0.01 (paired Student's t-test, n = 3-5); statistical differences between DRMs from cholesterol-depleted cells and DRMs from intact cells: # p &amp;lt;0.001, ** p &amp;lt;0.01 (unpaired Student's t-test, n = 3-5). a Data from Domingues et al. (2008).
Figure legends
Figure 1- Protein (A), cholesterol (B) and phospholipids content solubilized from erythrocyte ghosts by detergents Triton X-100 and C12E8. Samples of ghosts containing 1 mg/mL of protein were incubated with the detergents in 5 mM PBS buffer for 30 min at 4°C and centrifuged at 15,000 g for 30 min, at 4°C. Untreated samples of ghosts in PBS were used as control. The 100% values in panels A, B and C correspond to the total protein, cholesterol and phospholipids content, respectively, in the untreated ghosts' samples, in PBS.
Figure 2- Distribution of flotillin-2 (flot-2), stomatin (stom), band 3 and glycophorin (GPC) in different sucrose density fractions numbered from top to bottom. Fractions 2 and 3 correspond to DRMs obtained from intact and cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes with Triton X-100 (left) and C12E8 (right). Results are representative of 3 independent experiments.
Figure 3- SDS-PAGE of proteins present in the DRM fractions 2 and 3 prepared from cholesterol-depleted erythrocytes with Triton X-100 (lanes 3 and 5) and C12E8 (lanes 7 and 9). DRM fractions 2 and 3 prepared from intact erythrocytes (controls) were loaded in lanes 2 and 4 (Triton X-100) and in lanes 6 and 8 (C12E8). Lane 1 corresponds to an amount of ghost sample proportional to the total amount loaded for the DRM fractions 2 and 3. Results are representative of 3 independent experiments.
Figure 1
Triton X-100
Control	MBCD
fraction number
Figure 2
hit
Triton X-100	C12E8
MBCD -+-+-+-	+
123456789
Figure 3
PARTE 3: Variações metodológicas no preparo de DRMs
Efeito de diferentes detergentes no isolamento de DRMs
O detergente mais empregado no isolamento de DRMs tem sido o Triton X-100. No entanto, outros detergentes não iônicos como os da série Brij, os da série Tween, Lubrol WX, além do zwiteriônico CHAPS, também têm sido utilizados (Schuck et al. 2003; Pike, 2004; Delaunay et al., 2007). De acordo com dados experimentais, Triton X-100 e CHAPS se inserem mais eficientemente na membrana do que os demais detergentes citados acima, e, portanto, possuem um maior potencial de solubilização; já os detergentes da série Brij e Lubrol WX podem apresentar baixa ação solubilizadora na membrana, inclusive na fase líquido desordenada (Brown, 2007). Neste trabalho, demonstramos pela primeira vez o isolamento de DRMs a partir de eritrócitos utilizando outro detergente (C12E8) além do clássico Triton X-100 (Domingues et al., 2008b). Além de C12E8 e Triton X-100, os detergentes zwiteriônicos CHAPS, ASB-14 e ASB-16 também foram testados para isolar DRMs de eritrócitos seguindo a mesma metodologia descrita anteriormente (Domingues et al., 2008b). Para podermos comparar os resultados obtidos entre os diferentes detergentes padronizamos a concentraçao de todos em 16 mM, i.e., acima de suas CMC e correspondente a 1% de Triton X-100. Para o isolamento de DRMs, as amostras foram centrifugadas a 288000 x gmax usando o rotor SW 41 Ti (Beckman Coulter). Devido a maior capacidade de volume dos tubos utilizados nesse rotor, os experimentos foram realizados com os volumes das amostras proporcionalmente aumentados (dobro) em relação àqueles descritos na parte 2 (Domingues et al., 2008b). Dez frações de 1 mL foram coletadas iniciando-se pela parte superior dos tubos (5% sacarose) e nessas condições DRMs na interface 5-30% sacarose foram coletadas como fração 3 para análises sucessivas.
O efeito dos diferentes detergentes em isolar DRMs de eritrocitos pode ser observado na figura 6. Apenas com Triton X-100 e C12E8 foram obtidas DRMs de baixa densidade (interface 5-30% sacarose).
Figura 6 - Aspecto do gradiente de sacarose obtido após centrifugação de eritrocitos lisados com diferentes detergentes. Aproximadamente 2,5 x 109 células foram incubadas com C12E8 (tubo 1), Triton X-100 (tubo 2), ASB-14 (tubo 3), ASB-16 (tubo 4) e CHAPS (tubo 5) durante 30 min a 4°C e submetidas ao gradiente de sacarose. A centrifugação (288000 x gmáx) se procedeu por 16h a 4°C. DRMs na interface 5-30% sacarose estão indicadas pela seta.
Em relação aos tubos 3 e 4 (figura 6) onde eritrócitos foram tratados com ASB-14 e ASB-16, respectivamente, praticamente toda membrana foi solubilizada por esses detergentes. Dessa forma, devido ao maior potencial lítico desses detergentes (Domingues et al., 2008a) a solubilizaçao da membrana foi mais completa, incluindo as regiões mais organizadas que se encontram no estado líquido ordenado. Embora no tubo 3 (figura 6) possa ser visualizada uma banda discreta de baixa densidade, as dosagens de colesterol da fração 3 tanto nesse tubo quanto no tubo 4, resultaram em
valores que não superaram 10% do colesterol total da membrana, demonstrando uma solubilização efetiva de domínios ricos em colesterol, diferentemente do efeito dos detergentes não iónicos Triton X-100 e C12E8.
Já o tratamento de eritrocitos com CHAPS, que é o menos lítico entre os detergentes utilizados, resultou numa banda de alta densidade após centrifugação do gradiente de sacarose (tubo 5 da figura 6). Embora tal fração seja também rica em colesterol (30-50% do colesterol total da membrana), não foi utilizada em outras análises por não apresentar a baixa densidade característica de DRMs. Portanto, as técnicas de western blot e RPE não foram utilizadas nem para as amostras obtidas com CHAPS nem para aquelas obtidas com ASB. Outros experimentos com razões detergente:lipídio diferentes daquela utilizada nesse trabalho (aproximadamente 12:1), estão sendo conduzidos em nosso laboratório.
Efeito da temperatura no isolamento de DRMs
A solubilização de membranas por detergente é um processo dependente da temperatura e bastante complexo. De maneira geral a solubilização de bicamadas na fase líquido cristalina requer mais detergente (ResQl maior) com o aumento da temperatura. Segundo Lichtenberg et al. (2005), o aumento da temperatura induziria curvatura negativa espontânea das moléculas pela desordem das cadeias hidrofóbicas e, possivelmente, a desidratação das cabeças polares dos lipídios da membrana. Esta curvatura espontânea, mais negativa, dificultaria a transição para micelas mistas que apresentam curvatura positiva (Lichtenberg et al. 2005).
Independentemente da razão detergente:lipídio utilizada para isolamento de DRMs, a temperatura de 4°C tem sido praticamente universal
nos protocolos descritos na literatura. Assim, muitos trabalhos criticam uma possível relação existente entre DRMs e rafts, uma vez que DRMs não podem ser obtidas na temperatura fisiológica (London &amp;amp; Brown, 2000; Lingwood &amp;amp; Simon, 2007).
Para verificar se DRMs da membrana eritrocitária podem ser isoladas a temperaturas superiores a 4°C utilizamos a metodologia descrita em (Domingues et al., 2008b). Eritrócitos foram incubados com os detergentes Triton X-100 e Cí2E8 por 30 minutos a 37°C ou na temperatura ambiente (20-25°C) e, em seguida, as amostras foram submetidas à centrifugação em gradiente de sacarose por 16 horas a 20°C. Visualmente os resultados podem ser observados na figura 7, onde DRMs com baixa densidade foram obtidas na interface 5-30% sacarose.
Figura 7 - Aspecto do gradiente de sacarose obtido após centrifugação de eritrócitos lisados com Triton X-100 e C12E8 em diferentes temperaturas. Aproximadamente 2,5 x 109 células foram incubadas com Triton X-100 (tubos 1 e 3) e com C12E8 (tubos 2 e 4) durante 30 min a 37°C (tubos 1 e 2) e a temperatura ambiente (tubos 3 e 4) e submetidas ao gradiente de sacarose. A centrifugação (288000 x gmáx) se procedeu por 16h a 20°C. DRMs na interface 5-30% sacarose estão indicadas pela seta.
De acordo com os resultados apresentados na figura 8, o teor de colesterol presente nas frações de DRMs não se altera nas condições testadas (37°C, temperatura ambiente e 4°C). Em todas as situações, cerca de 30% do colesterol total presente nas membranas eritrocitárias estava presente nas frações de DRMs. Esses resultados sugerem, portanto, que DRMs podem ser obtidas a temperaturas mais elevadas (inclusive na fisiológica), sendo igualmente enriquecidas em colesterol.
Figura 8 - Conteúdo de colesterol em DRMs obtidas com Triton X-100 e C12E8 em diferentes temperaturas. Controle: quantidade total de colesterol presente nas membranas eritrocitárias intactas. Resultados correspondem a média de 3 experimentos independentes.
Em relação ao teor protéico, observamos que em temperaturas acima de 4°C ocorre uma solubilização mais eficiente das proteínas de membranas eritrocitárias, principalmente na presença de Triton X-100. Essa solubilização aumentada é refletida pelo aumento da razão colesterol/proteína (&gt; 1), como mostra a figura 9, em relação aos resultados a 4°C (&amp;lt;1) (Domingues et al., 2008b). Apesar dessa aparente diferença no conteúdo protéico entre DRMs isoladas em diferentes temperaturas, a dificuldade de reprodutibilidade
de dosagens protéicas, particularmente em membranas, e a sensibilidade de detecção das diferentes metodologias, além dos interferentes, devem ser considerados (Zaia et al., 1998). Os resultados descritos na figura 9 correspondem às dosagens protéicas em que utilizamos o método de Hartree (1972) enquanto que, os dados descritos a 4°C correspondem a dosagens baseadas no uso do ácido bicinconínico (Domingues et al., 2008b).
Figura 9 - Razão colesterol/proteína em DRMs obtidas com Triton X-100 e Ci2E8 a 37°C e temperatura ambiente. Resultados correspondem a média de 3 experimentos independentes.
Recentemente, Chen et al. (2008) demonstraram que em células de cérebro de ratos, o uso de tampões contendo Mg2+ e K+ (mimetizando o ambiente iônico intracelular) conferiu estabilidade às membranas (homogeneizado) durante a solubilização, permitindo o isolamento de DRMs a 37°C com características de rafts. Esses resultados demonstram, portanto, que a organização desses micro ou nanodomínios ainda não está totalmente esclarecida. De nosso conhecimento, não há nenhum relato na literatura até
o momento sobre o isolamento de DRMs de eritrócitos em temperatura fisiológica. No entanto, uma análise detalhada para investigar a composição protéica e lipídica dessas DRMs bem como sua organização se faz necessária.
Efeito de anestésicos locais em DRMs
Nosso grupo de pesquisa tem se dedicado ao estudo da interação de anfifílicos (anestésicos locais, detergentes, fenotiazínicos) com membranas usando diferentes abordagens metodológicas que nos permitem avaliar propriedades estruturais e dinâmicas de membranas modelo (de Paula &amp;amp; Schreier, 1996; Schreier et al., 2000; Fraceto et al., 2002, 2006; Pinto et al., 2006; de Paula &amp;amp; Fraceto, 2008; Lorite et al., 2009) e biológicas (Preté et al., 2002; Malheiros et al., 2005; Domingues et al., 2007; Domingues et al., 2008a,b).
Recentemente, Kamata et al. (2008) descreveram que o anestésico local lidocaína desorganiza de maneira reversível a estrutura de DRMs de eritrócitos obtidas com Triton X-100, resultando em falhas na transdução de sinal mediada por Gsa, uma proteína presente em rafts de eritrócitos.
Propusemo-nos, então, a avaliar possíveis efeitos ou interações de anestésicos locais com DRMs de eritrócitos obtidos com Triton X-100. Além da lidocaína, utilizamos prilocaína e bupivacaína. Inicialmente as células foram incubadas com os anestésicos locais (concentração final de 18,5 mM para lidocaína e prilocaína e 3,2 mM para bupivacaína) durante 20 minutos a 37°C, seguidos de outros 20 minutos em gelo. Em seguida as amostras foram centrifugadas e o concentrado de eritrócitos lavados por mais duas vezes. As células foram então submetidas ao tratamento com Triton X-100 e centrifugadas em gradiente de sacarose. Visualmente, as DRMs obtidas não
apresentaram diferenças em relação as DRMs controle obtidas a partir de eritrocitos tratados com Triton X-100 na ausência de anestésicos (figura 10).
Figura 10 - Aspecto do gradiente de sacarose obtido após centrifugação de eritrocitos tratados com anestésicos locais. Aproximadamente 2,5 x 109 células foram tratadas com anestésicos locais e lisadas com Triton X-100. Tubos 2, 3 e 4 referem-se aos tramentos com lidocaína (18,5 mM), prilocaína (18,5 mM) e bupivacaína (3,2 mM), respectivamente. Tubo 1 refere-se ao controle, onde as células foram lisadas com Triton X-100 na ausência de anestésico local. A centrifugação (288000 x gmáx) se procedeu por 16h a 4°C. DRMs na interface 5-30% sacarose estão indicados pela seta.
As figuras 11 e 12 mostram os valores de colesterol e proteínas, respectivamente, nas frações de DRMs obtidas a partir de eritrocitos tratados com anestésicos locais previamente à solubilização parcial com Triton X-100. Diferentemente dos resultados de Kamata et al. (2008), que registraram diminuição para níveis não detectáveis na quantidade de colesterol em DRMs de eritrocitos quando as células foram tratadas com lidocaína, nenhuma diferença estatística (p &gt; 0,05, Test t-Student, n=3) foi encontrada entre as
quantidades de colesterol e proteínas de DRMs isoladas de células tratadas e não tratadas com anestésicos locais. Aqueles autores encontraram, em DRMs controle, apenas 18% do colesterol total das membranas, contra os 30-40% encontrados em nossos experimentos. Embora as diferentes metodologias de dosagens de colesterol possam contribuir para essas diferenças, outras variáveis devem ser levadas em consideração: o maior volume (5 mL) das frações recolhidas por Kamata et al. (2008) favorece uma diluição das amostras, aumentando a possibilidade de erros nas dosagens; além disso, em nossos experimentos, somente foi possível o isolamento de DRMs em presença de carbonato de sódio, não usado por aqueles autores. Outros experimentos estão sendo conduzidos para verificar se esses anestésicos locais interferem ou não na organização de DRMs, através da detecção de proteínas específicas marcadoras de lipid rafts (ex. flotilina-2 e estomatina) e RPE.
Figura 11 - Conteúdo de colesterol em DRMs obtidas a partir de eritrócitos tratados com anésticos locais (LDC: lidocaína; PLC: prilocaína; BVC: bupivacaína) previamente à solubilização com Triton X-100. Controle: quantidade de colesterol presente em DRMs na ausência de anestésicos locais. Resultados correspondem a média de 3 experimentos independentes.
Figura 12 - Conteúdo protéico em DRMs obtidas a partir de eritrócitos tratados com anésticos locais (LDC: lidocaína; PLC: prilocaína; BVC: bupivacaína) previamente à solubilização com Triton X-100. Controle: quantidade de proteínas presente em DRMs na ausência de anestésicos locais. Resultados correspondem a média de 3 experimentos independentes.
CONSIDERAÇÕES FINAIS
Nas últimas duas décadas DRMs têm sido bastante exploradas para o estudo de rafts, ajudando a compreender a organização e funcionamento das membranas biológicas. No entanto, muitos aspectos são ainda obscuros em relação a essas estruturas e mesmo a existência de rafts como entidades funcionais da membrana tem sido alvo de muitas controvérsias.
Embora estudos de DRMs com membranas modelo sejam relevantes, o uso de membranas biológicas é crucial nessa área. As membranas biológicas apresentam uma variedade muito grande de lipídios e muitas proteínas associadas a esses lipídios. Além disso, a membrana biológica é uma bicamada assimétrica e a composição da monocamada interna bem como a extensão de associação entre suas monocamadas não é ainda totalmente conhecida. A temperatura também é um fator importante a ser considerado em estudos de DRMs e o fato de a maioria dessas frações serem obtidas a baixa temperatura - ao invés de 37°C - é bastante questionável.
Particularmente para DRMs de eritrócitos, diferentes resultados qualitativos e quantitativos são encontrados na literatura. Pequenos detalhes como pH e força iônica parecem ser cruciais para o isolamento dessas estruturas (Ciana et al., 2005; Domingues et al., 2008b; Chen et al., 2008). A composição de cátions nos tampões de extração de DRMs deve ser levada em consideração (Mcdonald &amp;amp; Pike, 2005), principalmente quando se deseja isolar DRMs a 37°C (Chen et al. 2008). Nossos resultados mostraram que, nas condições utilizadas neste trabalho, o isolamento de DRMs a partir de eritrócitos ocorre mesmo a 37°C. Esses resultados mostram que o protocolo de extração não é universal para todos os tipos celulares e ajustes devem ser feitos em cada caso. Embora o uso de detergentes possa induzir a formação de domínios na fase lo, o isolamento de DRMs e a análise de sua
composição protéica é muito importante para determinar a afinidade de proteínas por ambientes mais organizados da membrana. Neste sentido, o uso de diferentes detergentes pode contribuir para essas análises.
Outra questão bastante discutida é o envolvimento ou não do citoesqueleto em DRMs. Nossos resultados apontam para uma associação de DRMs com o citoesqueleto eritrocitário. Em alguns experimentos pré-eliminares conduzidos em nosso laboratório, o uso de cátions bivalentes como o magnésio parece causar algum efeito durante o procedimento de obtenção de DRMs, principalmente afetando o grau de associação entre proteínas do citoesqueleto e a membrana e/ou DRMs. Embora a presença de agentes quelantes como EDTA no tampão de extração pudesse comprometer o isolamento de DRMs verificamos que, mesmo na sua ausência (figura 13) houve necessidade da adição de carbonato de sódio, mostrando que a obtenção de frações resistentes a detergentes (na interface 5-30% sacarose e apresentando 30% do colesterol total) é dependente de um pH elevado e força iônica específica, que podem ser obtidos pela adição deste sal. Além disso, em membranas biológicas a composição lipídica de rafts da monocamada interna não está bem definida e ainda alguns estudos mostraram que a formação de rafts na monocamada externa da membrana pode induzir alterações no ambiente lipídico da monocamada interna (Radhakrishnan &amp;amp; McConnell, 1999). Essas alterações poderiam, portanto, resultar em modificações na associação entre o citoesqueleto e a bicamada. Essas e muitas outras questões já apontadas aqui, refletem a necessidade de mais estudos nessa área. Além disso, ainda há poucas evidências do papel biológico de DRMs ou rafts em eritrócitos.
Figura 13 - Aspecto do gradiente de sacarose obtido após centrifugação de eritrócitos lisados com Triton X-100, na ausência de EDTA e presença ou não de carbonato de sódio. Aproximadamente 2,5 x 109 células foram lisadas com Triton X-100 em tampão tris-HCl durante 30 min a 4°C e em seguida submetidas ao gradiente de sacarose na ausência (1) e presença (2) de 0,15 M de carbonato de sódio. A centrifugação (288000 x gmáx) se procedeu por 16h a 4°C. DRMs de baixa densidade foram obtidas na interface 5-30% sacarose somente na presença de carbonato de sódio.
CONCLUSÕES
Embora a membrana eritrocitária seja muito estudada e um ótimo modelo para o estudo de membranas mais complexas, muito pouco se conhece sobre a existência e funcionalidade de rafts nesta membrana. DRMs constituem uma ferramenta bastante útil na avaliação da composição de microdomínios de membranas. Neste trabalho estudamos a solubilização da membrana eritrocitária e caracterizamos as frações resistentes aos detergentes Triton X-100 e C12E8. Os resultados obtidos permitiram as seguintes conclusões:
Detergentes altamente hemolíticos, como ASB-14 e ASB-16, solubilizam mais eficientemente os componentes da membrana eritrocitária em relação ao Triton X-100 e C12E8. Desse modo, nas condições experimentais utilizadas neste trabalho não detectamos DRMs com os detergentes ASB. Já com o CHAPS, que apresenta um baixo efeito hemolítico em relação aos ASB, Triton X-100 e C12E8, uma fração resistente a esse detergente foi observada, mas devido a sua composição lipídica-protéica de alta densidade (não comumente observada em DRMs) não foi analisada em detalhes.
A metodologia tradicional para obtenção de DRMs, em que a membrana é simplesmente tratada com detergente (geralmente não iônico) a baixa temperatura, não é aplicável para membrana do eritrócito (ghosts ou células intactas). Nossos resultados indicam que, para o isolamento de DRMs da membrana eritrocitária, são necessárias condições específicas de pH e força iônica que requerem adição de carbonato de sódio. Dessa forma a existência de uma interação eletrostática entre o citoesqueleto e DRMs de eritrócitos proposta por Ciana et al. (2005) é também evidenciada em nossos resultados.
Além do Triton X-100, DRMs de membranas de eritrócito humano intactas e depletadas de colesterol são também obtidas com o uso do detergente não iônico Ci2E8.
DRMs obtidas com Ci2E8 e Triton X-100 são igualmente enriquecidas em colesterol (aproximadamente 30% do colesterol total da membrana) e possuem uma razão em massa colesterol/proteínas aumentada em pelo menos três vezes em relação à membrana original. No entanto, entre as proteínas especificamente estudas, a única que se distribui diferentemente nas DRMs obtidas com os diferentes detergentes é a flotilina-2, sendo seletivamente enriquecida em DRMs isoladas com Triton X-100.
As cadeias acilas dos lipídios presentes em DRMs isoladas com Triton X-100 e Ci2E8 se organizam de maneira semelhante e possuem parâmetro de ordem aumentado em relação à membrana original, compatível com a fase lo dos rafts. A compactação da membrana, nesses domínios, não é, portanto, influenciada pela presença ou não da flotilina-2.
DRMs obtidas a partir de eritrócitos íntegros e ghosts com os detergentes Triton X-100 e C12E8 não apresentam diferenças em relação à composição lipídica/protéica e organização das cadeias acilas.
A remoção de 40% do colesterol da membrana do eritrócito provoca um aumento ainda maior na ordem das cadeias acilas, além de reorganizar a membrana, resultando em domínios mais resistentes a C12E8 evidenciados pelo aumento da presença de flotilina-2 em DRMs. Uma vez que flotilina-2 está associada à monocamada interna da membrana, sugerimos que o C12E8 solubiliza mais seletivamente proteínas encontradas em domínios dessa monocamada em relação ao Triton X-100. Além disso, a depleção de
colesterol também resulta na dissociação da interação entre citoesqueleto e DRMs.
DRMs de eritrócitos podem ser obtidas em temperaturas acima de 4°C, preconizada na literatura. DRMs isoladas a 37°C na presença de tampão TNE apresentam quantidade de colesterol equivalente àquelas obtidas a 4°C.
Nas condições de extração utilizadas, os anestésicos locais lidocaína, prilocaína e bupivacaína parecem não alterar DRMs obtidas com Triton X100, pelo menos em relação ao conteúdo de colesterol e proteínas totais.
REFERÊNCIAS BIBLIOGRÁFICAS
Ahmed SN, Brown DA, London E (1997) On the origin of sphingolipid /cholesterol-rich detergent-insoluble cell membranes: physiological concentrations of cholesterol and sphingolipid induce formation of a detergent-insoluble, liquid-ordered lipid phase in model membranes. Biochemistry 36:10944-10953.
An X, Guo X, Sum H, Morrow J, Gratzer W, Mohandas N (2004) Phosphatidylserine binding sites in erythroid spectrin: location and implications for membrane stability. Biochemistry 43:310-315.
An X, Guo X, Sum H, Gratzer W, Mohandas N (2004) Phospholipid binding by proteins of the spectrin family: a comparative study. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun 327:794-800.
An X, Zhang X, Debnath G, Baines AJ, Mohandas N (2006) Phosphatidylinositol-4,5-biphosphate (PIP2) differentially regulates the interaction of human erythrocyte protein 4.1 (4.1R) with membranes proteins. Biochemistry 45:5725-5732.
Benga G (2006) Water channel proteins: from their discovery in 1985 in Cluj-Napoca, Romania, to the 2003 Nobel Prize in Chemistry. Cell. Mol. Biol. 52:10-19.
Benting J, Rietveld A, Ansorge I, Simons K (1999) Acyl and alkyl chain length of GPI-anchors is critical for raft association in vitro. FEBS Lett. 462:47-50.
Berg JM, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L (2007) Bioquímica. 6a Ed., Guanabara-Koogan, Rio de Janeiro.
Bhairi SM (2001) Detergents - A guide to the properties and uses of detergents in biological systems. Calbiochem-Novabiochem Corporation, La Jolla.
Brown DA (2006) Lipid rafts, detergent-resistant membranes, and raft targeting signals. Physiology 21:430-439.
Brown DA (2007) Analysis of raft affinity of membrane proteins by detergent-insolubility. In: McIntosh, T.J. (ed.), Methods in molecular biology. Lipid rafts. Humana Press, Totowa NJ, pp. 1-7.
Brown DA, London E (1998) Functions of lipid rafts in biological membranes. Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol. 14:111-136.
Brown RE (1998) Sphingolipid organization in biomembranes: what physical studies of model membranes reveal. J. Cell Sci. 111:1-9.
Brown DA, Rose JK (1992) Sorting of GPI-anchored proteins to glycolipid-enriched membrane subdomains during transport to the apical cell surface. Cell 68:533-544.
Chamberlain, LH (2004) Detergent as tool for purification and classification of lipid rafts. FEBS 559:1-5.
Chasis JA, Shohet SB (1987) Red-cell biochemical anatomy and membraneproperties. Ann. Rev. Physiol. 49:237-248.
Chen X, Jen A, Warley A, Lawrence MJ, Quinn PJ, Morris RJ (2008) Isolation at physiological temperature of detergent-resistant membranes with properties expected of lipid rafts: the influence of buffer composition. Biochem. J. doi:10.1042/BJ20081385.
Ciana A, Balduini C, Minetti G (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes in human erythrocytes and their connection to the membrane-skeleton. J. Biosci. 30:317-328.
Connor J, Gillum K, Schroit AJ (1990) Maintenance of lipid asymmetry in red-blood cells and ghosts - effect of divalent-cations and serum-albumin on the transbilayer distribution of phosphatidylserine. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1025:82-86.
Cooper GM (1997) The cell surface. In: The cell: a molecular approach. ASM Press, Washington, pp 467-517.
Cullis PR, Verkleij AJ (1979) Modulation of membrane structure by Ca2+ and dibucaine as detected by 31P NMR. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 552:546-551.
Datta DB (1987) A comprehensive introduction to membrane biochemistry. Floral Publishing, Madison, WI.
de Paula E, Schreier S (1996) Molecular and physicochemical aspects of local anesthetic-membrane interaction. Braz J Med Biol Res. 29:877-94.
de Paula E, Jarrell HC, Schreier S, Fraceto LF (2008) Preferential location of lidocaine and etidocaine in lecithin bilayers as determined by EPR, fluorescence and 2H-NMR. Biophys. Chem. 132:47-54.
Delaunay JL, Breton M, Godine JW, Trugnan G, Maurice M (2007) Differential detergent resistance of the apical and basolateral NPPases: relationship with polarized targeting. J. Cell Sci. 120:1009-1016.
Diakowski W, Szopa J, Sikorski AF (2003) Occurrence of lipid receptors inferred from brain and erythrocyte spectrums binding NaOH-extracted and protease-treated neuronal and erythrocyte membranes. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1611:115-122.
Diakowski W, Ozimek E, Bielska E, Bem S, Langner M, Sikorski AF (2006) Cholesterol affects spectrin-phospholipid interactions in a manner different from changes resulting from alterations in membrane fluidity due to fatty acyl chain composition. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1758:4-12.
Dietrich C, Volovyk ZN, Levi M, Thompson NL, Jacobson K (2001) Partitioning of Thy-1, GM1 and crosslinked phospholipid analogs into lipid rafts reconstituted in supported model membrane monolayers. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 98:10642-10647.
Dietrich C, Yang B, Fujiwara T, Kusumi A, Jacobson K (2002) Relationship of lipid rafts to transient confinement zones detected by single particle tracking. Biophys. J. 82:274-284.
Domingues CC (2004) Avaliação da solubilização de membranas eritrocitárias e suas proteínas por novos surfatantes zwiteriônicos. Dissertação de Mestrado, Instituto de Biologia, UNICAMP, Campinas.
Domingues CC, Cunha ES, Winck FV, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E (2007) Avaliação de detergentes na solubilização de proteínas de membrana eritrocitária humana em eletroforese bidimensional. Rev. Ciências Biológicas &amp;amp; Saúde 2: 38-46.
Domingues CC, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E. (2008a) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents. Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res. 41:758-764.
Domingues CC, Ciana A, de Paula E, Faucitano A, Minetti G (2008b) Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8. J. Membr. Biol. DOI 10.1007/s00232-008-9142-4.
Edidin M (2003) The state of lipid rafts: from model membranes to cells. Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct. 32:257-283.
Fielding CJ (2005) Role of cholesterol in membrane microdomain signaling. In: Mattson MP (ed) Membrane microdomain signaling. Lipid rafts in biology and medicine. Human Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 71-89.
Fielding CJ (2006) Lipid rafts and caveolae: from membrane biophysics to cell biology, Wiley-VCH Weinheim.
Fraceto LF, Pinto LMA, Franzoni L, Braga AA, Spisni A, Schreier S, de Paula E (2002) Spectroscopic evidences for a preferential location of lidocaine inside phospholipid bilayers. Biophys. Chem. 99:229-243.
Fraceto LF, Oyama Jr S, Nakaie CR, Spisni A, de Paula E, Pertinhez TA (2006) Interaction of Local Anesthetics with a Peptide encompassing the IV/S4-S5 linker of the Na+ Channel. Biophys. Chem. 123:29-39.
Galembeck E, Alonso A, Meirelles NC (1998) Effects of polyoxyethylene chain lengh on erythrocyte hemolysis induced by poly[oxyethylene (n) nonylphenol] non-ionic surfactants. Chem. Biol. Inter. 113:91-103.
Gallagher PG, Forget BG (2001) The red cell membrane. In: Beutler E, Lichtman MA, Coller BS, Kipps TJ, Selingsohn (ed) Hematology. McGraw-Hill, New York.
Gennis RB (1989) Biomembranes, Springer-Verlag, New York.
Glebov OO, Nichols BJ (2004) Distribution of lipid raft markers in live cells. Biochem. Soc. Trans. 32:673-675.
Gorter E, Grendel F (1925) apud Datta DB (1987) A comprehensive introduction to membrane biochemistry. Floral Publishing, Madison, WI.
Hancock JF (2006) Lipid raft: contentious only from simplistic standpoints. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell. Biol. 7:456-462.
Harder T (2003) Formation of functional cell membrane domains: the interplay of lipid- and protein-mediated interactions. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci. 358:863-868.
Hargestrand H, Isomaa B (1989) Vesiculation induced by amphiphiles in erythrocytes. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 982:179-186.
Hartree EF (1972) Determination of protein: a modification of the Lowry method that gives a linear photometric responce. Anal. Biochem. 48:422427.
Heerklotz H, Binder H, Lantzsch G, Klose G (1997) Lipid/detergent interaction thermodynamics as a function of molecular shape. J. Phys. Chem. B 101:639-645.
Heerklotz H, Seelig J (2000) Correlation of membrane/water partition coefficients of detergents with the critical micelle concentration. Biophys. J. 78:2435-2440.
Heerklotz H (2002) Triton promotes domain formation in lipid raft mixtures. Biophys. J. 83:2693-2701.
Helfrich, W (1973) Elastic properties of lipid bilayers - theory and possible experiments. Z. Naturforsch. (C) 28:693-703.
Hollan S (1996) Membrane Fluidity of blood cells. Haematologia 27:109-127.
Hope HR, Pike LJ (1996) Phosphoinositides and phosphoinositide-utilizing enymes in detergent-insoluble lipid domains. Mol. Biol. Cell 7:843-851.
Ikonen E (2001) Roles of lipid rafts in membrane transport. Curr. Opin. Cell. Biol. 13: 470-477.
Israelachvili JN, Marcelja S, Horn RG (1980) Physical principles of membrane organization. Q. Rev. Biophys. 13:121-200.
Jacobson K, Dietrich C (1999) Looking at lipid rafts? Trends Cell Biol. 9:8791.
Jain SK (1988) Evidence for membrane lipid peroxidation during the in vivo aging of human erythrocytes. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 937:205-210.
Janes PW, Ley SC, Magee AI (1999) Aggregation of lipid rafts accompanies signaling via the T cell antigen receptor. J. Cell Biol. 147:447461.
Jin S, Verkman AS (2007) Single particle tracking of complex diffusion in membranes: simulation and detection of barrier, raft, and interaction phenomena. J. Phys. Chem. 111:3625-3632.
Kamata K, Manno S, Ozaki M, Takakuwa Y (2008) Functional evidence for presence of lipid rafts in erythrocyte membranes: Gsa in rafts is essential for signal transduction. Am. J. Hematol. 83:371-375.
Karacay B, Chang LS (1999) Induction of erythrocyte protein 4.2 gene expression during differentiation of murine erythroleukemia cells. Genomics 59:6-17.
Kahya N (2006) Targeting membrane proteins to liquid-ordered phases: molecular	self-organization	explored by fluorescence correlation
spectroscopy. Chem. Phys. Lipids 141:158-168.
Kirat KE, Morandat S (2007) Cholesterol modulation of membrane resistance to Triton X-100 explored by atomic force microscopy. 1768:2300-2309.
Lagerholm BC, Weinreb GE, Jacobson K, Thompson NL (2005) Detecting microdomains in intact cell membranes. Ann. Rev. Phys. Chem. 56: 309336.
Langhorst MF, Reuter A, Stuermer CAO (2005) Scaffolding microdomains and beyond: the function of reggie/flotillin proteins. Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 62:2228-2240.
Langhorst MF, Friederike AJ, Mueller S, Hartmann LS, Luxenhofer G, Stuermer CAO (2008) Reggies/flotilins regulate cytoskeletal remodeling during neuronal differentiation via CAP/ponsin and Rho GTPases. Eur. J. Cell Biol. 87:921-931.
Laurialt VVM, Obrien PJ (1991) Disulfiram may mediate erythrocyte hemolysis induced by diethyldithiocarbamate and 1,4-naphthoquinone-2-sulfonate. Arch. Bioch. Biophys. 284:207-214.
le Maire M, Champeil P, Moller JV (2000) Interaction of membrane proteins and lipids with solubilizing detergents. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1508:86111.
Lichtenberg D (1985) Characterization of the solubilization of lipid bilayers by surfactants. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 821:470-478.
Lichtenberg D, Opatowski E, Kozlov MM (2000) Phase boundaries in mixtures of membrane-forming amphiphiles and micelle-forming amphiphiles. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1508:182-195.
Lichtenberg D, Goni FM, Heerklotz H (2005) Detergent-resistant membranes should not be identified with membrane rafts. Trends Biochem. Sci. 30:430-436
Lingwood D, Simons K. (2007) Detergent resistance as a tool in membrane research. Nat. Protoc. 2:2159-2165.
London E (2002) Insights into lipid raft structure and formation from experiments in model membranes. Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol. 12:480-486.
London E, Brown DA (2000) Insolubility of lipids in triton X-100: physical origin and relationship to sphingolipid/cholesterol membrane domains (rafts). Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1508:182-195.
Lorite GS, Nobre TM, Zaniquelli MED, de Paula E, Cotta MA (2009) Dibucaine effects on structural and elastic properties of lipid bilayers. Biophys. Chem. 139:75-83.
Low TY, Seow TK, Chung MCM (2002) Separation of human erythrocyte membrane associated proteins with one-dimensional and two-dimensional gel electrophoresis followed by identification with matrix-assisted laser desorption /ionization-time of flight mass spectrometry. Proteomics 2:1229-1239.
Luna EJ, Nebl T, Takizawa, Crowley JL (2005) Lipid raft membrane skeletons. In: Mattson MP (ed) Membrane microdomain signaling. Lipid rafts in biology and medicine. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 47-69.
Macdonald JL, Pike LJ (2005) A simplified method for the preparation of detergent-free lipid rafts. J. Lipid Res. 46:1061-1067.
Malheiros SVP, Gottardo L, Pinto LMA, Yokaichiya DK, Meirelles NC, de Paula E. (2004) A new look at the hemolytic effect of local anesthetics, considering their real membrane/water partitioning at pH 7.4. Biophys. Chem. 100:213-221.
Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2000) Pathways involved in trifluoperazine-, dibucaine-and praziquantel-induced hemolysis. Biophys. Chem. 83:89-100.
Malheiros SVP, Gottardo L, Pinto LMA, Yokaichiya DK, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2004) A new look at the hemolytic effect of local anesthetics, considering their real membrane/water partitioning at pH 7.4. Biophys. Chem. 100:213-221.
Mandal D, Baudin-Creuza V, Bhattacharyya A, Pathak S, Delaunay J, Kundu M, Basu J (2003) Caspase 3-mediated proteolysis of the N-terminal cytoplasmic domain of the human erythroid anion exchanger 1 (band 3). J. Biol. Chem. 278:52551-52558.
Matkó J, Szollósi J (2005) Regulatory aspects of membrane microdomain (raft) dynamics in live cells. In: Mattson MP (ed) Membrane microdomain signaling. Lipid rafts in biology and medicine. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 15-46.
Mauro-Chanteloup I, Delaunay J, Gane P, Nicolas V, Johansen M, Brown EJ, Peters LL, Le Van Kim C, Cartron JP, Colin Y (2003) Evidence that the red cell skeleton protein 4.2 interacts with the Rh membrane complex member CD47. Blood 101:338-344.
McIntosh, TJ (2007) Overview of membrane rafts. In: McIntosh TJ (ed) Methods in molecular biology. Lipid rafts. Humana Press, Totowa NJ, pp 1-
7.
Moffett S, Brown DA, linder ME (2000) Lipid-dependent targeting of G proteins into rafts. J. Biol. Chem. 275:2191-2198.
Montgomery R. (1994) Bioquímica - Uma abordagem Dirigida por Casos, 5a Ed. São Paulo, pp 277.
Morrow IC, Rea S, Martin S, Prior IA, Prohaska R, Hancock JF, James DE, Parton RG (2002) Flotillin-1/reggie-2 traffics to surface raft domains via a novel golgi-independent pathway. Identification of a novel membrane targeting domain and role for palmitoylation. J. Biol. Chem. 277:4883448841.
Mosior M, Bobrowska M, Gomulkiewcz J (1990) Effects of the level of ATP and of the state of spectrin on osmotic properties of bovine erythrocytes. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1022:355-360.
Murador P, Deffune E (2007) Aspectos estruturais da membrane eritrocitaria. Rev. Bras. Hematol. Hemoter. 29:168-178.
Murphy SC, Samuel BU, Harrison T, Speicher KD, Speicher DW, Reid ME, Prohaska R, Low PS, Tanner MJ, Mohandas N, Haldar K (2004) Erythrocyte detergent-resistant membrane proteins: their characterization and selective uptake during malaria infection. Blood 103:1920-1928.
Murphy SC, Fernandez-Pol S, Chung PH, Murthy SNP, Milne SB, Salomao M, Brown HA, Lomasney JW, Mohandas N, Haldar K (2007) Cytoplasmic remodeling of erythrocyte raft lipids infection by the human malaria parasite Plasmodium falciparum. Blood 110:2132-2139.
Murray RK (2007) Hemácias e leucócitos. In: Murray RK, Granner DK, Rodwell VW, Harper Bioquímica Ilustrada. 27a ed., McGraw-Hill, São Paulo.
Nagao E, Seydel KB, Dvorak JA (2002) Detergent-resistant erythrocyte membrane rafts are modified by a Plasmodium falciparum infection. Exp. Parasitol. 102:57-59.
Nelson DL, Cox MM (2006) Lehninger Princípios de Bioquímica. 4aed, Editora Sarvier, São Paulo.
Neumann-Giesen C, Falkenbach B, Beicht P, Clasen S, Lüers G, Stuermer CA, Herzog V, Tikkanen R (2004) Membrane and raft association of reggie-1/flotillin-2: role of myristoylation, palmitoylation and oligomerization and induction of filopodia by overexpression. Biochem. J. 378:509-518.
Nicolas V, Le Van Kim C, Gane P, Birkenmeier C, Cartron JP, Colin Y, Mauro-Chanteloup I (2003) Rh-RhAG/ankirin-R, a new interaction site between the membrane bilayer and the red skeleton, is impaired by Rh(null)-associated mutation. J. Biol. Chem. 278:25526-25533.
Nguyen DH, Hildreth JE (2000) Evidence for budding of human immunodeficiency virus tipe I selectively from glycolipid-enriched membrane lipid rafts. J. Virol. 74:3264-3272.
Overton E (1899) apud Datta DB (1987) A comprehensive introduction to membrane biochemistry. Floral Publishing, Madison, WI.
Pandit SA, Jakobsson E, Scott HL (2004) Simulation of the early stages of nano-domain formation in mixed bilayers of sphingomyelin, cholesterol, and dioleylphosphatidylcholine. Biophys. J. 87:3312-3322.
Pike LJ (2004) Lipid rafts: heterogeneity on the high seas. Biochem. J. 378:281-292.
Pike LJ (2006) Rafts defined: a report on the Keystone Symposium on lipid rafts and cell function. J.Lipid Res. 47:1597-1598.
Pinto LMA, Malheiros SVP, Lino ACS, de Paula E, Perillo MA (2006) Hydroxyzine, Promethazine and Thioridazine interaction with phospholipid
monomolecular layers at the air-water interface. Biophys. Chem. 119:247255.
Polozov IV, Grwrisch K (2004) Domains in binary SOPC/POPE lipid mixtures studied by pulsed field gradient H-1 MAS NMR. Biophys. J. 87:1741-1751.
Pralle A, Keller P, Florin E-L, Simons K, Horber JKH (2000) Sphingolipidcholesterol rafts diffuse as small entities in the plasma membrane of mammalian cells. J. Cell Biol. 148 :997-1007.
Preté PSC (2006) Solubilização de membranas eritrocitárias: análise quantitativa do efeito hemolítico induzido por surfatantes. Tese de Doutorado, Instituto de Biologia, UNICAMP, Campinas.
Preté PSC, Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2002a) Quantitative assessment of human erythrocyte membrane solubilization by Triton X100. Biophys. Chem. 97:1-5.
Preté PSC, Gomes K, Malheiros SVP, Meirelles NC, de Paula E (2002b) Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by non-ionic surfactants of the polyoxyethylene alkyl ether series. Biophys. Chem. 97:45-54.
Price PT, Nelson CM, Clarke SD (2000) Omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid regulation of gene expression. Curr. Opin. Lipidol. 11:3-7.
Radhakrishnan A, McConnell HM (1999) Condensed complexes of cholesterol and phospholipids. Biphys. J. 77:1507-1517.
Ray S, Chakrabarti A (2004) Membrane interaction of erythroid spectrin: surface-density-dependent	high-affinity	binding	to
phosphatidylethanolamine. Mol. Membr. Biol. 21:93-100.
Ridyard MS, Robbins SM (2003) Fibroblast growth factor-2-induced signaling through lipid raft-associated fibroblast growth factor receptor substrate 2 (FRS2). J. Biol. Chem. 278:13803-13809.
Rietveld A, Kai S (1998) The differential miscibility of lipids as the basis for the formation of functional membrane rafts. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1376:467-479.
Rivas MG, Gennaro AM (2003) Detergent resistant domains in erythrocyte membranes survive after cell cholesterol depletion: an EPR spin label study. Chem. Phys. Lipids 122:165-169.
Rodi PM, Cabeza MS, Gennaro AM (2006) Detergent solubilization of bovine erythrocytes. Comparison between the insoluble material and the intact membrane. Biophys. Chem. 122:114-122.
Salzer U, Prohaska R (2001) Stomatin, flotillin-1, and flotillin-2 are major integral proteins of erythrocyte lipid rafts. Blood 97:1141-1143.
Salzer U, Zhu R, Luten M, Isobe H, Pastushenko V, Perkmann T, Hinterdorfer P, Bosman GJ (2008) Vesicles generated during storage of red cells are rich in the lipid raft marker stomatin. Transfusion 48: 451-62.
Samuel BU, Mohandas N, Harrison T, McManus H, Rosse W, Reid M, Haldar K (2001) The role of cholesterol and glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored proteins of erythrocyte rafts in regulating raft protein content and malarial infection. J. Biol. Chem. 276:29319-29329.
Santos HL, Ciancaglini P (2000) A practical approach to the choice of a suitable detergent and optimal condicions for solubilizing a membrane protein. Biochem. Educ. 28: 178-182.
Scheiffele P, Roth M, Simons K (1997) Interaction of influenza virus haemagglutinin with sphingolipid-cholesterol membrane domains via its transmembrane domain. EMBO J. 16: 5501-5508.
Schnitzer E, Lichtenberg D, Kozlov MM. (2003) Temperature-dependence of the solubilization of dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine (DPPC) by the nonionic surfactant Triton X-100, kinetic and structural aspects. Chem. Phys. Lipids. 126:55-76.
Schnitzer JE, Oh P (1996) Aquaporin-1 in plasma membrane and caveolae provides mercury-sensitive water channels across lung endothelium. Am. J. Physiol. 270:H416-H422.
Schreier S, Malheiros SVP, de Paula E (2000) Surface active drugs: Selfassociation and interaction with membranes and surfactants. Physicochemical and biological aspects. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1508:210234.
Schuck S, Honsho M, Ekroos K, Shevchenko A, Simons K (2003) Resistance of cell membranes to different detergents. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 100:5795-5800.
Shah MB, Sehgal PB (2007) Nondetergent isolation of rafts. In: McIntosh TJ (ed) Methods in molecular biology. Lipid rafts. Humana Press, Totowa NJ, pp 21-28.
Silvius JR (2003) Role of cholesterol in lipid raft formation: lessons from lipid model systems. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1610:174-183.
Simons K, Ehehalt R (2002) Cholesterol, lipid rafts, and disease. J. Clin. Invest. 110:597-603.
Simons K, Ikonen E (1997) Functional rafts in cell membranes. Nature 387:569-572.
Simons K, Vaz WL (2004) Model systems, lipid rafts, and cell membranes. Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struc. 33:269-295.
Singer SJ (2004) Some history of membrane molecular biology. Annu. Rev. Physiol. 66:1-27.
Singer SJ, Nicolson GL (1972) The fluid Mosaic Model of the Structure of Cell membranes. Science 175:720-731.
Smart E, Ying YS, Mineo C, Anderson RG (1995) A detergent-free method for purifying caveolae membrane from tissue culture cells. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 92:10104-10108.
Snyers L, Umlauf E, Prohaska R (1999) Association of stomatin with lipid-protein complexes in the plasma membrane and the endocytic compartment. Eur. J. Cell. Biol. 78:802-812.
Soares, AA (2001) Formação de domínios lipídicos em membranas modelo: efeito da Dibucaína. Dissertação de mestrado, Instituto de Biologia, Unicamp, Campinas.
Song KS, Shengwen L, Okamoto T, Quilliam LA, Sargiacomo M, Lisanti MP (1996) Co-purification and direct interaction of Ras with caveolin, an integral membrane protein of caveolae microdomains. J. Biol. Chem. 271:9690-9697.
Sot J, Collado MI, Arrondo JLR, Alonso A, Goni FM (2002) Triton X-100-resistant bilayers: effect of lipid composition and relevance to the raft phenomenon. Langmuir 18:2828-2835.
Storch J, Kleinfeld AM (1985) The lipid structure of biological membranes. Trends Biochem. Sci. 10:418-421.
Subczynsky WK, Kusumi A (2003) Dynamics of raft molecules in the cell and artificial membranes: approaches by pulse EPR spin labeling and single molecule optical microscopy. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1610:231-243.
Tavernarakis N, Druscoll M, Kyrpides NC (1999) The SPFH domain: implicated in regulating targeted protein turnover in stomatin and other membrane-associated proteins. Trends Biochem. Sci. 2:425-427.
Thompson TE, Tillack TW (1985) Organization of glycosphingolipids in bilayers and plasma membranes of mammalian cells. Annu. Rev. Biophys. Chem. 14:361-386.
Umlauf E, Csaszar E, Moertelmaier M, Schuetz GJ, Parton RG, Prohaska R (2004) Association of stomatin with lipid bodies. J. Biol. Chem. 279:23699-23709.
Umlauf E, Mairhofer M, Prohaska R (2006) Characterization of the stomatin domain involved in homo-oligomerization and lipid raft association. J. Biol. Chem. 281:23349-23356.
van der Goot FG, Harder T (2001) Rafts membrane domain: from a liquid-ordered membrane phase to a site of patogen attack. Semin. Immunol. 13:87-89.
Varma S, Mayor S (1998) GPI-anchored proteins are organized into submicron domains at the cell surface. Nature 394:798-801.
Veatch SL, Polozov IV, Gawrisch K, Keller SL (2004) Liquid domains in vesicles investigated by NMR and fluorescence microscopy. Biophys. J. 86:2910-2922.
Veatch SL, Keller SL (2005) Seeing spots: complex phase behavior in simple membranes. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1746:172-185.
Veiga MP, Arrondo JL, Goni FM, Alonso A, Marsh D (2001) Interaction of cholesterol and sphingomyelin in mixed membranes containing phosphatidylcholine, studied by spin-label ESR and IR spectroscopies. A possible stabilization of gel-phase sphingolipid domains by cholesterol. Biochemistry 40:2614-2622.
Vereb G, Matko J, Vamosi G, Ibrahim SM, Magyar E, Varga S, Szollosi J, Jenei A, Gaspar RJr, Waldmann TA, Damjanovich S (2000) Cholesteroldependent clustering of IL-2Ra and its colocalization with HLA and CD48 on T lymphoma cells suggest their function association with lipid rafts. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 97:6013-6018.
Wang Y, Morrow JS (2000) Identification and characterization of human SLP-2, a novel homologue of stomatin (band 7.2b) present in erythrocytes and other tissues. J. Biol. Chem. 275:8062-8071.
Warren RC (1987) Physics and architecture of cell membranes. Adam-Hilger, Bristol and Philadelphia.
Wilkinson DK, Turner EJ, Parkin ET, Garner AE, Harrison PJ, Crawford M, Stewart GW, Hooper NM (2007) Membrane raft actin deficiency and altered Ca2+-induced vesiculation in stomatin-deficient overhydrated hereditary stomatocytosis. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1778:125:132.
Yavin E, Brand A (2005) From intramolecular asymmetries to raft assemblies. A short guide for the puzzled in lipidomics. In: Mattson MP (ed) Membrane microdomain signaling. Lipid rafts in biology and medicine. Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 1-14.
Yawata Y (2003) Cell Membrane: the red blood cell as a model, Wiley-VCH Weinheim.
Yeagle PL (2005) The Structure of cell membranes, 2nd ed. CRC Press, Boca Raton, 540 p.
Young RM, Zheng X, Holowka D, Baird B (2005) Reconstitution of regulated phosphorylation of FcepsilonRI by a lipid raft-excluded protein-tyrosine phosphatase. J. Biol. Chem. 280:1230-1235.
Yuan C, Johnston LJ (2000) Distribution of ganglioside GM-1 in L-alpha dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine/cholesterol monolayers: a model for lipid rafts. Biophys. J. 79:2768-2781.
Zachowski A (1993) Phospholipids in animal eukaryotic membranes: transverse asymmetry and movement. Biochem J. 294:1-14.
PRODUÇÕES CIENTÍFICAS
Artigos publicados em periódicos
1.	DOMINGUES, C. C., CIANA, A., BUTTAFAVA, A., BALDUINI, C., de PAULA, E., MINETTI, G. Resistance of human erythrocyte membranes to Triton X-100 and C12E8. J Membr Biol. DOI 10.1007/s00232-008-9142-4, 2008.
2.	DOMINGUES, C. C., MALHEIROS, S. V. P., de PAULA, E. Solubilization of human erythrocyte membranes by ASB detergents. Braz J Med Biol Res. 41:758-764, 2008.
3.	DOMINGUES, C. C., CUNHA, E. S., WINCK, F.V., MALHEIROS, S. V. P., de PAULA, E. Avaliação de detergentes na solubilização de proteínas de membrana eritrocitária humana em eletroforese bidimensional. Revista de Ciências Biológicas e Saúde. 2:38-46, 2007.
4.	MARTINS, D., OLIVEIRA, B. M., FARIAS, A. S., HORIUCHI, R. S. O., DOMINGUES, C. C., de PAULA, E., MARANGONI, S., GATTAZ, W. F., DIAS-NETO, E., NOVELLO, J. C. The use of ASB detergents in combination with CHAPS is the best for solubilization of Human Brain Proteins for TwoDimensional Gel Electrophoresis. Brief Funct Genomic Proteomic. 6:70-75,
2007.
Artigos a serem submetidos/em preparação
1.	DOMINGUES, C. C., CIANA, A., BALDUINI C., de PAULA E., MINETTI G. Detergent-resistant membranes from cholesterol-depleted human erythrocytes using Triton X-100 and C12E8.
2.	D'ANDREA, M. G., DOMINGUES, C. C., MALHEIROS, S. V. P., de PAULA, E., BIANCONI, M. L. Thermodynamics of micelle formation of the zwitterionic amidosulfobetaine surfactants ASB-14 and ASB-16.
Comunicações e resumos publicados em anais de congressos
1.	12. Membrane Skeleton. Recent Advances and Future Research Directions, Zakopane-Poland, 2008. (Triton X-100 and Ci2Es)-resistant membranes from cholesterol depleted human erythrocytes. (Comunicação Oral)
2.	DOMINGUES, C. C., CIANA, A., DONDI, D., de PAULA, E., MINETTI, G. (Triton X-100 and Ci2E8)-resistant membranes from cholesterol depleted human erythrocytes. In: 12. Membrane Skeleton. Recent Advances and Future Research Directions, 2008, Zakopane-Poland.
3.	DOMINGUES, C. C., CIANA, A., MALHEIROS, S.V.P., de PAULA, E., MINETTI, G. Characterization of (Triton X-100 and C12E8)-resistant membranes from human erythrocytes. In: XXXVII Annual Meeting of the Brazilian Biochemistry and Molecular Biology Society (SBBq) and XI Congress of the Pan-American Association for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (PABMB), 2008, Águas de Lindóia-Brazil.
4.	DOMINGUES, C. C., PRETÉ, P. S. C., MALHEIROS, S. V. P., CIANA, A., MINETTI, G., de PAULA, E. Different approaches to investigate the solubilisation of human erythrocyte membranes induced by detergent. In: 16th meeting of the European Association for Red Cell Research, 2007, Oxford-England.
5.	CIANA, A., DOMINGUES, C. C., de PAULA, E., BALDUINI, C., MINETTI, G. Localization of tyrosine kinases and phosphotyrosine phosphatases in detergent-resistant membranes from human erythrocytes. In: 16th meeting of the European Association for Red Cell Research, 2007, Oxford-England.
6.	CUNHA, E. S., DOMINGUES, C. C., de PAULA, E. Eletroforese bidimensional: extração de proteínas de membrana mitocondrial interna por surfatantes zwiteriônicos e não-iônicos. In: XXII Reunião Anual da Federação de Sociedades de Biologia Experimental, 2007, Águas de Lindóia-Brasil.
7.	CUNHA, E. S., DOMINGUES, C. C., de PAULA, E. Modified blue native electrophoresis protocol for the separation of mitochondria protein complexes. In: XXXVI Annual Meeting of the Brazilian Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (SBBq). 10th IUBMB Conference, 2007, Salvador-Brazil.
8.	DOMINGUES, C. C., D'ANDREA, M. G., de PAULA, E., MALHEIROS, S. V.
P., BIANCONI, M. L. Thermodynamics of micelle formation as a function of temperature: an isothermal titration calorimetry study. In: Workshop on Biocalorimetry and Biological Thermodynamics, 2006, Rio de Janeiro-Brazil.
9.	CUNHA, E. S., DOMINGUES, C. C., de PAULA, E. Two dimensional electrophoresis: extraction of erythrocyte membrane proteins by zwitterionic detergents In: XXXV Reunião Anual da Sociedade Brasileira de Bioquímica e Biologia Molecular - SBBq, 2006, Águas de Lindóia-Brasil.</field>
	</doc>
</add>